<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>Mrs. Lirriper's Legacy</title>
<subtitle>(All The Year Round Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1864</date>
<option name="part.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="part.number_style" value="I"/>
</info>
 
<prefix>
<info title="MRS. LIRRIPER'S LEGACY."/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>ALL THE YEAR ROUND.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1864.</centre>
<hr/>
<centre>Authors:</centre>
<centre>Charles Dickens</centre>
<centre>Charles Allston Collins</centre>
<centre>Rosa Mulholland</centre>
<centre>Henry Spicer</centre>
<centre>Amelia Edwards</centre>
<centre>Hesba Stretton</centre>
</prefix>

<part>
<info title="MRS. LIRRIPER RELATES HOW SHE WENT ON, AND WENT OVER."/>
<chapter>
<p>Ah! It's pleasant to drop into my own easy-chair 
my dear though a little palpitating what 
with trotting up-stairs and what with trotting 
down, and why kitchen-stairs should all be corner 
stairs is for the builders to justify though I do 
not think they fully understand their trade and 
never did, else why the sameness and why not 
more conveniences and fewer draughts and likewise 
making a practice of laying the plaster on 
too thick I am well convinced which holds the 
damp, and as to chimney-pots putting them on 
by guess-work like hats at a party and no more 
knowing what their effect will be upon the 
smoke bless you than I do if so much, except 
that it will mostly be either to send it down 
your throat in a straight form or give it a 
twist before it goes there. And what I says speaking 
as I find of those new metal chimneys all 
manner of shapes (there's a row of 'em at Miss 
Wozenham's lodging-house lower down on the 
other side of the way) is that they only work your 
smoke into artificial patterns for you before you 
swallow it and that I'd quite as soon swallow 
mine plain, the flavour being the same, not to 
mention the conceit of putting up signs on the 
top of your house to show the forms in which 
you take your smoke into your inside.</p>
<p>Being here before your eyes my dear in my 
own easy-chair in my own quiet room in my 
own Lodging House Number Eighty-one 
Norfolk-street Strand London situated midway between 
the City and St. James's--if anything is 
where it used to be with these hotels calling 
themselves Limited but called Unlimited by 
Major Jackman rising up everywhere and rising 
up into flagstaffs where they can't go any higher, 
but my mind of those monsters is give me a 
landlord's or landlady's wholesome face when I 
come off a journey and not a brass plate with an 
electrified number clicking out of it which it's not 
in nature can be glad to see me and to which I 
don't want to be hoisted like molasses at the 
Docks and left there telegraphing for help with 
the most ingenious instruments but quite in vain 
--being here my dear I have no call to mention 
that I am still in the Lodgings as a business 
hoping to die in the same and if agreeable to the 
clergy partly read over at Saint Clement's Danes 
and concluded in Hatfield churchyard when lying 
once again by my poor Lirriper ashes to ashes 
and dust to dust.</p>
<p>Neither should I tell you any news my dear in 
telling you that the Major is still a fixture in 
the Parlours quite as much so as the roof of the 
house, and that Jemmy is of boys the best and 
brightest and has ever had kept from him the 
cruel story of his poor pretty young mother Mrs. 
Edson being deserted in the second floor and 
dying in my arms, fully believing that I am his 
born Gran and him an orphan, though what with 
engineering since he took a taste for it and him 
and the Major making Locomotives out of parasols 
broken iron pots and cotton-reels and them 
absolutely a getting off the line and falling over 
the table and injuring the passengers almost 
equal to the originals it really is quite wonderful. 
And when I says to the Major, "Major 
can't you by <em>any</em> means give us a communication 
with the guard?" the Major says quite 
huffy, "No madam it's not to be done," and 
when I says "Why not?" the Major says, 
"That is between us who are in the Railway 
Interest madam and our friend the Right 
Honourable Vice-President of the Board of Trade" 
and if you'll believe me my dear the Major 
wrote to Jemmy at school to consult him on 
the answer I should have before I could get even 
that amount of unsatisfactoriness out of the 
man, the reason being that when we first began 
with the little model and the working signals 
beautiful and perfect (being in general as wrong 
as the real) and when I says laughing "What 
appointment am I to hold in this undertaking 
gentlemen?" Jemmy hugs me round the neck 
and tells me dancing, "You shall be the Public 
Gran" and consequently they put upon me just 
as much as ever they like and I sit a growling 
in my easy-chair.</p>
<p>My dear whether it is that a grown man as 
clever as the Major cannot give half his heart and 
mind to anything--even a plaything--but must 
get into right down earnest with it, whether it is 
so or whether it is not so I do not undertake to 
say, but Jemmy is far outdone by the serious 
and believing ways of the Major in the management 
of the United Grand Junction Lirriper 
and Jackman Great Norfolk Parlour Line, 
"For" says my Jemmy with the sparkling 
eyes when it was christened, "we must have a 
whole mouthful of name Gran or our dear old 
Public" and there the young rogue kissed me, 
"won't stump up." So the Public took the shares 
--ten at ninepence, and immediately when that 
was spent twelve Preference at one-and-sixpence 
--and they were all signed by Jemmy and 
countersigned by the Major, and between ourselves 
much better worth the money than some shares 
I have paid for in my time. In the same holidays 
the line was made and worked and opened 
and ran excursions and had collisions and burst 
its boilers and all sorts of accidents and offences 
all most regular correct and pretty. The sense of 
responsibility entertained by the Major as a military 
style of station-master my dear starting the 
down train behind time and ringing one of those 
little bells that you buy with the little coal-scuttles 
off the tray round the man's neck in 
the street did him honour, but noticing the 
Major of a night when he is writing out his 
monthly report to Jemmy at school of the state 
of the Rolling Stock and the Permanent Way 
and all the rest of it (the whole kept upon the 
Major's sideboard and dusted with his own 
hands every morning before varnishing his boots) 
I notice him as full of thought and care as full 
can be and frowning in a fearful manner, but 
indeed the Major does nothing by halves as 
witness his great delight in going out surveying with 
Jemmy when he has Jemmy to go with, carrying 
a chain and a measuring tape and driving I don't 
know what improvements right through Westminster 
Abbey and fully believed in the streets 
to be knocking everything upside down by Act 
of Parliament. As please Heaven will come to 
pass when Jemmy takes to that as a profession!</p>
<p>Mentioning my poor Lirriper brings into my 
head his own youngest brother the Doctor 
though Doctor of what I am sure it would be 
hard to say unless Liquor, for neither Physic nor 
Music nor yet Law does Joshua Lirriper know a 
morsel of except continually being summoned to 
the County Court and having orders made upon 
him which he runs away from, and once was taken 
in the passage of this very house with an 
umbrella up and the Major's hat on, giving his 
name with the door-mat round him as Sir Johnson 
Jones K.C.B. in spectacles residing at the 
Horse Guards. On which occasion he had got into 
the house not a minute before, through the girl 
letting him on to the mat when he sent in a piece 
of paper twisted more like one of those spills 
for lighting candles than a note, offering me the 
choice between thirty shillings in hand and his 
brains on the premises marked immediate and 
waiting for an answer. My dear it gave me such 
a dreadful turn to think of the brains of my 
poor dear Lirriper's own flesh and blood flying 
about the new oilcloth however unworthy to be 
so assisted, that I went out of my room here to 
ask him what he would take once for all not to 
do it for life when I found him in the custody 
of two gentlemen that I should have judged to 
be in the feather-bed trade if they had not 
announced the law, so fluffy were their personal 
appearance. "Bring your chains sir," says 
Joshua to the littlest of the two in the biggest 
hat, "rivet on my fetters!" Imagine my feelings 
when I pictered him clanking up Norfolk-street 
in irons and Miss Wozenham looking out 
of window! "Gentlemen" I says all of a 
tremble and ready to drop "please to bring him 
into Major Jackman's apartments." So they 
brought him into the Parlours, and when the 
Major spies his own curly-brimmed hat on him 
which Joshua Lirriper had whipped off its peg in 
the passage for a military disguise he goes into 
such a tearing passion that he tips it off his head 
with his hand and kicks it up to the ceiling 
with his foot where it grazed long afterwards. 
"Major" I says "be cool and advise me what to 
do with Joshua my dead and gone Lirriper's own 
youngest brother." "Madam" says the Major 
"my advice is that you board and lodge him in a 
Powder Mill, with a handsome gratuity to the 
proprietor when exploded." "Major" I says "as 
a Christian you cannot mean your words." 
"Madam" says the Major "by the Lord I do!" and 
indeed the Major besides being with all his 
merits a very passionate man for his size had 
a bad opinion of Joshua on account of former 
troubles even unattended by liberties taken with 
his apparel. When Joshua Lirriper hears this 
conversation betwixt us he turns upon the 
littlest one with the biggest hat and says "Come 
sir! Remove me to my vile dungeon. Where is 
my mouldy straw!" My dear at the picter of 
him rising in my mind dressed almost entirely 
in padlocks like Baron Trenck in Jemmy's book 
I was so overcome that I burst into tears and I 
says to the Major, "Major take my keys and 
settle with these gentlemen or I shall never 
know a happy minute more," which was done 
several times both before and since, but still I 
must remember that Joshua Lirriper has his 
good feelings and shows them in being always 
so troubled in his mind when he cannot wear 
mourning for his brother. Many a long year 
have I left off my widow's mourning not being 
wishful to intrude, but the tender point in 
Joshua that I cannot help a little yielding to is 
when he writes "One single sovereign would 
enable me to wear a decent suit of mourning for 
my much-loved brother. I vowed at the time of 
his lamented death that I would ever wear 
sables in memory of him but Alas how short-sighted 
is man, How keep that vow when 
penniless!" It says a good deal for the strength 
of his feelings that he couldn't have been seven 
year old when my poor Lirriper died and to 
have kept to it ever since is highly creditable. 
But we know there's good in all of us--if we 
only knew where it was in some of us--and though 
it was far from delicate in Joshua to work upon 
the dear child's feelings when first sent to 
school and write down into Lincolnshire for his 
pocket-money by return of post and got it, still 
he is my poor Lirriper's own youngest brother 
and mightn't have meant not paying his bill at 
the Salisbury Arms when his affection took 
him down to stay a fortnight at Hatfield 
churchyard and might have meant to keep sober 
but for bad company. Consequently if the Major 
had played on him with the garden-engine which 
he got privately into his room without my 
knowing of it, I think that much as I should 
have regretted it there would have been words 
betwixt the Major and me. Therefore my dear 
though he played on Mr. Buffle by mistake being 
hot in his head, and though it might have been 
misrepresented down at Wozenham's into not 
being ready for Mr. Buffle in other respects he 
being the Assessed Taxes, still I do not so much 
regret it as perhaps I ought. And whether Joshua 
Lirriper will yet do well in life I cannot say, 
but I did hear of his coming out at a Private 
Theatre in the character of a Bandit without 
receiving any offers afterwards from the regular 
managers.</p>
<p>Mentioning Mr. Buffle gives an instance of 
there being good in persons where good is not 
expected, for it cannot be denied that Mr. 
Buffle's manners when engaged in his business 
were not agreeable. To collect is one thing 
and to look about as if suspicious of the 
goods being gradually removing in the dead of 
the night by a back door is another, over taxing 
you have no control but suspecting is voluntary. 
Allowances too must ever be made for a 
gentleman of the Major's warmth not relishing being 
spoke to with a pen in the mouth, and while I 
do not know that it is more irritable to my own 
feelings to have a low-crowned hat with a broad 
brim kept on in-doors than any other hat still I 
can appreciate the Major's, besides which without 
bearing malice or vengeance the Major is a man 
that scores up arrears as his habit always was 
with Joshua Lirriper. So at last my dear 
the Major lay in wait for Mr. Buffle and it 
worrited me a good deal. Mr. Buffle gives his 
rap of two sharp knocks one day and the 
Major bounces to the door. "Collector has 
called for two quarters' Assessed Taxes" says 
Mr. Buffle. "They are ready for him" says the 
Major and brings him in here. But on the way 
Mr. Buffle looks about him in his usual suspicious 
manner and the Major fires and asks him "Do you 
see a Ghost sir?" "No sir" says Mr. Buffle. 
"Because I have before noticed you" says the 
Major "apparently looking for a spectre very hard 
beneath the roof of my respected friend. When 
you find that supernatural agent, be so good as 
point him out sir." Mr. Buffle stares at the 
Major and then nods at me. "Mrs. Lirriper 
sir" says the Major going off into a perfect 
steam and introducing me with his hand. 
"Pleasure of knowing her" says Mr. Buffle. 
"A--hum!--Jemmy Jackman sir!" says the 
Major introducing himself. "Honour of knowing 
you by sight" says Mr. Buffle. "Jemmy 
Jackman sir" says the Major wagging his head 
sideways in a sort of an obstinate fury "presents 
to you his esteemed friend that lady Mrs. Emma 
Lirriper of Eighty-one Norfolk-street Strand 
London in the County of Middlesex in the United 
Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland. Upon 
which occasion sir," says the Major, "Jemmy 
Jackman takes your hat off." Mr. Buffle looks 
at his hat where the Major drops it on the floor, 
and he picks it up and puts it on again. "Sir" 
says the Major very red and looking him full in 
the face "there are two quarters of the Gallantry 
Taxes due and the Collector has called." Upon 
which if you can believe my words my dear the 
Major drops Mr. Buffle's hat off again. "This--" 
Mr. Buffle begins very angry with his pen in his 
mouth, when the Major steaming more and more 
says "Take your bit out sir! Or by the whole 
infernal system of Taxation of this country and 
every individual figure in the National Debt, I'll 
get upon your back and ride you like a horse!" 
which it's my belief he would have done and 
even actually jerking his neat little legs ready 
for a spring as it was. "This" says Mr. Buffle 
without his pen "is an assault and I'll have the 
law of you." "Sir" replies the Major "if you 
are a man of honour, your Collector of whatever 
may be due on the Honourable Assessment by 
applying to Major Jackman at The Parlours 
Mrs. Lirriper's Lodgings, may obtain what he 
wants in full at any moment."</p>
<p>When the Major glared at Mr. Buffle with 
those meaning words my dear I literally gasped 
for a teaspoonful of sal volatile in a wine-glass 
of water, and I says "Pray let it go no further 
gentlemen I beg and beseech of you!" But 
the Major could be got to do nothing else but 
snort long after Mr. Buffle was gone, and the 
effect it had upon my whole mass of blood when 
on the next day of Mr. Buffle's rounds the 
Major spruced himself up and went humming a 
tune up and down the street with one eye 
almost obliterated by his hat there are not 
expressions in Johnson's Dictionary to state. But 
I safely put the street door on the jar and got 
behind the Major's blinds with my shawl on 
and my mind made up the moment I saw danger 
to rush out screeching till my voice failed me 
and catch the Major round the neck till my 
strength went and have all parties bound. I 
had not been behind the blinds a quarter of an 
hour when I saw Mr. Buffle approaching with his 
Collecting-books in his hand. The Major likewise 
saw him approaching and hummed louder and 
himself approached. They met before the Airy 
railings. The Major takes off his hat at arm's 
length and says "Mr. Buffle I believe?" Mr. 
Buffle takes off <em>his</em> hat at arm's length and says 
"That is my name sir." Says the Major "Have 
you any commands for me, Mr. Buffle?" Says 
Mr. Buffle "Not any sir." Then my dear both 
of 'em bowed very low and haughty and parted, 
and whenever Mr. Buffle made his rounds in 
future him and the Major always met and bowed 
before the Airy railings, putting me much in 
mind of Hamlet and the other gentleman in 
mourning before killing one another, though I 
could have wished the other gentleman had done 
it fairer and even if less polite no poison.</p>
<p>Mr. Buffle's family were not liked in this 
neighbourhood, for when you are a householder 
my dear you'll find it does not come by nature 
to like the Assessed, and it was considered 
besides that a one-horse pheayton ought not to 
have elevated Mrs. Buffle to that heighth 
especially when purloined from the Taxes which I 
myself did consider uncharitable. But they 
were <em>not</em> liked and there was that domestic 
unhappiness in the family in consequence of their 
both being very hard with Miss Buffle and one 
another on account of Miss Buffle's favouring 
Mr. Buffle's articled young gentleman, that it 
<em>was</em> whispered that Miss Buffle would go either 
into a consumption or a convent she being so 
very thin and off her appetite and two 
close-shaved gentlemen with white bands round their 
necks peeping round the corner whenever she 
went out in waistcoats resembling black 
pinafores. So things stood towards Mr. Buffle 
when one night I was woke by a frightful noise 
and a smell of burning, and going to my 
bed-room window saw the whole street in a glow. 
Fortunately we had two sets empty just then 
and before I could hurry on some clothes I 
heard the Major hammering at the attics' doors 
and calling out "Dress yourselves!--Fire! 
Don't be frightened!--Fire! Collect your 
presence of mind!--Fire! All right--Fire!" 
most tremenjously. As I opened my bedroom 
door the Major came tumbling in over himself 
and me and caught me in his arms. "Major" 
I says breathless "where is it?" "I don't 
know dearest madam" says the Major--"Fire! 
Jemmy Jackman will defend you to the last 
drop of his blood--Fire! If the dear boy was 
at home what a treat this would be for him--
Fire!" and altogether very collected and bold 
except that he couldn't say a single sentence 
without shaking me to the very centre with 
roaring Fire. We ran down to the drawing-room 
and put our heads out of window, and the 
Major calls to an unfeeling young monkey 
scampering by be joyful and ready to split 
"Where is it?--Fire!" The monkey answers 
without stopping "Oh here's a lark! Old 
Buffle's been setting his house alight to prevent 
its being found out that he boned the Taxes. 
Hurrah! Fire!" And then the sparks came 
flying up and the smoke came pouring down 
and the crackling of flames and spatting of 
water and banging of engines and hacking of 
axes and breaking of glass and knocking at 
doors and the shouting and crying and hurrying 
and the heat and altogether gave me a dreadful 
palpitation. "Don't be frightened dearest 
madam," says the Major, "--Fire! There's 
nothing to be alarmed at--Fire! Don't open the 
street door till I come back--Fire! I'll go and 
see if I can be of any service--Fire! You're 
quite composed and comfortable ain't you?--
Fire, Fire, Fire!" It was in vain for me to 
hold the man and tell him he'd be galloped to 
death by the engines--pumped to death by his 
over-exertions--wet-feeted to death by the slop 
and mess--flattened to death when the roofs fell 
in--his spirit was up and he went scampering 
off after the young monkey with all the breath 
ho had and none to spare, and me and the girls 
huddled together at the parlour windows looking 
at the dreadful flames above the houses over 
the way, Mr. Buffle's being round the corner. 
Presently what should we see but some people 
running down the street straight to our door, 
and then the Major directing operations in the 
busiest way, and then some more people and 
then--carried in a chair similar to Guy Fawkes 
--Mr. Buffle in a blanket!</p>
<p>My dear the Major has Mr. Buffle brought 
up our steps and whisked into the parlour and 
carted out on the sofy, and then he and all the 
rest of them without so much as a word burst 
away again full speed, leaving the impression of 
a vision except for Mr. Buffle awful in his blanket 
with his eyes a rolling. In a twinkling they all 
burst back again with Mrs. Buffle in another 
blanket, which whisked in and carted out on the 
sofy they all burst off again and all burst back 
again with Miss Buffle in another blanket, which 
again whisked in and carted out they all burst 
off again and all burst back again with Mr. 
Buffle's articled young gentleman in another 
blanket--him a holding round the necks of two 
men carrying him by the legs, similar to the 
picter of the disgraceful creetur who has lost the 
fight (but where the chair I do not know) and 
his hair having the appearance of newly played 
upon. When all four of a row, the Major rubs 
his hands and whispers me with what little 
hoarseness he can get together, "If our dear 
remarkable boy was only at home what a 
delightful treat this would be for him!"</p>
<p>My dear we made them some hot tea and 
toast and some hot brandy-and-water with a 
little comfortable nutmeg in it, and at first they 
were scared and low in their spirits but being 
fully insured got sociable. And the first use Mr. 
Buffle made of his tongue was to call the Major 
his Preserver and his best of friends and to say 
"My for ever dearest sir let me make you 
known to Mrs. Buffle" which also addressed 
him as her Preserver and her best of friends and 
was fully as cordial as the blanket would admit 
of. Also Miss Buffle. The articled young gentleman's 
head was a little light and he sat a moaning 
"Robina is reduced to cinders, Robina is 
reduced to cinders!" Which went more to the 
heart on account of his having got wrapped in 
his blanket as if he was looking out of a violin-celler-case, 
until Mr. Buffle says "Robina speak 
to him!" Miss Buffle says "Dear George!" and 
but for the Major's pouring down brandy-and-water 
on the instant which caused a catching in 
his throat owing to the nutmeg and a violent 
fit of coughing it might have proved too much 
for his strength. When the articled young 
gentleman got the better of it Mr. Buffle leaned 
up against Mrs. Buffle being two bundles, a 
little while in confidence, and then says with 
tears in his eyes which the Major noticing wiped, 
"We have not been an united family, let us 
after this danger become so, take her George." 
The young gentleman could not put his arm out 
far to do it, but his spoken expressions were 
very beautiful though of a wandering class. 
And I do not know that I ever had a much 
pleasanter meal than the breakfast we took 
together after we had all dozed, when Miss Buffle 
made tea very sweetly in quite the Roman style 
as depicted formerly at Covent Garden Theatre 
and when the whole family was most agreeable, 
as they have ever proved since that night when 
the Major stood at the foot of the Fire-Escape 
and claimed them as they came down--the young 
gentleman headforemost, which accounts. And 
though I do not say that we should be less liable 
to think ill of one another if strictly limited to 
blankets, still I do say that we might most of us 
come to a better understanding if we kept one 
another less at a distance.</p>
<p>Why there's Wozenham's lower down on the 
other side of the street. I had a feeling of much 
soreness several years respecting what I must 
still ever call Miss Wozenham's systematic 
underbidding and the likeness of the house in 
Bradshaw having far too many windows and a 
most umbrageous and outrageous Oak which 
never yet was seen in Norfolk-street nor yet a 
carriage and four at Wozenham's door, which it 
would have been far more to Bradshaw's credit 
to have drawn a cab. This frame of mind 
continued bitter down to the very afternoon in 
January last when one of my girls, Sally 
Rairyganoo which I still suspect of Irish extraction 
though family represented Cambridge, else why 
abscond with a bricklayer of the Limerick 
persuasion and be married in pattens not waiting 
till his black eye was decently got round with all 
the company fourteen in number and one horse 
fighting outside on the roof of the vehicle--I 
repeat my dear my ill-regulated state of mind 
towards Miss Wozenham continued down to the 
very afternoon of January last past when Sally 
Rairyganoo came banging (I can use no milder 
expression) into my room with a jump which may 
be Cambridge and may not, and said "Hurroo 
Missis! Miss Wozenham's sold up!" My dear 
when I had it thrown in my face and 
conscience that the girl Sally had reason to think 
I could be glad of the ruin of a fellow-creeter, I 
burst into tears and dropped back in my chair 
and I says "I am ashamed of myself!"</p>
<p>Well! I tried to settle to my tea but I 
could not do it what with thinking of Miss 
Wozenham and her distresses. It was a wretched 
night and I went up to a front window and 
looked over at Wozenham's and as well as I 
could make it out down the street in the fog it 
was the dismalest of the dismal and not a light 
to be seen. So at last I says to myself "This 
will not do," and I puts on my oldest bonnet 
and shawl not wishing Miss Wozenham to be 
reminded of my best at such a time, and lo and 
behold you I goes over to Wozenham's and knocks. 
"Miss Wozenham at home?" I says turning my 
head when I heard the door go. And then I saw 
it was Miss Wozenham herself who had opened 
it and sadly worn she was poor thing and her 
eyes all swelled and swelled with crying. "Miss 
Wozenham" I says "it is several years since 
there was a little unpleasantness betwixt us on 
the subject of my grandson's cap being down 
your Airy. I have overlooked it and I hope you 
have done the same." "Yes Mrs. Lirriper" she 
says in a surprise "I have." "Then my dear" 
I says "I should be glad to come in and speak 
a word to you." Upon my calling her my dear 
Miss Wozenham breaks out a crying most pitiful, 
and a not unfeeling elderly person that 
might have been better shaved in a nightcap 
with a hat over it offering a polite apology for 
the mumps having worked themselves into 
his constitution, and also for sending home to 
his wife on the bellows which was in his hand 
as a writing-desk, looks out of the back parlour 
and says "The lady wants a word of comfort" 
and goes in again. So I was able to say quite 
natural "Wants a word of comfort does she sir? 
Then please the pigs she shall have it!" And Miss 
Wozenham and me we go into the front room with 
a wretched light that seemed to have been crying 
too and was sputtering out, and I says "Now 
my dear, tell me all," and she wrings her hands 
and says "Oh Mrs. Lirriper that man is in 
possession here, and I have not a friend in the 
world who is able to help me with a shilling."</p>
<p>It doesn't signify a bit what a talkative old 
body like me said to Miss Wozenham when she 
said that, and so I'll tell you instead my dear that 
I'd have given thirty shillings to have taken her 
over to tea, only I durstn't on account of the 
Major. Not you see but what I knew I could 
draw the Major out like thread and wind him 
round my linger on most subjects and perhaps 
even on that if I was to set myself to it, but him 
and me had so often belied Miss Wozenham to one 
another that I was shamefaced, and I knew she 
had offended his pride and never mine, and likewise 
I felt timid that that Rairyganoo girl might 
make things awkward. So I says "My dear 
if you could give me a cup of tea to clear my 
muddle of a head I should better understand 
your affairs." And we had the tea and the 
affairs too and after all it was but forty pound, 
and----There! she's as industrious and straight 
a creeter as ever lived and has paid back half of 
it already, and where's the use of saying more, 
particularly when it ain't the point? For the 
point is that when she was a kissing my hands 
and holding them in hers and kissing them again 
and blessing blessing blessing, I cheered up at 
last and I says "Why what a waddling old 
goose I have been my dear to take you for 
something so very different!" "Ah but I too" 
says she "how have <em>I</em> mistaken <em>you</em>!" "Come 
for goodness' sake tell me" I says "what you. 
thought of me?" "Oh" says she "I thought 
you had no feeling for such a hard hand-to-mouth 
life as mine, and were rolling in 
affluence." I says shaking my sides (and very 
glad to do it for I had been a choking quite long 
enough) "Only look at my figure my dear and 
give me your opinion whether if I was in 
affluence I should be likely to roll in it!" That 
did it! We got as merry as grigs (whatever 
<em>they</em> are, if you happen to know my dear--<em>I</em> 
don't) and I went home to my blessed home as 
happy and as thankful as could be. But before 
I make an end of it, think even of my having 
misunderstood the Major! Yes! For next 
forenoon the Major came into my little room 
with his brushed hat in his hand and he begins 
"My dearest madam----" and then put his 
face in his hat as if he had just come into 
church. As I sat all in a maze he came out of 
his hat and began again. "My esteemed and 
beloved friend----" and then went into his hat 
again. "Major," I cries out frightened "has 
anything happened to our darling boy?" "No, 
no, no" says the Major "but Miss Wozenham 
has been here this morning to make her excuses 
to me, and by the Lord I can't get over what she 
told me." "Hoity toity, Major," I says "you 
don't know yet that I was afraid of you last night 
and didn't think half as well of you as I ought! 
So come out of church Major and forgive me 
like a dear old friend and I'll never do so any 
more." And I leave you to judge my dear 
whether I ever did or will. And how affecting 
to think of Miss Wozenham out of her small 
income and her losses doing so much for her poor 
old father, and keeping a brother that had had the 
misfortune to soften his brain against the hard 
mathematics as neat as a new pin in the three 
back represented to lodgers as a lumber-room 
and consuming a whole shoulder of mutton 
whenever provided!</p>
<p>And now my dear I really am a going to tell 
you about my Legacy if you're inclined to favour 
me with your attention, and I did fully intend to 
have come straight to it only one thing does so 
bring up another. It was the month of June 
and the day before Midsummer Day when my 
girl Winifred Madgers--she was what is termed 
a Plymouth Sister, and the Plymouth Brother 
that made away with her was quite right, for a 
tidier young woman for a wife never came into 
a house and afterwards called with the 
beautifullest Plymouth Twins--it was the day 
before Midsummer Day when Winifred Madgers 
comes and says to me "A gentleman from the 
Consul's wishes particular to speak to Mrs. 
Lirriper." If you'll believe me my dear the 
Consols at the bank where I have a little 
matter for Jemmy got into my head, and I says 
"Good gracious I hope he ain't had any dreadful 
fall!" Says Winifred "He don't look as if 
he had ma'am." And I says "Show him in."</p>
<p>The gentleman came in dark and with his hair 
cropped what I should consider too close, and he 
says very polite "Madame Lirrwiper!" I says 
"Yes sir. Take a chair." "I come," says he 
"frrwom the Frrwench Consul's." So I saw 
at once that it wasn't the Bank of England. 
"We have rrweceived," says the gentleman 
turning his r's very curious and skilful, "frrwom 
the Mairrwie at Sens, a communication which I 
will have the honour to rrwead. Madame 
Lirrwiper understands Frrwench?" "Oh dear no 
sir!" says I. "Madame Lirriper don't understand 
anything of the sort." "It matters not," 
says the gentleman, "I will trrwanslate."</p>
<p>With that my dear the gentleman after reading 
something about a Department and a Mairie 
(which Lord forgive me I supposed till the 
Major came home was Mary, and never was I 
more puzzled than to think how that young 
woman came to have so much to do with it) 
translated a lot with the most obliging pains, 
and it came to this:--That in the town of Sens 
in France, an unknown Englishman lay a dying. 
That he was speechless and without motion. That 
in his lodging there was a gold watch and a purse 
containing such and such money and a trunk 
containing such and such clothes, but no passport 
and no papers, except that on his table was a pack 
of cards and that he had written in pencil on the 
back of the ace of hearts: "To the authorities. 
When I am dead, pray send what is left, as a last 
Legacy, to Mrs. Lirriper Eighty-one Norfolk-street 
Strand London." When the gentleman had 
explained all this, which seemed to be drawn up 
much more methodical than I should have given 
the French credit for, not at that time knowing 
the nation, he put the document into my hand. 
And much the wiser I was for that you may be 
sure, except that it had the look of being made 
out upon grocery-paper and was stamped all over 
with eagles.</p>
<p>"Does Madame Lirrwiper" says the gentleman 
"believe she rrwecognises her unfortunate 
compatrrwiot?"</p>
<p>You may imagine the flurry it put me into 
my dear to be talked to about my compatriots.</p>
<p>I says "Excuse me. Would you have the 
kindness sir to make your language as simple as 
you can?"</p>
<p>"This Englishman unhappy, at the point of 
death. This compatrrwiot afflicted," says the 
gentleman.</p>
<p>"Thank you sir" I says "I understand you 
now. No sir I have not the least idea who 
this can be."</p>
<p>"Has Madame Lirrwiper no son, no nephew, 
no godson, no frrwiend, no acquaintance of any 
kind in Frrwance?"</p>
<p>"To my certain knowledge" says I "no 
relation or friend, and to the best of my belief no 
acquaintance."</p>
<p>"Pardon me. You take Locataires?" says 
the gentleman.</p>
<p>My dear fully believing he was offering me 
something with his obliging foreign manners--
snuff for anything I knew--I gave a little bend 
of my head and I says if you'll credit it, "No I 
thank you. I have not contracted the habit."</p>
<p>The gentleman looks perplexed and says 
"Lodgers?"</p>
<p>"Oh!" says I laughing. "Bless the man! 
Why yes to be sure!"</p>
<p>"May it not be a former lodger?" says the 
gentleman. "Some lodger that you pardoned 
some rrwent? You have pardoned lodgers 
some rrwent?"</p>
<p>"Hem! It has happened sir" says I, "but I 
assure you I can call to mind no gentleman of 
that description that this is at all likely to be."</p>
<p>In short my dear we could make nothing of 
it, and the gentleman noted down what I said 
and went away. But he left me the paper of 
which he had two with him, and when the Major 
came in I says to the Major as I put it in his hand 
"Major here's Old Moore's Almanack with the 
hieroglyphic complete, for your opinion."</p>
<p>It took the Major a little longer to read than 
I should have thought, judging from the copious 
flow with which he seemed to be gifted when 
attacking the organ-men, but at last he got 
through it and stood a gazing at me in amazement.</p>
<p>"Major" I says "you're paralysed."</p>
<p>"Madam" says the Major, "Jemmy Jackman 
is doubled up."</p>
<p>Now it did so happen that the Major had 
been out to get a little information about 
railroads and steam-boats, as our boy was coming 
home for his Midsummer holidays next day and 
we were going to take him somewhere for a 
treat and a change. So while the Major stood 
a gazing it came into my head to say to him 
"Major I wish you'd go and look at some of your 
books and maps, and see whereabouts this same 
town of Sens is in France."</p>
<p>The Major he roused himself and he went 
into the Parlours and he poked about a little, 
and he came back to me and lie says: "Sens 
my dearest madam is seventy odd miles south 
of Paris."</p>
<p>With what I may truly call a desperate effort 
"Major" I says "we'll go there with our 
blessed boy!"</p>
<p>If ever the Major was beside himself it was 
at the thoughts of that journey. All day long 
he was like the wild man of the woods after 
meeting with an advertisement in the papers 
telling him something to his advantage, and 
early next morning hours before Jemmy could 
possibly come home he was outside in the street 
ready to call out to him that we was all a going 
to France. Young Rosy-cheeks you may 
believe was as wild as the Major, and they did 
carry on to that degree that I says "If you two 
children ain't more orderly I'll pack you both 
off to bed." And then they fell to cleaning up 
the Major's telescope to see France with, and 
went out and bought a leather bag with a snap 
to hang round Jemmy, and him to carry the 
money like a little Fortunatus with his purse.</p>
<p>If I hadn't passed my word and raised their 
hopes, I doubt if I could have gone through with 
the undertaking but it was too late to go back 
now. So on the second day after Midsummer 
Day we went off by the morning mail. And 
when we came to the sea which I had never 
seen but once in my life and that when my poor 
Lirriper was courting me, the freshness of it 
and the deepness and the airiness and to think 
that it had been rolling ever since and that it 
was always a rolling and so few of us minding, 
made me feel quite serious. But I felt happy 
too and so did Jemmy and the Major and not 
much motion on the whole, though me with a 
swimming in the head and a sinking but able to 
take notice that the foreign insides appear to 
be constructed hollower than the English, leading 
to much more tremenjous noises when bad 
sailors.</p>
<p>But my dear the blueness and the lightness 
and the coloured look of everything and the very 
sentry-boxes striped and the shining rattling 
drums and the little soldiers with their waists 
and tidy gaiters, when we got across to the 
Continentit made me feel as if I don't know 
what--as if the atmosphere had been lifted off 
me. And as to lunch why bless you if I kept a 
man-cook and two kitchen-maids I couldn't get it 
done for twice the money, and no injured young 
women a glaring at you and grudging you and 
acknowledging your patronage by wishing that 
your food might choke you, but so civil and so 
hot and attentive and every way comfortable 
except Jemmy pouring wine down his throat by 
tumblers-full and me expecting to see him drop 
under the table.</p>
<p>And the way in which Jemmy spoke his 
French was a real charm. It was often wanted 
of him, for whenever anybody spoke a syllable to 
me I says "Noncomprenny, you're very kind 
but it's no use--Now Jemmy!" and then 
Jemmy he fires away at 'em lovely, the only 
thing wanting in Jemmy's French being as it 
appeared to me that he hardly ever understood 
a word of what they said to him which made it 
scarcely of the use it might have been though 
in other respects a perfect Native, and regarding 
the Major's fluency I should have been of 
the opinion judging French by English that 
there might have been a greater choice of words 
in the language though still I must admit that 
if I hadn't known him when he asked a 
military gentleman in a grey cloak what o'clock it 
was I should have took him for a Frenchman 
born.</p>
<p>Before going on to look after my Legacy we 
were to make one regular day in Paris, and I 
leave you to judge my dear what a day <em>that</em> was 
with Jemmy and the Major and the telescope 
and me and the prowling young man at the inn 
door (but very civil too) that went along with us 
to show the sights. All along the railway to Paris 
Jemmy and the Major had been frightening 
me to death by stooping down on the platforms 
at stations to inspect the engines underneath 
their mechanical stomachs, and by creeping in 
and out I don't know where all, to find improvements 
for the United Grand Junction Parlour, 
but when we got out into the brilliant streets 
on a bright morning they gave up all their 
London improvements as a bad job and gave 
their minds to Paris. Says the prowling young 
man to me "Will I speak Inglis No?" So I 
says "If you can young man I shall take it as 
a favour," but after half an hour of it when I 
fully believed the man had gone mad and me too 
I says "Be so good as fall back on your French 
sir," knowing that then I shouldn't have the 
agonies of trying to understand him which was 
a happy release. Not that I lost much more 
than the rest either, for I generally noticed that 
when he had described something very long 
indeed and I says to Jemmy "What does he 
say Jemmy?" Jemmy says looking at him with 
vengeance in his eye "He is so jolly 
indistinct!" and that when he had described it 
longer all over again and I says to Jemmy 
"Well Jemmy what's it all about?" Jemmy 
says "He says the building was repaired in 
seventeen hundred and four, Gran."</p>
<p>Wherever that prowling young man formed 
his prowling habits I cannot be expected to 
know, but the way in which he went round the 
corner while we had our breakfasts and was 
there again when we swallowed the last crumb 
was most marvellous, and just the same at dinner 
and at night, prowling equally at the theatre 
and the inn gateway and the shop-doors when 
we bought a trifle or two and everywhere else 
but troubled with a tendency to spit. And of 
Paris I can tell you no more my dear than that 
it's town and country both in one, and carved 
stone and long streets of high houses and 
gardens and fountains and statues and trees and 
gold, and immensely big soldiers and immensely 
little soldiers and the pleasantest nurses with 
the whitest caps a playing at skipping-rope with 
the bunchiest babies in the flattest caps, and 
clean tablecloths spread everywhere for dinner 
and people sitting out of doors smoking and 
sipping all day long and little plays being acted 
in the open air for little people and every shop a 
complete and elegant room, and everybody 
seeming to play at everything in this world. 
And as to the sparkling lights my dear after 
dark, glittering high up and low down and on 
before and on behind and all round, and the crowd 
of theatres and the crowd of people and the 
crowd of all sorts, it's pure enchantment. And 
pretty well the only thing that grated on me 
was that whether you pay your fare at the 
railway or whether you change your money at a 
money-dealer's or whether you take your ticket 
at the theatre, the lady or gentleman is caged 
up (I suppose by Government) behind the 
strongest iron bars having more of a Zoological 
appearance than a free country.</p>
<p>Well to be sure when I did after all get my 
precious bones to bed that night, and my Young 
Rogue came in to kiss me and asks "What do 
you think of this lovely lovely Paris, Gran?" I 
says "Jemmy I feel as if it was beautiful fireworks 
being let off in my head." And very cool 
and refreshing the pleasant country was next 
day when we went on to look after my Legacy, 
and rested me much and did me a deal of good.</p>
<p>So at length and at last my dear we come to 
Sens, a pretty little town with a great 
two-towered cathedral and the rooks flying in and 
out of the loopholes and another tower atop of 
one of the towers like a sort of a stone pulpit. 
In which pulpit with the birds skimming below 
him if you'll believe me, I saw a speck while I 
was resting at the inn before dinner which 
they made signs to me was Jemmy and which 
really was. I had been a fancying as I sat in 
the balcony of the hotel that an Angel might 
light there and call down to the people to be 
good, but I little thought what Jemmy all 
unknown to himself was a calling down from that 
high place to some one in the town.</p>
<p>The pleasantest-situated inn my dear! Right 
under the two towers, with their shadows a 
changing upon it all day like a kind of a 
sundial, and country people driving in and out of 
the court-yard in carts and hooded cabriolets and 
such-like, and a market outside in front of the 
cathedral, and all so quaint and like a picter. 
The Major and me agreed that whatever came 
of my Legacy this was the place to stay in for 
our holiday, and we also agreed that our dear 
boy had best not be checked in his joy that night 
by the sight of the Englishman if he was still 
alive, but that we would go together and alone. 
For you are to understand that the Major not 
feeling himself quite equal in his wind to the 
heighth to which Jemmy had climbed, had come 
back to me and left him with the Guide.</p>
<p>So after dinner when Jemmy had set off to 
see the river, the Major went down to the 
Mairie, and presently came back with a military 
character in a sword and spurs and a cocked-hat 
and a yellow shoulder-belt and long tags about 
him that he must have found inconvenient. And 
the Major says "The Englishman still lies in the 
same state dearest madam. This gentleman 
will conduct us to his lodging." Upon which 
the military character pulled off his cocked-hat 
to me, and I took notice that he had shaved his 
forehead in imitation of Napoleon Bonaparte but 
not like.</p>
<p>We went out at the court-yard gate and past 
the great doors of the cathedral and down a 
narrow High Street where the people were sitting 
chatting at their shop-doors and the children 
were at play. The military character went in 
front and he stopped at a pork-shop with a little 
statue of a pig sitting up, in the window, and a 
private door that a donkey was looking out of.</p>
<p>When the donkey saw the military character 
he came slipping out on the pavement to turn 
round and then clattered along the passage into 
a back-yard. So the coast being clear, the Major 
and me were conducted up the common stair 
and into the front room on the second, a bare 
room with a red tiled floor and the outside 
lattice blinds pulled close to darken it. As the 
military character opened the blinds I saw the 
tower where I had seen Jemmy, darkening as 
the sun got low, and I turned to the bed by the 
wall and saw the Englishman.</p>
<p>It was some kind of brain fever he had had, 
and his hair was all gone, and some wetted folded 
linen lay upon his head. I looked at him very 
attentive as he lay there all wasted away with 
his eyes closed, and I says to the Major</p>
<p>"I never saw this face before."</p>
<p>The Major looked at him very attentive too, 
and he says</p>
<p>"<em>I</em> never saw this face before."</p>
<p>When the Major explained our words to the 
military character, that gentleman shrugged his 
shoulders and showed the Major the card on 
which it was written about the Legacy for me. 
It had been written with a weak and trembling 
hand in bed, and I knew no more of the writing 
than of the face. Neither did the Major.</p>
<p>Though lying there alone, the poor creetur 
was as well taken care of as could be hoped, and 
would have been quite unconscious of any one's 
sitting by him then. I got the Major to say that 
we were not going away at present and that I 
would come back to-morrow and watch a bit by 
the bedside. But I got him to add--and I 
shook my head hard to make it stronger--"We 
agree that we never saw this face before."</p>
<p>Our boy was greatly surprised when we told 
him sitting out in the balcony in the starlight, 
and he ran over some of those stories of former 
Lodgers, of the Major's putting down, and asked 
wasn't it possible that it might be this lodger or 
that lodger. It was not possible and we went to 
bed.</p>
<p>In the morning just at breakfast-time the 
military character came jingling round, and said 
that the doctor thought from the signs he saw 
there might be some rally before the end. 
So I says to the Major and Jemmy, "You two 
boys go and enjoy yourselves, and I'll take my 
Prayer-Book and go sit by the bed." So I went, 
and I sat there some hours, reading a prayer for 
him poor soul now and then, and it was quite on 
in the day when he moved his hand.</p>
<p>He had been so still, that the moment he 
moved I knew of it, and I pulled off my 
spectacles and laid down my book and rose and 
looked at him. From moving one hand he began 
to move both, and then his action was the action 
of a person groping in the dark. Long after his 
eyes had opened, there was a film over them and 
he still felt for his way out into light. But 
by slow degrees his sight cleared and his hands 
stopped. He saw the ceiling, he saw the wall, 
he saw me. As his sight cleared, mine cleared 
too, and when at last we looked in one another's 
faces, I started back and I cries passionately:</p>
<p>"O you wicked wicked man! Your sin has 
found you out!"</p>
<p>For I knew him, the moment life looked out 
of his eyes, to be Mr. Edson, Jemmy's father 
who had so cruelly deserted Jemmy's young 
unmarried mother who had died in my arms, poor 
tender creetur, and left Jemmy to me.</p>
<p>"You cruel wicked man! You bad black 
traitor!"</p>
<p>With the little strength he had, he made an 
attempt to turn over on his wretched face to 
hide it. His arm dropped out of the bed 
and his head with it, and there he lay before 
me crushed in body and in mind. Surely the 
miserablest sight under the summer sun!</p>
<p>"O blessed Heaven" I says a crying, "teach 
me what to say to this broken mortal! I am 
a poor sinful creetur, and the Judgment is not 
mine."</p>
<p>As I lifted my eyes up to the clear bright 
sky, I saw the high tower where Jemmy had 
stood above the birds, seeing that very window; 
and the last look of that poor pretty young 
mother when her soul brightened and got free, 
seemed to shine down from it.</p>
<p>"O man, man, man!" I says, and I went on 
my knees beside the bed; "if your heart is rent 
asunder and you are truly penitent for what 
you did, Our Saviour will have mercy on you 
yet!"</p>
<p>As I leaned my face against the bed, his 
feeble hand could just move itself enough to 
touch me. I hope the touch was penitent. It 
tried to hold my dress and keep hold, but the 
fingers were too weak to close.</p>
<p>I lifted him back upon the pillows, and I says 
to him:</p>
<p>"Can you hear me?"</p>
<p>He looked yes.</p>
<p>"Do you know me?"</p>
<p>He looked yes, even yet more plainly.</p>
<p>"I am not here alone. The Major is with 
me. You recollect the Major?"</p>
<p>Yes. That is to say he made out yes, in the 
same way as before.</p>
<p>"And even the Major and I are not alone. 
My grandson--his godson--is with us. Do you 
hear? My grandson."</p>
<p>The fingers made another trial to catch at my 
sleeve, but could only creep near it and fall.</p>
<p>"Do you know who my grandson is?"</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>"I pitied and loved his lonely mother. When 
his mother lay a dying I said to her, 'My dear 
this baby is sent to a childless old woman.' He 
has been my pride and joy ever since. I love 
him as dearly as if he had drunk from my breast. 
Do you ask to see my grandson before you 
die?'</p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>"Show me, when I leave off speaking, if you 
correctly understand what I say. He has been 
kept unacquainted with the story of his birth. 
He has no knowledge of it. No suspicion of it. 
If I bring him here to the side of this bed, he 
will suppose you to be a perfect stranger. It 
is more than I can do, to keep from him the 
knowledge that there is such wrong and misery 
in the world; but that it was ever so near him 
in his innocent cradle, I have kept from him, 
and I do keep from him, and I ever will keep 
from him. For his mother's sake, and for his 
own."</p>
<p>He showed me that he distinctly understood, 
and the tears fell from his eyes.</p>
<p>"Now rest, and you shall see him."</p>
<p>So I got him a little wine and some brandy 
and I put things straight about his bed. But I 
began to be troubled in my mind lest Jemmy 
and the Major might be too long of coming 
back. What with this occupation for my 
thoughts and hands, I didn't hear a foot upon 
the stairs, and was startled when I saw the 
Major stopped short in the middle of the room 
by the eyes of the man upon the bed, and knowing 
him then, as I had known him a little while 
ago.</p>
<p>There was anger in the Major's face, and 
there was horror and repugnance and I don't 
know what. So I went up to him and I led 
him to the bedside and when I clasped my hands 
and lifted of them up, the Major did the like.</p>
<p>"O Lord" I says "Thou knowest what we 
two saw together of the sufferings and sorrows 
of that young creetur now with Thee. If this 
dying man is truly penitent, we two together 
humbly pray Thee to have mercy on him!"</p>
<p>The Major says "Amen!" and then after a 
little stop I whispers him, "Dear old friend fetch 
our beloved boy." And the Major, so clever as 
to have got to understand it all without being 
told a word, went away and brought him.</p>
<p>Never never never, shall I forget the fair 
bright face of our boy when he stood at the foot 
of the bed, looking at his unknown father. And O 
so like his dear young mother then!</p>
<p>"Jemmy" I says, "I have found out all about 
this poor gentleman who is so ill, and he did 
lodge in the old house once. And as he wants 
to see all belonging to it, now that he is passing 
away, I sent for you."</p>
<p>"Ah poor man!" says Jemmy stepping 
forward and touching one of his hands with great 
gentleness. "My heart melts for him. Poor, 
poor, man!"</p>
<p>The eyes that were so soon to close for ever, 
turned to me, and I was not that strong in the 
pride of my strength that I could resist them.</p>
<p>"My darling boy, there is a reason in the 
secret history of this fellow-creetur, lying as the 
best and worst of us must all lie one day, which 
I think would ease his spirit in his last hour if 
you would lay your cheek against his forehead 
and say 'May God forgive you!'"</p>
<p>"O Gran," says Jemmy with a full heart "I 
am not worthy!" But he leaned down and did 
it. Then the faltering fingers made out to catch 
hold of my sleeve at last, and I believe he was a 
trying to kiss me when he died.</p>
<p><section>* * * * *</section></p>
<p>There my dear! There you have the story of 
my Legacy in full, and it's worth ten times the 
trouble I have spent upon it if you are pleased 
to like it.</p>
<p>You might suppose that it set us against the 
little French town of Sens, but no we didn't 
find that. I found myself that I never looked up 
at the high tower atop of the other tower, but 
the days came back again when that fair young 
creetur with her pretty bright hair trusted in me 
like a mother, and the recollection made the place 
so peaceful to me as I can't express. And every 
soul about the hotel down to the pigeons in the 
court-yard made friends with Jemmy and the 
Major, and went lumbering away with them on all 
sorts of expeditions in all sorts of vehicles drawn 
by rampagious cart-horses--with heads and 
without--mud for paint and ropes for harness--and 
every new friend dressed in blue like a butcher, 
and every new horse standing on his hind legs 
wanting to devour and consume every other 
horse, and every man that had a whip to crack 
crack-crack-crack-crack-cracking it as if it was a 
schoolboy with his first. As to the Major my dear 
that man lived the greater part of his time with 
a little tumbler in one hand and a bottle of small 
wine in the other, and whenever he saw anybody 
else with a little tumbler, no matter who it was 
--the military character with the tags, or the 
inn servants at their supper in the court-yard, or 
towns-people a chatting on a bench, or country-people 
a starting home after market--down 
rushes the Major to clink his glass against their 
glasses and cry--Hola! Vive Somebody! or 
Vive Something! as if he was beside himself. 
And though I could not quite approve of the 
Major's doing it, still the ways of the world are 
the ways of the world varying according to 
different parts of it, and dancing at all in the 
open Square with a lady that kept a barber's shop 
my opinion is that the Major was right to dance 
his best and to lead off with a power that I did not 
think was in him, though I was a little uneasy at 
the Barricading sound of the cries that were set 
up by the other dancers and the rest of the 
company, until when I says "What are they ever 
calling out Jemmy?" Jemmy says "They're calling 
out Gran, Bravo the Military English! Bravo 
the Military English!" which was very gratifying 
to my feelings as a Briton and became the 
name the Major was known by.</p>
<p>But every evening at a regular time we all 
three sat out in the balcony of the hotel at the end 
of the court-yard, looking up at the golden and 
rosy light as it changed on the great towers, and 
looking at the shadows of the towers as they 
changed on all about us ourselves included, and 
what do you think we did there? My dear if 
Jemmy hadn't brought some other of those 
stories of the Major's taking down from the 
telling of former lodgers at Eighty-one Norfolk-street, 
and if he didn't bring 'em out with this 
speech:</p>
<p>"Here you are Gran! Here you are 
Godfather! More of 'em! <em>I</em>'ll read. And though 
you wrote 'em for me, Godfather, I know you 
won't disapprove of my making 'em over to 
Gran; will you?"</p>
<p>"No my dear boy," says the Major. "Everything 
we have is hers, and we are hers."</p>
<p>"Hers ever affectionately and devotedly J. 
Jackman, and J. Jackman Lirriper," cries the 
Young Rogue giving me a close hug. "Very 
well then Godfather. Look here. As Gran is in 
the Legacy way just now, I shall make these 
stories a part of Gran's Legacy. I'll leave 'em 
to her. What do you say Godfather?"</p>
<p>"Hip hip Hurrah!" says the Major.</p>
<p>"Very well then" cries Jemmy all in a bustle. 
"Vive the Military English! Vive the Lady 
Lirriper! Vive the Jemmy Jackman Ditto! 
Vive the Legacy! Now, you look out, Gran. 
And you look out, Godfather, <em>I</em>'ll read! And I'll 
tell you what I'll do besides. On the last 
night of our holiday here when we are all 
packed and going away, I'll top up with 
something of my own."</p>
<p>"Mind you do sir" says I.</p>
<p>"Don't you be afraid, Gran" cries Young 
Sparkles. "Now then! I'm going to read. Once, 
twice, three and away. Open your mouths and 
shut your eyes, and see what Fortune sends you. 
All in to begin. Look out Gran. Look out 
Godfather!"</p>
<p>So in his lively spirits Jemmy began a reading, 
and he read every evening while we were 
there, and sometimes we were about it late 
enough to have a candle burning quite steady 
out in the balcony in the still air. And so 
here is the rest of my Legacy my dear that I 
now hand over to you in this bundle of papers 
all in the Major's plain round writing. I wish 
I could hand you the church towers over too, 
and the pleasant air and the inn yard and the 
pigeons often coming and perching on the rail 
by Jemmy and seeming to be critical with their 
heads on one side, but you'll take as you find.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="A PAST LODGER RELATES A WILD STORY OF A DOCTOR."/>
<chapter>
<p>I have lived in a common-place way, Major, 
in common-place times, and should have mighty 
little to tell of my own life and adventures 
(if I were put to it) that would be likely to 
interest any one save myself. But I have a 
story by me that shall be yours if you please. 
Of this story I have only to say a very few 
words. My father had the manuscript of it in 
his possession as long as I can remember, and 
he once allowed me, when I began to approach 
years of discretion, to read it. It was given 
to him by a very old friend, whom I dimly 
remember about our house when I was a boy--
a French gentleman of obliging manners, and 
with a melancholy smile. He fades out of the 
memory of my youthful days very early, and 
I chiefly remember him because my father 
told me that he had received this manuscript 
from him, and that in parting with it the French 
gentleman had said: "Ah! few people would 
believe what went on at that time in France, 
but here's a specimen. I don't expect you to 
believe it, mind!"</p>
<p>When the time came for examining my 
deceased father's papers, this paper turned up 
among the rest. I put it aside, being immersed 
in business matters at the time, and only came 
upon it yesterday, in these very lodgings, in the 
course of a periodical rummage among a great 
box of papers from my bankers in the Strand 
hard by. The periodical rummage came to an 
end directly, and, with the zest naturally derived 
from a sense that I ought to be doing something 
else, I read over every word of the manuscript. 
It is faded and yellow, as you see; and it is odd, 
as you shall hear. Thus it goes:</p>
<br/>
<p>It is pretty well known that as the eighteenth 
century drew towards its close, and as the 
moment approached when the mighty change 
which had been long threatening, was actually 
about to take place--it is well known, I say, that 
we Parisians had got into a condition of mind, 
which was about as bad as bad could be. 
Luxurious, used up, we had for the most part lost 
all sense of enjoyment; while as to any feeling of 
duty--Heaven help us! there was little enough 
of that. What did we believe of man's 
responsibility? We were here to enjoy ourselves 
if we could; if we could not--why, there was a 
remedy.</p>
<p>It was just one of those states of things which 
all thinking men were able to see, could not 
possibly last long. A great shock must be at 
hand, such men said: a constitution so utterly 
deranged must pass through some serious 
attack before it would be likely to get better. 
That "serious attack" came, and the great 
French Revolution inaugurated a new condition 
of affairs. What I have to relate, however, has 
nothing to do with the revolution, but took 
place some few years before that great convulsion 
shook the world, and another era began.</p>
<p>It is not to be supposed that men who held 
the opinions, and led the lives of the better 
class of Parisians at that time, were happy. 
Indeed, a frank open-hearted man, who was 
tolerably content with the world as he found it, 
and was able and willing to enjoy himself in it, 
would have been looked upon with contempt 
by the more enlightened (and miserable) sort, 
and would have been regarded as a man 
deficient alike in intellect and "ton." There 
were few enough of such, however, and the 
representatives of the morbid class had it all 
their own way. Of course among these it was 
not likely that an agency so well calculated to 
help them out of their difficulties as suicide 
should be neglected, and it is not too much to 
say that the sacrifices offered up at that terrible 
shrine, were beyond all limits of ordinary 
proportion. It was such a resource to fall back 
upon, such a quick way out of the difficulty! 
Was money short? Was a wife troublesome, 
or a mistress obdurate? Was there a course of 
east wind setting in? Were pleasures pleasures 
no longer, while pain was still pain? Was life, 
for any reason, not worth having: was it a bore, 
a penance, a hell upon earth? Here was the 
remedy at hand--get rid of it. As to what lay 
beyond--pooh! one must take his chance. 
Perhaps there was nothing. Perhaps there were 
the Elysian Fields, with endless earthly 
gratifications, and sempiternal youth and freshness, 
to make them enjoyable. "Let us be off with all 
speed," said the weary ones; "who will help 
us on our way?"</p>
<p>Helpers were not wanting. There were 
cunning poisons which would dispose of you 
in a twinkling, and let you know nothing 
about it. There were baths and lancets, and 
anybody could seat himself in a warm bath 
and open one of his own veins and die with 
decency. Then there were pistols, beautiful 
little toys all inlaid with silver and mother-of-pearl, 
and with your own arms let into 
the butt, and your coronet, if you happened--
which was very likely--to be a marquis. And 
was there not charcoal? The sleep said to 
be produced by its fumes was of the soundest 
--no dreams--no waking. But then you must 
be sure to stop up all the chinks, or you might 
happen to inhale a breath of air, and so find 
yourself back among the east winds and 
creditors, and the rest of the ills of life, with only 
a congestion of the head for your pains. All 
the various modes by which our poor little spark 
of life may be quenched, were in vogue at that 
time, but there was one particular method of 
doing the terrible business which was more 
fashionable than the rest, and of which it is my 
special business to treat.</p>
<p>There was a certain handsome street in Paris, 
and in the Faubourg St. Germain, in which 
there lived a certain learned and accomplished 
Doctor. We will call this learned man, Dr. 
Bertrand. He was a man of striking and rather 
agreeable appearance, with a fine portly figure, 
and a handsome and strikingly intelligent face; 
his age was somewhere between forty and fifty; 
but there was one characteristic about his 
countenance, which every one who came in contact 
with him must have felt, though not all would 
have been able to explain what it was that 
affected them. His eyes were dead. They 
never changed, and they rarely moved. The rest 
of his face was as mobile as the faces of other 
people in the average, but not so with the eyes. 
They were of a dull leaden colour, and they 
actually seemed dead: the idea being further 
carried out by the livid and unwholesome tints 
of the skin around those organs. Judged from 
its hues, the skin might have mortified.</p>
<p>Dr. Bertrand, in spite of his dead eyes, was 
a personage of cheerful, almost gay, manners, 
and of an unvarying and amazing politeness. 
Nothing ever put him out. He was also a man 
surrounded by impenetrable mystery. It was 
impossible to get <em>at</em> him, or to break down the 
barriers which his politeness erected around 
him. Dr. Bertrand had made many discoveries 
by which the scientific world had profited. He 
was a rich man, and his pecuniary means had 
increased lately in a marked degree. The Doctor 
made no secret of his resources; it was part of 
his nature to enjoy luxury and splendour, and 
he lived in both. His house, an hotel of moderate 
size in the Rue Mauconseil, enclosed in a 
court-yard of its own, filled with shrubs and 
flowers, was a model of taste. His dining-room 
especially was the realised ideal of what such 
an apartment should be. Pictures, beautiful 
pictures--not pieces of wall furniture--decorated 
the walls, and these were lighted up at night in 
the most artful manner by lamps of enormous 
power. The floor was padded with the most 
splendid Persian carpets, the curtains and chairs 
were of the finest Utrecht velvet, and, in a 
conservatory outside, always heated to the most 
luxurious point, a fountain played perpetually: 
the light trickling of its water making music in 
the beautiful place.</p>
<p>And well might Dr. Bertrand have so perfect 
a dining-room in his house. To give dinners 
was a great part of Dr. Bertrand's business. In 
certain circles those dinners were highly 
celebrated, but they were always talked about under 
the rose. It was whispered that their splendour 
was fabulous; that the dishes and the wines 
reached a point of perfection absolutely 
unknown elsewhere; that the guests were waited 
upon by servants who knew their business, 
which is saying much; that they dined seated 
upon velvet fauteuils, and ate from golden 
plates; and it was said, moreover, that Dr. 
Bertrand entered into the spirit of the times, 
that he was a mighty and experienced chemist, 
and that it was an understood thing that Dr. 
Bertrand's guests did not feel life to be all they 
could wish, and had no desire to survive the 
night which succeeded their acceptance of his 
graceful hospitality.</p>
<p>Strange and intolerable imputation! Who 
could live under it? The Doctor could 
apparently. For he not only lived but throve and 
prospered under it.</p>
<p>It was a delicate and dainty way of getting 
out of the difficulties of life, this provided by 
Dr. Bertrand. You dined in a style of unwonted 
luxury, and you enjoyed excellent company, the 
Doctor himself the very best of company. You 
felt no uneasiness or pain, for the Doctor knew 
his business better than that; you went home 
feeling a little drowsy perhaps, just enough so 
to make your bed seem delightful; you went 
off to sleep instantly--the Doctor knew to a 
minute how to time it all--and you woke up in 
the Elysian Fields. At least that was where 
you expected to wake up. That, by-the-by, 
was the only part of the programme which the 
Doctor could not make sure of.</p>
<p>Now, there arrived at Dr. Bertrand's house 
one morning, a letter from a young gentleman 
named De Clerval, in which an application was 
made, that the writer might be allowed to 
partake of the Doctor's hospitality next day. This 
was the usual form observed, and (as was also 
usual) a very handsome fee accompanied the 
letter. A polite answer was returned in due 
time, enclosing a card of invitation for the 
following day, and intimating how much the Doctor 
looked forward to the pleasure of making 
Monsieur de Clerval's acquaintance.</p>
<p>A dull rainy day at the end of November, 
was not a day calculated to reconcile to life 
any one previously disapproving of the same. 
Everything was dripping. The trees in the 
Champs Elyses, the eaves of the sentry-boxes, 
the umbrellas of those who were provided with 
those luxuries, the hats of those who were 
not; all were dripping. Indeed, dripping was 
so entirely a characteristic of the day, that the 
Doctor, with that fine tact and knowledge of 
human nature which distinguished him, had, in 
arranging the evening programme, given orders 
that the conservatory fountain should be stopped, 
lest it should affect the spirits of his guests. 
Dr. Bertrand was always very particular that 
the spirits of his guests should not be damped.</p>
<p>Alfred de Clerval was something of an 
exception to the Doctor's usual class of visitors. 
ln his case it was not ennui, nor weariness of 
life, nor a longing for sensation, that made him 
one of the Doctor's guests. It was a mixture of 
pique and vexation, with a real conviction that 
what he had set his heart upon, as alone capable 
of bringing him happiness, was out of his reach. 
He was of a rash impetuous nature, he believed 
that all his chance of happiness was gone for life, 
and he determined to quit life. Two great causes 
ordinarily brought grist to Dr. Bertrand's mill; 
money troubles, and love troubles. De Clerval's 
difficulties were of the latter description. He 
was in a fever of love and jealousy. He was, 
and had been for some time, the devoted lover 
of Mademoiselle Thrse de Farelles: a noted 
beauty of that day. All had gone smoothly for 
a time, until a certain Vicomte de Noel, a cousin 
of the lady's, appeared upon the scene, and Alfred 
de Clerval becoming jealous, certain unpleasant 
scenes ensued, and finally a serious quarrel: 
Mademoiselle de Farelles belonging to that class 
of persons who are too proud to clear 
themselves from a false imputation when they might 
otherwise very easily do so. Throughout, De 
Clerval had never once seen the Vicomte; 
indeed, the principal intercourse between this last 
and Mademoiselle de Farelles, had been by letter, 
and it was partly this correspondence which had 
brought the quarrel about.</p>
<p>When De Clerval entered the salon of Dr. 
Bertrand where the guests were assembled 
before dinner, he found himself one of eight or 
ten persons, all about, like himself, to gather 
round the Doctor's table, with intentions of a 
desperate kind. Physiognomically they 
belonged to all manner of types, some being fat in 
the face, some thin in the face, some florid in 
the face, and some very pale in the face. In one 
respect alone there was a similarity among 
them; they <em>all</em> wore a sort of fixed impregnable 
expression which was intended to be, and to a 
certain extent was, unfathomable.</p>
<p>It has been said that there was every sort of 
person in this assembly. Here was, for instance, 
a fat man with a countenance naturally jovial, 
plethoric, in want of a little doctoring no doubt, 
too much, of a "bon vivant" assuredly, but 
why on earth here now? If he had come in 
the morning to consult the Doctor on his digestion, 
one could understand; but what does he do 
here now? That man knows that tomorrow 
morning it will be proclaimed to the world that 
he is ruined, and an impostor. His affairs will 
collapse, like a house made of cards, and he who 
has an especial affection for social importance, 
and who has hitherto enjoyed a good position 
among his fellows, knows that he would never 
be able to show his face again. True to his 
sociability and love of company, to the last, he 
comes to make an end in good society. Surely 
no other system, but Dr. Bertrand's, would ever 
have met the views of this unhappy speculator. 
Honour then to Dr. Bertrand! who provides 
every class of persons with the means of suicide.</p>
<p>Here, again, is an individual of another description 
altogether. A dark thin close-shaved man, 
who has the fixed unfathomable expression more 
developed than all the others. This morning 
his valet knocked at his door, and brought him a 
letter directed to Monsieur, which the fille de 
chambre had found on Madame's dressing-table. 
Madame herself was not in the room, there was 
only the letter lying before the looking-glass. 
Monsieur read it, and he is here dining with 
Dr. Bertrand, and his face is deadly white, and 
he does not speak a word.</p>
<p>Such guests as these and De Clerval were 
of an exceptional character. The right man 
in the right place was a tall faded young man, 
whom Alfred observed leaning against the 
chimney-piece, too languid to sit, stand, or 
recline, and so driven to lean. He had a 
handsome countenance as far as symmetry of feature 
and proportion went, but the expression was 
terrible: so blank, so weary, so hopeless, 
that one really almost felt that his coming 
there to dine with Dr. Bertrand was the best 
thing he could do. He was splendidly dressed, 
and the value of his waistcoat buttons and 
studs, seemed to prove that it was not poverty 
which had brought him there: just as the utter 
vapidity and blankness of his weary face seemed 
to indicate that he was incapable of such a 
strength of love as would drive him to this 
last resource. No, this was a case of ennui: 
hopeless, final, terrible. Some of his friends 
had dined with Dr. Bertrand, and it seemed 
to have answered, as they never bored him 
again. He thought he would try it, so here he 
was come to dinner. Others were there, like this 
one. Men who had already outlived themselves, 
so to speak--outlived their better selves--their 
belief, their health, their natural human interest 
in the things that happen beneath the sun men 
whose hearts had gone to the grave long ago, 
and whose bodies were now to follow.</p>
<p>"We do not go through the ceremony of 
introduction in these little runions of ours," 
whispered the Doctor in De Clerval's ear; 
"we are all supposed to know each other." 
This was after the servant had solemnly 
announced dinner, and when the guests and their 
entertainers were passing to the salle--manger.</p>
<p>The room looked charming. The Doctor had 
not only caused the fountains to be stopped, 
but had even, to increase the comfort of the 
scene, directed that the great velvet curtains 
should be drawn over the entrance to the 
conservatory. The logs blazed upon the hearth, 
and the table was covered with glittering 
candles. For the Doctor well knew the effect of 
these, and how they add to the gaiety of every 
scene into which they are introduced.</p>
<p>The guests all took their places round that 
dreadful board, and perhaps at that moment--
always a chilly one, under the circumstances--
a serious sense of what they were doing forced 
itself upon some of them. Certainly Alfred 
de Clerval shuddered as he sat down to table, 
and certain good thoughts made a struggle to 
gain possession of his mind. But the die was 
cast. He had come to that place with an 
intent known to everybody present, and he must 
go through with the intent. He thought, too, 
that he caught the Doctor's eye fixed upon him. 
He must be a man--A MAN.</p>
<p>The Doctor seemed a little anxious at about 
this period of the entertainment, and now and 
then would sign impatiently to the servants to 
do their work swiftly. And so the oysters went 
round, and then some light wine. It was Chteau 
Yquem. The Doctor's wine was matchless.</p>
<p>Dr. Bertrand seemed resolved that there 
should be no pauses in the conversation, and 
tore himself to tatters though apparently 
enjoying himself extremely in order to keep it 
going at this time. There was one horrible 
circumstance connected with the flagging talk. 
No one alluded to the future. Nobody spoke 
of to-morrow. It would have been indelicate 
in the host; in the guests it would have been 
folly.</p>
<p>"On such a day as this," remarked the 
Doctor, addressing a distinguished looking 
spectre at the other end of the table, "you 
will have missed your drive in the Bois, M. le 
Baron?"</p>
<p>"No," replied the person addressed, "I was 
there in the afternoon for two hours."</p>
<p>"But the fog--could you see?"</p>
<p>"I had runners before me with torches. I 
had the idea that it might prove interesting."</p>
<p>"And, was it?" inquired another spectral 
personage, looking up suddenly: as if he rather 
regretted having committed himself to the 
Doctor's hospitality before trying this new 
experiment. "<em>Was</em> it interesting?"</p>
<p>"Not in the remotest degree," replied the 
Baron, in an extinguished sort of voice, and to 
the other's evident satisfaction. "It was 
impossible to go beyond a foot-pace, nothing but 
a grey mist was to be seen on all sides, the 
horses were bewildered and had to be led. In 
short, it was an experience to make a man 
commit sui----"</p>
<p>"Allow me strongly to recommend this 
salmi," cried the Doctor, in a loud voice. 
"My chef is particularly good at it." The 
Baron had got upon an awkward tack, and it 
was necessary to interrupt him. Dr. 
Bertrand well knew how difficult it was on these 
occasions to keep that horrid word, which the 
Baron had so nearly spoken, out of the 
conversation. Everybody tried to avoid it, but it 
would come up.</p>
<p>"For my part, I spent the day at the 
Louvre," said a little man with a green 
complexion, and all his features out of drawing. He 
was a gentleman who had hitherto been entirely 
unsuccessful in putting an end to himself. He 
had been twice cut down, and once sewn up 
when he had had the misfortune to miss his 
jugular by the eighth of an inch. He had been 
saved from drowning by a passing friend, 
whom he hated ever afterwards. He had 
charcoaled himself, forgetting to stop up the 
key-hole; and he had jumped out of window, 
just in time to be caught by a passing manure-cart. 
"I spent the day at the Louvre," 
remarked this unfortunate gentleman; "the effect 
of the fog upon some of the pictures was terrible."</p>
<p>"Dear me!" said the gentleman who had 
before regretted having missed the Bois in a 
fog, and who on the whole seemed to have 
come to the Doctor's prematurely; "I should 
like to have seen that very much, very much 
indeed. I wonder if there will be a fog to--to----"</p>
<p>"To-morrow," he was going to say. The 
Doctor thought the moment a propitious one 
for sending round the champagne; and even in 
this assembly it did its usual work, and the 
buzz of talk followed as it circulated.</p>
<p>"This poulet," said the Doctor, "is a dish on 
which we pride ourselves rather." It was curious 
that the Doctor's guests always had a disposition 
to avoid those dishes which he recommended the 
most strongly. They knew why they were come, 
and that was all very well; but there was 
something treacherous in recommending things. 
But the Doctor was up to this. He had given 
enough of these entertainments to enable him 
to observe how regular this shyness was in 
its action, and so he thus paved the way for 
the next dish, which was always the dish he 
wanted his guests to partake of, and which they 
did partake of almost invariably. The next 
dish in this case was a new one, a "curry  
l'Anglaise," and almost everybody rushed at it 
headlong. The dish was a novelty even in 
England then, and in France wholly unknown. The 
Doctor smiled as he raised the champagne to 
his lips. "There is a fine tonic quality about 
these English curries," he remarked.</p>
<p>"And tonics always disagree with my head," 
said a little man at the end of the table, who 
had not yet spoken. And he ate no more curry.</p>
<p>Alfred de Clerval was, in spite of his sorrows, 
so far alive to all that was going on around him 
as to miss partaking of some of Dr. Bertrand's 
favourite dishes. He had also entered into 
conversation with one of his next neighbours. On 
his left was the commercial man, whose exposure 
was to take place next day; and this gentleman, 
naturally a bon vivant, was making the 
most of his time, and committing fearful havoc 
on the Doctor's dishes and wine. On the right 
of De Clerval was a gentleman whom Alfred 
had not observed until they were seated 
together at table, but he was a remarkable looking 
man. They talked at first of indifferent 
matters, or of what went on around them. They 
<em>got on</em> together, as the saying goes. Men are 
not very particular in forming acquaintances 
when their duration is likely to be short, and so 
when the wine had circulated for some time--
and every man there partook of it fiercely--
these two had got to speak freely, for men who 
were but friends of an hour.</p>
<p>"You are a young man," said the stranger, 
after a pause, during which he had observed De 
Clerval closely; "you are a young man to be 
dining with Dr. Bertrand."</p>
<p>"The Doctor's hospitality is, I suspect, 
suited at times to persons of all ages," replied 
Alfred. "I was going to add, and of both sexes. 
How is it, by-the-by, that there are no ladies 
among the Doctor's guests?"</p>
<p>"I suppose he won't have them," retorted 
the other, with bitterness; "and he is right! 
They would be going into hysterics in the middle 
of dinner, and disorganising the Doctor's arrangements, 
as they do disorder every system of which 
they form a part, even to the great world itself."</p>
<p>"True enough," thought Alfred to himself. 
"This man has suffered as I have, from being 
fool enough to put his happiness in a woman's 
keeping."</p>
<p>De Clerval stole a look at him. He was a 
man considerably his own senior. He was 
a very tall man, and had something of that 
languid air in all his movements which often 
belongs to height. His face was deeply marked 
for his age, but there was a very kind and 
merciful expression on it, and, though he looked 
weary and perhaps indolent, his was not by 
any means a blas countenance. He looked 
like a man who has goodness in him, but instinctively 
and quite independent of any influence 
wrought by principle. A good nature, 
kind and generous and honourable, was there; but 
the man had no rudder or compass to steer by. 
It was a fine new vessel adrift.</p>
<p>In his own terrible position one would say 
that such an one could have no leisure to think 
of anything else. A man under such circumstances 
might be excused for a little egotism, 
might be expected to be absorbed in himself and 
his own troubles; but it was not so with this 
stranger. His eye wandered from time to time 
round the table, and evidently his mind was 
largely occupied with speculations as to what 
the rest of Dr. Bertrand's patients were suffering 
under. "How curious it would be," he at length 
remarked to De Clerval, "if we could know 
what is amiss with each one of the guests 
assembled here. This is a little man opposite, 
for instance, who has not spoken once; see, he 
is writing in a furtive manner in his pocketbook 
--writing, perhaps to some one who will 
be sorry to-morrow to hear what has happened. 
What on earth brought <em>him</em> here? One would 
have expected that he would have died somewhere 
in the corner alone. Perhaps he was afraid. 
There, again, is a man who, to all appearance, is 
worn out of illness. A fixed pain, perhaps, 
which is never to be better, and which he can--
or will--bear no longer. One would have 
thought that he would have remained at home. 
But we all seem afraid to die in solitude, and 
the Doctor makes everything so pleasant. 
Listen; here is a new surprise for us."</p>
<p>Dr. Bertrand was an energetic person, and a 
man of resource. Not only had he, in consideration 
of the fog and the rain, caused the fountain 
to be stopped, and the curtains to be drawn 
over the entrance to the conservatory, but he 
had arranged that some musicians should be 
placed where the flowers used to show, in 
order that a novel air of luxury might be 
given to this particular festival. Nor were 
these, common musicians, whose performance 
might have infused gloom rather than cheerfulness 
into the assembly. The Doctor had caused 
performers of choice ability to be selected, and 
their music now stole gently on the senses of 
the guests, and produced an effect that was infinitely 
agreeable.</p>
<p>"How well this man understands his business," 
remarked de Cherval to his neighbour. 
"There is something almost great about him."</p>
<p>There is nothing that varies more in its effect 
upon us than music; according to the circumstances 
under which we hear it, it will, to a 
great extent, prove either stimulating or saddening; 
still more, of course, does the effect 
depend upon the music selected. In this case, 
with the talk already started, with the wine 
circulating inccessantly, with lights flashing in all 
directions, the effect of the music was exciting 
in the extreme. And then it had been selected 
with no common skill. It was not touching 
music, such as makes one think; but it was 
made up of a selection of vigorous gallant tunes 
that seemed to stir the blood in the veins, and 
rather agitate the nerves than serve them.</p>
<p>The music was an experiment which Dr. 
Bertrand had not tried before, and he watched 
the effect of it carefully.</p>
<p>De Clerval and his neighbour were silent for 
a time, partly because they were listening to the 
music, and also because, for the moment, it was 
difficult to hear one another. The Doctor's 
guests were noisy enough now. The wine--the 
good wine--was doing its work, and loosening 
the tied-up tongues. What talk it was! Talk 
of the gaming-table, and the night revel. The 
horrid infidelity of the time brayed out by throats 
through which no word of prayer or song of 
praise had passed since the days of earliest childhood.</p>
<p>De Clerval and his neighbour were persuing 
their conversation, when the attention of both 
was suddenly drawn to the opposite side of the 
table.</p>
<p>Behind the Doctor's chair there always stood 
a middle-aged man whose business it was to 
remain stationary in that place, and to keep 
a steady eye upon every one at the table, in order 
that the very first sign of anything going 
wrong with a guest might be instantly observed 
and acted on. The Doctor's calculations 
were generally most accurate; still he 
was human, and occasionally some pecliarity of 
constitution on the part of one of his patients 
would defeat him. Or they might partake of 
certain dishes in continuous succession, some 
one or two only of which the Doctor had 
intended to be eaten consecutively. In short, 
unpleasant things would take place occasionally, 
and so this special officer was in attendance.</p>
<p>This individual suddenly bent down and drew 
his master's attention to a gentleman seated at 
the other end of the table, over whom there 
had gathered a certain strange rigidity of figure 
and face. He had dropped his fork, and now sat 
bolt upright in his chair, staring straight before 
him with a fixity of gaze and a drop of the lower 
jaw which Dr. Bertrand understand perfectly 
well.</p>
<p>"Peste!" said the Doctor. "How cantankerous 
some exceptional constitutions are! One 
never knows where to have them. You must 
not lose a second; call in the others and remove 
him. He is of an epileptic constitution. Lose 
not a moment."</p>
<p>The familiar disappeared for an instant, and 
returned, accompanied by four noiseless men, 
who followed him swiftly to the end of the 
table where the wretched guest was seated. 
He had already begun to shriek aloud, while 
his features were distorted horribly, and the 
foam was gathering on his lips.</p>
<p>"Oh, my life!" he screamed. "My lost life! 
Give it me--I must have it--a loan--it was 
only a loan! I Have frittered it away. I want 
it back. Only a little of it, then; a very 
little would be something. Ah, it is this 
man!" The Doctor was near him now, and 
the epileptic made a furious attempt to get 
at him. "This man has got my life, my 
misspent life--it is going--going from me at 
his will--my life--my lost----" The miserable 
creature was overpowered and fainting, and 
the four noiseless men carried him away. 
Still, as they bore him through the door, he 
lifted up his voice again, and cried aloud for 
his youth--his lost youth--and said he would 
use it differently if they would give it back to 
him.</p>
<p>They could hear his screams for some time 
after that, even in the Doctor's padded and 
muffled house. The incident was horrible, and 
produced a state of excitement in the other 
guests. The noise and uproar that followed 
this terrible occurrence were hellish; everybody 
was up in arms at once, and it was upon 
the Doctor himself that all the indignation fell. 
What did he mean by it? He was an imposter. 
They had been bought there under false pretences. 
They had understood that what was 
done in that establishment was done decently, 
done effectually, done with a consideration for 
the feelings of the guests, done in a gentleman-like 
manner. Here they were, on the contrary, 
subjected to a scene which was horrible, disgusting, 
a thing of hospitals, a horror!</p>
<p>The Doctor bowed before this storm of 
invectives. He was deeply, abjectly, miserable 
at what had occurred: such a thing was 
rare--rare in the extreme. There were people 
with constitutions that defied all calculation; 
people who did not know how to live, nor even 
how to---- Well, he could only express his 
profound regret. Would they do him the 
favour to taste his new wine just brought 
up? It was Lafitte of a celebrated year, and 
the Doctor drained off a bumper, by way of 
setting a good example. It was soon followed 
by the already half-drunken guests, and 
the noise and uproar became worse than ever.</p>
<p>"Did you observe what that gentleman partook 
of?" asked Dr. Bertrand of his familiar. 
"The gentleman who has just made a scene, I 
mean?"</p>
<p>"By unlucky chance," was the reply, "he 
partook  in succession of three of your most 
powerfully <em>seasoned</em> dishes. I was thinking--
but it is not for me to speak----"</p>
<p>"Yes, yes, it is. What were you thinking?"</p>
<p>"I was thinking, monsieur, whether it was 
judicious to put three preparations of such great 
strength next to each other?"</p>
<p>"Quite true, quite true," answered the 
Doctor. "I will make a note of the case."</p>
<p>Meanwhile, De Clerval and his neighbour had 
fallen again into conversation. There seemed 
about the stranger something like an interest 
in his companion. It appeared as if he still 
thought this dining-room of the Doctor's no 
place for so young a man.</p>
<p>"If I am too young to be here," said De 
Clerval, "ought not you, who are of maturer 
years, to be too wise?"</p>
<p>"No," replied the other; "I have reasoned 
the thing out, and have thought well and carefully 
of what I am doing. I had one last chance 
of happiness after many missed or thrown 
away; the chance has failed me; there is 
nothing in store; there is nothing possible 
now that would give me the least satisfaction. 
The world is of no use to me, and I am of 
no use in the world."</p>
<p>There was a pause. Perhaps De Clerval felt 
that under the circumstances there was little 
room for argument; perhaps he perceived that, 
to reason against a course which he was himself 
pursuing, and yet which he felt unaccountably 
inclined to reason against, was preposterous 
--at any rate he was silent and the stranger 
went on:</p>
<p>"It is curious, with regard to certain of 
one's relatives, how we lose sight of them 
for a time, a very long time even, and then 
some circumstance brings one into contact with 
and the intercourse becomes intimate and 
frequent. It was so with me and my cousin. 
I had not seen her for years. I had been much 
away from Paris during those years--in Russia, 
at Vienna, and elsewhere--engaged in diplomatic 
service. In all the wild dissipations to be found 
at the different courts to which I was attached, 
I engaged with the most dissipated; and when 
I lately returned to Paris I believed myself to 
be a totally exhausted man, for whom a veritable 
emotion was henceforth out of the question. 
But I was mistaken."</p>
<p>"There is nothing," remarked Alfred, "that 
men are more frequently mistaken about."</p>
<p>"Well! I was so at any rate," continued the 
stranger. "After a lapse of many years I met 
my cousin again, and found in her, qualities so 
irresistible, so unlike any I had met with in the 
world, such freshness and truth--"</p>
<p>"There <em>are</em> such women on earth," interrupted 
De Clerval.</p>
<p>"In a word," continued the other, without 
noticing the interruption, "I came to the conclusion 
that, could I ally her destiny with mine, 
there was a new life and a happy one 
yet in store for me. I believed that I should be able 
to shake off my old vile garments, get rid of my 
old nad habits, and--<em>begin again</em>. What a vision 
came up before me of a life in which SHE would 
lead me and help me, be my guide along a 
good way better known to her than to me! I 
determined to make the cast, and that my 
life should depend on the issue of the throw. 
It was only yesterday that the cast was made 
--and the consequence is, that--that I am 
here,"</p>
<p>Alfred was silent; a strange feeling of pity 
came over him for this man. In spite of his 
own trouble, there seemed to be a corner in his 
heart that was sorry yet for his neighbour.</p>
<p>"At that terrible interview," the stranger 
went on, "I forced the truth from here. Thrse 
was not a demonstrative woman. There 
was a fund of reserve about her which kept her 
from showing herself to every one. It was a 
fault, and so was her pride, the besetting sin of 
those who have never fallen."</p>
<p>From the moment when the name of Thrse 
had been mentioned, the attention of Alfred had 
been drawn with increased fixity to the narrative 
to which he was listening. It was with 
greediness that he now caught at every word 
which followed.</p>
<p>"I forced the truth from her. I Believe she 
spoke it the less unwillingly because it was 
her wish to save me from any delusion in the 
matter, and mercifully to deprive me of hope 
which could never have any real foundation. I 
besought her to tell me, in the name of Heaven's 
truth, was there one in the world more favoured 
--one who possessed the place in her heart 
which I had sought to occupy? She hesitated, 
but I Pressed her hard and wrung it from her. 
Yes, there was one: one who held her heart for 
ever. I was greedy, I would know all: his 
name: his condition. And I did. I got to know 
it all--the history of their love--the name of my 
rival."</p>
<p>"And what was it?" asked Alfred, in a voice 
that seemed to himself like that of another 
man.</p>
<p>"Alfred De Clerval."</p>
<p>Alfred sprung to his feet, and looked towards 
the Doctor. "She loves me," he gasped, "and 
I am <em>here!</em>"</p>
<p>The sudden move of De Clerval attracted all 
attention. "Ah! another!" the guests yelled 
out. "Another who does not know how to 
behave himself. Another who is going to scream 
at us and drive us mad, and die before out very 
faces!"</p>
<p>"No, no!" cried Alfred. "No, no! not die 
but live! I <em>must</em> live. All is changed, and I 
call upon this Doctor here to save me."</p>
<p>"How do you mean that 'all is changed?'" 
whispered the man whose narration had brought 
all this about. "Changed by what I have 
said?"</p>
<p>The noise was so great that De Clerval could 
nor for the moment answer. The self-doomed 
wretches round the table seemed to feel a 
horrible jealousy at the idea of an escape. Even 
the Doctor sought in vain to restore order 
now.</p>
<p>"Ah, the renegade," cried the guests, "the 
coward! He is afraid. He has thought better 
of it! Impostor, what did he ever come among 
us for!"</p>
<p>"Hold! gentlemen," cried Alfred, in a voice 
that made the glasses ring; "I am neither 
coward nor renegade. I came here to die, 
becase I wished to die. And now i wish 
to live--not from caprice nor fear, but because 
the circumstances which made me wish 
to die, are changed; because I have learnt 
the truth but this moment, learnt it in this 
room, learnt it at this table, learnt it of this gentleman."</p>
<p>"Tell me," said the stranger, now seizing 
him by the arm, "what had my story to do with 
all this? Unless--unless----"</p>
<p>"Monsieur le Vicomte de Noel," replied the 
other, "I am Alfred de Clerval, and the story 
you told was of Thrse de Farelles. Judge 
whether I am anxious to live or not."</p>
<p>A frightful convulsion passed over the features 
of the Vicomte de Noel, and he fell back in his 
chair.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the uproar continued among Dr. 
Bertrand's guests.</p>
<p>"We acknowledge nothing," one of the maddened 
wretches cried, "as a reason for breaking 
faith with Death. We are all his votaries. 
We came together in good fellowship to do him 
honour. Hurrah for Death! Here is a fellow 
who would turn infidel to our religion. A renegade, 
I say again,  and what should be the fate 
of renegades!"</p>
<p>"Follow me without a moment's delay," whispered 
a voice in Alfred's ear. "You are in the 
greatest danger."</p>
<p>It was the Doctor's familiar spirit who spoke. 
Alfred turned to follow him. Then he hesitated, 
and, hastily leaning down, said these words in De 
Noel's ear:</p>
<p>"For Heaven's sake, don't let your life be 
sacrificed in this horrible way. Follow me, I 
entreat you."</p>
<p>"Too late! It is over," gasped the dying 
man. He seemed to make an ineffectual effort 
to say more, and then he spread his arms out 
on the table, and his head fell heavily upon 
them.</p>
<p>"You will be too late in another instant," 
said the Doctor's servant, seizing Alfred 
hastily by the arm. As De Clerval passed 
through the side-door which the man opened, 
such a rush was made towards the place as 
plainly showed what a narrow escape he had 
had. The servant, however, locked and bolted 
the door in time, and those poor half-poisoned 
and half-drunken wretches were foiled in their 
purpose.</p>
<p>And now, that escape effected, and the excitement 
of the previous moment at an end, a strange 
weakness and giddiness came over De Clerval, 
and he sunk upon a large sofa to which he 
had mechanically found his way. The room 
was a large one, and dimly lighted by a simple 
lamp, shaded, which stood upon a bureau or 
escritoire nearly large enough to occupy one end 
of the room, and covered with papers, bottles, 
surgical instruments, and other medical lumber. 
The room was filled with such matter, and it 
opened into another and a smaller apartment, in 
which were cubicles, a furnace, many chemical 
preparations, and a bath which could be heated 
at the shortest notice.</p>
<p>"The Doctor will be here himself immediately," 
said the familiar, approaching De 
Clerval with a glass, in which was some compound 
which he had hastily mixed; "meantime, 
he bade me give you this."</p>
<p>De Clerval swallowed the mixture, and the 
attendant left the room. No doubt there was 
work enough for him elsewhere. Before leaving, 
however, he told Alfred that he must by all 
means keep awake.</p>
<p>In compliance with these instructions, and 
feeling an unwonted drowsiness creeping over 
him, De Clerval proceeded to walk up and down 
the room. He was not himself. He would 
stop, almost without knowing it, in the middle of 
his promenade, become unconscious for a moment, 
then would he suddenly and violently 
roused by finding that his balance was going, 
and once he did fall. But he sprang up instantly, 
feeling that his life depended on it. He 
set himself mental tasks, tasks of memory, or 
he would try to convince himself that he was in 
possession of his faculties by reasoning as to 
where he was, what circumstances had occurred, 
and the like: "I am in Dr.--Dr.--study," he 
would say to himself. "I know all about it--
waiting to see--waiting, mind, to see--I am 
waiting--Dr.----" He was falling into a state 
of insensibility in spite of all his efforts, when 
Dr. Bertrand, whose approach he had not heard, 
stood there before him. The sight of the 
Doctor roused him.</p>
<p>"Doctor, can you save me?"</p>
<p>"First, I must ask <em>you</em> a question," replied 
the Doctor. "It is about one of the dishes at 
table--now recollect yourself. The 'Curry a 
l'Anglaise.' Did you partake of it?"</p>
<p>De Clerval was silent fora moment, making a 
violent effort to collect his bewildered faculties.</p>
<p>At last he remembered something that decided 
him.</p>
<p>"No, I did not. I remember thinking that 
an English dish is never good in France, and I 
let it pass."</p>
<p>"Then," said Dr. Bertrand, "there is good 
hope. Follow me into this room."</p>
<br/>
<p>For a long time Alfred de Clerval's life was in 
the greatest danger. Although he had not partaken 
of that one particular dish which Dr. 
Bertrand considered it. beyond hrs power to 
counteract, he had yet swallowed enough that 
was poisonous, to make his ultimate recovery 
exceedingly doubtful. Probably no other man 
but he who had so nearly caused his death 
could have saved his life. But Dr. Bertrand 
knew what was wrong--which is not always the 
case with doctors--and he also knew how to 
deal with that wrong. So, after a long and 
tedious illness and couvaleseencc, Alfred so far 
recovered as to be able to drop the Doctor's 
acquaintance, which he was very anxious to 
do, and to take advantage of the information 
he had gained from the unfortunate Vicomte de 
Noel.</p>
<p>Whether Mademoiselle de Farelles was able 
to pardon the crime her lover had so nearly 
committed, in consideration of the fact that it 
was love for her which had led him on to attempt 
it, I don't know; but my belief is that she did 
pardon it.</p>
<p>For Dr. Bertrand, his career was a short one. 
The practices by which he was amassing a 
large fortune were not long in coming to the 
knowledge of the police authorities, and in 
due time it was determined by those who had 
the power to carry out their conclusions, that it 
would be for the good of the Doctor's health 
that the remainder of his life should be passed 
in the neighbourhood of Cayenne, where, if he  
chose, he might give dinners to such of the 
convicts as could be the most easily spared by 
government.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="ANOTHER PAST LODGER RELATES HIS EXPERIENCE AS A POOR RELATION."/>
<chapter>
<p>The evening was raw and there was snow on 
the streets, genuine London snow, half-thawed, 
and trodden, and defiled with mud. I remembered 
it well, that snow, though it was fifteen 
years since I had last seen its cheerless face. 
There it lay, in the same old ruts, and spreading 
the same old snares on the side-paths. Only a 
few hours arrived from South America via 
Southampton, I sat in my room at Morley's 
Hotel, Charing Cross, and looked gloomily 
out at the fountains, walked up and down the 
floor discontentedly, and fiercely tried my best 
to feel glad that I was a wanderer no more, and 
that i had indeed get home at last.</p>
<p>I poked up my fire, and took a long look backward 
upon my past life, through the embers. I 
remembered how my childhood had been embittered 
by dependence, how my rich and respectable 
uncle, whose ruling passion was vainglory, 
had looked on my existence as a nuisance, 
not so much because he was obliged to open his 
purse to pay for my clothing and education, as 
because that, when a man, he thought I could 
reflect no credit upon his name. I remembered 
how in those days I had a soul for the beautiful, 
and a certain almost womanish tenderness of 
heart, which by dint of much sneering had been 
successfully extracted from me. I remembered 
my uncle's unconcealed relief at my determination 
to go abroad and seek my fortune, the cold 
good-by of my only cousin, the lonely bitter 
farewell to England hardly sweetened by the impatient 
hopes that consumed rather than cheered 
me-the hopes of name and gold, won by my own 
exertions, with which I should yet wring from 
those who deSpised me, the worthless respect 
which they denied me now.</p>
<p>Sitting there at the fire, I rang the bell, and 
the waiter came to me: an old man whose face 
I remembered. I asked him some questions. 
Yes, he know Mr. George Rutland; recollected 
that many years ago he used to stay at Morley's 
when he came to London. The old gentleman 
had always stayed there. But Mr. George was 
too grand for Morley's now. The family always 
came to town in the spring, but, at this season, 
"Rutland Hall, Kent," would be pretty sure to 
be their address.</p>
<p>Having obtained all the information I desired, 
I began forthwith to write a letter:</p>
<letter>
<p>"Dear George,--I dare say you will be as 
much surprised to see my handwriting as you 
would to behold an apparition from the dead. 
However, you know I was always a ne'er-do-well, 
and I have not had the grace to die yet. 
I am ashamed not to be able to announce myself 
as having returned home with my fortune 
made; but mishaps will follow the most hard-working 
and well-meaning. I am still a young 
man, even though fifteen of the best years of 
my life may have been lost, and I am willing to 
devote myself to any worthy occupation. Meantime, 
I am anxious to see you and yours. A 
long absence from home and kindred makes one 
value the grasp of a friendly hand. I shall not 
wait for your reply to this, but go down to 
Kent the day after tomorrow, arriving, I believe, 
about dinner-time. You see I am making 
myself assured of your welcome for a few weeks, 
till I have tune to look about me.</p>
<centre>"I remain, dear George,</centre>
<right>"Your old friend and cousin,</right>
<right>"GUY RUTLAND."</right>
</letter>
<p>I folded this missive and placed it in its envelope. 
"I shall find out, once for all, what they 
are made of," I said, complacently, as I wrote 
the address, "George Rutland, Esq, Rutland 
Hall, Kent."</p>
<p>It was about seven on a frosty evening: when 
I arrived at the imposing entrance of Rutlaud 
Hall. No Cousin George came rushing out to 
meet. me. "Of course not," I thought; "I am 
unused to their formal manners in this country. 
lie is lying in wait for me on the mat inside." 
I was admitted by a solemn person as quietly 
and mechanically as though my restoration to 
home and kindred were a thing that had happened 
regularly in his presence every day since 
his birth. He ushered me into a grand hall, 
but no mat supported the impatient feet 
of the dignified master of the house. "Ah!" 
said I, "even this, perhaps, were scarcely 
etiquette. No doubt. he stands chafing on the 
drawing-room hearth-rug, and I have little 
enough tune to make myself presentable before 
dinner." So, resigning myself to circumstances, 
I meekly followed a guide who volunteered 
to conduct me to the chamber assigned 
to my especial use. I had to travel a considerable 
distance before I reached it. "Dear 
me!" I remarked to myself when I did reach 
it, "I had expected to find the rooms in such 
a house more elegantly appointed than this!"</p>
<p>I made my toilette, and again submitting myself 
to my guide, was conveyed to the drawing-room 
door. All the way down stairs I had been 
conning pleasant speeches with which to greet 
my kinsfolk. I am not a brilliant person, but I 
sometimes succeed in pleasing when I try, and 
on this occasion I had the desire to do my best.</p>
<p>The drawing-room door was at the distant end 
of the hall, and my arrival had been so very 
quiet, that I conceived my expectant entertainers 
could hardly be aware of my presence in 
the house. I thought I should give them a surprise. 
The door opened and closed upon me, 
leaving me within the room. I looked around me, 
and saw--darkness there, and nothing more.</p>
<p>Ah, yes, but there was something more! There 
was a blazing fire which sent eddying swirls of 
light througi the shadows, and right in the 
blush of its warmth a little figure was lounging 
in an easy-chair. The little figure was a girl of 
apparently about fifteen or sixteen years of age, 
dressed in a. short shabby black frock, who was 
evidently spoiling her eyes by reading by the 
firelight. She lay with her head thrown back, a 
mass of fair curly hair being thus tossed over 
the velvet cushion on which it rested, while she 
held her book aloft to catch the light. She was 
luxuriating in her solitude, and little dreaming 
of interruption.</p>
<p>She was so absorbed in her book, the door 
had opened and closed so noiselessly, and the 
room was so large, that I was obliged to make a 
sound to engage her attention. She started 
violently then, and looked a with a nervous 
fearfulness in her face. She dropped her book, 
sat upright, and put out her hand, eagerly 
grasping a thing I had not noticed before, and 
which leaned against the chair--a crutch. She 
then got up leaning on it and stood before me. 
The poor little thing was lame, and had two 
crutches by her.</p>
<p>I introduccd myself, and her fear seemed to 
subside. She asked me to sit down, with a prim 
little assumption of at-home-ness, which did 
not sit upon her with ease. She picked up her 
book and laid it on her lap; she produced a net 
from the recesses of her chair, and with a blush 
gathered up the curls and tucked them into its 
meshes. Then she sat quiet, but kept her hand 
upon her crutches, as if she was ready at a 
moment's notice to limp away across the carpet, 
and leave me to my own resources.</p>
<p>"Thomson thought there was nobody in the 
room," she said, as if anxious to account for 
her own presence there. "I always stay in the 
nursery, except sometimes when they all go out 
and I get this room to myself. Then I like to 
read here."</p>
<p>"Mr. Rutland is not at home?" I said.</p>
<p>"No, they are all out dining."</p>
<p>"Indeed! Your papa, perhaps, did not got 
my letter?" .</p>
<p>She blushed crimson.</p>
<p>"I am not a Miss Rutland," she said. "My 
name is Teecie Ray. I am an orphan. My 
father was a friend of Mr. Rutland, and he takes 
care of me for charity."</p>
<p>The last word was pronounced with a certain 
controlled quiver of the lip. But she went on. 
"I don't know about the letter, but I heard a 
gentleman was expected. I did not think it 
could be to-night, though, as they all went out."</p>
<p>"A reasonable conclusion to come to," I 
thought, and thereupon began nursing on the 
eagerness of welcome displayed by my affectionate 
Cousin George. If I were the gentleman 
expected, they must have received my letter, 
and in it were fully set forth the day and hour 
of my proposed arrival. "Ah! George, my dear 
follow," I said, "you are not a whit changed!"</p>
<p>Arriving at this conclusion, I raised my glance, 
and met, full, the observant gaze of a pair of 
large shrewd grey eyes. My little hostess for 
the time being was regarding me with such a 
curiously legible expression on her face, that I 
could not but read it and be amused. It said 
plainly: "I know more about you than you 
think, and I pity you. You come here with expectations 
which will not be fulfilled. There is 
much mortification in store for you. I wonder you 
came here at all. If I were once well outside these 
gates, I should never limp inside them again. If 
I knew a road out into the world you come from, 
I would set out bravely on my crutches. No, 
not even for the sake of a stolen hour like this, 
in a velvet chair, would I remain here."</p>
<p>How any one glance could say all this, was a 
riddle; but it did say all this. The language of 
the face was as simple to me as though every word 
had been translated into my ear. Perhaps a 
certain internal light, kindled long ago, before 
this little orphan was born, or George Rutland 
had become owner of Rutland Hall, assisted me 
in deciphering so much information so readily. 
However that may be, certain things before surmised 
became assured facts in my mind, and a 
quaint bond of sympathy became at once established 
between me and my companion.</p>
<p>"Miss Ray," I said, "what do you think of 
a man who, having been abroad for fifteen years, 
has the impudence to come home without a 
shilling in its pocket? Ought he not to be 
stoned alive?"</p>
<p>"I thought how it was," said she, shaking her 
head, and looking up with another of her shrewd 
glances. "I knew it, when they put you into 
such a bad bedroom. They are keeping all the 
good rooms for the people who are coming next 
week. The house will be full for Christmas. 
It won't do," she added, meditatively.</p>
<p>"What won't do?" I said.</p>
<p>"Your not having a shilling in your pocket. 
They'll sneer at you for it, and the servants will 
find it out. I have a guinea that old Lady 
Thornton gave me on my birthday, and if you 
would take the loan of it I should be very glad. 
I don't want it at all, and you could pay me 
back when you are better off."</p>
<p>She said this with such business-like gravity, 
that I felt obliged to control my inehnation to 
laugh. She had evidently taken me under her 
protection. Her keen little wits foresaw snares 
and difficulties besetting my steps during my 
stay at Rutland Hall, to which my newer eyes, 
she imagined, must be ignorantly blind. I 
looked at her with amusement, as she sat there 
seriously considering my financial interests. I 
had a fancy to humour this quaint confidential 
relation that had sprung up so spontaneously 
between us. I said gravely:</p>
<p>"I am very much obliged to you for your 
offer, and will gladly take advantage of it. Do 
you happen to have the guinea at hand?"</p>
<p>She seized her crutches, and limped quickly 
out of the room. Presently she returned with 
a little bon-bon box, which she placed in my 
hand. Opening it, I found one guinea, wrapped 
up carefully in silver paper.</p>
<p>"I wish it had been more!" she said, wistfully, 
as I coolly transferred it to my pocket, 
box and all. "But I so seldom get money!"</p>
<p>At this moment, the solemn person who had 
escorted me hither and thither before, announced 
that my dinner was served.</p>
<p>On my return to the drawing-room, I found, 
to my intense disappointment, that my beneficent 
bird had fiown. Teecie Ray had limped 
off to the nursery.</p>
<br/>
<p>Next morning, at breakfast, I was introduced 
to the family. I found them, on the whole, 
pretty much what I had expected. My Cousin 
George had developed into a pompous portly 
patcrfamilias; and, in spite of his cool professions 
of pleasure, was evidently very sorry to 
see me. The Mamma Rutland just countenanced 
me, in a manner the most frigidly polite. 
The grown-up young ladies treated me with 
the most well-bred negligence. Unless I had 
been very obtuse indeed, I could scarcely have 
failed to massive the place appointed for me in 
Rutland Hall. I was expected to sit below the 
salt. I was that dreadful thing--a person of no 
importance. George amused himself with me 
for a few days, displaying to me his various fine 
possessions, and then, on the arrival of grander 
guests, left me to my own resources. The 
Misses Rutland endured my escort on their 
riding expeditions only till more eligible cavaliers 
appeared. As for the lady of the house, 
her annoyance at having me quartered indefinitely 
on her premises, was hardly concealed. 
The truth was, they were new people in the 
circle in which they moved, and it did not 
suit them to have a poor relation coming suddenly 
among them, calling them "cousin," and 
making himself at home in the house. For me, 
I was not blind, though none of these things 
did it suit me to see. I made myself as comfortable 
as was possible under the circumstances, 
took every sneer and snub in excellent 
part, and Was as amiable and satisfied 
on all occasions as though I believed myself to 
be the most cherished inmate of the household. 
That this meanness of mine should provoke 
their contempt, I had hardly a right to complain 
of. Nor did I. I accepted this like the rest 
of their hospitality, and smiled contentedly as 
the days went on. The gloom which had oppressed 
me on my first arrival in England had 
all betaken itself away. How could I feel otherwise 
than supremely happy at finding myself 
thus surrounded by my kind relations, thus generously 
entertained under their hospitable roof?</p>
<p>As I found that the guests at Rutland Hall 
enjoyed a certain freedom in their choice of 
amusements, and the disposal of their time, I 
speedily availed myself of this privilege. I 
selected my own associates, and I entertained 
myself as pleased me best. Not finding myself 
always welcomed in the drawing-room, I contrived, 
by a series of the most dexterous artifices, 
to gain the free entre of the nursery. In this 
nursery were growing up, some five or six 
younger branches of the Rutland family. After 
a certain hour in the day none of the elders ever 
thought of invading its remote precincts. Five 
o'clock in the evening was the children's tea-hour, 
and the pleasantest, I thought, in the 
twenty-four. Nurse was a staid woman, who 
knew how to appreciate a little present now and 
again, and to keep her own counsel on the 
subject. The children were not pleasant children; 
they were unruly mischievous little 
wretches. They conceived a sort of affection 
for me, because I sometimes brought to the 
nursery, sundry purchases made during solitary 
rides; picture-books, tops, dolls, or sweet-meats, 
procured by means of Teecie Ray's 
guinea. I suggested as much to Teecie one 
evening as she sat by, watching the distribution, 
and she nodded her head in sage satisfaction. 
She thought .that I economised my substance 
very well. It covered a great many small 
extravagances, that guinea did.</p>
<p>Whatever might be my position at Rutland 
Hall, Teecie Ray's was simply intolerable. A 
spirit less brave must have been cowed and 
broken by it: a nature less delicate must have 
been blunted and made coarser. The servants 
Openly neglected her, the children used her as 
they pleased; wreaked their humours on her, 
sparing neither blow nor taunt in their passions, 
and demanding from her at all times 
whatever service it suited their capricious 
fancy to need. Nurse, the only one who 
ever showed a grain of consideration for the 
orphan, would sometimes shield her from their 
impish attacks, when she could do so with 
safety to herself; but she was not permitted to 
deal with those darlings in the only fashion 
which would have been at all likely to bring 
them to reason. As for the elders of the house, 
Teecie Ray's momentary presence, or the mere 
mention of her name, was sufficient to ruffle 
their peace of mind. "What is to be done 
with that girl?" I heard Mrs. Rutland remark 
to one of her daughters. "If she were not lame, 
one might set her to earn her bread in some 
way; but, as it is----" A shrug of the 
shoulders, and a certain vinegar-like expression 
of countenance, which this lady knew how to 
assume, sufficiently developed the idea thus imperfectly 
expressed.</p>
<p>And how did Teecie Ray meet all this? She 
did not complain nor rebel, she did not sulk nor 
fret. Under that well-worn black frock of 
hers, she carried a little breastplate of sober determined 
endurance. When sorely tried, there 
was never any cowardly submission to be seen in 
her grave little face, neither was there ever in 
her manner or words either reproach or remonstrance. 
She simply endured. Her large patient 
eyes and mute wise mouth seemed to say, "Whatever 
I suffer, whatever I long to dare, gratitude 
shackles my limbs, and seas my lips. I am 
saved from many things; therefore I am dumb."</p>
<p>The second time I met my little benefactress, 
was a day or two after our first interview in the 
drawing-room. I came upon her, one afternoon 
by chance, limping down a hedge lane which 
lay to the back of the house, away beyond the 
gardens, and the kitchen gardens, and the 
pleasure-grounds. This lane, I found, led to a 
large meadow, and beyond the meadow there was a 
wooded hill, and far down at the distant side of the 
hill there was a river. This was Teecie Ray's 
favourite ramble, and her one avenue of escape 
from the torments of the nursery. I immediately 
began pouring forth a legion of perplexing 
troubles and difficulties, to all of which she 
listened with perfect credulity, expressing her 
sympathy as I went along by an expressive nod 
of the head, or a shrewd swift glance. Then she 
gave me her wise little counsel when all was told, 
and went home, I believe, pondering on my case.</p>
<p>As the days passed, and my relations became 
more and more involved in their winter gaieties, 
I found myself more and more thrown upon my 
own resources for amusement. Occasionally I 
was included in an invitation, and accepted it; 
but in general I preferred indulging my fancy 
for keeping aloof from those who were little 
charmed with my company. A system of the 
most unblushing bribery had won for me a warm 
welcome from t to savage tribes in the nursery. 
Many and many an evening found me walking 
down that hedged lane in the frosty dusk, with 
Teecie Ray limping by my side, and talking her 
grave simple little talk. I had always some 
fresh puzzle to propose to her, and she was 
always ready to knit her smooth brows over its 
solution. Once she stopped short, and struck 
her little crutches on the snow.</p>
<p>"You ought to go away from here and work," 
she cried. "O, if <em>I</em> could!"</p>
<p>A certain Sir Harry arrived at Rutland Hall; 
I will not trouble myself to think of his second 
name; it is not worth remembering. He was a 
wealthy bachelor of high family, and his movements 
were watched with interest by the lady of 
the house. This Sir Harry had a fancy for 
smoking his cigar in the hedged lane, and on 
more than one occasion he encountered my little 
benefactress limping on her solitary way, and 
stared at the pretty fresh face under her old 
black hat, till it blushed with uncomfortable 
brilliance. Teecie changed her track like a 
hunted hare, but Sir Harry scented her out, and 
annoyed her With his fulsome compliments. 
The matter reached Mrs. Rutland's ears, and 
she Vented her chagrin on the defenceless little 
girl. I know not what sorry accusations and 
reproaches she bestowed upon her during a long 
private lecture; but, that evening when, at the 
children's tea-hour, I entered the nursery door 
with a new ball in my hand for Jack (the 
youngest and least objectionable of the band), I 
saw Teecie Ray's face grievously clouded for 
the first time. It was flushed and swollen with, 
passionate crying. I do not intend to commit 
to paper certain remarks which I made sotto 
voce on beholding this disfigurement.</p>
<p>"Come, come, Teecie," I said, while nurse 
was busy quelling a disturbance which had arisen 
because "Cousin Guy" had not brought something 
to every one else as well as Jack; "where 
is all your philosophy, little mother? You need 
never preach to me again, if you set me such a 
bad example."</p>
<p>Teecie said never a word, but stared on into 
the fire. This wound had cut deep. Sir Harry, 
and Mrs. Rutland, of Rutland Hall, at that 
moment I should have dearly loved to knock 
your two good-for-nothing heads together!</p>
<p>"Teecie," I said, "you have one friend, at 
any rate, even if he be not a very grand one."</p>
<p>She gave one of her quaint expressive little 
nods. Translated, it meant: "I understand all 
that, but I cannot talk just now." By-and-by, 
however, she brightened up, and went to the 
table to claim her share of tea and thick bread-and-butter, 
and I began to mend a bow belonging 
to Tom. Tom was one of the leaders of the 
unruly tribes, a regular savage chieftain.</p>
<p>Ere two days more had passed I felt strongly 
inclined to exercise the horsewhip on this 
young gentleman's shoulders. Toni, one fine 
morning, was seized with an impish inspiration 
to play a trick upon Teecie. Stealing her 
crutches, he walked about the nursery mimicking 
her poor little limp, and then marching off 
with them, heedless of her entreaties to have 
them restored, carried them in triumph out 
of doors, and smashed them in pieces with a 
hatchet. Teecie sat helpless in the din and riot 
of that ill-conditioned nursery. Bright bracing 
days came and found her a prisoner, looking 
with longing eyes through the window-panes, 
out over the beautiful country lanes. Tom saw 
her patience with the most audacious indifference. 
But why talk about Tom? I could not 
help believing, nor do I ever intend to help 
believing, that older heads than Tom's plotted 
the cruel caging of that bonnie bird.</p>
<p>The bird drooped on its perch; but who 
cared? Nurse vowed it was a shame, and 
showed more kindness than usual to the prisoner, 
but I will not venture to decide how much of 
this tenderness was owing to the odd crown-pieces 
which found their way from my hand to 
hers--all out of the guinea, of course? O yes, 
all out of the guinea. And there was another 
friend who sometimes expressed an interest in 
Teecie Ray's existence. This was that Lady 
Thornton, whose bounty had indirectly furnished 
me with pocket-money during my stay at Rutland 
Hall. The favour of this old lady I had done my 
best to win. She was a nice comfortable old 
lady, and I liked her. It happened that she 
called one day during Teecie Ray's imprisonment, 
to invite the Rutlands and their visitors, 
great and small, young and old, to a party to be 
given at her house, a few miles distant. I 
chanced to be alone in the drawing-room when 
she arrived, and I seized the Opportunity to tell 
her the story of Teecie's crutches.</p>
<p>"A bad boy!" she said. "A bad, malicious 
boy! She must get new crutches before my 
party."</p>
<p>"Of course she must," I said, very heartily.</p>
<p>The old lady threw back her head, raising her 
fat chin in a peculiar sort of way, and looking 
at me direct through her spectacles.</p>
<p>"Indeed!" she said. "Pray, young man, 
what particular interest do you take in Teecie 
Ray?"</p>
<p>I smiled. "Oh, Teecie and I are excellent 
friends," I said.</p>
<p>"Teecie and you!" she repeated. "Pray, 
are you aware that; Miss Ray is eighteen years 
of age?"</p>
<p>"Is she indeed? I know nothing about the 
ages of little girls."</p>
<p>"But Teecie is not a little girl, Mr. Guy Rutland. 
Teecie Ray is a woman, I tell you!"</p>
<p>Teecie Ray a woman! I could not help laughing. 
What? My little benefactress, my little 
mother! I am afraid I scandalised Lady Thornton 
on that occasion by my utter scorn of her 
proposition. Christina Rutland swept into the 
room at this crisis, and relieved me in my difficulty. 
But. often afterwards during that day, 
I laughed when I thought of Lady Thornton's 
piece of information. Teecie Ray a woman? 
Preposterous!</p>
<br/>
<p>One morning, when it wanted but a week of 
the party, a curious event occurred. The 
heads of the house met in consultation on the 
matter, in the library, before breakfast. An extraordinarv 
Thing had arrived from London at 
Rutland Hall. The Thing was a large wooden 
case, directed to Teecie Ray. On being eagerly 
opened, it was found to contain a pair of 
crutches.</p>
<p>And such a pair of crutches! Light and symmetrical, 
and fanciful, works of art in their way. 
Tortoiseshell stems with Silver mountings of exquisite 
workmanship, capped with dainty little 
cushions of embroidered velvet. Thunder-stricken 
were the elders of the house. "Who could have 
done this thing?" was on every lip. Who, indeed? 
Who outside of Rutland Hall had ever 
heard of Teecie Ray? These crutches were 
costly affairs. I knew the conclusion they came 
to, one and all. They pitched on Sir Harry as 
the culprit. It was a thorn in their side, and I 
rubbed my hands in glee.</p>
<p>Having considered the question in their dismay, 
they decided that Teecie should be kept 
in ignorance of her mysterious present. It was 
not fit for her to use, it would fill her mind with 
absurd ideas. And so, in spite of the arrival 
of her beautiful new crutches, poor Teecie still 
sat helpless in the nursery. The wooden case 
and its contents were hidden array, and no word 
was spoken of their existence.</p>
<p>I waited a few days to see if the elders 
would relent, but to no purpose. The bird still 
pined on its perch. No kindly hand seemed 
likely to open the cage door and let it fly. 
There sat Teecie, day after day, in her nursery 
chair, hemming aprons for nurse, or darning 
the children's stockings, looking longingly out 
of the window, and growing pale for want of 
fresh air. Still never rebelling, never complaining. 
Meantime the stir of Christmas preparation 
was agitating all the household, and the children 
were full of rapture at the prospect of 
Lady Thornton's Christmas party. There was 
great excitement in the nursery about pretty 
new dresses, wonderful fussing about ribbons, 
and muslins, and fripperies. Teecie alone sat 
silent in her shabby frock. By-and-by, her hands 
were full, bowing up sashes, sewing on tuckers, 
stitching rosettes on shoes. She one a nimble 
little workwoman, and they kept her busy. 
Seeing how well a lapful of bright ribbons became 
her, I thought it a pity she should not 
have a gay dress as well as the rest.</p>
<p>Nobody said, "Tessie, what will you wear?" 
nor even, " Teecie, are not you invited too P" No  
one seemed to expect for a moment that Teecie 
could wish to be merry with the rest. How could  
she go, she who was lame and had no crutches?</p>
<p>It happened that I had an errand to the 
nearest town. It was rather late when, on my 
return, I called at the best millinery establishment 
in the place, and asked for a parcel.</p>
<p>Yes, the parcel was ready. A large flat box. 
"Would the gentleman like to see the lady's 
pretty dress?" The box was opened, and a 
cloud of some airy fabric shaken out under my 
eyes. I cannot, of course, describe it, but it 
was something white, very pure and transparent, 
with something else of pink just blushing through 
it. It was very tasteful, I pronounced, trying 
to look wise. There was only one fault: "Did 
it not seem rather long for a little girl?" I 
asked, remembering the figure it was to adorn, 
With its short skirt just coming to the top of the 
boots, so well worn and mended.</p>
<p>"Uh, sir," said the milliner, with dignity, 
"you said the young lady was eighteen years of 
age, and of course we have given her a flowing 
skirt!"</p>
<p>It was late in the evening when I reached 
home. Two merry carriage-tulle were just departing 
from the door as I drove up. A few 
minutes afterwards, I was in the nursery with 
the milliner's parcel in my hands. There sat 
dear little Cinderella. resting one flushed check 
on her hand, and contemplating the litter of 
scraps of ribbon, fragments of lace, scissors, 
flowers, and reels of cotton, which lay scattered 
around her. She had had a toilsome tiresome 
day, and now they had got all they wanted of 
her, and had left her to her solitude.</p>
<p>A flash of pleasure sprang to her face when 
she saw me. "Oh! I thought you had gone 
With the rest," she said.</p>
<p>"No," said I, "I have not gone yet, but I 
am going presently. I came for you."</p>
<p>"For me!" she echoed in dismay. "You 
know I could not go. I have no dress, even if I 
could walk."</p>
<p>"A friend has sent you a dress," I said, "and 
I will undertake to provide the crutches. Nurse, 
will you please to take this box, and get Miss 
Teecie ready as quickly as possible. The carriage 
is waiting for us at the door."</p>
<p>Teecie flushed very red at first, and I thought 
she was going to burst out crying, and then she 
turned pale, and looked frightened. Nurse, to 
whom I had slipped a magnificent Christmas-box, 
immediately fell into raptures over the 
pretty dress.</p>
<p>"Come, Teecie," I said, "make haste!" And, 
trembling between dread and delight, Teecie 
suffered herself to be carried off to her toilette.</p>
<p>By the time I returned from an exploring expedition, 
with the wonderful silver-and-tortoiseshell 
crutches under my arm, Teecie was ready.</p>
<p>Teecie was ready. Those three simple little 
words mean so much that I feel I must stop and 
try to translate them into all they are bound 
to convey. They do not mean that Teecie, the 
child whom I was wont to call my little benefactress, 
my little mother, had got on a nice 
new frock, and was equipped for a juvenile 
party like other children. But they mean, that 
there, when I came back, stood a beautiful girl 
by the nursery fire, in a fair sweeping blush-coloured 
robe. When she turned her head, I 
saw that the sweet face framed in its childlike 
curls was the same, but still the old Teecie 
Ray was gone, and here was (<em>peccavi</em> Lady 
Thornton!) a lovely woman.</p>
<p>We were all three ludicrously amazed at the 
sudden metamorphose that had taken place. 
Teecie was too simple not to show that she felt 
the change in herself, felt it keenly, with a 
strange delight and a strange shyness. Nurse 
had so long been accustomed to use her as a 
child that. she stood bewildered. As for me, I 
was first frightened at what I had done, then 
enchanted, then foolishly awkward, and almost as 
shy as Teecie herself.</p>
<p>When I presented the crutches, nurse looked 
at me as though I must be some prince in 
disguise, out of the Arabian Nights. It was 
with a curious feeling that I saw Teecie try 
them, not limping now, rather gliding over 
the. nursery floor, With the little velvet cushions 
hidden away amidst clouds of lace and muslin 
under her round white shoulders, and the airy 
masses of the fresh tinted gown just crushed 
hack a little by the gleaming silver slaves. I 
don't know why it was that I thought at that 
moment, with a certain rapture, of a games in a 
little bon-bon box, that lay below in the one 
shabby portmanteau which I had thought proper 
to bring with me to Rutland Hall!</p>
<p>Our equipage awaited us. It was too into 
new to withdraw from what I had undertaken. 
Teecie and I were soon dashing over the snowy 
roads to Lady Thornton's. I will not attempt 
to describe the remainder of that memorable 
evening, or the sensation caused by our arrival; 
the wonder and mortification of my kind relations; 
or the mingled pleasure and displeasure of 
the hostess, who, while delighted to see her little 
favourite, took occasion to whisper angrily in my 
ear, "And pray, sir, how is all this to end?"</p>
<p>The scene was all new and delightful to 
Teecie, but her dread of Mrs. Rutland's portentous 
frown would not let her enjoy it. We 
both felt that a storm would burst over our 
heads that night, and we were not wrong. 
None of the family from Rutland Hall took the 
least notice of us. When the time came for 
going home, they went off in their two carriages, 
and Teecie and I drove home as we had come. 
When we arrived, we found Cousin George and 
his wife waiting for us in the library, armed to the 
teeth. I saw it was to be war and no quarter. 
Mrs. Rutland took Teecie into her clutches, and 
carried her off, and I was left with George. I 
need not repeat all that passed between us.</p>
<p>"Sir," he said, "we have suffered your 
insolent intrusion long enough. You leave this 
house tomorrow morning."</p>
<p>"Cousin George," I said, "don't put yourself 
in a passion. I will go tomorrow morning, 
but upon one condition--that Teecie Ray may 
come with me, if she will."</p>
<p>He looked at me perfectly aghast. "Do you 
know," he said, "that she is a penniless friendless 
orphan, whom I have sheltered through charity?"</p>
<p>"I want to make her my wife," I said, sternly, 
"if, indeed, I be so fortunate as to have won 
her affections."</p>
<p>"And after that," he said, with a sneer "how 
do you propose to live? Upon air, or your 
friends?"</p>
<p>"Not upon you, George Rutland," I said, 
looking him steadily in the eyes. "Mark me. 
I have tried you out. I have sifted you, all 
in this house, like a handful of wheat. I found 
you all chaff', but the one golden grain which lies 
on my palm. I will keep it and treasure it, if I 
may. God grant I may!"</p>
<p>"Very fine," said George, "<em>very</em> fine. Remember, 
however, that from this moment I wash 
my hands of you both: you, Guy Rutland, and 
her, Teecie Ray."</p>
<p>"Amen!" I said, and bade him good night, 
and turned on my heel and left him.</p>
<p>Early next morning I knocked at the nursery 
door, and begged of nurse to awake Miss Teecie, 
and ask her to speak with me in the garden. I 
then went out to wait for her. It was Christmas 
morning, the day of peace and good will. What 
I felt was scarcely peace, as I looked over the 
calm landscape. And yet I here no ill will to 
any man or woman.</p>
<p>Teecie came to me by-and-by; just the same 
old Teecie, limping over the frosty path in her 
short shabby frock, and looking half ashamed of 
her grand new crutches. I felt relieved when 
I saw her so. I was shy of the dainty lady 
whom I had called into existence the night before. 
And yet when I looked more closely, I knew 
that this was not quite the old Teecie, and that 
the very same Teecie of a day ago never, never, 
could come back. Something was altered. 
Whether the change was in her or me, or in 
both of us, I did not inquire. The change was 
not an unpleasant one.</p>
<p>We strolled out of the garden, and into the 
lane, and we talked earnestly all the way. On 
our way back I said:</p>
<p>"And you're not afraid of starving with me, 
Teecie? You'll take the risk?"</p>
<p>One of her old nods was Teecie's answer.</p>
<p>"Go and fetch your hat, then," said I, "and 
we won't even wait for breakfast. Don't bring 
anything else with you, not a shred. I have 
still some halfpence left--out of the guinea, you 
know--and we'll get all we want."</p>
<p>Teecie fetched her hat and returned, and we 
set off together. An hour afterwards we were 
man and wife. We said our prayers side 
by side in the church, and then we walked 
back to Rutland Hall, to say good-by to our 
kinsfolk. I believe they all thought me mad, 
and her a little fool;--at least until Cousin 
George received the cheque, which I sent him 
next day; a cheque to cover the expenses 
incurred by him through his charity to Teecie 
Ray. Then they began to wonder, and to 
waver. I took my Wife abroad, and showed her 
the world. Time and care cured her of her 
lameness. It was not surprising that on her 
return to England her kinsfolk should scarcely 
recognise her--Teecie Rutland nee Ray--
walking without crutches, and the wife of a 
millionaire! Half a bride-cake conciliated Lady 
Thornton, and the wonderful guinea is still in 
my possession. I call it Teecie's dower. The 
crutches, the donor of which I beg to assure 
you, major, was <em>not</em> Sir Harry, are also preserved 
as family curiosities.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="ANOTHER PAST LODGER RELATES WHAT LOT HE DREW AT GLUMPER HOUSE."/>
<chapter>
<p>If the dietary at Doctor Glumper's could not 
be pronounced purely Spartan in its principles, it 
was simply that the Spartan stomach--well disciplined 
as we know it to have been--would have 
revolted at such treatment. Salamis demanded 
other stamina than could be supplied by the washings 
of a beef-bone. Xerxes was not deified under 
the immediate inspiration of rice-dumpling.</p>
<p>Doctor Glumper's was not much worse, in its 
commissariat, my dear Major Jackman, than hundreds 
of other establishments, at which--in those 
days--the sons of gentlemen studied and starved. 
There was enough to live upon, provided we 
could have fairly eaten what there <em>was</em>. Therein 
lay the difficulty. Our meals, bad enough at the 
beginning of the week, grew gradually worse 
towards the end: insomuch that we arrived at 
the Sabbath, much in the condition of a band of 
young seafarers, who had been cast away, and 
were only saved from utter starvation by the 
opportune arrival of a ship freighted with roast-beef 
and Yorkshire pudding.</p>
<p>True, there was a life-boat. It's name, in our 
case, was "Hannah's Basket." Hannah was the 
laundress, and, on Saturday afternoon, after delivering 
the linen, regularly made her appearance 
in the playground, displaying the bottom of her 
buck-basket paved with delicacies, carefully 
selected on the principle of combining the three 
grand qualities of sweetness, stickiness, and 
economy.</p>
<p>Elegance and refinement were little thought 
of, in those days. The boy who brought a silver 
fork, Would have been simply regarded as 
possessed of a jocular turn. As for the spoon 
and six towels, which, according to the printed 
terms of Glumper House, seemed absolutely 
essential to a sound classical education--the 
spoon found its way into a species of armoury of 
Mrs. Glumper's, formed of the spoils of the 
young Philistines, her pupils, prohibited toys, 
confiscated literature, and so forth; while the 
towels, absorbed in the general republic of that 
article, passed into indiscriminate use. Well, 
we had nothing to say against steel forks. The 
meat, peradventure, might have proved impervious 
to any less undaunted metal.</p>
<p>Our Monday's dinner was boiled leg of mutton. 
One helping. More was not refused; but the 
ill-concealed impatience with which the application 
was received, established the custom of contenting 
ourselves with what was first supplied. 
The due reward of this pusillanimity appeared 
on the following day, in the form of half-consumed 
joints--cold, ghastly, seamed with red 
murderous streaks, and accompanied by certain 
masses of ill-washed cabbage, interesting as an 
entomological study; but, as a viand, repulsive 
by reason of the caterpillars, whose sodden dull-green 
corpses I have seen lying in ranks beside 
the plates of fastidious feeders.</p>
<p>Three days a week, we had rice-pudding--a 
confection which, by an unfortunate conjuncture 
of circumstances, I never could from infancy 
endure; but the great trial of our lives, and 
stomachs, was reserved for Saturday, when we 
sat down to what was satirically styled a "beefsteak-pie."</p>
<p>Mean and debased must be the spirit of that 
bullock who would confess to any share in such 
a production! into the composition of that dish 
beef entered as largely as the flesh of the unicorn 
into peas-porridge. The very wildness of the 
rumours that were afloat respecting its actual 
origin proved how dark, difficult, and mysterious 
was the inquiry. School tradition pointed to the 
most grotesque and inharmonious elements, as 
actually detected in the pie. Substances, in 
texture, flavour, and appearance, the reverse of 
bovine, had been over and over again deposed to 
by the dismayed recipients, who proved their 
good faith by preferring famine itself to "beefsteak"-pie. 
The utter impossibility of identifying 
the ingredients as having pertained to 
any animal recognised by British cooks, was the 
terrific feature of the case.</p>
<p>Whatever was the prevailing element of the 
pic, it was supplemented with minor matters, 
about which, though they do not appear in any 
accepted recipe for the dish in question, there 
could be no dispute.</p>
<p>Sholto Shillito, for instance, who had the appetite 
of an ogre, boldly swallowed the portion 
assigned him, but quietly and sternly removed to 
the side of his plate three fingers and a ligament 
of the thumb of an ancient dog-skin glove.</p>
<p>Billy Duntze discovered and secreted something 
that was for several halves preserved in the 
school as the leg of a flamingo. At all events, it 
was introduced, so labelled, to every new arrival, 
on the very first evening of his sojourn among us.</p>
<p>George van Kempen found a pair of snuffers.</p>
<p>Charley Brooksbank remarked a singular protuberance 
in his portion of pie, and, carefully excavating 
the same, as if it were a Phoenician relic, 
brought to light something that looked like the 
head of a doll that had been afflicted with hydrocephalus. 
On being cut into, it was green. 
For the first few weeks of each half--that is, 
while our pocket-money held out--we got on 
pretty well. Our pocket-money exhausted, starvation 
stared us in the face.</p>
<p>The present generation may wonder why we 
did not try the effect of respectful remonstrance. 
The times, as I have said, were different then, and 
besides, the present generation didn't personally 
know Mrs. Glumper. A fearful woman was Mrs. 
Glumper. I don't mean that she raved, struck, 
or demeaned herself in any way not ordinarily 
witnessed in polite society; but I do mean that 
she had a cool quiet seem, a consciousness of a 
putting-down power, as though an elephant, just 
tickling the ground with a foot as big as a 
writing-table, were to show how easily and effectually 
he might, if he pleased, turn that table 
upon <em>you</em>.</p>
<p>In addition to this overbearing contempt, Mrs. 
Glumper had a thousand ways of making us uncomfortable, 
without resorting to overt tyranny; insomuch 
that to be "out of favour" with that excellent 
lady was regarded as the climax of school 
misery.</p>
<p>Not a word have I to say against the doctor. 
Even <em>then</em> I felt him to be a good man. In remembering 
his character, I believe him to have 
been one of the best that ever breathed. With 
the understanding of a sage, he was as simple as 
a child; <em>so</em> simple, that it was matter of genuine 
astonishment that he retained the coat upon his 
back; <em>so</em> simple, that the circumstance of his 
having espoused Mrs. G. became almost intelligible. 
For this guileless act, rumour even supplied 
the motive. Mrs. Glumper, then Miss 
Kittiewinkle, was herself the mistress of an extremely 
preparatory school, and it was in the 
cowed and miserable victims of her Muscovite 
rule that the kind doctor read an invitation of the 
most pressing kind, to take the mistress under 
<em>his</em>. The consequence of this union of interests 
was, that the establishment, losing its infantine 
character, flourished up into a school of seventy 
boys; only the very smallest of whom were submitted 
to Mrs. Glumper's immediate dominion.</p>
<p>Affairs were in this unsatisfactory position 
towards the middle of a certain half. It was precisely 
the period at which the greatest impecuniosity 
usually prevailed. Money was tighter 
than any one could recollect. Hannah's bread-stuff's 
were in a condition of blockade. Could 
"shirtings" have been exchanged for ratings, 
Hannah might have done a brisk business in 
turn-downs, but the old lady was too wary for 
such traffic.</p>
<p>We held a consultation. The doctor's cow, 
which sometimes grazed in the playing-field, was 
incidentally present, and by her sleek contented 
aspect, excited universal disgust.</p>
<p>"Crib her oilcake!" squeaked a voice from 
the outer senatorial circle.</p>
<p>"It is well for the honourable felon on the 
back benches," remarked our president, Jack 
Rogers, who delighted to give to our consultations 
the aspect of a grave debate, "that his 
skull is beyond punching-distance. If the oilcake, 
lavished on yonder pampered animal, had 
been vested in trustees, to the sole and separate 
use, notwithstanding coverture, of <em>Mrs</em>. Glumper 
--I--well, I will go so far as to say this council 
might have taken into consideration what has 
fallen from the distinguished thief. But it's 
Glumper's, and the proposal of the estimable 
criminal will be received with the contempt it 
deserves."</p>
<p>A murmur of approval greeted this speech, 
after which sundry suggestions were offered.</p>
<p>Burned pens (Gus Halfacre remarked) were 
edible. He <em>might</em> say, toothsome.</p>
<p>"My left boot is at the service of the commonwealth," 
said Frank Lightfoot. "The right, 
having been recently repaired and thickened, and 
being devoid of a large nail in the sole (of which 
I invite the state to take heed), I reserve to 
myself for the last extremity."</p>
<p>"Thus extremes <em>will</em> meet," observed the 
president. "But this is no season for jesting. 
Has anybody anything to propose?"</p>
<p>"We have always Murrell Robinson," said 
Sholto Shillito, gloomily, and with an aspect so 
wolfish, that the young gentleman alluded to--a 
plump rosy child of eight, who had not yet had 
time to dwindle--set up a howl of terror.</p>
<p>"It might--humph--yes, it might be politic," 
said the chairman, thought fully. "'Twould touch 
her home. If Jezebel Glumper lost a couple, 
say, of pupils, under the peculiar circumstances 
glanced at by the honourable senator in the 
inky corduroys, she might have some--shall I 
say bowels?--for those of the remainder. But 
the observation of my honourable friend has suggested 
to my mind a course of action which, 
though in some respects similar, and promising 
the like results, is not open to the same objections. 
Some fellow must <em>bolt</em>, placing on record 
his reasons for that step."</p>
<p>Jack's proposal, unexpected as it was, met 
with considerable favour, the only difficulty being 
to decide who the fugitive should be. Bolting 
from school by no means implied return to the 
paternal mansion. Everybody looked inquiringly 
at his neighbour. No one volunteered.</p>
<p>The chairman surveyed us with mournful 
severity.</p>
<p>"There was once," he faltered, "an individual, 
known to you all (except the fifth 
class)--wept over by some--who, on learning 
that he might greatly benefit certain public property 
by jumping into a hole, asked no questions, 
popped in, and did it. Has our school no 
Curtius? Must seventy stomachs languish unsatisfied 
for want of a single heart? Shillito, 
you greedy young beggar, <em>you</em> will go."</p>
<p>Mr. Shillito emphatically invoked benediction 
on himself, in the event of his doing anything of 
the kind.</p>
<p>"Percy Pobjoy," said the president, "you are 
one at odds with fortune. You are penniless--
worse, for your week's pay, old chap, is impounded 
for a month. You have sailed into the extreme 
north of Mrs. Glumper's favour, and are likely to 
make it your persistent abode. You detest rice. 
You have scruples concerning caterpillars. Percival, 
my friend, three ladies of eminence, whose 
names and office are fully recorded in your classical 
dictionary, unanimously select <em>you</em> as the party to 
perform this public service."</p>
<p>Mr. Pobjoy regretted to run counter to the 
anticipations of <em>any</em> lady, but, possessing, as he 
did, a grandmother who would, he conceived, 
prove more than a match for the three Destinies 
--and he would throw the Furies in--he must 
deny himself the gratification proposed.</p>
<p>"Then," resumed the president, cheerfully, 
with the air of having at last secured his man, 
"I at once address myself to the distinguished 
senator on the inverted flower-pot. He who 
hatred that bully, the miller's boy, in twelve 
minutes and a half, Will be again our champion. 
Joles will go."</p>
<p>Mr. Joles somewhat sullenly failed to perceive 
the analogy between pitching into a cheeky 
clown, and running away from school. Could 
the honourable president detect the smallest indication 
of verdure in his (Mr. J.'s) sinister 
organ of Vision? Such a contingency was, nevertheless, 
essential to his (Mr. J.'s) adopting the 
course required of him.</p>
<p>Other honourable senators hating, when appealed 
to, returned answers of a no less discouraging 
character, there seemed to be but one 
course remaining--that of drawing lots. A resolution 
to do this was carried, after some discussion: 
it being agreed that he on whom the lot 
might fall should decamp on the morrow, and, 
having found some secure hiding-place, write to 
one of his schoolmates, or (perhaps preferably) 
to his own friends, declaring that the stop he had 
taken was prompted by a reluctance to perish 
of starvation.</p>
<p>The proposed time was subsequently extended 
to one week, in order that he who drew the fatal 
lot might have tune to try the effect of a touching 
appeal to his parents or friends, fairly setting 
forth the treatment we were experiencing. If 
this answered, well and good. If not, the 
honourable gentleman (said our chief) "will cut 
his lucky this day se'nnight."</p>
<p>Lots were then solemnly drawn, in the primitive 
Homeric fashion, every boy's name--those 
of the fifth class excepted--being inscribed in a 
slip of paper, and flung into a hat. There was a 
strong feeling in favour of exempting Jack 
Rogers, our president--the Nestor of the school 
--who, being near seventeen, and  about to leave, 
would, no doubt, have preferred fighting through 
the remainder of his term, famish as he might. But 
the good fellow flounced at the idea, as though it 
had been an insult, and himself cast in his name.</p>
<p>Carefully following our classic model, the hat 
was then violently shaken. The lot that, in obedience 
to a fillip from the Fates, first leaped out 
and touched the earth, was to decide the question. 
<em>Two</em> flew out, but one of these rested on the 
shaker's sleeve. There was a decided disinclination 
to take up the other. It seemed as if nobody 
had, until this supreme crisis, fully realised 
the consequences that might ensue from thus 
abandoning at. once both school and home.</p>
<p>My heart, I confess, stood still for a moment, 
as Jack Rogers stood forward and picked up the 
paper. Then I felt the blood mount to my 
cheeks, as our leader slowly read, "Charles 
Stuart Trelawny."</p>
<p>"Always in luck, Charley!" he continued, 
laughing; but I think Jack only intended to keep 
up my spirits. "Write directly, my boy,"he added, 
in a graver tone, "and, take my advice, write hang 
up to the governor. Treat it as a matter of business. 
Mamma is safe to put in <em>her</em> word."</p>
<p>I wrote at once:</p>
<letter>
<p>"My dear Papa,--I hope you are quite well. 
I ain't. You know I'm not greedy, and not so 
foolish as to expect at school such jolly things 
as at home. So you must not be angry when 
I say what I'm <em>obliged</em> to say, that we can't eat 
what Mrs. Glumper says is dinner; and as there's 
nothing else but slop and a bit of bread, everybody's 
starving.</p>
<right>"I remain, your dutiful Son,</right>
<right>"C. S. T<sc>RELAWNY</sc>.</right>
<br/>
<p>"PS. If you don't like to speak to Mrs. 
Glumper, would you mind asking mamma and 
Agnes, with my love, to send me a big loaf of 
bread (With Crust, and, if possible, browned) that 
might last a week?</p>
<right>"Lieut.-Gen. Trelawny, C.B., K.H.,</right>
<right>Penrhyn Court."</right>
</letter>
<p>I thought this despatch sufficiently business-like, 
and wanted with some anxiety for the result. 
If papa only knew what depended on his decision! 
He <em>ought</em> to put faith in me, for I had never been 
untruthful, and had done myself no more than  
justice in reminding him that I was no glutton.</p>
<p>It was, I believe, on the fourth day of suspense 
that a large parcel was brought into the 
playground, a crowd of curious and expectant 
youths escorting it, and witnessing its delivery. 
Small blame to them!</p>
<p>There resided within the limits of that parcel 
--for, though mighty, it <em>had</em> its limits--first, a 
beefsteak-pie, not only composed of real beef, 
but enriched with eggs and minor excellences, all 
trembling in a jellied gravy of surpassing savour, 
There was, secondly , a chosen company of mince-pies, 
clinging together from sheer richness, in 
such wise that a very stoic, it' hungry, might be 
reluctant to "sever such sweet friends," and 
devour them two at a time.</p>
<p>There was revealed, in the third place, a large 
apple turnover: so called, I should surmise, 
because a boy might turn it over and over, and 
back again, and, after all, find himself unable to 
determine which looked the more enticing--the 
sugary, or the buttery side. And, finally, there 
was a cake which I can scarcely repent having 
characterised, at the moment, as "tremendous!"</p>
<p>There was no letter, but the augury seemed 
good. Such ambassadors as pics and turnovers 
Speak with tongues of their own. It was <em>not</em> 
intended that we should perish. We should see 
the effect of my manly and business-like appeal, 
perhaps that very day, in an improved bill of 
fare, and a diminution of caterpillars. As to 
husbanding our new supplies, such an idea never 
occurred to any one. Alas, that we could not <em>all</em> 
partake! Lots had to be once more drawn, and 
a lucky party of eighteen, with Jack Rogers and 
myself, honorary, made extremely short work of 
the parcel.</p>
<p>Shade follows sunshine. There was no amelioration 
of the accustomed fare at dinner; but a 
decided cloud on Mrs. Glumper's haughty brow 
was interpreted favourably by Jack--a close 
observer of human nature--as evincing her disgust 
at the costly reform to which she saw herself 
committed.</p>
<p>Alas! for once, our leader was wrong. Not 
that day, nor the following day, nor any other 
day, so long, as that establishment survived, was 
there any departure from the time-(dis)honoured 
rules of diet.</p>
<p>It was long before I came into possession 
of the state papers actually exchanged on this occasion. 
Premising that my father, busied with his 
other letters, had handed over mine to my mother, 
saying, "Do see to this, my dear," here they are:</p>
<br/>
<p>The Lady Caroline Trelawny to Mrs. Glumper.</p>
<letter>
<p>"Dear Mrs. Glumper,--I trust that the size 
of the parcel Iforward to my boy, will not alarm 
you. Charley is growing very rapidly, so rapidly, 
indeed, that his father drew my attention to the 
circumstance, not without some misgiving the 
he might outgrow his strength. You may smile 
at the anxiety that prompts me to remind one so 
experienced as yourself in the care of youth, that 
good, clean, and sufficient food is more than ever 
necessary to my tall boy. He is not a dainty 
boy, and the conditions I have mentioned will, I 
am sure, meet all that he, or I, on his behalf, 
could desire. With compliments to Dr. Glumper, 
I am, dear Mrs. Glumper, sincerely yours,</p>
<right>"C<sc>AROLINE</sc> M. T<sc>RELAWNY</sc>."</right> 
</letter>
<p>Mrs. Glumper to the Lady Caroline Trelawny.</p>
<letter>
<p>"Dear Madam--Perhaps the most satisfactory 
answer I can make to your obliging note will be 
conveyed in the assurance that Dr. Glumper, 
myself, our family, and the masters (except 
Monsieur Legourmet, who insists on providing 
his own meals), live invariably with, and as, our 
boys; and that, in the matter of food, there is 
neither stint nor compulsion.</p>
<right>"Respectfully yours,</right>
<right>"J<sc>EZEBEL</sc> G<sc>LUMPER</sc>."</right> 
</letter>
<p>There was, unfortunately, just sufficient colouring 
of truth in this to satisfy the consciences of 
both ladies. They <em>did</em> dine, or rather sit down, 
with us, and, being helped first to the tit-bits, 
accompanied with hot gravy and et ceteras, at 
their own cross-table, got on pretty well. As for 
the good old doctor, he was the most innocent of 
accomplices in promoting our starvation. He 
simply did as his wife decreed, caring nothing for 
himself, and would have starved with his boys, 
without a murmur.</p>
<p>After it became apparent that our move had 
failed, all, before the arrival of the fatal day, passed 
with me like a curious dream. I felt as if I no 
longer belonged to the school, hardly to myself, 
and though no verbal reference was made to my 
impending disappearance, I saw that no one had 
forgotten it. Significant were the facts, that 
Percy Pobjoy, who had owed me eightpence from 
time immemorial, borrowed that sum to repay 
me; and that another chap, with whom I had 
had a row, spontaneously asked my pardon.</p>
<p>Saturday--<em>the</em> day--appeared in due course. 
There remained but one more meal, one more 
chance for Mrs. Glumper and for me.</p>
<p>"If she gives us but a commonly decent feed 
to-day," muttered Jack Rogers, pinching my 
elbow, as we went in, "by Jove, Charley, my 
boy, we'll stop <em>your</em> nefarious plans!"</p>
<p>No such chance. There it Was, the flabby 
mass of rice, helped first, as a good appetite-choking 
stuff, to relieve the succeeding dish from 
any undue pressure.</p>
<p>After rice appeared the much-dreaded pie, 
glaring yellowly, with its coarse pretentious outside 
--prototype of many a living humbug--veiling 
one knows not what of false and vile. O, 
the contrast to the rich and delicate article--
alike only in name--sent by my mother!</p>
<p>The pie was served, and was undergoing the 
usual suspicious scrutiny, when Mrs. Glumper, 
with the voice of a herald, proclaimed:</p>
<p>"Master Trelawny will eat every grain of that 
rice before he receives anything further."</p>
<p>There was a half-audible titter; but I remained 
firm, and thus ended the last "dinner" at 
Glumper House.</p>
<p>Jack Rogers put his arm in mine.</p>
<p>"I'm sorry for this, Trelawny," he said.</p>
<p>"I'm <em>not</em>," said I, trying to smile, "exc--
except for--" I thought of my mother, and 
broke down.</p>
<p>"We'll have a Palaver, at all events," said Jack,</p>
<p>In a moment, a large concourse assembled 
under our favourite elm. If the truth must out, 
I could have dispensed with this ceremony, 
which somehow imparted a sensation of being 
present at one's own burial. But Jack Rogers 
was not to be denied this splendid opportunity 
of speech-making.</p>
<p>He did speak, in a manner, and at a length, that 
must have been remembered in the school long 
after I--its theme--was forgotten there. In his 
peroration, he observed that the honour and the 
well-being of Glumper's could not, in this extremity, 
have been confided to worthier hands. 
Nor was it this community alone that was to 
profit by the important step about to be taken. 
The eyes of every school in Europe were, or 
would be, if they knew what was going on, 
fixed on Glumper House. Mr. Trelawny was about 
to place his foot on the first rung of the ladder 
of affluence, fame, and power. What pecuniary 
means, he would frankly ask, were at my disposal?</p>
<p>I replied, with the like openness, "Eightpence."</p>
<p>"The precise amount," resumed Jack, triumphantly, 
"(within one and tenpence) from 
whence colossal fortunes spring! 'He began 
his immortal career with half-a-crown.' Or, 
'The origin of this eminent citizen was of the 
humblest; he commenced life with two-and-sixpence.' 
Or, 'Our modern Croesus began the 
battle of life with the moiety of a five-shilling 
piece. He died worth TWO MILLIONS sterling!' 
Such, are among our most familiar passages in 
biography. Charles, my boy, again you are in 
luck." And he shook my hand warmly.</p>
<p>I ventured incidentally to suggest that I was 
<em>not</em> in possession of the magical amount required.</p>
<p>"Nay, by George, but you shall be!" exclaimed 
Jack. "Here's Sixpence towards it. Think of 
it when you're a confoundedly crusty old millionnaire, 
and send old Jack a haunch from one of 
your deer-parks--the Scotch one. Who'll subscribe 
to the Trelawny Testimonial?"</p>
<p>Hard up as the good chaps,were, so many 
came forward, that a sum of about nine-and-sixpence 
was poured into the hands of our chief. 
But Jack's remark had been working strangely 
in my mind. Something admonished me to keep 
strictly to the rule which had, apparently, prospered 
so well.</p>
<p>In a few words I thanked my mates, therefore, 
for their kind intentions, but declined to take 
more than was required to make up the exact 
fortune-making sum. I would do nothing (I 
added, in substance) to risk a failure, nor impair 
the innate vigour, the youthful freshness, of half-a-crown, 
by dabbling with an adolescent amount 
like ten-and-twopence: a sum entirely unassociated 
with any of those encouraging biographies 
quoted by our president. I would take my 
half-crown--no more.</p>
<p>As the day was waning, it became necessary to 
make preparations for my departure. Accordingly, 
attended by a few faithful friends, I proceeded 
to make up a small bundle, such as I 
could conveniently carry, leaving the remainder 
of my possessions at the disposal of fate. There 
was one thing I was very loth to abandon. It 
was a flower-pot, containing the commencement 
of a very promising scarlet-runner. It had been 
the source of great interest and consolation. I 
half resolved to make it the sharer of my fortunes. 
But Jack Rogers objected. In vain he taxed 
his memory to recall any one instance in which 
the successful adventurer had flung himself upon 
the world with half-a-crown <em>and</em> a scarlet-runner 
If the case of Jack and the Beanstalk were relied 
upon, he (Rogers) would only remark that the 
present age of inquiry had succeeded in throwing 
very considerable doubt upon portions of that 
narrative. This was enough.</p>
<p>About escaping, there was no difficulty. Part 
of the playing-field was out of sight of the house, 
and, although it was penal to frequent this portion, 
and it was the duty of the monitor of the 
day to report any one so doing, on the present 
occasion the monitor in person gave me a leg up 
the wall. There was a last shaking of hands, and 
a suppressed cheer, when I paused for a moment 
on the top.</p>
<p>"You'll write that letter to-morrow, then, 
from--from somewhere?" said Jack, mysteriously. 
(I nodded.) "All right, old boy?"</p>
<p>"Ye-es," I responded. "All right, you know. 
Hoor----"</p>
<p>Down I dropped----adrift!</p>
<p>That wall seemed to make all the difference. 
I don't think that, until my feet alighted on the 
ahen ground of Mr. Turfitt's brick-field, I had 
fully realised the fact of running away. But a 
runaway 'I was now; and, to do my boyish courage 
Justice, no thought of returning or seeking 
the protection of home, ever entered into my 
imagination. One brief and bitter pang I did experience, 
as I thought of the probable effect the 
tidings of my flight might have upon the happy 
home circle; but I met it with the reflection that 
the letter I should write must set them at ease 
as to my personal safety and prospects. In the 
mean time, it was obviously desirable to get away.</p>
<p>Dr. Glumper's was situated in an open suburb 
north of London, and therefore, well on the high 
road to fortune. I set my face straight towards 
the quarter in which I concluded the City to lie, 
and trudged on, vaguely wondering what would 
happen to me when bedtime came.</p>
<p>Suddenly, a bright thought, suggested by 
the name on a public-house sign, shot across 
my mind. I had a friend--Philip Concanen--
who resided at Chelsea, nothing of a walk, five 
miles. Phil had long outgrown Glumper's, 
though his name and his fame and a very rudely-executed 
miniature of Mrs. G., carved on the 
inside of his whilom desk, still survived. He 
was a middle-aged man now--going on, I should 
think, for nineteen--and had called once at 
Glumper's in a gig, driving himself. I had been 
a favourite of Phil's, and felt convinced that he 
would not only afford me his counsel, but keep 
<em>mine</em>. Well over the first steps of my pilgrimage, 
I had no fears about the remainder.</p>
<p>Philip was already in business with his father 
and uncle--wealthy brewers and distillers--
whose establishment displayed on its river-face 
a frontage so imposing as almost to justify the 
tradition that it had once been mistaken for 
Chelsea Hospital. On the land side, you merely 
dived down a dark and narrow lane, sole shaft 
to the gold mine that lay beyond. Down this 
passage, as evening fell, I groped my way, and, 
by great good luck, found Philip in sole command 
(till Monday morning) of "Conanen 
Brothers, and Concanen."</p>
<p>Philip gave me a cordial welcome, and, thanks 
to his old housekeeper, a most heart-reviving 
supper, and listened to my story with all the 
kindness and interest I had expected; also with 
a degree of gravity I had <em>not</em> expected. Intercourse 
with men and vats had already taken off 
the edge of his romance. There is, in beer, a 
decided tendency to sap the life of sentiment. 
In meal, I have since observed, a contrary rule 
prevails. Your miller's daughter--if he has one 
--is almost always a heroine.</p>
<p>My friend criticised with some severity the J 
golden visions of Jack Rogers, repudiated belief 
in the efficacy of half-a~crown as the especial 
keystone of affluence, and even hinted (though 
remotely) at the desirability of my making terms 
with the home authorities, and abandoning my 
enterprise.</p>
<p>On this point, however, I was firmness itself, 
and after a lengthened discussion the following 
convention was agreed to:</p>
<p>That the old housekeeper, Mrs. Swigsby, 
should be admitted to our complete confidence, 
with a view to my occupancy of the spare bedroom 
till Monday. That on that day I should 
transfer my quarters to Philip's own private 
smoke-harness room, from whence a side portal 
and a passage, dark at noon, gave upon Paradise-alley, 
and thence to the privacy of Jew's-road. 
That I should retain such refuge until I had 
enjoyed an opportunity of "feeling my way"--
which, indeed, would necessarily occur whenever 
I crossed the threshold. That on the slightest 
suspicion of my whereabout becoming known, 
I should depart, so as to avoid compromising my 
friend. Lastly, that I should at once write to 
my parents an assurance of my personal safety.</p>
<p>With some difficulty--owing to Mrs. Swigsby's 
being a deafer human creature than I could have 
conceived possible--that excellent lady was indoctrinated 
in the matter, and dismissing from 
her mind a first idea that I was the nephew of 
Mr. Arthur Thistlewood, and deeply compromised 
in certain, then recent, proceedings in Cato-street, 
promised every assistance. This arranged, 
I sat down to my letter:</p>
<letter>
<p>"My dear Papa and Mama,--I hope you are 
quite well. We ate up the Pie and other 
Things you so kindly sent, and then began 
Starving again. Rice, and Catterpillars, and 
what they call Beefstake-Pie but Isn't, <em>as usual</em>. 
I hoped you would have written to Mrs. Glumper, 
but perhaps you were Afrade. We held 
a Counsel, and Settled to run away One by 
One--till the Dinners get better. We drew 
Lots, and it Fell to me. I knew you would 
Aprove, for I heard you once say, about Captain 
Shurker, that it wasn't honourable to Back Out. 
I have my Second-best suit, some linen, my Bible, 
and Latin Delectus, and a Sum of Money which 
is the Beginning of a Fortune. I know what I am 
Doing--that is, I shall To-morrow--so I hope 
you won't be angry and kiss Mama and my love 
to Agnes and I am your Afectionate Dutiful Son,</p>
<right>"C. S. TRELAWNY."</right>
</letter>
<p>Early on Monday morning, Phil introduced me 
to my new quarters in the smoke-harness room, 
where we found Mrs. Swigsby engaged in constructing 
what she called a "trumpery" bed. 
From the good lady's demeanour, I could not 
help fancying that she even now harboured some 
misgivings concerning me, for she glanced at me 
now and then as if she expected me to go off like 
a grenade. It was useless, however, to attempt 
to enlighten her further. Phil confessed as much, 
and owned that we must take our chance.</p>
<p>He introduced me to the dark passage and 
private entrance, and presenting me with the key, 
took his leave, assuring me that no one would 
enter the apartment until evening, when he would 
himself bring me supper, hear me company at 
that meal, and hear how I had felt my way.</p>
<p>When, a few minutes later, I turned into Jew's-road, 
the sensation of not belonging to myself 
came back rather strongly, bringing with it a 
brother sensation, still less soothing--that of 
not, for the moment, belonging to anybody else! 
Nevertheless, I held up my head, and marched on 
as confidently as if I expected an influential friend 
to meet me by appointment at the next corner.</p>
<p>How--<em>how</em> did people begin? Usually, I 
thought, with some happy incident. Would any 
obliging infant, of high birth, do me the favour 
to be nearly run over? Any stout gentleman--
victim to casual orange-peel--trip and be picked 
up by me? Any hurrying man of commerce let 
fall a book containing securities of inestimable 
value, close to my feet? No; most of these 
things had had their turn. Fortune scorns to 
repeat herself. I had a conviction that I must 
begin at the foot of the ladder. "He" (some great 
man)" once swept a barber's shop," was a legend 
of my childhood. Where was such a barber?</p>
<p>"Wanted, a Lad."</p>
<p>It came like an answer. Were these characters 
<em>real</em>? If so, Fortune--though she writes 
an indifferent hand--has not deserted me. <em>I</em> am 
a lad. And wanted. Behold me!</p>
<p>I entered the establishment. It wasn't a barber's. 
Greasier. Pigs' toes, I imagine, prevailed.</p>
<p>"What can I do for <em>you</em>, young gentleman?" 
inquired the stout white-aproned proprietor, 
brandishing an immense knife.</p>
<p>'Please, do you want a lad?" I asked.</p>
<p>The man looked at me from head to foot. Then 
he said:</p>
<p>"We <em>did</em>, but unfortnetly we only takes six 
parlour-boarders at a time; and the Markiss o' 
Queerfinch has just grabbed the last wacancy for 
his seventeenth son."</p>
<p>"I--I want to be a lad, sir," I faltered.</p>
<p>"Lookee here, young gentleman; if you don't 
want none of <em>my</em> trotters, use your own, or you'll 
get <em>me</em> into a scrape as well as yourself. Now, 
off with you!"</p>
<p>Twice more ,tempted by similar announcements, 
I ventured to prefer my claims, but with no 
better success. One glance at my exterior 
seemed to satisfy everybody that I was not the 
lad for <em>them</em>. Yes, I was too smart! The 
recent runaway was visible in my still glossy blue 
jacket and gilt buttons; not to mention them 
snowy turn-down. I was not sorry when evening 
came, that I might return home, and recount 
my adventures to the sympathising Phil.</p>
<p>Philip agreed that I was <em>not</em>, perhaps, exactly 
the sort of messenger a struggling tripe-seller 
would select, but suggested that I might fly at 
higher game. Why not feel my way among 
classes to whom a gentlemanly appearance and 
manner did <em>not</em> form an inseparable objection?</p>
<p>Why not, indeed? Time was precious. Mrs. 
Swigsby's misgivings were evidently on the increase. 
I would do it to-morrow.</p>
<p>"Right, my boy," said Phil, as he bade me 
good night. "Straight, now, to the fountain 
head, you know."</p>
<p>I <em>didn't</em> exactly know. Feeling one's way, 
and going to the fountain head--though admirable 
as general principles--were, not so easy of 
application. Where <em>was</em> the fountain head?</p>
<p>"In your great banking and commercial firms," 
Phil had said, over our wine; "always deal with 
Principals."</p>
<p>My friend evidently assumed that I should 
seek out parties of this description. Accordingly, 
selecting from the Directory the names of 
a very eminent City banking firm, I "felt my 
way" towards their distant domicile, and found 
myself in the presence of about fifty clerks--all 
busily employed. After standing for some time 
unnoticed, I approached one of the desks.</p>
<p>"Please, sir, I want your head."</p>
<p>"My <em>what</em>?" inquired the clerk, with considerable 
energy "What do you want with my head?"</p>
<p>I explained that I meant his Principal; the 
head of the firm: whereupon the clerk smiled 
languidly.</p>
<p>"Mr. Ingott's down at Goldborough Park," 
he said, "but if it's anything about the Turkish 
Loan, we'll send an express. He can be here to-morrow."</p>
<p>I assured him it had nothing to do with the 
Turkish Loan, or any loan, and that any other 
partner of the house would do as well.</p>
<p>The clerk nodded whispered to another clerk, 
and desiring me to follow, led the way through 
a labyrinth of desks, into an inner room, where 
sat an old gentleman reading the paper. He 
looked at me inquiringly though his gold eye-glasses. 
The clerk whispered--and--</p>
<p>"Well, my young friend?" said the old banker.</p>
<p>"Pl--please, sir," I blurted out, "do you 
want a confidential lad?"</p>
<p>The clerk tittered; but the old gentleman, 
with one look, dismissed him, and proceeded:</p>
<p>"Who sent you hither, my boy, and what do 
you mean?"</p>
<p>His manner was very kind, so I told him 
at once, that nobody sent me; that, acting upon 
advice, I was engaged in feeling my way, and 
wished to begin by being a lad--a <em>confidential</em> 
lad, if possible; that, With that view, I had 
come straight to the fountain head; that, being, 
I must confess, at variance with my friends, I 
could not mention whence I came, but that he 
might rely upon my honesty; and that I was 
prepared, if necessary, to deposit in the hands of 
the firm a certain sum of money, as an indemnification 
for any losses that might be incurred 
through my inexperience.</p>
<p>The old gentleman inquired the amount.</p>
<p>"Two-and-sixpence."</p>
<p>I saw his eye twinkle; then, as if a sudden 
thought had struck him, he put his hand upon 
my shoulder and turned me to the light.</p>
<p>"Hem--I thought so," I fancied I heard him 
mutter. Then he added aloud: "See here, my 
lad. I cannot make so important an engagement 
on my own responsibility. I must consult my 
partners in the firm. Sit down in the messenger's 
room--that door yonder. In half an hour I will 
give you your answer."</p>
<p>In the messenger's room I found a respectable-looking 
youth, eating bread-and-cheese. He 
offered me some, but I could not eat. Kind as 
the old gentleman's manner was, there was 
something in it that gave me uneasiness. It 
almost seemed as if he knew me.</p>
<p>"Who," I asked the messenger, "is that old 
gentleman who said he must consult his 
partners?"</p>
<p>"Sir Edward Goldshore--him that lives at 
Bilton Abbey, near Penrhyn."</p>
<p>"Penrhyn? General Trelawny's?"</p>
<p>"That, sir, is the ticket. The general often 
lunches here when he's in town. Consult his 
partners, did the governor say? Why, they're 
all out of town but <em>him</em>!"</p>
<p>"Don't you," I asked, faintly, "think this 
room of yours rather hot? I'll--take a run--
and--and come back before I'm wanted."</p>
<p>Ere the youth could start any objections I had 
vanished.</p>
<p>That unlucky day was doomed to an unluckier 
close. Concanen made his appearance in the 
harness-room with a somewhat harassed face.</p>
<p>"It's a bore, my dear old fellow, but I fear your 
camp must be broken up. There's no trusting 
old Swigsby. You must move on, Charley, my 
boy, and, if you won't go slick home, like a reasonable 
chap, feel your way in other quarters."</p>
<p>There was, obviously, no alternative. I 
marched on the following morning. But Phil's 
good offices did not cease until he had seen me 
established in a (very humble) lodging not far 
distant, but in a locality where I could continue 
to feel my way without much chance of recognition. 
The rent--five shillings a week--Phil at 
first insisted on paying; but, on my representation 
that the acceptance of any money aid might 
vitiate my entire future, the kind fellow consented 
to purchase, at full value, such articles of 
my wardrobe as would supply me with all that 
was necessary for an entire week, leaving my 
half-crown still intact.</p>
<p>Thus was I, for the second time, adrift. Fortune 
kept steadily aloof. Go whither, ask whom, 
I would, the same suspicious look invariably 
greeted me. Whether I brushed my jacket 
neatly, or tore experimental holes in the elbows, 
it seemed that I could never hit the desired 
medium between gentility and vagabondism.</p>
<p>I shall not describe at length those miserable 
days, nor the steady diminution of my hopes and resources, 
until the middle of the second week found 
me, with my rent paid, indeed, but destitute of 
everything save the clothes I stood in, and <em>sixpence</em>!</p>
<p>I had given up in despair all search for employment. 
Go home I would not. Of Phil I had 
heard nothing, and I feared to compromise him by 
any overt communication. What was to be done?</p>
<p>One morning, I was prowling feebly about, 
<em>very</em> hungry, and, every now and then, feeling 
the sixpence in my jacket-pocket, as though 
the very sight of a cook-shop might have 
drawn it forth, when I noticed an old Jew 
seated on the lower steps of a house. He was 
not a neat or a well-washed Jew. I don't think 
that I ever in after life beheld a dirtier; but my 
attention was drawn to him by the demeanour of 
a potboy, who, in passing, had muttered, "Old 
chap's sewn up!" and whistled on two fingers, 
almost over the man's head, a paean of congratulation 
upon the circumstance.</p>
<p>The old Jew looked faintly up. The face, 
though grimy, was not, I thought, ignoble; and, 
indifferent whither I strolled, I turned to take 
another look at him. He was very old, very 
ragged, and, to all appearance, famine-stricken; 
at least, I never saw hunger written so legibly 
in any face, except my own. He made a 
languid motion with his fingers towards me, like 
a dying creature, but did not beg, and I passed 
on my way. Suddenly, the thought shot across 
me, "Should the old man <em>die</em>!"</p>
<p>The sixpence seemed to give a spontaneous 
leap in my pocket, as though inspired with the 
same idea. Back I went, wavering, for, if I 
yielded to charitable impulse, what must I myself 
do? If he would divide it With me--but how ask 
a dying man for change? I passed him again.</p>
<p>Either my fancy misled me, or the sixpence 
gave me a discontented punch in the side. "<em>But</em>," 
I answered, as though in remonstrance with it, 
"you, are the last hope of my fortune; in giving 
<em>you</em>, I part with millions--'two millions.'" A 
last emphatic punch determined me. I turned 
once more, walked hastily back, and dropped my 
two millions into the old man's hand!</p>
<p>How I got through the remainder of that 
day I hardly know. It was about dusk, when, 
growing every moment more faint and desponding, 
I turned to crawl homeward. I was 
pausing unconsciously before a baker's window, 
when a hand touched my shoulder. It was my 
Jew. The old man had changed considerably for 
the better, and now, of the two, looked far the 
more alive.</p>
<p>"Good rolls those," said the old Jew, approvingly. 
"Hungry?"</p>
<p>Almost too weary to speak, I nodded.</p>
<p>"And--~and--no money?" asked the old man, 
with curious eagerness.</p>
<p>I shook my head, and prepared to move away.</p>
<p>"I--I spent that sixpence," resumed the Jew, 
"but if you don't despise a poor man's haunt, 
I'll give you a supper, and, if you need it, lodging 
too. My castle is close at hand".</p>
<p>I looked at him with surprise, and followed 
him. Falling into a sort of mendicant gait, he 
shuttled feebly on, and, turning into a dark 
narrow street, composed of very small tenements 
indeed, paused at one of the nearest, and struck 
upon the window-sill with his crutch-stick.</p>
<p>"Take hold of my coat when she opens the 
door," said the old Jew. "You may find it 
darkish below."</p>
<p>"It <em>was</em> darkish, insomuch that the "she" who 
opened to us was invisible in the gloom, but a 
silver voice, that was not the Jew's, uttered an 
exclamation of welcome, and died away, like a 
spirit's, into some upper region, whither we 
stumbled in pursuit. A candle-end, dimly 
flickering in the corner, revealed our conductress 
in the person of a girl of about fifteen, attired in 
a thick white robe which covered her from neck 
to foot, and seemed, so far as I might presume 
to judge, to be her only garment. The large 
sleeves were turned back to the elbows, as if she 
had been engaged in household work, and the 
inaudibility of her movements was accounted 
for by her feet being bare. A broad white 
fillet tied back immense masses of dark brown 
hair. The face! Boy as I was, and a very 
sleepy and exhausted one--I was roused at once 
into a state of stupid ecstasy by one glance at 
her marvellous beauty. "Is it a woman? Is it 
a woman?" I remember gasping, as it were, to 
myself. And as she stood, for a few seconds, 
motionless, her form and dress like sculpture, 
her white arms extended towards me in questioning 
surprise, I felt as if it would be no sin to 
fall at her feet, in adoration of what seemed more 
of Heaven than earth.</p>
<p>"Supper, Zell," said the old Jew, and darkness 
fell upon the scene. Zell had vanished.</p>
<p>The rest of that evening was a blank, with 
passing gleams of Paradise. Fatigue and inanition 
forced me to sleep, even while striving to 
eat. But, in those intervals of glory, I was conscious 
of sitting at a feast, between the Queen of 
the Fairies, and an exceedingly ragged old Hebrew 
whom she addressed as grandfather; sensible 
that the latter (speaking as though I had been 
absent) told the former a story about me and a sixpence, 
which seemed to be amusing; aware, finally, 
that Queen Titania remarked, in a pitying voice:</p>
<p>"The child! He ought to be in bed!" And, 
without further ceremony, put me there.</p>
<p>My couch was on the floor of that same apartment, 
and the last thing I remember was Titania's 
foot, so small, so purely white, so bluely veined, 
withal so near my lips, that I would have kissed it, 
if I dared--but went to sleep while thinking of it.</p>
<p>My rest was so profound, that, when I awoke 
to another day, Zell and her grandfather were 
finishing breakfast. Both were dressed as on the 
preceding day; the old man, with his squalid 
aspect, tattered garments, and rusty shoes, offering 
a strange contrast to the bewitching creature, 
fresh and sweet as a dewy moss-rose, who sat beside 
him. If her beauty had asserted itself in the 
semi-darkness overnight, the full light of day only 
continued it more. The countenance was unquestionably 
of the Jewish order, but of the richest 
tint, the most refined and delicate mould. I lay 
in a sort of joyful stupor, utterly unable to remove 
my eyes from the glorious object. If love were 
ever born at eleven years old, here was the nativity 
of a passion that could never die. O, angel!--
Zell suddenly discovered that I was awake.</p>
<p>After bringing me some tea, she quitted the 
room, and the old man came and sat down beside 
me. Having questioned me about my home and 
friends--to which I candidly replied that I had, 
at present, none to speak of, being engaged in 
simply feeling my way--he went on:</p>
<p>"You have been frank with me, my boy. I'll 
be frank with <em>you</em>. Though a very poor, poor 
man--oh, a <em>very</em> poor man--I am not, as you 
supposed, a beggar. I have means of living, 
such as they are, but these compel me to be 
much from home. My granddaughter, my Zell 
(what fool gave her that name I know not; she 
is called Zeruiah), has neither relation nor friend. 
For reasons I cannot now explain, she never 
quits this house. My heart bleeds at the solitude 
to which I am forced to condemn her. 
Stay with us, child, for a while. You shall have 
board and lodging, it may be some trifle over, 
when times are good. You can go on messages for 
Zell, and help her in the house. What say you?"</p>
<p>If the old gentleman had intimated that the 
reversion of the crown of England awaited my 
acceptance, my heart would have throbbed with 
far less exultant joy! <em>Stay</em> with her! See her! 
Serve her! Be her blessed thrall!</p>
<p>What I replied, I know not. I only know that 
ten minutes later the old gentlemen had shuffled 
forth, and I, washing teacups under the eye of 
my beautiful mistress, had broken one, and received 
a box on the ear, delivered without any 
ceremony whatever. Zell was evidently as impulsive 
as she was beautiful. Presuming on 
her immense seniority of four years, the young 
lady made no more account of me than if I had 
been a kitten.</p>
<p>The room we sat in, and a little nook above, 
where Zell slept, were, like herself, scrupulously 
clean: all the remainder of the mansion being 
apparently given fairly over to decay and dirt. 
Our slender meals were prepared in the sitting-room, 
and provided from a daily sum, of I should 
think about fourpence-halfpenny, doled out by 
the lord of the mansion before leaving. My 
lady would instruct me where and how to invest 
this capital to the greatest advantage, and, according 
to my success, reward me on my return 
with a radiant smile, or a sounding box on the ear.</p>
<p>Mistress Zell seldom making me the recipient 
of her thoughts and words, it was by slow degrees 
that I learned the following particulars: 
That my host, Mr. Moses Jeremiah Abrahams, 
was a gentleman of habits so penurious, that he 
might have rivalled, if not eclipsed, the most illustrious 
misers of the age, had he only possessed anything 
to hoard. That Zell was dressed as I beheld 
her, to preclude the possibility of her going forth 
--to incur expenses--in the public ways. (As, 
sitting on the ground, while she told me this, I 
looked up in my lady's glorious eyes, it struck me 
that the old man might have had a tenderer 
reason.) That Mr. Abrahams, absent, most 
days, till dark, was, on certain days, later still. 
finally, that I must not be surprised if, on one 
or more of those days, I heard his signal on the 
window-sill, but not himself on the stairs. "And 
<em>woe</em> to you!" concluded my lady, threatening me 
with her little hand, "if you betray our secret!"</p>
<p>"Our!" My heart turned faint, I caught her 
meaning instantly, and experienced the first 
burning touch of jealousy. My mistress had a 
lover.</p>
<p>"What makes you colour so, you stupid 
foolish boy?" said my lady, half laughing, half 
angry. "Can we trust you, or can we <em>not</em>?"</p>
<p>I stammered some nonsense about being at her 
command, body and soul. And I have no doubt 
I meant it.</p>
<p>My devotion was soon tested. That very 
evening (one of Mr. Abrahams' late ones) a. 
knock, like his, sounded on the window-sill. 
Zell, bidding me follow, flew down stairs, and, 
softly opening the window, was clasped in the embrace 
of an individual to all appearance as ragged 
and infirm of mien as her grandfather himself.</p>
<p>For a moment she suffered this, then drew 
back, leaving the visitor her hand, which that 
monster, whoever he was, seemed to devour with 
kisses. There ensued a whispered conversation, 
during which I observed that the speakers 
referred to me. Then, as if alarmed by a signal 
from without, the stranger vanished. We 
returned up-stairs.</p>
<p>Next morning my mistress gave me a note 
without address. I was to take it to a particular 
shop, and give it to a particular stranger who 
would accost me. No particular stranger was 
there. Afraid to return without fulfilling 
my mission, I was lingering over some trifling 
purchase, when a phaeton dashed up to the 
door, and a gentleman entered the shop. He 
was very handsome, wore thick black moustaches 
carefully curled, had long gilt spurs, 
and looked like an officer. He was well known 
to the shop-people, for he tossed about a number 
of articles, laughing and jesting with the mistress, 
but purchased nothing. Could <em>this</em> be my 
man? I managed, at all events, to let him see 
what I was carrying. We left the shop together.</p>
<p>"Toss it over! Quick, my lad!" said the 
gentleman, sharply. "Take this, and <em>this</em>" (he 
gave me another note, and half-a-crown). "And 
meet me here to-morrow."</p>
<p>I told him I did not want his money, but 
would take his note. He looked at me, uttered 
a long low whistle--expressive, I take it, of 
astonishment--and drove away.</p>
<p>The joy in my sweet mistress's eyes, and a 
White hand stroking my curls, even while she 
read the letter, were a sufficient reward. Then 
she made me her confidant. Her suitor was 
Lord John Loveless, son of the proud Earl of St. 
Buryans, with whom, owing to some little 
financial misunderstanding, poor Lord John was, 
for the moment, on terms so far from satisfactory, 
as to render it improbable that the earl would 
yield anything like a cordial assent to his son's 
union with the granddaughter of an impoverished 
Jew. Hence the necessity for those clandestine 
interviews, which my mistress atoned for to her 
conscience: by sternly forbidding her lover ever 
to cross the threshold.</p>
<p>My lord was at the shop next morning as soon 
as I.</p>
<p>He took me familiarly by the arm.</p>
<p>"Come and take a pull on the river, boy. I 
want to have a talk with you."</p>
<p>It was not far to the river. We got a boat, and 
pulled off, my companion chatting pleasantly 
enough. At last he said:</p>
<p>"That old governor of yours keeps you pretty 
short, I take it? What does he do, now, with 
his money? Do you never hear him counting I 
his guineas? Come!"</p>
<p>I positively denied it, and gave such candid 
reasons for my conviction that he was all 
but a pauper, that my companion seemed staggered. 
He became grave, not to say morose, and 
the row home seemed to bore him. I did not 
report to my lady all that had passed between us; 
I could not have left out his bad spirits when I 
described to him her poverty, and that might 
have pained her.</p>
<p>After this, my lord's visits became less frequent, 
and my mistress's smiles rarer. She moved 
about with a slower and a sadder step; and sometimes 
sat with her marble arms crossed on her 
lap, until I almost doubted if she lived. At which 
times, I would creep into the field of her eye, if 
but to change its fixed expression.</p>
<p>A terrible event came to rouse her. The old 
gentleman was brought home, one night, dying. 
He had been hustled, knocked down, and robbed, 
by some miscreants in the street. Though he 
had sustained no injury that should ordinarily 
prove mortal, the shock to his system, and, still 
more, the alleged robbery to which he perpetually 
referred, combined to give him to the 
grave. In spite of medical efforts he sank fast, 
and, at midnight, died.</p>
<p>My mistress, who had never left his side, here 
all with a strange patience. I never saw her 
weep, but her white face and gleaming eyes 
struck me with awe.</p>
<p>A will, duly executed, was found, in which the 
old man, in general terms, bequeathed to his 
granddaughter, Zeruiah Abrahams. everything 
of which he should die possessed, appointing one 
Lemuel Samuelson guardian and executor. What 
money the old man had about him, when robbed, 
was never known. All the coin in the house 
amounted to no more than sufficed to pay the 
medical attendant, while the furniture was probably 
not worth more than twenty or thirty 
pounds. Part of this, with the assistance of a 
neighbour, we sold, to spare the old man a 
pauper's funeral; the rest, we thought, would 
provide clothes for Zell (since we must <em>both</em> now 
go out and feel our way), and support us both until 
we found our way. When this was done, the house 
looked desolate and wretched enough, and my 
poor mistress scarcely less so. Though she never 
spoke of it, the desertion of her lover--of whom 
in all that distressful time we never heard--cut 
her to the heart's core.</p>
<p>One day, before her clothes came, as I was 
moving restlessly about the room, thinking what 
I could say to comfort her, she suddenly lifted 
her, head:</p>
<p>"Charley, will <em>you</em> desert me, too?"</p>
<p>"Zell! '<em>Desert</em> you!'" Like a young fool, 
as I was, I burst into a passion of tears.</p>
<p>"Don't--don't! My dear child--my good 
ch----!" And, infected by my tears, poor Zell 
laid her head on the table and wept aloud.</p>
<p>Almost at that moment my eye was caught by 
an urchin in the street, beckoning eagerly. 
Stammering some excuse, I ran out.</p>
<p>"Gem' giv' me a bob," said the boy, "fur to 
say as he's a waitin' at the corner."</p>
<p>At the corner; or, more correctly, <em>round</em> it, 
stood Lord John Loveless.</p>
<p>"Now, my boy," said his lordship, very 
hurriedly, "I am here at great risk to--to myself, 
and have only a moment to stay. About 
your mistress? Is she well? Is she cared for? 
Did the old fellow <em>really</em> die a beggar?"</p>
<p>I replied, that the old gentleman had neither 
lived nor died a beggar, but that we had no 
money, and intended to feel our nay towards 
work, as soon as we could go out.</p>
<p>Lord John seemed struck at this, and made 
an irresolute movement in the direction of the 
house.</p>
<p>"Won't you come in?" I forced myself to 
say.</p>
<p>"N--no," was the reply. "I can't. Urgent 
business elsewhere. See, boy. Give her this. 
Say I have been absent with my regiment, or I'd 
have sent before."</p>
<p>And, if ever noble gentleman skulked away, 
I think Lord John did.</p>
<p>Kneeling at my sweet mistress's feet, I faithfully 
recounted the interview. Zell listened, 
without once removing her eyes from mine. Then 
she said: " Put his--his wretched alms--into a 
cover, and take it to the address I shall write." 
All which was duly done.</p>
<p>But, the events of the day were not over. As 
we sat towards evening, discussing projects for 
the morrow, a stranger somewhat peremptorily 
demanded admittance, and, in company with 
another individual who had apparently been 
lurking aloof, produced some papers, and declared 
himself in possession of the house. He 
was our landlord. Our rent was deeply in 
arrear. His applications and threats having 
been alike disregarded by the eccentric Mr. 
Abrahams, he had taken the necessary steps to 
resume possession, and now came, inspired with 
an intense hatred (as he openly declared) for all 
Jew tenants, to enforce his rights.</p>
<p>It was in vain to remonstrate. We had not one 
shilling in our possession, and, for furniture, only 
our beds, chairs, table, and cooking utensils: all 
which, united, would not have paid half the debt.</p>
<p>"At least, sir," said my mistress, "you will 
not turn us into the streets, <em>to-night</em>?"</p>
<p>"Well!" said the fellow, reluctantly, "hardly 
<em>that</em>. But I'm up to these dodges, <em>I</em> promise 
you. Let you stay, and here you <em>will</em> stay. We'll 
stop that game. Without beds and window-sashes, 
you'll soon be ready to go. Collect the 
traps, Bill Bloxam, and look alive."</p>
<p>"It will soon be night, sir," said Zell, pale 
as a ghost: "a night that promises to be both 
cold and wet; in charity, leave us the protection 
of windows."</p>
<p>"Pin up your petticoat," returned the landlord, 
coolly. "<em>Here</em> she goes!"</p>
<p>He roughly tore at the window-sash. Out it 
came, crashing. But the rotten woodwork at 
the side, deprived of its support, and yielding as 
it seemed to some pressure from within, came 
away also. There was a heavy rushing fall that 
shook the very house--a rolling, ringing, spinning, 
settling down! From end to end, the 
apartment was literally carpeted with <em>gold</em>!</p>
<p>"Phsh!" said the reeling landlord, as he 
wiped the dust from his eyes.</p>
<p>My mistress was the first to recover composure. 
A watchman, on his way to night-duty, 
attracted by the crash, stood opposite. She bade 
me call him in, and, dismissing the now subdued 
landlord, procured a trusty guardian for the night. 
My mistress also despatched a special messenger 
in quest of Mr. Lemuel Samuelson, who, arriving 
With the dawn, joined us in further investigations.</p>
<p>Two thousand seven hundred guineas had been 
scattered on the floor. In different parts of the 
house, generally crammed into chinks and chasms 
of the decaying woodwork, were bank-notes to 
the amount of thirty-two thousand pounds. But 
even <em>that</em> was a trifle compared to the crafty old 
miser's foreign securities, which, disinterred in 
one lump, represented the immense sum of two 
hundred and ninety thousand pounds.</p>
<p>"And now, my love," said Mr. Samuelson, 
when both search and calculation were exhausted, 
"you will give Mrs. S. and me the 
pleasure of your company, at my little box at 
Sydenham, until you decide what <em>next</em> to do."</p>
<p>My mistress at once assented. Since the discovery 
of the treasure, she had had intervals of 
the deepest melancholy. Was she thinking what 
<em>might</em> have been, had the old man been less reticent? 
She had hardly addressed a word to me, 
and, until Mr. Samuelson came obsequiously to 
hand her to the carriage, I knew not if she would 
even bid me farewell. At last it was her guardian 
himself who drew her attention to me, by asking 
if she had any directions to give the "lad."</p>
<p>"The lad," repeated Zell, abstractedly.</p>
<p>"Call at my office, boy!" said Mr. Samuelson, 
who seemed impatient to get away. "By-the-by, 
what's your name?"</p>
<p>I made no answer. I was looking at my mistress.</p>
<p>"Sulky, eh?" said Mr. Samuelson. "Worse 
for <em>you</em>. Come, my love."</p>
<p>"Charley! Charley!" said Zell.</p>
<p>Then I <em>could</em> not answer. She waved her 
hand towards me, but her guardian led her away.</p>
<p>All that day, I sat at the window, as though I 
had fully expected her to return; but, in reality, 
I had no such idea. I knew that my darling 
mistress was gone--for ever, ever, gone--and had 
taken with her all joy, all happiness, all desire 
of life. I was conscious of a sense of hunger, 
but had no heart to look for food; at the time 
when we used to prepare our supper on those 
happy evenings, I crept to my lady's little bed, 
and lay down <em>there</em>. A curious rushing sound 
was in my ears, and my pulse seemed rather to 
give a continuous shudder, than to beat. Dreams 
came, Without introductory ceremony of the 
sleep. I heard myself shouting and struggling. 
Then, darkness....</p>
<p>I awoke in my father's house. I had been 
there three weeks. Though very weak, I was in 
the path of recovery, and was soon in condition 
to return to school. But not to Glumper's. No.</p>
<p>I learned that, in my delirium, I had given a 
clue to my name and residence. What after-communications 
I made, I cannot say: I only 
know that both my mother, and my saucy little 
Agnes, were as familiar with the name of Zell as 
my own daily thoughts were. She was my love, 
my queen, my darling only mistress. In that 
faith, and in the firm assurance that I should one 
blessed day see her again, I grew to manhood.</p>
<br/>
<p>There was a grand ball at Dublin Castle, 
at which I, a young lieutenant of dragoons, 
chanced to be present and abetting. The reception 
was more than usually crowded and 
magnificent, it being the farewell of a popular 
lord-lieutenant.</p>
<p>As the latter moved about among his smiling 
guests, be halted at a group beside me.</p>
<p>"Well, young gentlemen," said his excellency, 
"who is the successful knight? Surely this prize 
is not to escape us all! Resplendent beauty--
sweetness--accomplishments--twelve thousand 
a year. Shame to Ireland, if this Mexican belle 
quits us to-night, her last in the land (for I hear 
she returns to Mexico), a disengaged woman!"</p>
<p>"She will <em>not</em>, my lord," replied Colonel 
Walsingham.</p>
<p>"Hah! Who wins?" asked his excellency, 
hardly less interested than if he had himself been 
a candidate.</p>
<p>"That is doubtful, still," put in young Lord 
Goring. "Hawkins, Rushton, O'Rourke, Walsingham, 
St. Buryans, my humble self, have all 
been 'mentioned' in the race. St. Buryans for 
choice."</p>
<p>"Why so?" asked his lordship.</p>
<p>"The lady has been seated this whole 
evening beside St. Buryans' lady-mother," said 
Goring, in a low voice. "And she's the cleverest 
woman, at a finish, in Christendom--er Jewry 
either."</p>
<p>"You said it would be decided to-night?"</p>
<p>"Thus. The young lady will dance but once, 
the last dance. We have all solicited the honour. 
She reserves her choice. It has been agreed to 
accept the augury. Your lordship understands? 
The unsuccessful withdraw."</p>
<p>His excellency nodded, smiled, and passed on.</p>
<p>A few minutes later, a movement in the room 
drew my attention. All eyes seemed directed 
towards one object. Up the centre of the room, 
leaning on the arm of Lord John Loveless, now 
Earl St. Buryans, was passing my beautiful 
mistress! Taller--fuller, no whit lovelier, for 
that could not be. She looked full in my face. 
I thought she paused for a second. No, the 
superb brown eyes were languidly withdrawn, 
and, without recognition, she moved on.</p>
<p>The last dance was announced from the orchestra. 
As if under a spell, I placed myself opposite 
to my lady's chair, though remote from 
it. I saw the rival suitors, with well-bred 
self-possession, gather round, and each in turn 
prefer his claim. All were declined. St. 
Buryans--by whose haughty-looking mother 
my lady sat--alone remained. He approached 
her with confidence, his mother greeting him 
with a victorious smile. Before he could open 
his lips, Zell rose:</p>
<p>"Give me your arm. I wish to cross the room," 
she said to him haughtily.</p>
<p>She <em>did</em> cross. She came to <em>me</em>. Drawing 
her arm away from her conductor's, she held out 
both her little hands.</p>
<p>"Charley, Charley! Don't you know me? I 
come to ask you to--to dance with me--with 
your old friend, Zell."</p>
<br/>
<p>We have more than one deer park--but it was 
from the Scotch one that, on Zell's reminder (she 
always pretends to be older and more thoughtful 
than I), I sent my friend Jack Rogers a haunch 
worthy of a king's acceptance.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="ANOTHER PAST LODGER RELATES HIS OWN GHOST STORY."/>
<chapter>
<p>The circumstances I am about to relate to 
you have truth to recommend them. They happened 
to myself, and my recollection of them 
is as vivid as if they had taken place only yesterday. 
Twenty years, however, have gone by since 
that night. During those twenty years I have 
told the story to but one other person. I tell 
it new with a reluctance which I find it difficult 
to overcome. All I entreat, meanwhile, is that 
you will abstain from forcing your own conclusions 
upon me. I want nothing explained away. 
I desire no arguments. My mind on this subject 
is quite made up, and, having the testimony of my 
own senses to rely upon, I prefer to abide by it.</p>
<p>Well! It was just twenty years ago, and 
within a day or two of the end of the grouse 
season. I had been out all day with my gun, 
and had had no sport to speak of. The wind was 
due east; the month, December; the place, a 
bleak wide moor in the far north of England. 
And I had lost my way. It was not a 
pleasant place in which to lose one's way, 
with the first feathery flakes of a coming 
snow-storm just fluttering down upon the 
heather, and the leaden evening closing in all 
around. I shaded my eyes with my hand, and 
stared anxiously into the gathering darkness, 
where the purple moorland melted into a range 
of low hills, some ten or twelve miles 
distant. Not the faintest smoke-wreath, not the 
tiniest cultivated patch, or fence, or sheep-track, 
met my eyes in any direction. There was 
nothing for it but to walk on, and take my 
chance of finding what shelter I could, by 
the way. So I shouldered my gun again, and 
pushed wearily forward; for I had been on foot 
since an hour after daybreak, and had eaten 
nothing since breakfast.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the snow began to come down with 
ominous steadiness, and the wind fell. After 
this, the cold became more intense, and the 
night came rapidly up. As for me, my prospects 
darkened with the darkening sky, and 
my heart grew heavy as I thought how my 
young wife was already watching for me through 
the window of our little inn parlour, and thought 
of all the suffering in store for her throughout 
this weary night. We had been married four 
months, and, having spent our autumn in the 
Highlands, were now lodging in a remote little 
village situated just on the verge of the great 
English moorlands. We were very much in love, 
and, of course, very happy. This morning, when 
we parted, she had implored me to return before 
dusk, and I had promised her that I would. What 
would I not have given to have kept my word!</p>
<p>Even now, weary as I was, I felt that with a 
supper, an hour's rest, and a guide, I might 
still get back to her before midnight, if only 
guide and shelter could be found.</p>
<p>And all this time, the snow fell and the night 
thickened. I stopped and shouted every now 
and then, but my shouts seemed only to make 
the silence deeper. Then a vague sense of 
uneasiness came upon me, and I began to 
remember stories of travellers who had walked 
on and on in the falling snow until, wearied 
out, they were fain to lie down and sleep 
their lives away. Would it be possible, I 
asked myself, to keep on thus through all the 
long dark night? Would there not come a 
time when my limbs must fail, and my resolution 
give way? When I, too, must sleep the 
sleep of death. Death! I shuddered. How 
hard to die just now, when life lay all so bright 
before me! How hard for my darling, whose 
whole loving heart--but that thought was 
not to be borne! To banish it, I shouted 
again, louder and longer, and then listened 
eagerly. Was my shout answered, or did I only 
fancy that I heard a far-off cry? I halloed 
again, and again the echo followed. Then a 
wavering speck of light came suddenly out of 
the dark, shifting, disappearing, growing momentarily 
nearer and brighter. Running towards it 
at full speed, I found myself, to my great joy, 
face to face with an old man and a lantern.</p>
<p>"Thank God!" was the exclamation that burst 
involuntarily from my lips.</p>
<p>Blinking and frowning, he lifted his lantern 
and peered into my face.</p>
<p>"What for?" growled he, sulkily.</p>
<p>"Well--for you. I began to fear I should be 
lost in the snow."</p>
<p>"Eh, then, folks do get cast away hereabouts 
fra' time to time, an' what's to hinder you from 
bein' cast away likewise, if the Lord's so 
minded?"</p>
<p>"If the Lord is so minded that you and I 
shall be lost together, friend, we must submit," 
I replied; "but I don't mean to be lost without 
you. How far am I now from Dwolding?"</p>
<p>"A gude twenty mile, more or less."</p>
<p>"And the nearest village?"</p>
<p>"The nearest village is Wyke, an' that's 
twelve mile t'other side."</p>
<p>"Where do you live, then?"</p>
<p>"Out yonder," said he, with a vague jerk of 
the lantern.</p>
<p>"You're going home, I presume?"</p>
<p>"Maybe I am."</p>
<p>"Then I'm going with you."</p>
<p>The old man shook his head, and rubbed his 
nose reflectively with the handle of the lantern.</p>
<p>"It ain't o' no use," growled he. "He 'ont 
let you in--not he."</p>
<p>"We'll see about that," I replied, briskly. 
"Who is He?"</p>
<p>"The master."</p>
<p>"Who is the master?"</p>
<p>"That's nowt to you," was the unceremonious reply.</p>
<p>"Well, well; you lead the way, and I'll 
engage that the master shall give me shelter and a 
supper to-night."</p>
<p>"Eh, you can try him!" muttered my 
reluctant guide; and, still shaking his head, he 
hobbled, gnome-like, away through the falling 
snow. A large mass loomed up presently out 
of the darkness, and a huge dog rushed out, 
barking furiously,</p>
<p>"Is this the house?" I asked.</p>
<p>"Ay, it's the house. Down, Bey!" And he 
fumbled in his pocket for the key.</p>
<p>I drew up close behind him, prepared to lose 
no chance of entrance, and saw in the little 
circle of light shed by the lantern that the door 
was heavily studded with iron nails, like the door 
of a prison. In another minute he had turned 
the key and I had pushed past him into the house.</p>
<p>Once inside, I looked round with curiosity, 
and found myself in a great raftered hall, 
which served, apparently, a variety of uses. 
One end was piled to the roof with corn, 
like a barn. The other was stored with flour-
sacks, agricultural implements, casks, and all 
kinds of miscellaneous lumber; while from the 
beams overhead hung rows of hams, flitches, 
and bunches of dried herbs for winter use. In 
the centre of the floor stood some huge object 
gauntly dressed in a dingy wrapping-cloth, and 
reaching half way to the rafters. Lifting a 
corner of this cloth, I saw, to my surprise, a 
telescope of very considerable size, mounted on 
a rude moveable platform with four small 
wheels. The tube was made of painted wood, 
bound round with bands of metal rudely 
fashioned; the speculum, so far as I could 
estimate its size in the dim light, measured at 
least fifteen inches in diameter. While I was yet 
examining the instrument, and asking myself 
whether it was not the work of some self-taught 
optician, a bell rang sharply.</p>
<p>"That's for you," said my guide, with, a 
malicious grin. "Yonder's his room."</p>
<p>He pointed to a low black door at the opposite 
side of the hall. I crossed over, rapped 
somewhat loudly, and went in, without waiting 
for an invitation. A huge, white-haired old man 
rose from a table covered with books and papers, 
and confronted me sternly.</p>
<p>"Who are you?" said he. "How came you 
here? What do you want?"</p>
<p>"James Murray, barrister-at-law. On foot 
across the moor. Meat, drink, and sleep."</p>
<p>He bent his bushy brows into a portentous 
frown.</p>
<p>"Mine is not a house of entertainment," he 
said, haughtily. "Jacob, how dared you admit 
this stranger?"</p>
<p>"I didn't admit him," grumbled the old man. 
"He followed me over the muir, and shouldered 
his way in before me. I'm no match for six foot 
two."</p>
<p>"And pray, sir, by what right have you forced 
an entrance into my house?"</p>
<p>"The same by which I should have clung to 
your boat, if I were drowning. The right of 
self-preservation."</p>
<p>"Self-preservation?"</p>
<p>"There's an inch of snow on the ground 
already," I replied, briefly; "and it would be 
deep enough to cover my body before daybreak."</p>
<p>He strode to the window, pulled aside a 
heavy black curtain, and looked out.</p>
<p>"It is true," he said. "You can stay, if you 
choose, till morning. Jacob, serve the supper."</p>
<p>With this he waved me to a seat, 
resumed his own, and became at once absorbed in 
the studies from which I had disturbed him.</p>
<p>I placed my gun in a corner, drew a chair to 
the hearth, and examined my quarters at leisure. 
Smaller and less incongruous in its arrangements 
than the hall, this room contained, nevertheless, 
much to awaken my curiosity. The floor was 
carpetless. The whitewashed walls were in parts 
scrawled over with strange diagrams, and in 
others covered with shelves crowded with 
philosophical instruments, the uses of many of which 
were unknown to me. On one side of the 
fire-place, stood a bookcase filled with dingy folios; 
on the other, a small organ, fantastically 
decorated with painted carvings of mediaeval saints 
and devils. Through the half-opened door of a 
cupboard at the further end of the room, I saw 
a long array of geological specimens, surgical 
preparations, crucibles, retorts, and jars of 
chemicals; while on the mantelshelf beside me, 
amid a number of small objects, stood a model 
of the solar system, a small galvanic battery, 
and a microscope. Every chair had its burden. 
Every corner was heaped high with books. 
The very floor was littered over with maps, 
casts, papers, tracings, and learned lumber of 
all conceivable kinds.</p>
<p>I stared about me with an amazement 
increased by every fresh object upon which 
my eyes chanced to rest. So strange a room I 
had never seen; yet seemed it stranger still, to 
find such a room in a lone farm-house amid those 
wild and solitary moors! Over and over again, 
I looked from my host to his surroundings, 
and from his surroundings back to my host, 
asking myself who and what he could be? His 
head was singularly fine; but it was more the 
head of a poet than of a philosopher. Broad in 
the temples, prominent over the eyes, and 
clothed with a rough profusion of perfectly 
white hair, it had all the ideality and much of 
the ruggedness that characterises the head of 
Louis von Beethoven. There were the same 
deep lines about the mouth, and the same stern 
furrows in the brow. There was the same 
concentration of expression. While I was yet 
observing him, the door opened, and Jacob 
brought in the supper. His master then closed 
his book, rose, and with more courtesy of manner 
than he had yet shown, invited me to the table.</p>
<p>A dish of ham and eggs, a loaf of brown 
bread, and a bottle of admirable sherry, were 
placed before me.</p>
<p>"I have but the homeliest farm-house fare 
to offer you, sir," said my entertainer. "Your 
appetite, I trust, will make up for the 
deficiencies of our larder."</p>
<p>I had already fallen upon the viands, and now 
protested, with the enthusiasm of a starving 
sportsman, that I had never eaten anything so 
delicious.</p>
<p>He bowed stiffly, and sat down to his own 
supper, which consisted, primitively, of a jug 
of milk and a basin of porridge. We ate 
in silence, and, when we had done, Jacob 
removed the tray. I then drew my chair back 
to the fireside. My host, somewhat to my 
surprise, did the same, and turning abruptly 
towards me, said:</p>
<p>"Sir, I have lived here in strict retirement 
for three-and-twenty years. During that time, 
I have not seen as many strange faces, and I have 
not read a single newspaper. You are the first 
stranger who has crossed my threshold for more 
than four years. Will you favour me with a few 
words of information respecting that outer world 
from which I have parted company so long?"</p>
<p>"Pray interrogate me," I replied. "I am 
heartily at your service."</p>
<p>He bent his head in acknowledgment; leaned 
forward, with his elbows resting on his knees 
and his chin supported in the palms of his 
hands; stared fixedly into the fire; and 
proceeded to question me.</p>
<p>His inquiries related chiefly to scientific 
matters, with the later progress of which, as 
applied to the practical purposes of life, he was 
almost wholly unacquainted. No student of 
science myself, I replied as well as my slight 
information permitted; but the task was far 
from easy, and I was much relieved when, 
passing from interrogation to discussion, he 
began pouring forth his own conclusions upon 
the facts which I had been attempting to place 
before him. He talked, and I listened 
spell-bound. He talked till I believe he almost forgot 
my presence, and only thought aloud. I had 
never heard anything like it then; I have never 
heard anything like it since. Familiar with all 
systems of all philosophies, subtle in analysis, 
bold in generalisation, he poured forth his 
thoughts in an uninterrupted stream, and, still 
leaning forward in the same moody attitude 
with his eyes fixed upon the fire, wandered from 
topic to topic, from speculation to speculation, 
like an inspired dreamer. From practical science 
to mental philosophy; from electricity in the 
wire to electricity in the nerve; from Watts to 
Mesmer, from Mesmer to Reichenbach, from 
Reichenbach to Swedenborg, Spinoza, Condillac, 
Descartes, Berkeley, Aristotle, Plato, and the 
Magi and mystics of the East, were transitions 
which, however bewildering in their variety and 
scope, seemed easy and harmonious upon his 
lips as sequences in music. By-and-by--I forget 
now by what link of conjecture or illustration--
he passed on to that field which lies beyond the 
boundary line of even conjectural philosophy, 
and reaches no man knows whither. He spoke 
of the soul and its aspirations; of the spirit 
and its powers; of second sight; of prophecy; 
of those phenomena which, under the names 
of ghosts, spectres, and supernatural appearances, 
have been denied by the sceptics and 
attested by the credulous, of all ages.</p>
<p>"The world," he said, "grows hourly more 
and more sceptical of all that lies beyond its 
own narrow radius; and our men of science 
foster the fatal tendency. They condemn as 
fable all that resists experiment. They reject as 
false all that cannot be brought to the test of 
the laboratory or the dissecting-room. Against 
what superstition have they waged so long and 
obstinate a war, as against the belief in 
apparitions? And yet what superstition has 
maintained its hold upon the minds of men so 
long and so firmly? Show me any fact in 
physics, in history, in archaeology, which is 
supported by testimony so wide and so various. 
Attested by all races of men, in all ages, and in 
all climates, by the soberest sages of antiquity, 
by the rudest savage of to-day, by the Christian, 
the Pagan, the Pantheist, the Materialist, this 
phenomenon is treated as a nursery tale by the 
philosophers of our century. Circumstantial 
evidence weighs with them as a feather in the 
balance. The comparison of causes with effects, 
however valuable in physical science, is put 
aside as worthless and unreliable. The evidence 
of competent witnesses, however conclusive in 
a court of justice, counts for nothing. He who 
pauses befere he pronounces, is condemned as a 
trifler. He who believes, is a dreamer or a fool."</p>
<p>He spoke with bitterness, and, having said 
thus, relapsed for some minutes into silence. 
Presently he raised his head from his hands, and 
added, with an altered voice and manner,</p>
<p>"I, sir, paused, investigated, believed, and 
was not ashamed to state my convictions to the 
world. I, too, was branded as a visionary, held 
up to ridicule by my contemporaries, and hooted 
from that field of science in which I had laboured 
with honour during all the best years of my life. 
These things happened just three-and-twenty 
years ago. Since then, I have lived as you see me 
living now, and the world has forgotten me, as I 
have forgotten the world. You have my history."</p>
<p>"It is a very sad one," I murmured, scarcely 
knowing what to answer.</p>
<p>"It is a very common one," he replied. "I 
have only suffered for the truth, as many a better 
and wiser man has suffered before me."</p>
<p>He rose, as if desirous of ending the conversation, 
and went over to the window.</p>
<p>"It has ceased snowing," he observed, as he 
dropped the curtain, and came back to the fire-side.</p>
<p>"Ceased!" I exclaimed, starting eagerly to 
my feet. "Oh, if it were only possible--but no! 
it is hopeless. Even if I could find my way 
across the moor, I could not walk twenty miles 
to-night."</p>
<p>"Walk twenty miles to-night!" repeated my 
host. "What are you thinking of?"</p>
<p>"Of my wife," I replied, impatiently. "Of 
my young wife, who does not know that I have 
lost my way, and who is at this moment breaking 
her heart with suspense and terror."</p>
<p>"Where is she?"</p>
<p>"At Dwolding, twenty miles away."</p>
<p>"At Dwolding," he echoed, thoughtfully. 
"Yes, the distance, it is true, is twenty miles; 
but are you so very anxious to save the next 
six or eight hours?"</p>
<p>"So very, very anxious, that I would give ten 
guineas at this moment for a guide and a horse."</p>
<p>"Your wish can be gratified at a less costly 
rate," said he, smiling. "The night mail from 
the north, which changes horses at Dwolding, 
passes within five miles of this spot, and will be 
due at a certain cross-road in about an hour and 
a quarter. If Jacob were to go with you across 
the moor, and put you into the old coach-road, 
you could find your way, I suppose, to where it 
joins the new one?"</p>
<p>"Easily--gladly."</p>
<p>He smiled again, rang the bell, gave the old 
servant his directions, and, taking a bottle of 
whisky and a wine-glass from the cupboard in 
which he kept his chemicals, said:</p>
<p>"The snow lies deep, and it will be difficult 
walking to-night on the moor. A glass of 
usquebaugh before you start?"</p>
<p>I would have declined the spirit, but he 
pressed it on me, and I drank it. It went down 
my throat like liquid flame, and almost took my 
breath away.</p>
<p>"It is strong," he said; "but it will help to 
keep out the cold. And now you have no 
moments to spare. Good night!"</p>
<p>I thanked him for his hospitality, and would 
have shaken hands, but that he had turned away 
before I could finish my sentence. In another 
minute I had traversed the hall, Jacob had 
locked the outer door behind me, and we were 
out on the wide white moor.</p>
<p>Although the wind had fallen, it was still 
bitterly cold. Not a star glimmered in the 
black vault overhead. Not a sound, save the 
rapid crunching of the snow beneath our feet, 
disturbed the heavy stillness of the night. Jacob, 
not too well pleased with his mission, shambled 
on before in sullen silence, his lantern in his 
hand, and his shadow at his feet, I followed, 
with my gun over my shoulder, as little inclined 
for conversation as himself. My thoughts were 
full of my late host. His voice yet rang in my 
ears. His eloquence yet held my imagination 
captive. I remember to this day, with surprise, 
how my over-excited brain retained whole 
sentences and parts of sentences, troops of brilliant 
images, and fragments of splendid reasoning, in 
the very words in which he had uttered them. 
Musing thus over what I had heard, and striving 
to recal a lost link here and there, I strode 
on at the heels of my guide, absorbed and 
unobservant. Presently--at the end, as it seemed 
to me, of only a few minutes--he came to a 
sudden halt, and said:</p>
<p>"Yon's your road. Keep the stone fence to 
your right hand, and you can't fail of the way."</p>
<p>"This, then, is the old coach-road?"</p>
<p>"Ay, 'tis the old coach-road."</p>
<p>"And how far do I go, before I reach the 
cross-roads?"</p>
<p>"Nigh upon three mile."</p>
<p>I pulled out my purse, and he became more 
communicative.</p>
<p>"The road's a fair road enough," said he, "for 
foot passengers; but 'twas over steep and narrow 
for the northern traffic. You'll mind where the 
parapet's broken away, close again the sign-post. 
It's never been mended since the accident."</p>
<p>"What accident?"</p>
<p>"Eh, the night mail pitched right over into 
the valley below--a gude fifty feet an' more--
just at the worst bit o' road in the whole county."</p>
<p>"Horrible! Were many lives lost?"</p>
<p>"All. Four were found dead, and t'other 
two died next morning."</p>
<p>"How long is it since this happened?"</p>
<p>"Just nine year."</p>
<p>"Near the sign-post, you say? I will bear it 
in mind. Good night."</p>
<p>"Gude night, sir, and thankee." Jacob 
pocketed his half-crown, made a faint pretence 
of touching his hat, and trudged back by the 
way he had come.</p>
<p>I watched the light of his lantern till it 
quite disappeared, and then turned to pursue 
my way alone. This was no longer matter of 
the slightest difficulty, for, despite the dead 
darkness overhead, the line of stone fence 
showed distinctly enough against the pale gleam 
of the snow. How silent it seemed now, with 
only my footsteps to listen to; how silent and 
how solitary! A strange disagreeable sense of 
loneliness stole over me. I walked faster. I 
hummed a fragment of a tune. I cast up 
enormous sums in my head, and accumulated them 
at compound interest. I did my best, in short, 
to forget the startling speculations to which I 
had but just been listening, and, to some extent, 
I succeeded.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the night air seemed to become 
colder and colder, and though I walked fast I 
found it impossible to keep myself warm. My 
feet were like ice. I lost sensation, in my 
hands, and grasped my gun mechanically. I 
even breathed with difficulty, as though, instead 
of traversing a quiet north country highway, I 
were scaling the uppermost heights of some 
gigantic Alp. This last symptom became 
presently so distressing, that I was forced to stop 
for a few minutes, and lean against the stone 
fence. As I did so, I chanced to look back 
up the road, and there, to my infinite relief, 
I saw a distant point of light, like the gleam 
of an approaching lantern. I at first 
concluded that Jacob had retraced his steps and 
followed me; but even as the conjecture 
presented itself, a second light flashed into sight--
a light evidently parallel with the first, and 
approaching at the same rate of motion. It needed 
no second thought to show me that these must 
be the carriage-lamps of some private vehicle, 
though it seemed strange that any private 
vehicle should take a road professedly disused 
and dangerous.</p>
<p>There could be no doubt, however, of the fact, 
for the lamps grew larger and brighter every 
moment, and I even fancied I could already 
see the dark outline of the carriage between 
them. It was coming up very fast, and quite 
noiselessly, the snow being nearly a foot deep 
under the wheels.</p>
<p>And now the body of the vehicle became 
distinctly visible behind the lamps. It looked 
strangely lofty. A sudden suspicion flashed 
upon me. Was it possible that I had passed 
the cross-roads in the dark without observing 
the sign-post, and could this be the very coach 
which I had come to meet?</p>
<p>No need to ask myself that question a second 
time, for here it came round the bend of the road, 
guard and driver, one outside passenger, and 
four steaming greys, all wrapped in a soft haze 
of light, through which the lamps blazed out, 
like a pair of fiery meteors.</p>
<p>I jumped forward, waved my hat, and shouted. 
The mail came down at full speed, and passed me. 
For a moment I feared that I had not been seen 
or heard, but it was only for a moment. The 
coachman pulled up; the guard, muffled to the 
eyes in capes and comforters, and apparently 
sound asleep in the rumble, neither answered 
my hail nor made the slightest effort to 
dismount; the outside passenger did not even turn 
his head. I opened the door for myself, and 
looked in. There were but three travellers 
inside, so I stepped in, shut the door, slipped into 
the vacant corner, and congratulated myself on. 
my good fortune.</p>
<p>The atmosphere of the coach seemed, if 
possible, colder than that of the outer air, and was 
pervaded by a singularly damp and disagreeable 
smell. I looked round at my fellow-passengers. 
They were all three, men, and all silent. They 
did not seem to be asleep, but each leaned back 
in his corner of the vehicle, as if absorbed in 
his own reflections. I attempted to open a conversation.</p>
<p>"How intensely cold it is to-night," I said, 
addressing my opposite neighbour.</p>
<p>He lifted his head, looked at me, but made no reply.</p>
<p>"The winter," I added, "seems to have 
begun in earnest."</p>
<p>Although the corner in which he sat was so 
dim that I could distinguish none of his features 
very clearly, I saw that his eyes were still 
turned full upon me. And yet he answered 
never a word.</p>
<p>At any other time I should have felt, and 
perhaps expressed, some annoyance, but at the 
moment I felt too ill to do either. The icy 
coldness of the night air had struck a chill to my very 
marrow, and the strange smell inside the coach 
was affecting me with an intolerable nausea. I 
shivered from head to foot, and, turning to my 
left-hand neighbour, asked if he had any objection 
to an open window?</p>
<p>He neither spoke nor stirred.</p>
<p>I repeated the question somewhat more loudly, 
but with the same result. Then I lost patience, 
and let the sash down. As I did so, the leather 
strap broke in my hand, and I observed that the 
glass was covered with a thick coat of mildew, 
the accumulation, apparently, of years. My 
attention being thus drawn to the condition of 
the coach, I examined it more narrowly, and 
saw by the uncertain light of the outer lamps 
that it was in the last state of dilapidation. 
Every part of it was not only out of repair, but 
in a condition of decay. The sashes splintered 
at a touch. The leather flttings were crusted 
over with mould, and literally rotting from the 
woodwork. The floor was almost breaking away 
beneath my feet. The whole machine, in short, 
was foul with damp, and had evidently been 
dragged from some outhouse in which it had 
been mouldering away for years, to do another 
day or two of duty on the road.</p>
<p>I turned to the third passenger, whom I had 
not yet addressed, and hazarded one more remark.</p>
<p>"This coach," I said, "is in a deplorable 
condition. The regular mail, I suppose, is under 
repair?"</p>
<p>He moved his head slowly, and looked me in 
the face, without speaking a word. I shall never 
forget that look while I live. I turned cold at 
heart under it. I turn cold at heart even now 
when I recal it. His eyes glowed with a fiery 
unnatural lustre. His face was livid as the face 
of a corpse. His bloodless lips were drawn back 
as if in the agony of death, and showed the 
gleaming teeth between.</p>
<p>The words that I was about to utter died 
upon my lips, and a strange horrora dreadful 
horror--came upon me. My sight had by 
this time become used to the gloom of the 
coach, and I could see with tolerable distinctness. 
I turned to my opposite neighbour. 
He, too, was looking at me, with the same 
startling pallor in his face, and the same 
stony glitter in his eyes. I passed my baud 
across my brow. I turned to the passenger on 
the seat beside my own, and saw--oh Heaven! 
how shall I describe what I saw? I saw that he 
was no living man--that none of them were 
living men, like myself! A pale phosphorescent 
light--the light of putrefaction--played upon 
their awful faces; upon their hair, dank with 
the dews of the grave; upon their clothes, 
earth-stained and dropping to pieces; upon 
their hands, which were as the hands of corpses 
long buried. Only their eyes, their terrible eyes, 
were living; and those eyes were all turned 
menacingly upon me!</p>
<p>A shriek of terror, a wild unintelligible cry 
for help and mercy, burst from my lips as I 
flung myself against the door, and strove in vain 
to open it.</p>
<p>In that single instant, brief and vivid as a 
landscape beheld in the flash of summer lightning, I 
saw the moon shining down through a rift of 
stormy cloud--the ghastly sign-post rearing its 
warning finger by the wayside--the broken 
parapet--the plunging horses--the black gulf 
below. Then, the coach reeled like a ship at sea. 
Then, came a mighty crash--a sense of crushing 
pain--and then, darkness.</p>
<br/>
<p>It seemed as if years had gone by when I 
awoke one morning from a deep sleep, and found 
my wife watching by my bedside. I will pass 
over the scene that ensued, and give you, in 
half a dozen words, the tale she told me with 
tears of thanksgiving. I had fallen over a 
precipice, close against the junction of the 
old coach-road and the new, and had only been 
saved from certain death by lighting upon a deep 
snowdrift that had accumulated at the foot of 
the rock beneath. In this snowdrift I was 
discovered at daybreak, by a couple of shepherds, 
who carried me to the nearest shelter, and 
brought a surgeon to my aid. The surgeon found 
me in a state of raving delirium, with a broken 
arm and a compound fracture of the skull. The 
letters in my pocket-book showed my name and 
address; my wife was summoned to nurse me; 
and, thanks to youth and a fine constitution, I 
came out of danger at last. The place of my fall, 
I need scarcely say, was precisely that at which 
a frightful accident had happened to the north 
mail nine years before.</p>
<p>I never told my wife the fearful events which 
I have just related to you. I told the surgeon 
who attended me; but he treated the whole 
adventure as a mere dream born of the fever in 
my brain. We discussed the question over and 
over again, until we found that we could discuss 
it with temper no longer, and then we dropped 
it. Others may form what conclusions they please 
--I <em>know</em> that twenty years ago I was the fourth 
inside passenger in that Phantom Coach.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="ANOTHER PAST LODGER RELATES CERTAIN PASSAGES TO HER HUSBAND."/>
<chapter>
<p>[INTRODUCTORY NOTE BY MAJOR JACKMAN. 
The country clergyman and his quiet and better 
than pretty wife, who occupied my respected 
friend's second floor for two spring months of 
four successive years, were objects of great 
interest, both with my respected friend and with me. 
One evening we took tea with them, and 
happened to speak of a pretty wilful-looking young 
creature and her husband--friends of theirs--
who had dined with them on the previous day. 
"Ah!" said the clergyman, taking his wife's 
hand very tenderly in his; "thereby hangs a 
tale. Tell it to our good friends, my dear." 
"I can address it, Owen," said his wife, 
hesitating, " to nobody but you." "Address it, then, 
to me, my darling," said he, "and Mrs. Lirriper 
and the Major will be none the worse listeners." 
So she went on as follows, with her hand resting 
in his all the time. Signed, J. JACKMAN.]</p>
<br/>
<p>The first time I saw you again, after the 
years long and many which had passed over us 
since our childhood, I was watching for you on 
the peak of the hill, from whence I could see 
furthest down the steep and shady lane along 
which you were coming up to our hamlet from 
the plain below me. All day I had been anxious 
that when you arrived, our hills, which you 
must have forgotten, should put on their most 
gorgeous beauty; but now the sunset was come 
which would leave us the bare and grey outlines 
of the rocks only, and, from the kindling sky 
there fell bars of golden sunshine, with darker 
rays underlying them, slanting down the slopes 
of the mountain, and touching every rounded 
knoll and little dimpling dell with such a glory, 
that even the crimson and purple tints of the 
budding bilberry wires far away towards the 
level table-land where the summits blended, 
glowed, and burned under the farewell light. 
Just then there came a shout of welcome, like 
the shout of harvest home, ringing up through 
the quiet air, and, straining my shaded eyes to 
catch the first glimpse, I saw you walking in the 
midst of a band of our sturdy, sunburnt villagers, 
with the same slight and delicate-looking frame, 
and pale, grave pleasant face, and shy and timid 
manner that were yours when we were boy and 
girl together.</p>
<p>Our little hamlet had gathered itself from 
time to time, without any special plan or 
purpose, upon one of the lower terraces of our 
cluster of mountains, separated from the nearest 
villages by a wide tract of land, only to be 
crossed by steep, stony, deep-rutted lanes, 
overhung with wild hedgerows, and almost impassable 
in the winter. During the summer, when the 
faint tones of the bells of our parish church were 
borne up to us on the calm air, a little procession 
of us, the girls and children riding on rough 
hill-ponies, were wont to wind down the lanes to 
the Sunday morning service; but in winter no 
one thought of the pilgrimage, unless some of 
the young men had sweethearts in the village 
whom they hoped to meet at church. Mr. 
Vernon, the rector, being an archdeacon, hardly 
less than a bishop in dignity and importance, 
was deeply distressed at the heathenish darkness 
of his mountain district; and he and my father, 
who owned the great hill-farm, which gave 
employment to the people of our hamlet, at last 
built the little red-brick church, with no tower, 
and smaller than our barn, which stands upon the 
point of the mountain terrace, overlooking the 
great plain that stretches away from our feet up 
to the very far horizon.</p>
<p>There might have been a difficulty in finding 
a curate who would live up at Katlinghope, 
with no other social intercourse than could be 
obtained by a long march into the peopled plain 
below us; but I knew afterwards that the 
church, so far as my father's share in it was 
concerned, had been built for you. You were just 
taking orders, and you had a pleasant remembrance 
of the large old rambling half-timber 
house where you had spent some months of your 
childhood; so when we wrote to you that your 
dwelling would be in our own house, your study 
being the blue parlour which looked down the 
green sheltered dell where the young lambs were 
folded, you answered that you would gladly take 
the charge, and live with us again on the sweet, 
free heathery uplands, where you had breathed 
in health and strength in your early boyhood.</p>
<p>You were grave and studious, and withal so 
simple-hearted, that the seclusion and the primitive 
manners of our hamlet made it a very Eden 
to you. You had never forgotten our old haunts, 
and we revisited them together, for in the first 
moment of our greeting you had fallen into your 
habit of dependence upon me, and of demanding 
my companionship, as when you were a delicate 
boy of six years, and I a strong, healthy, mountain 
girl three years older. To me only, could you 
utter your thoughts freely, for your natural 
shyness closed your lips to strangers; and all 
were strangers to you, even those who had 
known you for a lifetime, if they did not possess 
the touch of sympathy which your spirit 
needed before it would open its treasures. Up 
on the hill-side, when the steady noontide seemed 
as unchangeable as the everlasting rocks about 
us, or when the tremulous dusk stole with silent 
shadows over the fading headlands, you and I 
sat together, while I listened to the unreserved 
outpourings of your thoughts and fancies, boyish 
sometimes, for you were young still, but in my 
heart there was an ever-growing tenderness and 
care for you, which could find no flaw, and feel 
no weariness. You were apt to be unmindful of 
the hours, and it was I who made it my duty to 
watch their flight for you, and see to it that the 
prayer-bell, the single bell that hung under a 
little pent-roof against the church, should be 
tolled at the due time; for Mr. Vernon, in 
consideration of our heathenish condition, made it 
a point that the evening service should be read 
three times a week. And as it was needful that 
our household should set a pattern to the rest 
of the villagers, and it interfered with my father's 
evening pipe, and my mother could not be 
troubled to change her afternoon cap for her 
church bonnet, it always fell to my lot to walk 
with you--do you remember?--only a few 
hundred yards or so along the brow of the hill, 
to the little church.</p>
<p>I was about to say that it was the happiest 
time of my life; but all true life is gain; and 
the sorrows that befal us are none other than 
solemn massive foundation-stones laid low in 
unfathomable gloom, that a measureless 
content may be built upon them. You remember 
the first burial-service you had to read, when 
you besought me to stand beside you at the 
open grave, because never before had the 
mournful words been uttered by your lips. It 
was only the funeral of a little child, and the 
tiny grave, when the clods were heaped upon it, 
was no larger than a molehill in the meadows; 
yet your voice faltered, and your hands trembled 
as you cast this first small seed into that God's 
Acre of ours. The autumn night set in while 
we lingered in silence beside the nameless 
coffin, long after the mother and her companion 
who had brought it to its solitary grave, had 
turned away homeward. It was the flapping 
of wings close beside us that caused us to lift 
up our eyes, and from the fir-trees above us four 
rooks flew home across the darkening sky to 
their nests in the plain below. You know how 
of old the flight of birds would fill me with 
vague superstitions, and just then the heavy 
fluttering of their dusky wings overhead, as 
they beat the air for their start, caused a sudden 
tremor and shudder to thrill through me.</p>
<p>"What ails you, Jane?" you asked.</p>
<p>"Nothing ails me, Mr. Scott," I said.</p>
<p>"Call me Owen," you answered, laying your 
hand upon my arm, and looking straight into 
my eyes, for we were of the same height, and 
stood level with one another: "I do not like to 
hear you call me anything but Owen. Have 
you forgotten how we used to play together? 
Do you remember how I fell into the sheep-
pool when we were alone in the valley, and you 
wasted no time in fruitless cries, but waded in 
at once, and dragged me out of the water? 
You would carry me home in your strong arms, 
though the path was along the hill-side, and you 
had to rest every few minutes; while I looked 
up into your rosy face with a very peaceful 
feeling. Your face is not rosy now, Jane."</p>
<p>How could it be, while your words brought 
such a dull heavy pain to my heart? I seemed 
suddenly to be so many, many years older than 
you! Sometimes of late I had detected myself 
reckoning your age and mine by the month, and 
the day of the month, and always finding, with 
a pang faint and slight, that you were indeed so 
many years younger than I. Yet the heart 
takes little heed of age. And I, for the quiet 
life I had led among the mountains, just one 
regular single round of summer and winter, 
coming stealthily and uncounted in their turn 
from season to season, might have been little 
more than some yearling creature, that has seen 
but one spring-time and felt the frosts of but 
one Christmas. While you, with your great 
acquirements of learning, and the weighty 
thoughts that had already wrinkled your broad 
forehead, and the burden of study that had 
bowed down your young shoulders, seemed to 
have borne the full yoke of the years which had 
laid so gentle a touch upon me.</p>
<p>"I remember very well, Owen," I said; "I 
was proud of having you to take charge of. 
But you must go in now; the fog is rising, and 
you are not over strong."</p>
<p>I spoke with the old tone of authority, and 
you left me, standing alone beside the little 
grave. The churchyard extended to the very 
edge of the steep hill, which looked far and 
wide over the great plain. It was hidden now 
by a white lake of mist floating beneath me, 
upon which the hunting-moon, rising slowly 
behind the eastern hills, shone down with cold 
pale beams; for the harvest was over, and the 
heavy October fogs gathered in the valleys, and 
hung in light clouds about the fading coppices 
in the hollows of the mountains. I turned 
heart-sick to the little open grave, the first in 
the new graveyard, which was waiting until the 
sheep were herded for the sexton to fill it up 
for ever with the clods; the baby hands and 
feet folded there in eternal rest, had never been 
stained with selfishness, and the baby lips, sealed 
in eternal silence, had uttered never a word of 
bitterness. So, I said, looking down sadly into 
the narrow tiny grave, so shall it be with my 
love; I bury it here while it is yet pure and 
unselfish, like a seed sown in God's Acre; and 
from it shall spring a plentiful harvest of 
happiness for Owen, and of great peace for myself.</p>
<p>It may be that the autumn fog was more 
harmful than usual, for I was ill after that 
night with my first serious illness; not merely 
ailing, but hanging doubtfully between life and 
death. I grew to think of our summer months 
together as of a time long since passed, and 
almost enwrapped in forgetfulness. My mother 
laughed when I stroked her grey hair with 
my feeble fingers, and told her I felt older 
than she was.</p>
<p>"Nay," she said, "we must have you younger 
and bonnier than ever, Jane. We must see 
what we can do for you before you come down 
stairs, and meet Owen. Poor Owen! Who 
would have dreamt that he could be more 
heart-broken and disconsolate than Jane's own 
mother? Poor Owen!"</p>
<p>My mother was smiling significantly, and looking 
keenly at me over her glasses, but I said 
nothing; only turned away my face from her 
scrutiny to the frosted window, where winter had 
traced its delicate patterns upon the lattice panes.</p>
<p>"Jane," she went on, clasping my fingers in 
hers, "don't you know that we all wish it, 
Owen's father, and yours, and me? We thought 
of it before he came here. Owen is poor, but 
we have enough for both of you, and I love him 
like my own son. You need never leave the 
old home. Jane, don't you love Owen?"</p>
<p>"But I am older than he is," I whispered.</p>
<p>"A marvellous difference," she said, with 
another laugh; "so am I older than father, but 
who could tell it was so now? And what does 
it matter if Owen loves you?"</p>
<p>I wish to cast no blame on you, but there was 
much in your conduct to feed the sweet delusion 
which brought fresh health and strength to 
me. You called my mother, "Mother." You 
sent fond messages by her, which lost nothing 
in tone or glance by her delighted repetition of 
them. You considered no walk too far to get 
flowers for me from the gardens in the plain 
below. When I grew well enough to come 
down stairs you received me with a rapture of 
congratulation. You urged that the blue 
parlour, with its southern aspect and closely-fitting 
wainscot, was the warmest room in the house, 
and you would not be satisfied until the great 
chintz-covered sofa with its soft cushions was 
lifted out of its corner, and planted upon the 
hearth, for me to lie there, watching you while 
you were busy among your books; and many 
times a day you read some sentence aloud, or 
brought a volume to my side that I might look 
over the same page, while you waited patiently 
as my slower eyes and brain were longer than 
yours in taking in the sense. Even when you 
were away at the rectory--for during my illness 
you had begun to spend your evenings there, 
when you had no church duty--I sat in your 
study, with your books about me, in which 
there were passages marked out for me to read. 
I lingered over getting well.</p>
<p>I was lying on the sofa one evening, wrapped 
in my mother's white shawl, and just passing 
into a dreamy slumber, when I heard you entering 
from one of your visits to the rectory. I 
cannot tell why I did not rouse myself, unless 
it seemed to me only as part of a dream, but 
you crossed the floor noiselessly, and stood 
beside me for a minute or two, looking down--
I felt it--upon my changed face, and closed 
eyelids. Had I been asleep I should never have 
felt the light, timid, fluttering touch of your 
lips upon mine. But my eyes opened at once, 
and you fell back.</p>
<p>"What is it, Owen?" I asked you calmly, 
for I felt as if by instinct that the caress was 
not for me. "Why did you kiss me, Owen?"</p>
<p>"I wonder I never did it before," you said, 
"you are so like a sister to me. I have no other 
sister, Jane, and my mother died when I was very 
young,"</p>
<p>You stood opposite to me in the bright fire-
light with a face changing and flushing like a 
girl's, and a happy youthful buoyant gladness 
in it very different to your usually quiet aspect. 
As I looked at you the old pain returned like a 
forgotten burden upon my heart.</p>
<p>"I am so happy," you said, crossing over the 
hearth again, and kneeling down beside me.</p>
<p>"Is it anything you can tell me, dear Owen?" 
I said, laying my hand upon your hair, and 
wondering even then at the whiteness and 
thinness of my poor fingers. The door behind 
you was opened quietly, but you did not hear 
it, and my mother stood for an instant in the 
doorway smiling on us both; I felt keenly how 
she would misunderstand.</p>
<p>Then you spoke to me, shyly at first, but 
gathering confidence, of Adelaide Vernon. I 
knew her well: a little lovely graceful creature, 
with coquettish school-girl ways, which 
displayed themselves even at church, though her 
black browed and swarthy aunt sat beside her in 
the rector's pew. While you spoke, growing 
eloquent with a lover's rhapsodies, the fair young 
face, with its pink and white tints, and soft dainty 
beauty, rose up before me; and your praises 
seemed to flood my aching heart like a wide 
breaking in of water, which rolled desolately 
against me.</p>
<p>I need not remind you of the opposition your 
love met. Mr. Vernon was averse to marrying 
his portionless niece to his poor curate of 
Ratlinghope; but his disapproval was nothing to 
the vehement rage with which Mrs. Vernon, who 
had other views for Adelaide, set her face against 
it. The rector came up to our house, and told 
us--you remember?--with tears wrung from 
him, proud and reticent man as he was, that he 
dreaded nothing less than a return of that fearful 
malady of madness, which had kept his wife 
a prisoner for years under his own roof. There 
was as bitter, but a more concealed resentment 
in our own household, which you only felt 
indirectly and vaguely. I learned now with what 
a long premeditated plan your father and mine 
had schemed for our marriage. Your poor 
foolish love seemed to every one but yourself and 
me a rash selfishness. Even I thought at times 
that half Adelaide's love for you sprang from 
pure contrariness and childish romance, just 
feeding upon the opposition it met with. How 
I smoothed your path for you; how, without 
suffering the coldness of disappointment to 
creep over me, I sought your happiness in your 
own way as if it had been mine also; you partly 
know. So we prevailed at last.</p>
<p>In spite of all my smothered pain, it was 
pleasant to see you watch the building of your 
little parsonage, the square red brick house 
beside the church, with the doors and windows 
pricked out with blue tesselated tile-work. It 
was not a stone's throw from our home, and the 
blue parlour saw little of your presence, and the 
dust gathered on the books you had been wont 
to read. But you would have me to share your 
exultation. Whenever the large beams were 
being fitted into your roof, or the cope-stones 
built into your walls, or the blue tiles set round 
your windows, I must look on with you, and 
hearken to your fears lest the home should be 
unworthy of Adelaide. All my sad thoughts--
for day after day you were setting your foot 
upon my heart--I worked away in busy labour 
at your house, and in wistful contrivances to 
make the little nest look elegant and pretty 
in the sight of Adelaide Vernon.</p>
<p>Your marriage was to be on the Tuesday, and on 
the Monday I went down with you to the rectory. 
The place had become familiar to you, all but 
the long low southern wing, with its blank 
walls ivy-grown, and with its windows opening 
upon the other side over a wide shallow mere, 
fed with the waters of a hundred mountain 
brooks. They were Mrs. Vernon's apartments, 
built for her during her protracted and seemingly 
hopeless malady, for her husband had promised 
her that she should never be removed from under 
his roof. She kept them under her own charge, 
rarely suffering any foot to enter them, and Mr. 
Vernon drew me aside when we readied the 
house, and implored me to venture upon making 
my way, if possible, to his wife, who had shut 
herself up in them since the previous evening, 
and had refused to admit even him. I crossed the 
long narrow passage which separated them from 
the rest of the dwelling, and rapped gently at 
the door, and after a minute's silence I heard 
Mrs. Vernon's voice asking, "Who is there?"</p>
<p>"Only Jane Meadows," I answered.</p>
<p>I was a favourite with her, and after a slight 
hesitation, the door was opened, and Mrs. Vernon 
stood before me: her tall and powerful figure 
wrapped in a dressing-gown, which left the 
sinewy arms bare to the elbow, while the thick 
locks of her black hair, just streaked with grey, 
fell dishevelled about her swarthy face. The 
room behind her was littered from end to end, 
and the fire at which she had been sitting was 
choked up with cinders, while the window, 
tarnished with dust, gave no glimpse of the 
mountain landscape beyond. She returned to 
her chair before the fire, and surveyed me with 
a sullen frown from under her reddened eyelids. 
The trembling of her limbs, muscular as they 
were, and the glistening of her face, told me not 
more surely than the faint and sickly odour 
pervading the room, that she had been taking 
opium.</p>
<p>"Jane," she cried, with a burst of maudlin 
tears, which she did not attempt to conceal, 
"come here, and sit down beside me. I am 
so miserable, Jane. Your mother was here 
on Saturday, telling me that you love Owen 
Scott, and everybody wanted him to marry you. 
Adelaide, the poor little painted doll, is not fit 
to be his wife, and she will make him wretched. 
And you will be miserable, like all of us."</p>
<p>My heart sank at the thought of your 
wretchedness. "I am not miserable," I replied, throwing 
my own arms round her, and looking up 
into her wrathful eyes. "You don't know how 
strong and peaceful we grow when we seek the 
happiness of those we love. We cannot decide 
who shall love whom, and it was not God's 
will that Owen should choose me. Let us make 
them as happy as we can."</p>
<p>She let me lead her to her seat, and talk to 
her about you and Adelaide in a way that 
tranquillised her, until she consented to dress herself 
with my aid, and return with me to the company 
assembled in the other part of the house.</p>
<p>But there was something in Adelaide's whole 
conduct which tended to irritate Mrs. Vernon. 
She was playing silly pranks upon us all, 
but especially upon her gloomy aunt, about 
whom she hovered with a fretting waywardness 
mingled with an unquiet tenderness, 
which displayed itself in numberless childish 
ways; but with such grace and prettiness, 
that none of us could find it in our hearts to chide 
her, except Mrs. Vernon herself. I was glad 
when the time came for us to leave; though you 
loitered across the lawn, looking back every 
minute at Adelaide, who stood in the portico: 
her white dress gleaming amid the shadows, and 
she kissing her little hand to you with a laugh 
whose faint musical ringing just reached our ears.</p>
<p>You slept that night, as we often sleep, 
unwitting that those who are dear to us as our 
own souls are passing through great perils. 
You slept, and it was I who watched all night, 
and called you early in the morning, with the 
news that the sun was rising over the hills 
into a cloudless sky, and that your marriage-
day was come.</p>
<p>We were at the rectory betimes, yet the 
villagers had reared an arch of flowers over the 
gates. Mrs. Vernon, dressed with unusual 
richness and care, was watching for us at 
the portico, and received us both with a 
grave but kindly greeting. All the house 
was astir with the hurrying of many feet, and 
the sharp click of doors slamming to and fro; 
but though you waited restlessly, no one else 
came near us in the little room where we three 
sat together, until the door was slowly opened 
--you turning to it with rapturous impatience 
--and Mr. Vernon entered and told us that 
Adelaide was nowhere to be found.</p>
<p>"Don't alarm yourself," said Mr. Vernon to 
his wife, "but Adelaide has been missing since 
daybreak; she was gone when her companions 
went to call her. You remember she used to 
walk in her sleep if she were much excited; and 
this morning the hall door was open, and her 
bonnet was found on the way to Ratlinghope. 
The agitation of yesterday must have caused 
this."</p>
<p>"She was coming to me!" you said, with a 
vivid smile and a glow, which faded as you began 
to realise the fact of Adelaide's disappearance.</p>
<p>The hills stretched away for many a mile, with 
shelving rocks here and there, which hung over 
deep still tarns, black with shadows, and hedged 
in by reedy thickets. And there were narrow rifts, 
cleaving far down into the living stone of the 
mountain range, and overgrown with brambles, 
where the shepherds sometimes heard their 
lambs bleating piteously, out of sight or reach 
of help, until the dreary moan died away from 
the careless echoes. "Children have been lost 
there," cried Mrs. Vernon, wringing her hands 
distractedly; and if Adelaide had wandered 
away in the darkness, she might be lying now 
dead in the depths of the black tarns, or 
imprisoned alive in one of the clefts of the rocks.</p>
<p>I never left your side that day; and as hour 
after hour passed by, I saw a grey ghastly 
change creep over your young face, as your 
heart died within you. Mrs. Vernon kept close 
beside us, though we soon distanced every other 
seeker, and her wonderful strength continued 
unabated, even when your despairing energy 
was exhausted. I knew the mountains as well 
as the shepherds did; and from one black 
unruffled tarn, to another like itself, gloomy 
and secret-looking, I led you without speaking; 
save that into every gorge, whose depth 
our straining eyes could not penetrate, we 
called aloud, until the dark dank walls of the 
gulf muttered back the name of Adelaide. 
There was no foot-weariness for us as long as 
the daylight lasted; and it seemed as if the sun 
<em>could</em> not go down until we had found her. 
Now and then we tarried upon the brow of 
some headland, with our hands lifted to our 
ears that we might catch the most distant 
whisper of the signal-bells; the faintest tone 
that ever reached the uplands, if there were any 
to be borne to us upon the breeze, from the 
church belfry in the plain far away.</p>
<p>The search was continued for many days; but 
no trace of Adelaide was found, except a lace 
cap which lay soiled and wet with dew near 
to one of the tarns which we three had visited; 
but without discovering it then. Mrs. Vernon 
rallied our hopes and energies long after all 
reasonable ground for either was lost, and then she 
fell into a depression of spirits which almost 
threatened a renewal of her early malady. She 
collected all Adelaide's little possessions, and spent 
many hours of each day among them in her own 
apartments; but she was always ready to leave 
them, when you, in your sore grief, wandered to 
the old home of the lost girl; and then she 
strove to console you with a patient tenderness 
strange to see in a woman so rigid and haughty. 
But you refused to be comforted; and putting 
on one side all the duties of your office, you 
roamed ceaselessly about the hills; dragging 
yourself back again almost lifeless to our house--
for your own you would never enter--and asking 
me night after night, as the sunset and darkness 
spread upon the mountains, if there were no 
place left unexplored. As though it were possible 
to call back again the dead past, and find her yet 
alive among the desolate hills!</p>
<p>In the midst of it all another trouble befel 
us. Before the new year came in, my mother 
fell ill of the sickness in which she died. I 
think that first roused you from the solitude of 
your despair. Though you could not yet front 
the kindly familiar faces of your old congregation, 
there seemed to be some little break in the 
cloud of hopelessness which hung about you, in 
the care you began to feel for her. It was but 
a few days before she died, and after you had been 
reading to her, as she lay very feeble, and often 
dozing away with weakness, that she suddenly 
roused herself, and looked at you with eager, eyes.</p>
<p>"You'll always be fond of Jane, Owen?"</p>
<p>"Always. She has been the truest of sisters to me."</p>
<p>"Ah!" sighed my mother, "you little think 
how she has loved you. Not one woman in a 
thousand could have done as our Jane has. Boy, it's 
not possible you'll ever be loved so again on earth."</p>
<p>You had never thought of it before, and 
your face grew paler than my mother's. I sat 
behind the curtains, where you could see me 
though she could not; and you looked across 
at me fixedly, still keeping your station by her 
side. I smiled with the tears standing in my eyes, 
but with no foolish burning in my cheeks, for if 
it would comfort you in any degree, I was neither 
afraid nor ashamed that you should know it.</p>
<p>"Ever since you came," my mother 
murmured, "smoothing every stone out of your 
path, and only fretting because she could not bear 
every trouble for you! If you ever marry, Owen, 
she will live only for you, and your wife and 
children. You will always care for her, Owen?"</p>
<p>"I will never marry any other woman," you 
said, laying your lips upon my mother's wrinkled 
hand.</p>
<p>I know it was a comfort to you. Perhaps in 
the suddenness and mystery of your loss, you 
felt as if everything was wrecked, and nothing 
remained to life but a bleak, black dreariness. 
But from that hour, there was a light, very 
feeble and dim and lustreless a mere glow-worm 
in the waste wilderness--which shone upon your 
path. You began to return to your old duties, 
though it was as if you were leaning upon me, 
and trusting to my guiding. There was no talk 
of love between us; it was enough that we 
understood one another.</p>
<p>We might have gone on quietly thus, year 
after year, until the memory of Adelaide had 
faded away, but that it was not many months 
before my father, who had been younger than my 
mother, and was a fine man yet, announced to 
me that he was about to marry again. The 
news had reached you elsewhere; for, on the 
same evening, while I was sitting alone with my 
troubled thoughts, you called me into the blue 
parlour, and made me take my old seat in the 
corner of the chintz-covered sofa, while you 
knelt down beside me.</p>
<p>"Jane," you said, very gently, " I want to 
offer my poor home to you."</p>
<p>"No, no, Owen," I cried, looking down upon 
your face, so grey and unsmiling, with dark 
circles under your sunken eyes, "you are young 
yet, and will meet with some other woman--a 
dear sister she shall ever be to me--younger 
and brighter, and more fitted for you than I 
am. You shall not sacrifice yourself to me."</p>
<p>"But, Jane," you urged, and a pleasant light 
dawned in your eyes, "I cannot do without you. 
You know I could not go alone into yonder 
little house, which stands empty by the church; 
and how could I go away from. Ratlinghope, 
leaving you behind me? I have no home but 
where you are; and I love you more than I 
ever thought to love any woman again."</p>
<p>Maybe you remember what more you said; 
every word is in <em>my</em> heart to this day.</p>
<p>I thought it over in the quiet night. You 
were poor, and I, inheriting my mother's fortune, 
could surround you with comforts; secretly in 
my judgment, there had grown the conviction 
that you would never be what the world calls a 
prosperous man. The time was come when we 
must be separated or united for ever; and if 
you parted from me, I could never more stand 
between you and any sorrow. So I became 
your wife nearly twelve months after your great 
loss and misery.</p>
<p>Those first weeks of our marriage had more 
sunshine than I had ever dared to hope for. 
You seemed to shake off a great burden, 
now that it was irrevocably settled that our 
lives were to be passed together. Not a single 
lurking dread remained in my heart that you 
were otherwise than happy.</p>
<p>We came back to England some days earlier 
than we intended, for a letter reached me after 
many delays, with the news that Mrs. Vernon 
was ill, and implored us to hasten our return. 
We stayed on our way homeward at the 
rectory, where I soon left you with Mr. Vernon, 
while I was conducted to the entrance of the 
long passage which led to Mrs. Vernon's apartments. 
Her lady, the servant said in a whisper, 
was ailing more in mind than in body, and she 
dared not disobey her strict orders not to 
venture further. I went on, for I knew her caprices; 
and once again I was admitted, when she heard 
me say, calling myself by your name, that it 
was Jane Scott who sought entrance. There 
was no new gleam of madness in her dark 
eyes. She grasped my hands nervously, and 
held them fast, while she questioned me about 
our journey, and what your manner had been. 
Were you happy? Had you altogether ceased 
to grieve for Adelaide? Was your whole love 
mine? Was there perfect unalloyed content in 
our mutual affection?</p>
<p>"Jane," she said, with her lips close to my 
ear, though she spoke in a loud shrill tone, "I 
had sworn that Adelaide should never marry 
Owen Scott. Partly for your sake, for your 
mother said it was killing you. Partly 
because it was better for her to marry my rich 
nephew. Jane, I must have what I set my mind 
upon, or I should die. What was Adelaide, 
that I should lose my life, or worse, ten times 
worse, lose my reason again for her sake? I 
did it for the best, Jane. I never thought how 
it was to end. It only seemed to me, if I could 
hide her from one day till the next, something 
would happen. But it was a long long time, 
a dreadful time, till Owen came to tell us he was 
going to marry you. You understand, Jane?"</p>
<p>"No, no!" I cried.</p>
<p>"It seemed so easy a thing to do, and best 
for all of us. I carried her here in the night, 
like the baby she is. I have never been cruel 
to her, never, Jane. But the time seemed long, 
long, and she was wild and cunning at first. 
I only thought of a little while, and afterwards 
I grew afraid. But she will not come out now, 
though I try to rouse her. Go in, Jane, and 
make her come out!"</p>
<p>Mrs. Vernon drew me across the inner 
apartment to the door of a small chamber, 
padded throughout, and with no opening except 
into the ante-room. It had been constructed 
for herself in the seasons of her most dangerous 
paroxysms, and was so carefully planned that no 
sound of her wild ravings could be heard, and no 
glimpse of her face could be seen, through the 
window which overlooked the mere. And here 
lay your Adelaide asleep, wan and emaciated, 
with a dimness on her golden curls, and all the 
rosy tints of her beauty faded.</p>
<p>"She has been taking laudanum," said Mrs. 
Vernon. "I gave it to her at first, when I was 
compelled to be away for a long time, and now 
she has a craving for it. I have never been cruel to 
her, Jane. She has had everything she wanted."</p>
<p>You know how I came down to the library, 
where you and Mr. Vernon were sitting, and 
told you and Mr. Vernon all. You know how, 
while Mr. Vernon bowed his grey head upon his 
hands, you stretched out your arms to me, and 
cried, with an exceeding bitter cry as if I could 
find a remedy for you, "Help me, Jane!"</p>
<p>Dear, my heart fluttered towards you for a 
moment, longing to be clasped in your out-
stretched arms, and pour out all my love to you, 
which had ever been tongue-tied, lest you should 
weary of it; but I hardened myself against the 
yearning. In the great mirror on the staircase 
I scarcely knew the white-faced despairing 
woman, who was sweeping by, erect and stern, 
and the two men with downcast heads and 
lingering footsteps who were following her. You 
spoke no word, either of you, but passed through 
the outer apartment, with its tarnished window 
and sullied disorder, where Mrs. Vernon sat 
cowering in the furthest corner, and entered the 
room within, where Adelaide lay asleep, but 
breathing fitfully, as on the verge of waking. I 
dragged myself (for I was faint) to the casement, 
which I pushed open, and looked out upon the 
purple hills, purple with heather-bells, where we 
had thought her unknown tomb was. Up yonder 
stood our home, the home we had built for 
Adelaide, and which we had never yet entered; 
and turning away my aching eyes from it, I 
looked back again upon you, who were standing 
beside her, with a depth of tender and horror-
stricken pity on your bending face.</p>
<p>Whether it was the fresh air from the hills, or 
some mysterious influence of your presence 
penetrating her sleeping senses, we cannot tell; but 
while I looked, unable to turn away my eyes 
from you both, her mouth quivered, and her long 
eyelashes trembled, half opening and closing 
again, as if too languid to bear the light, until 
you touched her hands softly and timidly, and 
breathed "Adelaide!" And she awoke fully, 
with a sharp shrill cry, as if you were at last 
come for her deliverance, and springing into 
your arms, she clung to you, with her little hands 
clasped round you as though they would never 
unlock again; while you laid your cheek down 
upon her dim dishevelled curls, and I heard 
you murmur, "My darling!" Yet yonder was 
our home, yours and mine, Owen; and the ring 
that was on my finger--the only one I wore, I 
cared so much for it--was our marriage-ring.</p>
<p>You turned to me, Owen, with that full, 
searching gaze, eye to eye, and soul to soul, 
which we could bear from one another. Adelaide 
was come back from the dead to bring to us 
greater sorrow than her death had brought. We 
saw it all, you and I, while she was still clinging 
to you with sobs and childish caresses, and 
I stood aloof at the window. I knew how much 
you had to say to her which no other ear might 
listen to. I knew what it would be wisest and 
best to do. I took Mr. Vernon's arm, and I 
drew him away from the room, and I left you 
and Adelaide together.</p>
<p>I know now that it was not long before 
you came to me--only ten minutes--such a 
trifle of time as one gives ungrudgingly to the 
dreariest beggar on the roadside who has a 
piteous tale to tell. But all the past, and all 
the dreaded future being present with me, the 
moments seemed endless in their immortal bitterness, 
until you entered the room where I had 
shut myself in alone, and coming swiftly up to 
me where I stood upon the hearth, hid your face 
upon my shoulder with strong sobs and tears.</p>
<p>"I will go away, Jane," you said at last, "by 
myself for a few days, till she is gone from here. 
You will take care of her for me. She knows 
all now."</p>
<p>"I will do anything for you," I answered, 
still chary of my words, as it was my wont to 
be, lest my love should weary you.</p>
<p>You left me, as it was best you should do, 
alone, with the charge of that perplexed house 
hold upon me; Adelaide broken in health and 
spirits; Mrs. Vernon plunged into the frenzy 
of her old malady; the story running far and 
wide throughout the country. Every day I 
found my comfort and strength in the letter that 
came from you, wherein you had the generosity 
to lay bare your heart to me as frankly as ever. 
So the hard task began to grow lighter; the 
tangled coil to unravel itself. Mr. Vernon 
procured a nurse to take care of his wife, and I 
accompanied Adelaide to the distant dwelling of 
some friends, where we hoped she might sooner 
recover her health; nor did I leave her until 
I saw her resuming her playful girlish ways, 
and coquettish graces. At last I was free to 
go home; to go to the home you and I had built 
on the rock, watching together its beams laid, 
and its roof raised. But I was alone there. If 
Adelaide had been your young and beautiful 
wife, you would have crossed the threshold 
hand in hand, uttering such words of welcome 
as would never have died out of her memory, if 
it had been like mine.</p>
<p>The jealous misgiving was unworthy of you 
and myself, dear. I paced the little rooms, 
taking up the trinkets which you had bought 
anxiously and lavishly for Adelaide, and 
always laying them down again with a sharper 
pang. Did you wish me to die, Owen? Was 
your heart aching to take her back again? 
I rested at last in your little study, where 
your books lay in scattered heaps before the 
empty shelves. The days were gone for ever 
when we had read them together on the hill-side, 
in the first careless freedom of your sojourn 
with us. I sat down among them, covering my 
face with my hands, and I heard and I saw 
nothing.</p>
<p>Nothing, my love, my dear, until your hand 
rested on my head, and your voice, in hearty 
cheery tones, fell on my delighted ear.</p>
<p>"Jane," you said, "my darling, my wife! 
We are come home at last. I meant to be here 
first, but it is ever you who welcome me. The 
trouble is past. I love you better, love you 
more, than ever I loved Adelaide."</p>
<p>You lifted up my head, and made me look into 
your face. It was at once peaceful and 
exultant, as the face of a man who has gone through 
a great conflict, and come out of it more than 
conqueror. You laid your lips to mine with 
one long kiss, which told me infinitely better 
than words could tell, that never more need 
shadow of doubt or distrust of your love fall 
upon my spirit. Such as I was, you gathered 
me into your inmost heart, barring it against 
any memory or any fancy that might betray 
me. The deep foundations had been laid, 
and any storm that beat against our confidence 
and content would beat against them all in 
vain.</p>
<p>Love, we have learned to speak of the past 
calmly, and Adelaide has been to see us with 
her husband.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="MRS. LIRRIPER RELATES HOW JEMMY TOPPED UP."/>
<chapter>
<p>Well my dear and so the evening readings of 
these jottings of the Major's brought us round 
at last to the evening when we were all packed 
and going away next day, and I do assure you 
that by that time though it was deliciously 
comfortable to look forward to the dear old house in 
Norfolk-street again, I had formed quite a high 
opinion of the French nation and had noticed 
them to be much more homely and domestic in 
their families and far more simple and amiable 
in their lives than I had ever been led to expect, 
and it did strike me between ourselves that in 
one particular they might be imitated to advantage 
by another nation which I will not mention, 
and that is in the courage with which they take 
their little enjoyments on little means and with 
little things and don't let solemn big-wigs stare 
them out of countenance or speechify them dull, 
of which said solemn big-wigs I have ever had 
the one opinion that I wish they were all made 
comfortable separately in coppers with the lids 
on and never let out any more.</p>
<p>"Now young man," I says to Jemmy when 
we brought our chairs into the balcony that last 
evening, "you please to remember who was to 'top up.'"</p>
<p>"All right Gran" says Jemmy. "I am the 
illustrious personage."</p>
<p>But he looked so serious after he had made 
me that light answer, that the Major raised his 
eyebrows at me and I raised mine at the Major.</p>
<p>"Gran and Godfather," says Jemmy, "you 
can hardly think how much my mind has run 
on Mr. Edson's death."</p>
<p>It gave me a little check. "Ah! It was a 
sad scene my love" I says, "and sad 
remembrances come back stronger than merry. But 
this" I says after a little silence, to rouse myself 
and the Major and Jemmy all together, "is not 
topping up. Tell us your story my dear."</p>
<p>"I will" says Jemmy.</p>
<p>"What is the date sir?" says I. "Once 
upon a time when pigs drank wine?"</p>
<p>"No Gran," says Jemmy, still serious; "once 
upon a time when the French drank wine."</p>
<p>Again I glanced at the Major, and the Major 
glanced at me.</p>
<p>"In short, Gran and Godfather," says Jemmy, 
looking up, "the date is this time, and I'm 
going to tell you Mr. Edson's story."</p>
<p>The flutter that it threw me into. The change 
of colour on the part of the Major!</p>
<p>"That is to say, you understand," our bright-
eyed boy says, "I am going to give you my 
version of it. I shall not ask whether it's right or 
not, firstly because you said you knew very little 
about it, Gran, and secondly because what little 
you did know was a secret."</p>
<p>I folded my hands in my lap and I never took 
my eyes off Jemmy as he went running on.</p>
<p>"The unfortunate gentleman" Jemmy 
commences, "who is the subject of our present 
narrative was the son of Somebody, and was 
born Somewhere, and chose a profession Somehow. 
It is not with those parts of his career 
that we have to deal; but with his early attachment 
to a young and beautiful lady."</p>
<p>I thought I should have dropped. I durstn't 
look at the Major; but I knew what his state 
was, without looking at him.</p>
<p>"The father of our ill-starred hero" says 
Jemmy, copying as it seemed to me the style of 
some of his story-books, "was a worldly man 
who entertained ambitious views for his only 
son and who firmly set his face against the 
contemplated alliance with a virtuous but 
penniless orphan. Indeed he went so far as roundly 
to assure our hero that unless he weaned his 
thoughts from the object of his devoted affection, 
he would disinherit him. At the same time, he 
proposed as a suitable match, the daughter of a 
neighbouring gentleman of a good estate, who 
was neither ill favoured nor unamiable, and 
whose eligibility in a pecuniary point of view 
could not be disputed. But young Mr. Edson, 
true to the first and only love that had inflamed 
his breast, rejected all considerations of self-
advancement, and, deprecating his father's anger 
in a respectful letter, ran away with her."</p>
<p>My dear I had begun to take a turn for the 
better, but when it come to running away I 
began to take another turn for the worse.</p>
<p>"The lovers" says Jemmy "fled to London 
and were united at the altar of Saint Clement's 
Danes. And it is at this period of their simple 
but touching story, that we find them inmates of 
the dwelling of a highly respected and beloved 
lady of the name of Gran, residing within a 
hundred miles of Norfolk-street."</p>
<p>I felt that we were almost safe now, I felt that 
the dear boy had no suspicion of the bitter truth, 
and I looked at the Major for the first time and 
drew a long breath. The Major gave me a nod.</p>
<p>"Our hero's father" Jemmy goes on "proving 
implacable and carrying his threat into 
unrelenting execution, the struggles of the young 
couple in London were severe, and would have 
been far more so, but for their good angel's having 
conducted them to the abode of Mrs. Gran: 
who, divining their poverty (in spite of their 
endeavours to conceal it from her), by a thousand 
delicate arts smoothed their rough way, and 
alleviated the sharpness of their first distress."</p>
<p>Here Jemmy took one of my hands in one of 
his, and began a marking the turns of his story 
by making me give a beat from time to time 
upon his other hand.</p>
<p>"After a while, they left the house of Mrs. 
Gran, and pursued their fortunes through a 
variety of successes and failures elsewhere. 
But in all reverses, whether for good or evil, the 
words of Mr. Edson to the fair young partner 
of his life, were: 'Unchanging Love and Truth 
will carry us through all!'"</p>
<p>My hand trembled in the dear boy's, those 
words were so wofully unlike the fact.</p>
<p>"Unchanging Love and Truth" says Jemmy 
over again, as if he had a proud kind of a noble 
pleasure in it, "will carry us through all! 
Those were his words. And so they fought 
their way, poor but gallant and happy, until 
Mrs. Edson gave birth to a child."</p>
<p>"A daughter," I says.</p>
<p>"No" says Jemmy, "a son. And the father 
was so proud of it that he could hardly bear it out 
of his sight. But a dark cloud overspread the 
scene. Mrs. Edson sickened, drooped, and 
died."</p>
<p>"Ah! Sickened, drooped, and died!" I says.</p>
<p>"And so Mr. Edson's only comfort, only 
hope on earth, and only stimulus to action, was 
his darling boy. As the child grew older, he 
grew so like his mother that he was her living 
picture. It used to make him wonder why his 
father cried when he kissed him. But 
unhappily he was like his mother in constitution 
as well as in face, and he died too before he had 
grown out of childhood. Then Mr. Edson, who 
had good abilities, in his forlornness and despair 
threw them all to the winds. He became 
apathetic, reckless, lost. Little by little he sank 
down, down, down, down, until at last he almost 
lived (I think) by gaming. And so sickness 
overtook him in the town of Sens in France, and he 
lay down to die. But now that he laid him down 
when all was done, and looked back upon the 
green Past beyond the time when he had covered 
it with ashes, he thought gratefully of the good 
Mrs. Gran long lost sight of, who had been 
so kind to him and his young wife in the early 
days of their marriage, and he left the little that 
he had as a last Legacy to her. And she, being 
brought to see him, at first no more knew him 
than she would know from seeing the ruin of a 
Greek or Roman Temple, what it used to be 
before it fell; but at length she remembered 
him. And then he told her with tears, of his 
regret for the misspent part of his life, and 
besought her to think as mildly of it as she 
could, because it was the poor fallen Angel 
of his unchanging Love and Constancy after all. 
And because she had her grandson with her, 
and he fancied that his own boy, if he had lived, 
might have grown to be something like him, he 
asked her to let him touch his forehead with 
his cheek and say certain parting words."</p>
<p>Jemmy's voice sank low when it got to that, 
and tears filled my eyes, and filled the Major's.</p>
<p>"You little Conjuror" I says, "how did you 
ever make it all out? Go in and write it every 
word down, for it's a wonder."</p>
<p>Which Jemmy did, and I have repeated it to 
you my dear from his writing.</p>
<p>Then the Major took my hand and kissed it, 
and said "Dearest madam all has prospered 
with us."</p>
<p>"Ah Major" I says drying my eyes, "we 
needn't have been afraid. We might have 
known it. Treachery don't come natural to 
beaming youth; but trust and pity, love and 
constancy they do, thank God!"</p>
</chapter>
</part>
</book>
