<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<subtitle>(All The Year Round Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<title>Tom Tiddler's Ground</title>
<date>1861</date>
</info>
 
<prefix>
<info title="TOM TIDDLER'S GROUND"/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>ALL THE YEAR ROUND.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1861.</centre>
</prefix>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up Soot And Cinders."/>
<p>
"AND why Tom Tiddler's ground?" asked 
the Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Because he scatters halfpence to Tramps 
and such-like," returned the Landlord, "and of 
course they pick 'em up. And this being 
done on his own land (which it is his own land, you 
observe, and were his family's before him), why it 
is but regarding the halfpence as gold and silver, 
and turning the ownership of the property a bit 
round your finger, and there you have the name 
of the children's game complete. And it's 
appropriate too," said the Landlord, with his favourite 
action of stooping a little, to look across the table 
out of window at vacancy, under the window-
blind which was half drawn down. "Leastwise 
it has been so considered by many gentlemen 
which have partook of chops and tea in the 
present humble parlour." 
</p>
<p>
The traveller was partaking of chops and tea 
in the present humble parlour, and the 
Landlord's shot was fired obliquely at him. 
</p>
<p>
"And you call him a Hermit?" said the 
Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"They call him such," returned the Landlord, 
evading personal responsibility; "he is in 
general so considered." 
</p>
<p>
"What is a Hermit?" asked the Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"What is it?" repeated the Landlord, drawing 
his hand across his chin. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, what is it?" 
</p>
<p>
The Landlord stooped again, to get a more 
comprehensive view of vacancy under the window-
blind, and--with an asphyxiated appearance on 
him as one unaccustomed to definition--made no 
answer. 
</p>
<p>
"I'll tell you what I suppose it to be," said the 
Traveller. "An abominably dirty thing." 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Mopes is dirty, it cannot be denied," 
said the Landlord. 
</p>
<p>
"Intolerably conceited." 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Mopes is vain of the life he leads, 
some do say," replied the Landlord, as another 
concession. 
</p>
<p>
"A slothful unsavoury nasty reversal of the 
laws of human nature," said the Traveller; 
"and for the sake of GOD'S working world and 
its wholesomeness, both moral and physical, I 
would put the thing on the treadmill (if I had 
my way) wherever I found it; whether on a 
pillar, or in a hole; whether on Tom Tiddler's 
ground, or the Pope of Rome's ground, or a 
Hindoo fakeer's ground, or any other ground." 
</p>
<p>
"I don't know about putting Mr. Mopes on 
the treadmill," said the Landlord, shaking his 
head very seriously. "There ain't a doubt but 
what he has got landed property." 
</p>
<p>
"How far may it be to this said Tom 
Tiddler's ground?" asked the Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Put it at five mile," returned the Landlord. 
</p>
<p>
"Well! When I have done my breakfast," 
said the Traveller, "I'll go there. I came over 
here this morning, to find it out and see it." 
</p>
<p>
"Many does," observed the Landlord. 
</p>
<p>
The conversation passed, in the Midsummer 
weather of no remote year of grace, down 
among the pleasant dales and trout-streams of 
a green English county. No matter what county. 
Enough that you may hunt there, shoot there, 
fish there, traverse long grass-grown Roman 
roads there, open ancient barrows there, see 
many a square mile of richly cultivated land 
there, and hold Arcadian talk with a bold 
peasantry, their country's pride, who will tell 
you (if you want to know) how pastoral house-
keeping is done on nine shillings a week. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller sat at his breakfast in the little 
sanded parlour of the Peal of Bells village ale-
house, with the dew and dust of an early walk 
upon his shoes--an early walk by road and 
meadow and coppice, that had sprinkled him 
bountifully with little blades of grass, and scraps 
of new hay, and with leaves both young and 
old, and with other such fragrant tokens of the 
freshness and wealth of summer. The window 
through which the landlord had concentrated 
his gaze upon vacancy, was shaded, because the 
morning sun was hot and right on the village 
street. The village street was like most other 
village streets: wide for its height, silent for 
its size, and drowsy in the dullest degree. 
The quietest little dwellings with the largest 
of window-shutters (to shut up Nothing as 
carefully as if it were the Mint, or the Bank of 
England) had called in the Doctor's house so 
suddenly, that his brass door-plate and three 
stories stood among them as conspicuous 
and different as the Doctor himself in his 
broadcloth, among the smock-frocks of his 
patients. The village residences seemed to 
have gone to law with a similar absence of 
consideration, for a score of weak little lath-
and-plaster cabins clung in confusion about the 
Attorney's red-brick house, which, with glaring 
door-steps and a most terrific scraper, seemed 
to serve all manner of ejectments upon them. 
They were as various as labourers--high-
shouldered, wry-necked, one-eyed, goggle-eyed, 
squinting, bow-legged, knock-knee'd, 
rheumatic, crazy. Some of the small tradesmen's 
houses, such as the crockery-shop and the 
harness-maker's, had a Cyclops window in the 
middle of the gable, within an inch or two of 
its apex, suggesting that some forlorn rural 
Prentice must wriggle himself into that apartment 
horizontally, when he retired to rest, after 
the manner of the worm. So bountiful in its 
abundance was the surrounding country,and so lean 
and scant the village, that one might have thought 
the village had sown and planted everything it 
once possessed, to convert the same into crops. 
This would account for the bareness of the little 
shops, the bareness of the few boards and trestles 
designed for market purposes in a corner of 
the street, the bareness of the obsolete Inn and 
Inn Yard, with the ominous inscription "Excise 
Office," not yet faded out from the gateway, as 
indicating the very last thing that poverty could 
get rid of. This would also account for the 
determined abandonment of the village by one 
stray dog, fast lessening in the perspective 
where the white posts and the pond were, and 
would explain his conduct on the hypothesis 
that he was going (through the act of suicide) 
to convert himself into manure, and become a 
part proprietor in turnips or mangold-wurzel. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller having finished his breakfast 
and paid his moderate score, walked out to the 
threshold of the Peal of Bells, and, thence 
directed by the pointing finger of his host, 
betook himself towards the ruined hermitage of 
Mr. Mopes the hermit. 
</p>
<p>
For, Mr. Mopes, by suffering everything 
about him to go to ruin, and by dressing 
himself in a blanket and skewer, and by steeping 
himself in soot and grease and other nastiness, 
had acquired great renown in all that countryside--
far greater renown than he could ever 
have won for himself, if his career had been that 
of any ordinary Christian, or decent Hottentot. 
He had even blanketed and skewered and sooted 
and greased himself, into the London papers. 
And it was curious to find, as Mr. Traveller 
found by stopping for a new direction at this 
farm-house or at that cottage as he went along, 
with how much accuracy the morbid Mopes had 
counted on the weakness of his neighbours to 
embellish him. A mist of home-brewed marvel 
and romance surrounded Mopes, in which (as in 
all fogs) the real proportions of the real object 
were extravagantly heightened. He had 
murdered his beautiful beloved in a fit of jealousy 
and was doing penance; he had made a vow 
under the influence of grief; he had made a 
vow under the influence of a fatal accident; he 
had made a vow under the influence of religion; 
he had made a vow under the influence of 
drink; he had made a vow under the influence 
of disappointment; he had never made any 
vow, but "had got led into it" by the possession 
of a mighty and most awful secret; he was 
enormously rich, he was stupendously 
charitable, he was profoundly learned, he saw 
spectres, he knew and could do all kinds of 
wonders. Some said he went out every night, 
and was met by terrified wayfarers stalking along 
dark roads, others said he never went out, some 
knew his penance to be nearly expired, others 
had positive information that his seclusion was 
not a penance at all, and would never expire but 
with himself. Even, as to the easy facts of how 
old he was, or how long he had held verminous 
occupation of his blanket and skewer, no 
consistent information was to be got, from those 
who must know if they would. He was 
represented as being all the ages between five-and-
twenty and sixty, and as having been a hermit 
seven years, twelve, twenty, thirty--though 
twenty, on the whole, appeared the favourite 
term. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, well!" said Mr. Traveller. "At any 
rate, let us see what a real live Hermit looks 
like." 
</p>
<p>
So, Mr. Traveller went on, and on, and on, 
until he came to Tom Tiddler's Ground. 
</p>
<p>
It was a nook in a rustic by-road, which the 
genius of Mopes had laid waste as completely, as 
if he had been born an Emperor and a Conqueror. 
Its centre object was a dwelling-house, 
sufficiently substantial, all the window-glass of which 
had been long ago abolished by the surprising 
genius of Mopes, and all the windows of which 
were barred across with rough-split logs of 
trees nailed over them on the outside. A rick-
yard, hip-high in vegetable rankness and ruin, 
contained outbuildings, from which the thatch 
had lightly fluttered away, on all the winds of 
all the seasons of the year, and from which the 
planks and beams had heavily dropped and rotted. 
The frosts and damps of winter, and the heats 
of summer, had warped what wreck remained, 
so that not a post or a board retained the position 
it was meant to hold, but everything was 
twisted from its purpose, like its owner, and 
degraded and debased. In this homestead of the 
sluggard, behind the ruined hedge, and sinking 
away among the ruined grass and the nettles, 
were the last perishing fragments of certain ricks: 
which had gradually mildewed and collapsed, 
until they looked like mounds of rotten honeycomb, 
or dirty sponge. Tom Tiddler's ground 
could even show its ruined water; for, there was 
a slimy pond into which a tree or two had 
fallen one--soppy trunk and branches lay across 
it then--which in its accumulation of stagnant 
weed, and in its black decomposition, and in all 
its foulness and filth, was almost comforting, 
regarded as the only water that could have 
reflected the shameful place without seeming 
polluted by that low office. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller looked all around him on Tom 
Tiddler's ground, and his glance at last 
encountered a dusty Tinker lying among the weeds 
and rank grass, in the shade of the dwelling-
house. A rough walking-staff lay on the ground 
by his side, and his head rested on a small 
wallet. He met Mr. Traveller's eye without 
lifting up his head, merely depressing his chin a 
little (for he was lying on his back) to get a 
better view of him. 
</p>
<p>
"Good day!" said Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Same to you, if you like it," returned the 
Tinker. 
</p>
<p>
"Don't you like it? It's a very fine day." 
</p>
<p>
"I ain't partickler in weather," returned the 
Tinker, with a yawn. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller had walked up to where he 
lay, and was looking down at him. "This is a 
curious place," said Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Ay, I suppose so!" returned the Tinker. 
"Tom Tiddler's ground, they call this." 
</p>
<p>
"Are you well acquainted with it?" 
</p>
<p>
"Never saw it afore to-day," said the Tinker, 
with another yawn, "and don't care if I never 
see it again. There was a man here just now, 
told me what it was called. If you want to see 
Tom himself, you must go in at that gate." He 
faintly indicated with his chin, a little mean 
ruin of a wooden gate at the side of the house. 
</p>
<p>
"Have you seen Tom?" 
</p>
<p>
"No, and I ain't partickler to see him. I 
can see a dirty man anywhere." 
</p>
<p>
"He does not live in the house, then?" said 
Mr. Traveller, casting his eyes upon the house 
anew. 
</p>
<p>
"The man said," returned the Tinker, rather 
irritably,--" him as was here just now,--
'this what you're a lying on, mate, is Tom 
Tiddler's ground. And if you want to see Tom,' 
he says, 'you must go in at that gate.' The 
man come out at that gate himself, and he 
ought to know." 
</p>
<p>
"Certainly," said Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Though, perhaps," exclaimed the Tinker, so 
struck by the brightness of his own idea, 
that it had the electric effect upon him of 
causing him to lift up his head an inch or so, 
"perhaps he was a liar! He told some rum'uns--
him as was here just now, did--about this 
place of Tom's. He says--him as was here 
just now--'When Tom shut up the house, 
mate, to go to rack, the beds was left, all made, 
like as if somebody was a going to sleep in every 
bed. And if you was to walk through the 
bedrooms now, you'd see the ragged mouldy 
bedclothes a heaving and a heaving like seas. 
And a heaving and a heaving with what?' he 
says. 'Why, with the rats under 'em.'" 
</p>
<p>
"I wish I had seen that man," Mr. Traveller 
remarked. 
</p>
<p>
"You'd have been welcome to see him 
instead of me seeing him," growled the Tinker; 
"for he was a long-winded one." 
</p>
<p>
Not without a sense of injury in the remembrance, 
the Tinker gloomily closed his eyes. Mr. 
Traveller, deeming the Tinker a short-winded one, 
from whom no further breath of information was 
to be derived, betook himself to the gate. 
</p>
<p>
Swung upon its rusty hinges, it admitted him 
into a yard in which there was nothing to be 
seen but an outhouse attached to the ruined 
building, with a barred window in it. As there 
were traces of many recent footsteps under this 
window, and as it was a low window, and 
unglazed, Mr. Traveller made bold to peep within 
the bars. And there to be sure he had a 
real live Hermit before him, and could judge how 
the real dead Hermits used to look. 
</p>
<p>
He was lying on a bank of soot and cinders, 
on the floor, in front of a rusty fireplace. There 
was nothing else in the dark little kitchen, or 
scullery, or whatever his den had been originally 
used as, but a table with a litter of old bottles 
on it. A rat made a clatter among these bottles, 
jumped down, and ran over the real live Hermit 
on his way to his hole, or the man in his hole 
would not have been so easily discernible. 
Tickled in the face by the rat's tail, the owner 
of Tom Tiddler's ground opened his eyes, saw Mr. 
Traveller, started up, and sprang to the window. 
</p>
<p>
"Humph!" thought Mr. Traveller, retiring 
a pace or two from the bars. "A compound of 
Newgate, Bedlam, a Debtors' Prison in the 
worst time, a chimney-sweep, a mudlark, and 
the Noble Savage! A nice old family, the 
Hermit family. Hah!" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller thought this, as he silently 
confronted the sooty object in the blanket and 
skewer (in sober truth it wore nothing else), 
with the matted hair and the staring eyes. 
Further, Mr. Traveller thought, as the eyes 
surveyed him with a very obvious curiosity in 
ascertaining the effect they produced, "Vanity, 
vanity, vanity! Verily, all is vanity!" 
</p>
<p>
"What is your name, sir, and where do you 
come from?" asked Mr. Mopes the Hermit--with 
an air of authority, but in the ordinary human 
speech of one who has been to school. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller answered the inquiries. 
</p>
<p>
"Did you come here, sir, to see me?" 
</p>
<p>
"I did. I heard of you, and I came to see 
you.--I know you like to be seen." Mr. 
Traveller coolly threw the last words in, as a matter 
of course, to forestal an affectation of resentment 
or objection that he saw rising beneath the 
grease and grime of the face. They had their 
effect. 
</p>
<p>
"So," said the Hermit, after a momentary 
silence, unclasping the bars by which he had 
previously held, and seating himself behind them 
on the ledge of the window, with his bare legs 
and feet crouched up, "you know I like to be 
seen?" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller looked about him for something 
to sit on, and, observing a billet of wood in a 
corner, brought it near the window. Deliberately 
seating himself upon it, he answered: 
"Just so." 
</p>
<p>
Each looked at the other, and each appeared 
to take some pains to get the measure of the 
other. 
</p>
<p>
"Then you have come to ask me why I lead 
this life," said the Hermit, frowning in a stormy 
manner. "I never tell that to any human being. 
I will not be asked that." 
</p>
<p>
"Certainly you will not be asked that by 
me," said Mr. Traveller, "for I have not the 
slightest desire to know." 
</p>
<p>
"You are an uncouth man," said Mr. Mopes 
the Hermit. 
</p>
<p>
"You are another," said Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
The Hermit, who was plainly in the habit of 
overawing his visitors with the novelty of his 
filth and his blanket and skewer, glared at 
his present visitor in some discomfiture and 
surprise: as if he had taken aim at him with a sure 
gun, and his piece had missed fire. 
</p>
<p>
"Why do you come here at all?" he asked, 
after a pause. 
</p>
<p>
"Upon my life," said Mr. Traveller, "I was 
made to ask myself that very question only a few 
minutes ago--by a Tinker too." 
</p>
<p>
As he glanced towards the gate in saying it, 
the hermit glanced in that direction likewise. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes. He is lying on his back in the 
sunlight outside," said Mr. Traveller, as if he had 
been asked concerning the man, "and he won't 
come in; for he says--and really very reasonably--
'What should I come in for? I can see 
a dirty man anywhere.'" 
</p>
<p>
"You are an insolent person. Go away from 
my premises. Go!" said the Hermit, in an 
imperious and angry tone. 
</p>
<p>
"Come, come!" returned Mr. Traveller, quite 
undisturbed. "This is a little  too much. You 
are not going to call yourself clean? Look at 
your legs. And as to these being your 
premises:--they are in far too disgraceful a condition 
to claim any privilege of ownership, or 
anything else." 
</p>
<p>
The Hermit bounced down from his window-
ledge, and cast himself on his bed of soot and 
cinders. 
</p>
<p>
"I am not going," said Mr. Traveller, glancing 
in after him: "you won't get rid of me in that 
way. You had better come and talk." 
</p>
<p>
"I won't talk," said the Hermit, flouncing 
round to get his back towards the window. 
</p>
<p>
"Then I will," said Mr. Traveller. "Why 
should you take it ill that I have no curiosity to 
know why you live this highly absurd and 
highly indecent life? When I contemplate a 
man in a state of disease, surely there is no moral 
obligation on me to be anxious to know how 
he took it." 
</p>
<p>
After a short silence, the Hermit bounced up 
again, and came back to the barred window. 
</p>
<p>
"What? You are not gone?" he said, affecting 
to have supposed that he was. 
</p>
<p>
"Nor going," Mr. Traveller replied: "I 
design to pass this summer day here." 
</p>
<p>
"How dare you come, sir, upon my 
premises--" the Hermit was returning, when 
his visitor interrupted him. 
</p>
<p>
"Really, you know, you must not talk about 
your premises. I cannot allow such a place 
as this to be dignified with the name of 
premises." 
</p>
<p>
"How dare you," said the Hermit, shaking 
his bars, "come in at my gate, to taunt me 
with being in a diseased state?" 
</p>
<p>
"Why, Lord bless my soul," returned the 
other, very composedly, "you have not the face 
to say that you are in a wholesome state? Do 
allow me again to call your attention to your legs. 
Scrape yourself anywhere--with anything--
and then tell me you are in a wholesome state. 
The fact is, Mr. Mopes, that you are not only 
a Nuisance--" 
</p>
<p>
"A Nuisance?" repeated the Hermit, fiercely. 
</p>
<p>
"What is a place in this obscene state of 
dilapidation but a Nuisance? What is a man in 
your obscene state of dilapidation but a 
Nuisance? Then, as you very well know, you 
cannot do without an audience, and your audience 
is a Nuisance. You attract all the disreputable 
vagabonds and prowlers within ten miles round, 
by exhibiting yourself to them in that 
objectionable blanket, and by throwing copper 
money among them, and giving them drink out 
of those very dirty jars and bottles that I see in 
there (their stomachs need be strong!); and in 
short," said Mr. Traveller, summing up in a 
quietly and comfortably settled manner, "you 
are a Nuisance, and this kennel is a Nuisance, 
and the audience that you cannot possibly 
dispense with is a Nuisance, and the Nuisance is 
not merely a local Nuisance, because it is a 
general Nuisance to know that there can be  
such a Nuisance left in civilisation so very long 
after its time." 
</p>
<p>
"Will you go away? I have a gun in here," 
said the Hermit. 
</p>
<p>
"Pooh!" 
</p>
<p>
"I have!" 
</p>
<p>
"Now, I put it to you. Did I say you 
had not? And as to going away, didn't I say I 
am not going away? You have made me forget 
where I was. I now remember that I was 
remarking on your conduct being a Nuisance. 
Moreover, it is in the last and lowest degree 
inconsequent foolishness and weakness." 
</p>
<p>
"Weakness?" echoed the Hermit. 
</p>
<p>
"Weakness," said Mr. Traveller, with his 
former comfortably settled final air. 
</p>
<p>
"I weak, you fool?" cried the Hermit, "I, 
who have held to my purpose, and my diet, and 
my only bed there, all these years?" 
</p>
<p>
"The more the years, the weaker you," 
returned Mr. Traveller. "Though the years are 
not so many as folks say, and as you willingly 
take credit for. The crust upon your face is 
thick and dark, Mr. Mopes, but I can see 
enough of you through it, to see that you are 
still a young man." 
</p>
<p>
"Inconsequent foolishness is lunacy, I 
suppose?" said the Hermit. 
</p>
<p>
"I suppose it is very like it," answered Mr. 
Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Do I converse like a lunatic?" 
</p>
<p>
"One of us two must have a strong 
presumption against him of being one, whether or 
no. Either the clean and decorously clad man, 
or the dirty and indecorously clad man. I don't 
say which." 
</p>
<p>
"Why, you self-sufficient bear," said the 
Hermit, "not a day passes but I am justified 
in my purpose by the conversations I hold here; 
not a day passes but I am shown, by everything 
I hear and see here, how right and strong I am 
in holding my purpose." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller, lounging easily on his billet of 
wood, took out a pocket pipe and began to fill 
it. "Now, that a man," he said, appealing to 
the summer sky as he did so, "that a man--
even behind bars, in a blanket and skewer--
should tell me that he can see, from day to day, 
any orders or conditions of men, women, or 
children, who can by any possibility teach him 
that it is anything but the miserablest drivelling 
for a human creature to quarrel with his 
social nature--not to go so far as to say, to 
renounce his common human decency, for 
that is an extreme case; or who can teach 
him that he can in any wise separate 
himself from his kind and the habits of his kind, 
without becoming a deteriorated spectacle 
calculated to give the Devil (and perhaps the 
monkeys) pleasure; is something wonderful! 
I repeat," said Mr. Traveller, beginning to 
smoke, "the unreasoning hardihood of it, is 
something wonderful--even in a man with the 
dirt upon him an inch or two thick--behind 
bars in a blanket and skewer!" 
</p>
<p>
The Hermit looked at him irresolutely, and 
retired to his soot and cinders and lay down, and 
got up again and came to the bars, and again 
looked at him irresolutely, and finally said with 
sharpness: 
</p>
<p>
"I don't like tobacco." 
</p>
<p>
"I don't like dirt," rejoined Mr. Traveller; 
"tobacco is an excellent disinfectant. We shall 
both be the better for my pipe. It is my 
intention to sit here through this summer day, 
until that blessed summer sun sinks low in the 
west, and to show you what a poor creature you 
are, through the lips of every chance wayfarer 
who may come in at your gate." 
</p>
<p>
"What do you mean?" inquired the Hermit, 
with a furious air. 
</p>
<p>
"I mean that yonder is your gate, and there 
are you, and here am I; I mean that I know it 
to be a moral impossibility that any person can 
stray in at that gate from any point of the 
compass, with any sort of experience, gained at first 
hand, or derived from another, that can confute 
me and justify you." 
</p>
<p>
"You are an arrogant and boastful hero," 
said the Hermit. "You think yourself 
profoundly wise." 
</p>
<p>
"Bah!" returned Mr. Traveller, quietly 
smoking. "There is little wisdom in knowing 
that every man must be up and doing, and that 
all mankind are made dependent on one 
another." 
</p>
<p>
"You have companions outside," said the 
Hermit. "I am not to be imposed upon by your 
assumed confidence in the people who may 
enter." 
</p>
<p>
"A depraved distrust," returned the visitor, 
compassionately raising his eyebrows, "of 
course belongs to your state. I can't help 
that." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you mean to tell me you have no 
confederates?" 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
"I mean to tell you nothing but what I have 
told you. What I have told you, is, that it is a 
moral impossibility that any son or daughter of 
Adam can stand on this ground that I put my 
foot on, or on any ground that mortal treads, 
and gainsay the healthy tenure on which we 
hold our existence." 
</p>
<p>
"Which is," sneered the Hermit, "according 
to you--" 
</p>
<p>
"Which is," returned the other, "according 
to Eternal Providence, that we must arise and 
wash our faces and do our gregarious work and 
act and re-act on one another, leaving only the 
idiot and the palsied to sit blinking in the corner. 
Come!" apostrophising the gate; "Open 
Sesame! Show his eyes and grieve his heart! 
I don't care who comes, for I know what must 
come of it!" 
</p>
<p>
With that, he faced round a little on his 
billet of wood towards the gate; and Mr. 
Mopes the Hermit, after two or three ridiculous 
bounces of indecision at his bed and back again, 
submitted to what he could not help himself 
against, and coiled himself on his window-ledge, 
holding to his bars and looking out rather 
anxiously. 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up Evening Shadows."/>
<p>
THE first person to appear at the gate, was a 
gentleman who looked in accidentally, and who 
carried a sketch-book under his arm. From the 
amazement and alarm expressed in his look and 
manner, it was plain that the Hermit's fame had 
not reached him. As soon as he could speak, 
he mentioned apologetically that he had been 
struck, as a stranger in that part of the country, 
by the picturesquely-ruinous appearance of the 
yard and out-houses, and that he had looked in 
at the gate, with the idea of finding nothing 
more remarkable than the materials for a sketch 
of still-life. 
</p>
<p>
After revealing the mystery of the Hermit, 
to this bewildered stranger, Mr. Traveller 
explained that any narrative-contributions towards 
the enlivening of Mr. Mopes and the morning, 
drawn from the personal experience of visitors 
at the gate, would be highly appreciated in that 
mouldy locality. At first, the visitor thus 
addressed hesitated; not so much, as it afterwards 
appeared, from want of means to answer the call 
made upon him, as from want of resources in 
his own memory to use on the spur of the 
moment. Pondering on Mr. Traveller's request, he 
entered rather absently into conversation with 
the Hermit. 
</p>
<p>
"I never knew any good to come yet," said 
this gentleman, "of a man shutting himself up 
in the way you're doing. I know the temptation 
to it myself, have experienced it myself, 
and yielded to it myself; but I never knew any 
good--stop, though," he added, correcting 
himself as a scrupulous man does, who will not 
accept the help of the smallest false statement 
to aid his dearest theory--"I do remember one 
good thing which came, in some degree, of a 
man's leading a solitary life." 
</p>
<p>
The Hermit hugged his bars in triumph. 
Mr. Traveller, nothing discouraged, requested 
the stranger to mention the circumstance. 
</p>
<p>
"You shall hear it," was the answer. "But, 
before I begin, I must tell you that the period 
of my tale dates some years back into the past, 
that at the time of which I shall speak I had 
newly experienced a considerable reverse of 
fortune, and that, fancying my friends would make 
me feel the loss if I remained among them, 
I had determined to shut myself up away from them, 
and lead an entirely solitary life till I could 
in some degree retrieve my losses." 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
IT is a tale, this that I am about to tell, 
of good deeds revealed, of good instincts 
roused, of a good work done, and a good result 
attained, and all through Evening Shadows. 
</p>
<p>
I have often thought what tell-tell things 
shadows are. I mean the shadows that one who 
stands outside sees in the windows of a lighted-
up room or building; the shadows thrown on a 
blind by figures interposing between it and the 
lamp-light. I have noticed these in churches 
during divine service, when I, wandering about 
outside, have looked up at the windows and 
seen the shades of a pair of lovers reading out 
of the same hymn-book; of children evidently 
chattering and grinning together; and sometimes 
a shadow which bobbing forward from time to 
time in a jerking fashion, then catching itself, 
still with a jerk, then remaining preternaturally 
erect and still, and then beginning to bob again, 
has suggested to me that the fourth head of a 
sermon in eight compartments was being 
developed, and that the shadow before me was 
that of one who was taking refuge from oratory 
in sleep. 
</p>
<p>
Among the number of the shadows which 
my memory retains, there are some that lie upon 
it with no dark and shuddering chill; some that 
were cast by objects in themselves so pure and 
noble that the shade itself seemed only a 
subdued brightness, and the light that cast it--a 
glory. 
</p>
<p>
My story begins at the time, some years ago, 
when, as a single man, I was living in a narrow 
and rather crowded street in one of the old parts 
of London--one of those streets where very 
decent houses are mixed with much poorer ones--
and in one of the best and cleanest of which 
I occupied two rooms; a bedroom and a 
sitting-room. Having at that time, as I have 
now, a great dread of noise while at work, 
I made use of the back room as my studio, 
sleeping in the front of the house, which was 
quiet at night but not in the daytime, by reason 
of the day traffic. My painting-room, then, was 
on the second floor, and at the back of the house, 
and as there was a street running at an acute 
angle to that in which I lived, and joining it 
only a few yards higher up, it will easily be 
understood that the backs of the houses in this 
slanting thoroughfare, which was called 
appropriately enough, Cross-street, were in tolerably 
close proximity to my painting-room window. 
I have been thus exact in describing the 
topography of my place of abode, because then 
you will be better able to understand how it 
happened that my attention was directed to the 
circumstances which I am about to detail. 
</p>
<p>
You will be able to understand how it was 
that, sitting, especially during the short days, 
as the dusk was beginning to fall, looking 
meditatively out of window and thinking of 
my work, my attention would often be drawn, 
almost without my knowledge, to some of the 
windows in the slanting street which I have 
described, and how I found myself not 
unfrequently speculating about some of the inhabitants 
of the rooms which were separated from 
that in which I was sitting, by so small a space. 
</p>
<p>
There was one window more than all the rest 
which, for some reason or other, used 
especially to occupy my thoughts. It was a window 
exactly level with my own, and exactly opposite 
to it. During the daytime, though the 
blind was always drawn up as high as it could 
be, I could see but little of the room, but 
what I could make out only showed me that it 
was a very poor place indeed. Long habits 
of a speculative use of my eyes, if I may so 
express myself, have perhaps given me a tendency 
to attach much importance to the external 
aspects of things as indicative of what goes on 
within. Be that as it may, I possess that 
tendency, and possess it very strongly on the 
subject of windows. I think that the windows of 
a house give one a great idea of the dispositions, 
the habits, and the tempers of the occupants. 
Who has not felt, in passing by a house whose 
well-cleaned windows are filled with flowers, 
where the solid white and green of the Arum, 
and the delicate shades of colour in the rows of 
blossoming hyacinths, stand out in pleasant freshness 
against the dark background formed by the 
interior of the room--who has not felt that the 
inhabitant of a house whose windows are thus 
decorated, are in a calmer and happier condition 
than their next-door neighbours, where the yellow 
blind hangs crookedly across the dirty window, 
and the wire screen beneath has got a bulging 
ragged hole in it? 
</p>
<p>
Holding, then, the theory which I have 
ventured thus to put forward, it will be readily 
believed that I augured the better of the occupants 
of the room opposite, from the fact that I could 
see through the lower panes of the window the 
leaves and branches of a great big fuchsia spread 
out fan-wise on a wooden frame. Other little 
contrivances and adornments there were about 
this poor casement, which, though of the cheapest 
and most twopenny order of decorative art, 
showed yet some love of the gentler side of 
things, and a wish to put a good face on 
poverty. 
</p>
<p>
But it is, as I have already said, towards dusk 
and in the evening that my attention has been 
oftenest fixed on the window which I have been 
describing. It is then that, the room being 
lighted up, the shadows of things and persons 
within it are thrown upon the blind with a 
clearness and distinctness which those who have 
never observed such matters would hardly credit. 
The shadows tell me, then, that the room is 
tenanted by a husband and wife both young, I 
am certain. The man, as I gather from his 
position, and what I take to be the shadow of a 
tissue-paper screen behind which he stoops over 
his labour, is a poor drudging engraver for 
whom the days are not long enough, sitting 
cramped up at his patient toil through many 
hours of the night. As I watch him, he will 
rise and stretch back his head to relieve the 
muscles of his neck, and then I see that the 
shadow thrown on the blind is that of a young 
figure, spare but well made. The light shows 
me also that he wears a beard; it is a very 
strong light indeed, and this makes me more 
sure than ever that he is an engraver. The 
shadow of his wife is there beside him--almost 
always. How she watches over and tends him, 
how she hangs over his chair, or kneels 
beside him! I had never, at the time I speak 
of, seen her, but I could not help fancying 
that she was pretty and good enough to light 
up a darker room than that in which she 
lives, and to make her husband's life of toil--
if he can keep it up--not only bearable but 
delightful. 
</p>
<p>
IF he can keep it up--but can he? His 
shadow is all that I have seen of him, but it 
looks like the shadow of one in delicate health. 
I never miss him from his place at night, and I 
can see the edge of his blind by which he works, 
at his window all day. "If he sits drudging 
there," thought I, "he will surely, as is the case 
in all excess, defeat his own object and end in 
being disabled altogether." 
</p>
<p>
It was not long before I began to fear that 
what I had apprehended had taken place. There 
came a day when the blind was not drawn up to 
let in the light on the engraver's work, but 
remained drawn down the whole day. It would 
be difficult to express how anxiously I longed 
for the evening, and the shadows which should 
tell me more. 
</p>
<p>
That evening the light was burning in the 
room as usual, but the straight-edge of the 
engraver's blind was not seen cutting against it. 
There was the shadow of but one person, it was 
that of a woman, and as the figure which cast it 
moved so quietly about, I could make out that 
she was pouring out drugs and mixing the 
different compounds wanted in a sick-room by the 
light of the lamp. Sometimes she would pause 
in these occupations and look towards one end 
of the room, where I concluded the bed was 
placed; and sometimes I could even imagine, 
but this must have been pure fancy, that, looking 
still in the same direction, her lips would 
move at times, and that she was speaking. I 
could even see her tasting the food she was 
mixing, with her head a little on one side; altering 
and tasting it often before she carried it across 
the room to where, I felt sure, the sick man lay. 
So much will shadows tell. 
</p>
<p>
From my front window I can see a long way 
up and down the street, even to that corner 
where the early breakfast depôt is found every 
morning--a poor stall enough, and driving a 
poor business, I should have thought; a business, 
however, in which I am so deeply 
interested that my first morning act is to go to the 
window and see if the poor old proprietor has 
got a customer--nay, once I put on a pilot-coat 
and a wideawake hat to appear in character, and 
purchased a cup of his coffee, which was a sound 
coffee enough, though a little gritty, and 
perhaps a thought weak. Enough of that. I can 
see to the coffee-stall one way, and nearly as far 
the other, and at the back I command a bit of a 
court, two mewses and a half, and, by great 
dislocation of neck, a little scrap of Brewer-street, 
Golden-square. Now in all these regions which 
are continually under my eye, I have noticed 
one constantly pervading presence, one figure 
which comes upon the scene without fail every 
day in the year and at all conceivable hours. It 
is the figure of a tallish gentleman of about five-
and-thirty, who stoops a little, has a very round 
back, wears spectacles, is always dressed in a 
buttoned black frock-coat, is always in a hurry, 
always expected anxiously at the houses he 
visits, and always followed to the door, on coming 
out again, by some who question him eagerly as 
he leaves them, and who seem to seek for 
comfort in his most inscrutable face. Of course I 
have not watched this gentleman's proceedings 
long, without coming to the conclusion that it is 
Mr. Cordial, the parish doctor, whose surgery in 
Great Pulteney-street I am so often in the habit 
of passing. 
</p>
<p>
If there had been any previous doubt on my 
mind as to the state of things in the house 
opposite, it would at once have been put to flight 
when, on the day succeeding that evening on 
which I had watched the engraver's wife in her 
capacity of nurse, I caught a dark glimpse of 
this gentleman's head (rather a bald head for so 
young a man) at the window of the room 
opposite, which he had come to, to prepare some 
mixture or other. 
</p>
<p>
"Now here," I thought to myself, "is a 
pretty business. This is just what I feared. 
Here is this poor fellow laid up, unable to work, 
and probably not only ill in body, but harassed 
in mind by the consciousness that as long as he 
is ill, there can be no money coming in to 
supply the daily expenses which, however poorly 
they live, he and his wife must of necessity 
incur." 
</p>
<p>
I thought over this matter, and turned it all 
sorts of ways, as people who are unlucky 
enough, or unwise enough, to live alone do 
turn and twist things, and was so haunted by 
the thought of what was going on in the room 
opposite, that in the course of the afternoon I 
was obliged to go out and take a long walk, in 
order to fill up the time that must necessarily 
intervene before the lamp would be lit, and the 
shadows thrown upon the blind. When I got 
back from that walk I was in such hot haste for 
such silent news as I might reasonably hope to 
gain, that I did not even stay to light my candle, 
but felt my way as well as I could across the 
room, and stationed myself at the window. 
</p>
<p>
At first I thought that there were no shadows 
at all on the white glaring blind, except those 
of the poor bits of curtain and of the spread-
out fuchsia before mentioned, but by-and-by, 
noticing a small and continually moving shadow 
mixed up with that of the curtain, and observing 
that it rose and fell regularly and quickly, I 
presently connected it with another mass of 
shade a little above it, and arrived at the conclusion 
that this last was thrown by a woman's head, 
and by the moving shadow by her hand, as it rose 
and fell in the action of working with the needle. 
It was not long before I found out that my 
hypothesis was well grounded; for a little while 
the shadow of the hand was still and that 
of the head was raised, as if the person whose 
silhouette lay thus upon the blind was in 
the act of listening--and then it rose, and 
I saw the well-known figure of the engraver's 
wife pass the light, and knew that she had moved 
towards that quarter of the room in which I had 
made up my mind that the bed with the sick 
man in it was placed. 
</p>
<p>
During the greater part of that evening, as I 
watched, and my occupations were frequently 
interrupted that I might do so, I made out no 
shadow but that which I have just mentioned. 
But, at about nine o'clock, I saw another 
shadow pass before the blind, and as it was that 
of a man, I had for a moment the hope that it 
was cast by the invalid. It was only for a 
moment, another glance showed me that this person 
wore no beard, and that there was greater bulk 
of figure than would have been cast by the poor 
engraver. I soon concluded that it was the 
doctor; and if I had any doubt on this subject it 
was removed when I presently observed the 
workman-like angle of elbow made by the 
shadow as it stood before the light, pouring 
something into what I suppose, from its size, 
must have been a teacup. 
</p>
<p>
Twice a day, then. He was ill enough for 
the doctor to come to him twice a day. 
</p>
<p>
My determination was taken as I made that 
reflection. I had got wrought up to a great 
state of interest and suspense about this case 
which I could hardly explain to myself. I felt a 
strange longing to know more of it, and I came 
to the resolution--it was like what might have 
been expected of a man half-cracked with living 
alone--that I would go out then and there, 
waylay the doctor as he came away from his 
patient, and ask him all about it. 
</p>
<p>
I had lost some time in reflection, and when 
I looked hastily across before leaving my room 
I did not see any shadows on the blind, yet it 
was reasonable to suppose that I might still 
catch the doctor in the street; so out I rushed. 
Sure enough there was the doctor just coming 
out of No. 4, Cross-street. How lucky I was 
to be in time! 
</p>
<p>
I found the parish medical authority not very 
communicative or prone to take a very romantic 
view of sickness and suffering. He was a good 
sort of man enough, no doubt, but dry and 
matter-of-fact. He had seen so much of sickness 
and misery that he was used to it. He 
answered all my questions, however, politely, 
though seeming a good deal surprised at them. 
</p>
<p>
"He had just been visiting a sick man in that 
house, had he not?" I asked. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes," he replied, "he had. Bad case of low 
fever." 
</p>
<p>
"Second floor--a married couple?" was my 
next inquiry. 
</p>
<p>
Again an answer in the affirmative. 
</p>
<p>
"Was it a case of great distress?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, of very great distress." 
</p>
<p>
"They have nothing to live upon but what the 
husband makes by his labour?" I asked. 
</p>
<p>
"Nothing," was the answer. 
</p>
<p>
"And he is laid up and unable to work." 
</p>
<p>
"That is the state of the case," replied the 
doctor. 
</p>
<p>
"Ah! I thought so," said I. "Would you 
be kind enough, Doctor Cordial," I continued, 
"to take charge of this small sum" (it was a 
very small one) "for the benefit of these poor 
people--on no account mentioning how you 
came by it." 
</p>
<p>
The doctor promised that he would, and I was 
just going to leave him, when I thought I would 
ask the poor fellow's name. 
</p>
<p>
"His name is Adams," said the doctor, and so 
we parted. 
</p>
<p>
I now felt quite a sense of proprietorship in 
looking at my poor shadows opposite, and 
watched them more eagerly than ever. There 
was one action of the shadow, now unfortunately 
the only action to watch, which used 
to puzzle me not a little. The sick man's 
wife used at times to stand before the light, 
and, as it appeared to me, used to hold some 
article of clothing, or other piece of drapery, 
and examine it closely; sometimes I fancied 
that I could make the object out to be a 
shirt, or a coat, at another time a pair of 
trousers. After this she would disappear, and I 
always noticed that the lamp would then be 
turned down till its light was very low, and 
would remain so for a considerable period. I 
could not understand this at the time, though 
I did afterwards. She was testing the condition 
of different, articles of clothing before taking 
them to the pawnbroker's. 
</p>
<p>
And now I began to discover one of the bad 
results of my solitary life. Though I had given 
Doctor Cordial a small sum to go towards helping 
these poor people, it was quite impossible, 
in my straitened circumstances, that I could 
spare more. If I had resolutely kept my 
friends about me, there would have been 
somebody or other to whom I could apply in behalf 
of my poor shadows, while now it was impossible 
to do so. Even when the idea entered my mind 
of trying to revive some former friendships with 
this view, the fear that any one so applied to 
might imagine I wanted the help for myself, at 
once deterred me. 
</p>
<p>
Whilst I was engaged in turning all these 
things over in my mind, there came across it the 
memory of one individual to whom I really felt 
as if I should not mind applying in this difficulty. 
</p>
<p>
This was a certain Mr. Pycroft, a copper-
plate printer, with whom I had formerly had 
dealings. He was an old man, and it so happened 
that at one time in my life I had been in a 
position to do him a service, and had done it. 
There was something about his age, his position, 
and our former relations, which made me 
feel less shy of approaching him than I should 
have felt with any one else. He was a fat, 
jolly-looking old boy, and was, as far as I had 
had opportunities of judging, as good natured as 
he looked. 
</p>
<p>
There was, however, one circumstance 
connected with his history which seemed to show 
him in a less amiable light, and the remembrance 
of which made me for a time hesitate about 
applying to him. I remembered to have heard 
that some short time ago he had acted with 
great severity towards his eldest son, who, having 
contracted a marriage against his father's wishes, 
had been deprived of his share in the business, 
which he had formerly enjoyed, and left to make 
a living as well as he could by his own exertions. 
The fact is, that the old man had had a darling 
project of marrying his eldest son to a young 
girl whose father was a business connexion of 
his own. The old copper-plate printer was not 
only thwarted in this, but was further outraged 
by his son's choice having fallen in a direction 
particularly distasteful to him for private reasons. 
I suspected also from what I had heard, that the 
conduct of the eldest son, which had been 
represented to his father as being violent and 
rebellious in no ordinary degree, had been made 
the worst of by the younger brother, who not 
only stepped into the lion's share of the business 
on his brother's removal, but himself contracted 
the marriage which his brother had declined. I 
could not help thinking when I heard the 
circumstances of the case that this younger son 
had had a great deal to do in poisoning the old 
man's mind with regard to his elder brother's 
conduct. 
</p>
<p>
At all events, old Mr. Pycroft was the only 
person I could think of just now as likely to 
help my unfortunate shadows, and to him I 
determined to apply, but in a roundabout way. It 
occurred to me that if I could enlist his 
sympathy in the fate of these poor people, just as 
my own had been awakened, by means of the 
shadows, it would be a far better plan than any 
other. 
</p>
<p>
It so happened that I had often promised my 
old acquaintance to show him a collection which 
I had of Rembrandt etchings, and it occurred to 
me that now was the time when these might 
come into play with great effect. So, making an 
excuse in relation to the matter of business 
which had formerly brought us together, I 
called on my old acquaintance, and, in the course 
of conversation, invited him, naming an evening, 
to come to my lodgings, and examine these 
curiosities, intimating that we would moisten 
that pleasing labour with a glass of brandy-and-
water. Punctual to the time named Mr. Pycroft 
arrived, and we got through the first hour very 
comfortably, though I could not help feeling 
rather anxious about the success of my scheme. 
</p>
<p>
After examining the etchings, Mr. Pycroft, 
over the second glass, began to rally me about 
living in such a labyrinth of streets, asking me 
if I did not find it dreadfully confined at the 
back. 
</p>
<p>
"By-the-by," I said--and here I must own 
that I was guilty of some small amount of 
deception, for I spoke as if the matter in hand 
were of no sort of importance--"by-the-by, Mr. 
Pycroft, you wouldn't imagine how much 
recreation I derive from observing my neighbours 
in that very cross street which you find comes 
too near my windows." 
</p>
<p>
"If you was to come out of this kind of 
solitary life," replied Mr. P., "you would have 
other things to amuse yourself with besides the 
goings on of a parcel of people whom you know 
nothing about." 
</p>
<p>
"Now here, for instance," I went on, unmindful 
of the interruption, as I drew aside my own 
curtain and pointed out the window of the room 
occupied by my poor young couple--"here is a 
window which has revealed to me all sorts of 
interesting matter--enough to make a story 
out of almost, I can tell you." 
</p>
<p>
"What, this window opposite? But do you 
mean to say, Mr. B., that you think it right to 
look into people's rooms like that?" 
</p>
<p>
"I have scrupulously abstained from doing 
so," was my answer, "and have made all my 
observations with the blind down, as you see it 
now." 
</p>
<p>
"With the blind down? But how could you 
make any observations with the blind down?" 
</p>
<p>
"By means of the shadows of the occupants 
of the apartment," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
"Shadows?" cried Mr. Pycroft, obviously 
incredulous. "You don't mean to tell me that 
you could make out what was going on in that 
room by means of the shadows on the blind?" 
</p>
<p>
"Something of what goes on," I replied, "at 
any rate. Enough to interest me in the fortunes 
of those to whom the room belongs." 
</p>
<p>
"Well, really Mr. B.! If I had it on any 
other testimony than your own I should have 
thought it simply impossible." 
</p>
<p>
"Would you like to look for yourself?" I 
said. "I dare say something will take place 
behind the blind before long, which will give 
you an opportunity of testing the accuracy of 
what I have said." 
</p>
<p>
"Well, without doubting that at all," replied 
my guest, "I really think I should." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Pycroft was sitting near the window, but 
my reading-lamp upon the table made the room 
rather too light for our observations. So I 
pushed the table away to the other end of the 
room, turned down the wick of the lamp, and 
lowered the shade over it as well. 
</p>
<p>
"Well," said Mr. Pycroft, "I see nothing at 
present but a white blind with a light behind it." 
</p>
<p>
The shadow of the little wife's head was 
there in the corner by the curtain, and the 
shadow of the hand rose and fell as usual; but 
Mr. Pycroft had not such a practised eye as I 
had for detecting such matters. I pointed these 
out to my friend. 
</p>
<p>
"I do see something bobbing up and down," 
he said, "now you mention it. But I should 
never have found it out without your help. 
Stop! there's a shadow now covering nearly 
the whole blind. What's that?" 
</p>
<p>
"I suspect that it is the shadow of the same 
person," was my answer. "She will probably 
go nearer the window and farther from the light 
presently, and then you will see." 
</p>
<p>
In a minute or two the shadow appeared 
again, and this time not so large. 
</p>
<p>
"I can make it out now," said my friend, 
"quite easily; it is the shadow of a woman. 
I can see the line of the waist and of the skirts 
of the dress." 
</p>
<p>
"Can you make out the face at all?" I asked. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh yes," answered Mr, P. "It is turned 
sideways, looking to the left there. She's gone 
now," he added in a moment. 
</p>
<p>
In a few minutes her shadow was thrown again 
upon the blind. 
</p>
<p>
"What's she about now?" asked Mr. Pycroft. 
</p>
<p>
"Nay, you shall tell me," I answered. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, she seems to have some small object 
in her hand which she is shaking." 
</p>
<p>
"And now?" I asked again. 
</p>
<p>
"I can't make out, her elbow seems raised--
both hands are raised. No, I can't make out 
at all." 
</p>
<p>
"I think she is pouring something out," 
said I. 
</p>
<p>
"So she is, no doubt," answered my guest, 
who was evidently becoming much interested. 
"Stay," he continued, after a moment's pause, 
and looking at me quite anxiously as he spoke--
"shaking, pouring--'to be well shaken before 
taken'--why, it must be medicine." 
</p>
<p>
"I suspect it is medicine," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
"Is there some one ill, then?" asked Mr. 
Pycroft. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes," I replied, "her husband." 
</p>
<p>
"And did the shadow tell you that, too?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, the shadow of her husband used to 
appear on the blind as often as hers, now I 
never see it. Exactly coincident with the 
disappearance of the husband's shadow has been 
the arrival of another shadow, which has been 
that of the parish doctor." 
</p>
<p>
"And pray," asked Mr. Pycroft with the air 
of one whose credulity had been really too much 
tasked at last, "may I ask how you knew it to 
be the doctor's shadow?" 
</p>
<p>
"Doctor Cordial has the roundest back you 
ever saw in your life," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, this is really very curious," ejaculated 
the old copper-plate printer, who was now 
evidently powerfully interested. 
</p>
<p>
As we continued to look, the light was 
suddenly removed, and the room was left in 
darkness. 
</p>
<p>
"What do you suppose has happened now?" 
inquired my companion. 
</p>
<p>
"I suppose," was my answer, "that she has 
left the room for a short time. We shall see 
more presently, no doubt;" and almost as I 
spoke the light reappeared, and another shadow 
was in the room besides that of the little wife. 
</p>
<p>
"The doctor?" asked Mr. Pycroft. 
</p>
<p>
"There," I cried, triumphantly, "you see how 
much may be discovered by shadows. You are 
expert already." 
</p>
<p>
"He has a round back, certainly," said the 
old copper-plate printer. 
</p>
<p>
The round-backed shadow now faded off softly 
in the direction towards which the profile of the 
little wife was turned so often. The white blind 
remained for some minutes shadowless. 
</p>
<p>
"I suppose he is examining his patient now," 
said Mr. Pycroft; "here he is again," he added 
in another minute. The doctor, however, stood 
so near the light this time and so completely 
with his back towards us, that we were unable 
to determine what he was doing. This was, 
naturally, often the case with the shadows. 
Much as one was able to make out, there was, 
of course, infinitely more, an explanation of 
which it was impossible even to guess at. 
</p>
<p>
In a short time the round-backed shadow was 
joined by that of the sick man's wife, and then 
the two stood for some time in conversation; at 
least it was reasonable to suppose so. 
</p>
<p>
"Giving her directions, I shouldn't wonder," 
said the copper-plate printer. 
</p>
<p>
"Most likely," I answered. 
</p>
<p>
"I wonder if he's very bad," said my 
companion. After this there was a pause. The 
two shadows continued standing by the table. 
At last, we both thought that the doctor's 
shadow appeared to give something to the shade 
of the engraver's wife, and immediately after, the 
light was removed as it had been before: it had 
been probably taken out on to the landing in 
order that the doctor might see his way down 
stairs. 
</p>
<p>
"And so they're very poor," said Mr. Pycroft, 
as if talking to himself. 
</p>
<p>
"They had nothing but what the husband 
could earn," I answered, "and he is wholly 
incapable of working, and will remain so probably 
for weeks to come." 
</p>
<p>
The light had now reappeared in the room. 
The shadow of the little wife seemed to linger 
by the table after setting it down. Her figure 
was motionless for a considerable time, and then 
we noted that the head fell forward, and that 
the face was buried in the hands as if in an 
agony of silent grief. 
</p>
<p>
We neither of us spoke, and at the same 
moment I dropped the curtain of my own window 
which had before been fastened back, for I felt 
that this was sorrow with which a spectator had 
no right to intermeddle. 
</p>
<p>
Soon afterwards my old friend rose to go, and 
we spoke not another word on the matter. Just 
before I retired to rest, however, I looked out 
once more. The shadow of the little wife's head 
was in its usual place, and the shadow of her 
hand rose and fell as usual. She was at work 
again. 
</p>
<p>
The next day, by an early post, I received a 
letter from Mr. Pycroft. He had been thinking 
a great deal, he said, of what he had seen the 
night before, and enclosed a little money, which 
he asked me to see applied to the benefit of the 
young couple in whose fortunes I had interested 
myself. He also begged me from time to time 
to let him have tidings of what "the shadows" 
were about. 
</p>
<p>
I handed the money over to Dr. Cordial, asking 
him to apply it as might seem best to his 
judgment, but making no mention of who it 
came from. I asked him also to let me have 
news as frequently as possible of the condition 
of his patient. These I transmitted pretty nearly 
as often as I received them to the old copper-
plate printer. 
</p>
<p>
For some days there was not much to report, 
nor did the shadows tell me anything different 
from what they had before revealed. The poor 
engraver's shadow was still wanting, and that of 
his little wife was either stationary in the corner, 
when she did what she could to earn a little 
money with her needle, or else was seen flitting 
about the room in attendance on her sick 
husband. At length there came a time when the 
fever reached its crisis, and when it was clear, 
according to the doctor's report, that the sufferer 
must sink under it or recover. To make my 
story as short as possible, I will not dwell on 
the details of this period of suspense. The 
one quality of youth, possessed by the patient, 
enabled his constitution to rally, and after this 
crisis in his disorder he began to mend. 
</p>
<p>
And now a long convalesence followed, and a 
time arrived when one evening the shadow of a 
wasted figure moved slowly past the light, and I 
could guess as I watched it, and observed that 
it was accompanied by the well-known shadow 
of the little wife, that the sick man was moving 
from his bed to a chair by the fire. 
</p>
<p>
Of course I made this advance known to my 
friend, the copper-plate printer, and kept him 
well acquainted with all the particulars of the 
gradual improvement in our invalid's health, 
even to the period when it was so far 
re-established that he was able at last to sit up 
for a certain number of hours every day at his 
engraving table, and work once more for his 
wife's support. 
</p>
<p>
"They are very grateful," I said, when I 
made this announcement to my old acquaintance, 
"to the unknown friend who has assisted them 
from time to time throughout their trouble." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh no, nonsense, nonsense; it's nothing, 
nothing at all--nothing at all," ejaculated the 
old fellow, trying to get away from the subject. 
</p>
<p>
"And they are very anxious," I continued, 
resolutely, "to thank him personally, if he would but 
reveal himself and give them the opportunity." 
</p>
<p>
"No, no, not for the world," was the answer; 
"oh dear no, impossible. Here, here's a little 
trifle extra just to set them going you know, 
because he mustn't work too much at first." 
</p>
<p>
"And you won't let them see you?" I asked 
again: 
</p>
<p>
"No, no, no, on no account," said the old 
boy. "I'll tell you what, though," he continued 
in a moment, "I should like to see them--see 
them as I did before--the shadows you know," 
he added. "I'll come and have a glass of 
brandy-and-water with you some evening, and 
have a look at the shadows again." 
</p>
<p>
I was obliged to be satisfied with this, and 
making an engagement with my old friend for 
an early day, I left him, and went home. 
</p>
<p>
The evening came, and with it an unusual 
amount of stir and bustle in the quiet room 
opposite. The figure of the little wife was 
continually flitting backwards and forwards in 
front of the light, as if she were engaged 
in smartening up the poor apartment. Hanging 
in the very middle of the window, and 
so close to the thin white blind that I could 
see it distinctly, there was a birdcage with 
a bird in it; and it was owing to the 
presence of this object that I had been chiefly 
able to form some idea of what my two friends 
opposite were like. When either of them 
approached the birdcage, as would sometimes 
happen, to give a chirp of encouragement to its 
occupant, I could see the profile of the person 
who did so, as distinctly as one used to trace 
the silhouettes of the old black portraits which 
itinerant artists were wont to cut out at fairs. 
Except at such times as this, when the engraver 
or his wife stood thus near the window and far 
from the light, I could distinguish little but 
a shapeless mass; and when either of them 
approached the candle nearly, their shadows 
became so gigantic that the whole space of the 
window--an unusually large one--was 
completely darkened, even by one figure. I must 
repeat what I have said before, that the 
opportunities were very rare when I could make out 
what the shadows were about, and that in all 
cases in which I could detect such processes of 
mixing drinks, pouring out of medicines, and the 
like, it was owing to the fact that some necessary 
object connected with the proceeding was 
placed on some article of furniture which stood 
in or near the window. 
</p>
<p>
Punctual to the appointed time, my old friend, 
the copper-plate printer, made his appearance, 
and his first question after the usual greeting 
had been exchanged, was: 
</p>
<p>
"Well--how are the shadows?" 
</p>
<p>
I placed his chair in the old position, and we 
both sat down. 
</p>
<p>
The bustle and movement to which I have 
adverted as going on in the room opposite, were 
still noticeable, and I had little doubt that the 
apartment was being "cleaned up;" an impression 
to which additional force was soon given 
by the dawning on the scene of a thin, straight 
shadow, which I took to be a broomstick, and 
which was now brought into active service. 
</p>
<p>
I must not omit to mention, that at the 
moment of a certain pause in the career of the 
broom, the figure of the poor engraver was 
thrown with great distinctness on the blind. He 
had come to the window to stick some object, 
probably a piece of groundsel, between the wires 
of the birdcage. 
</p>
<p>
When this happened, I noticed a great change 
come over the countenance of my guest. He 
raised himself in his chair, and looking eagerly 
forward, said, in quite a strange tone of voice: 
</p>
<p>
"What did you say was the name of these 
people?" 
</p>
<p>
"Adams," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
"Adams--you are quite sure?" 
</p>
<p>
"Quite," I replied. By this time the shadow 
had vanished again, but I remarked that for 
a considerable time Mr. Pycroft seemed 
absent and uncomfortable, and we had talked of 
many matters foreign to the subject I had at 
heart, before he again returned to the shadows. 
</p>
<p>
"They seem quiet enough now," said Mr. 
Pycroft at last. 
</p>
<p>
"I dare say," I answered, "that the cleaning 
of the room is over, and that they have sat 
down to a bit of supper." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you think so?" asked the old copper-
plate printer. 
</p>
<p>
"I dare say they have some little luxury, 
furnished by your liberality." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you really think so?" said the old boy, 
who had a great idea of comfort. "What do you 
think they've got? I wish the shadows would 
show us that!" 
</p>
<p>
I darted at once at the opening which I saw 
here. 
</p>
<p>
"The shadows will not show it," I said; 
"but why not go across and see it in substance? 
It would make their supper all the sweeter to 
them, I am sure." 
</p>
<p>
The old gentleman had just finished a tumbler 
of hot grog. He was in high good humour, and 
as I finished speaking his eyes began to twinkle, 
and a latent smile developed itself about the 
corners of his mouth. 
</p>
<p>
"It wouldn't be bad fun, would it?" he said. 
</p>
<p>
I wanted nothing more, and in another 
minute I had him on his legs, and we were on our 
way to No. 4. 
</p>
<p>
A little girl was on the door-step with a pot 
of beer in her hand, and we had no sooner 
stopped before the house than she made known 
a want incidental to the lives of maidens who 
stand only three feet two inches in their 
stockings: 
</p>
<p>
"Please, sir, will you ring the second bell 
from the top?" 
</p>
<p>
"Second floor?" I said, as I complied; 
"that's where Mr. and Mrs. Adams live, isn't 
it?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, sir, and he's my father," said the 
young lady, who evidently looked upon the 
couple alluded to as one flesh. I thought it 
odd I had never seen this child's shadow on the 
blind. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, I want to see him, then," I replied, 
"and so does this gentleman." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, but you can't, though," said the little 
girl, who, by the way, appeared to be a 
precocious shrew--"for father's at supper, and 
there's a fowl, and father's been ill, and you 
can't disturb him just as he's a little better--so 
that you can't." 
</p>
<p>
"You just hold your tongue, miss, will you?" 
said a voice at this juncture, "and let me talk 
to the gentleman." 
</p>
<p>
I looked up and saw that the door had been 
opened by a tall gaunt-looking woman, with a 
large nose. 
</p>
<p>
"Who did you please to want, sir?" she asked 
in a whining tone, which I disliked very much. 
</p>
<p>
I told her briefly who we were, and the object 
of our visit. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, what a joyful surprise!" said the gaunt 
woman, whining as before in a manner infinitely 
offensive to me. "Get along up-stairs, Lizzy," 
she continued, addressing the child, "and tell 
your father that the kind gentleman as assisted 
him in his illness is coming to see him; I'm 
his wife, kind gentlemen"--(this the shadow 
that I had interested myself in!)--"I'm his 
poor wife that nussed him through his illness, 
and--take care of the stairs, kind gentlemen--
and this is the room, gentlemen; and here's a 
joyful surprise, James; the gentlemen that's 
been so kind all the time you've been ill; and 
be pleased to take a seat, gentlemen, and honour 
our poor room by sitting down in it." 
</p>
<p>
I was thunderstruck. A little common-looking 
man was sitting at the table on which a 
smoking fowl, a bit of bacon, and some potatoes 
had been placed. He bore the evident marks of 
recent illness, and rose with some effort at our 
entry. He resumed his seat, however, as I and 
my companion sat down. I took a chair, as I 
should have taken anything that was offered me 
in sheer surprise and bewilderment. I looked 
once more at the man's wife. What, was that 
the substance of the neat little shadow which I 
knew so well--that great gaunt sloping 
creature? Were shadows so deceptive as this? 
Would anybody tell me that my opposite neighbour 
could have had such a nose as I now saw, 
and that it would not have stood out in bold 
relief and left its mark upon my memory every 
time she approached the window? 
</p>
<p>
The husband, too. That was not my poor 
engraver. He was an inoffensive man enough, 
as he sat there full of clumsy expressions of 
gratitude to my companion for the assistance 
accorded to him during his recent attack of 
fever. He was a harmless little man, no doubt. 
Not quite such a heavy blow as his wife; but 
still, he was not my engraver. 
</p>
<p>
All this time, even while her husband was 
speaking, the gaunt woman kept up an 
undercurrent of gratitude of the slimiest description, 
to which the old gentleman answered not a 
word, for he seemed as little prepared for the 
real Mr. and Mrs. Adams by what he had seen 
of their shadows as I was. In short, beyond a 
few words of inquiry as to the state of the 
invalid's health, which I had managed to utter on 
first coming into the room, we had neither of us 
spoken a word. 
</p>
<p>
Suddenly the tremendous idea entered my 
mind that there must be some mistake. I had 
been staring some time at the little girl whom 
we originally met on the door-step, and who, 
to do her justice, returned the compliment with 
interest, when it struck me that her head came 
considerably above the window-sill, and that 
consequently, it was a most extraordinary thing 
that its shadow had never caught my attention. 
My eyes having in the course of this comparison 
of the young lady with the window-sill been 
directed towards this last part of the room, I 
next observed that there was no birdcage hanging 
in the window. 
</p>
<p>
"Halloa!" I ejaculated, "you've taken down 
the birdcage." 
</p>
<p>
"Birdcage, sir?" whined the gaunt woman, 
deferentially. 
</p>
<p>
"We ain't got no birdcage," burst out the 
small child of the door-step, "nor never haven't 
had none--nor yet no bird neither." 
</p>
<p>
"Will you hold your tongue, miss?" 
interposed her mother. 
</p>
<p>
There was an awkward pause. I looked again 
about the room, I looked at the woman, I looked 
at her husband--he had no beard, I now 
observed. I had, however, presence of mind enough 
not to ask after that missing appendage as I had 
done after the birdcage. I determined to make 
assurance doubly sure, and walking towards the 
window and pulling aside the blind, observed, as 
an excuse for looking out: 
</p>
<p>
"I am afraid you must be a good deal choked 
up at the back with houses. Isn't that rather 
unwholesome?" 
</p>
<p>
A voluble answer on the subject of confined 
lodgings, their advantages and disadvantages, 
followed, but I did not hear it. I was looking 
for my own window in the house opposite. I 
had left the lamp alight and the blind half drawn 
up. The window before me, exactly in front 
of that which I was looking from, was fastened 
up and secured with shutters. Stretching my 
neck, and glancing in a slanting direction towards 
the next of the opposite houses, I saw that the 
second-floor window was illuminated, and that 
the blind was half lowered. 
</p>
<p>
"Your supper is getting cold," I said, coming 
back to the table, and exchanging a glance of 
meaning with my companion; "my friend and I 
only wished to come in and see how you were 
enjoying yourselves, and so now we will leave 
you to do better justice to the fowl than you 
could if we remained here." 
</p>
<p>
So saying, and resisting all entreaties to stay 
and take a share of the good things, I made for 
the door, and was soon on the staircase, 
followed closely by Mr. Pycroft, who, speechless as 
long as we remained in the room, did nothing now 
but repeat, "Wrong people, eh?--been feeding 
the wrong people, haven't we?" in a loud and 
perfectly audible whisper. The gaunt woman 
was, however, too loquacious herself to hear 
what was said, and during the time that she 
lighted us down the stairs, never ceased whining 
out her gratitude for a single moment. 
</p>
<p>
When we got into the street I turned round 
and looked my companion in the face. 
</p>
<p>
"It is some comfort, at any rate," I said, "to 
think that you have been assisting people who 
were really in need of help, but it is evident 
that every penny of your bounty has gone to the 
family we have just left." 
</p>
<p>
"And how do you account for the mistake?" 
asked my old friend. 
</p>
<p>
"I can only conclude," was my answer, "that 
by a curious coincidence there have been two 
second-floor lodgers ill in two houses next door 
to each other; that after my seeing Dr. Cordial 
at the window opposite to mine, he had gone 
from the one house to the other; that he had 
had time to pay a short visit to the invalid we 
have just left; and that then I had met him 
coming away, as I thought, from attending on 
our poor shadows, but in reality from the 
deserving personage whose supper has been 
supplied by your benevolence." 
</p>
<p>
"And the shadows?" gasped Mr. Pycroft, 
utterly aghast. 
</p>
<p>
"Have, through my unfortunate mistake, not 
received a single shilling," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Pycroft stared at me for some time in 
petrified amazement. 
</p>
<p>
"We can never leave the thing like this," he 
said, at last. "Do you think you could be sure 
of the house this time?" 
</p>
<p>
"I can understand your feeling some mistrust 
about it," I said, "but I own that I feel none 
myself. This is the house beyond a doubt." I 
looked up as I spoke at No. 5. 
</p>
<p>
"Then let's bring the matter to a conclusion 
at once," said the old copper-plate printer, 
stoutly; and with that we actually rang at the 
second bell handle on the left hand door-post. 
</p>
<p>
After the proper amount of delay the door 
was opened by a slatternly woman. 
</p>
<p>
"Second-floor back?" said I, in a mellifluous 
voice. 
</p>
<p>
"Front," replied the slatternly woman, in 
rather an injured tone; "you should have rung 
the bell on the right door-post." 
</p>
<p>
I begged pardon with all humility, and the 
slatternly woman relented a little. 
</p>
<p>
"The two-pair-back's at home, I know," she 
said, "and if you're coming up I may as well 
light you." 
</p>
<p>
We availed ourselves of this offer, and, in a 
few seconds, we were on the second-floor landing. 
The slatternly woman pointed out the 
door at which we were to knock, and opening 
her own, and letting out in so doing a blast of 
onions that almost made my eyes water, she 
disappeared into the refreshing vapour, and shut 
herself in with it. 
</p>
<p>
My curiosity was now powerfully piqued, and 
I felt as if some great stake hinged upon the 
opening of the door at which we stood and 
knocked. 
</p>
<p>
A clear, cheerful voice called to us to enter, 
and in another moment we stood inside the 
room. 
</p>
<p>
Two people, a man and a woman, occupied the 
apartment. One of them, the man, was at first 
hidden from view, but in the other, as she rose 
upon our entrance, I recognised at once the 
shadow with which I was so familiar. 
</p>
<p>
The room was a great contrast to that which 
we had just left, which was tolerably well 
provided with furniture. This room was utterly 
bare, looking as if all available objects had been 
removed, as probably they had, to be turned into 
money. A mattress and some bedding were on 
the floor at one end of the room. The table, and 
a couple of old chairs, were the only articles of 
furniture I could see. The engraver's lamp was 
on the table, and the materials for a very poor 
meal which the two had evidently just been 
cooking--a very little scrap of bacon and some 
boiled rice. The birdcage was hanging in the 
window, if I had wanted any confirmation of my 
conviction that I had found my shadows at 
last. 
</p>
<p>
Of course, all these things were taken in by 
me at a single glance, it being necessary that I 
should at once account for my visit and that of 
my friend. I had begun to do so in a few hurried 
words, when my attention was suddenly arrested 
by an exclamation from Mr. Pycroft, who had 
followed me. The second occupant of the room, 
whom we had at first seen but imperfectly, had 
now risen to his feet, and stood with the light 
full upon him, straining his eyes into the shade 
where my companion stood behind me. I turned 
hastily round, and met the stern gaze of my old 
friend. 
</p>
<p>
"If this is a trick, Mr. Broadhead," he said, 
speaking very thick, and with choking utterance, 
"I can tell you that it does you little credit." 
</p>
<p>
"What do you mean?" I asked, in utter 
bewilderment. 
</p>
<p>
"I mean that if this has all been a planned 
thing to bring about a reconciliation between 
me and my son--" 
</p>
<p>
"Your son?" I gasped. 
</p>
<p>
"I can only say," continued Mr. Pycroft, 
"that it shall meet with the success it 
deserves." 
</p>
<p>
He turned as he spoke and made for the door, 
but I was beforehand with him. 
</p>
<p>
"Stay, Mr. Pycroft!" I cried. "If you 
choose to retain this feeling of animosity, which 
so ill becomes you, you must, but you shall not 
go away with a false impression of this matter 
as far as I am concerned in it. I swear to you 
that your suspicions of me are false, that when 
we came to this room I had no more idea of who 
were its occupants than you had, and that I 
never knew your son was living in this abject 
misery; though, if I had, I would certainly 
have done my best to rouse you to a feeling of 
what, under such circumstances, you owe to one 
who bears your name." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Pycroft had glanced once searchingly 
towards me when I denied his imputation of 
having been concerned in a plot to trick him 
into a reconciliation, and now his eyes were 
directed towards the place where his son stood 
before him. 
</p>
<p>
He was a fine manly-looking fellow, and as he 
stood there holding his wife's hand in his, and 
with the refining influence of recent illness 
showing on his worn but handsome face, I could 
not help feeling that surely this picture must 
complete the work which the shadows had so 
well begun. 
</p>
<p>
"Look at them!" I said--"look at this 
room--look at that meal! Can you see such 
wretchedness and not be moved? If your son 
has displeased you, has he not suffered? If he 
has disobeyed, he has paid the penalty." 
</p>
<p>
I looked in my companion's face, and I 
thought that I saw some shadow of compunction 
working there. 
</p>
<p>
"Do not," I said, "let the sympathy which 
you bestowed upon the shadows be wanting for 
the realities which cast them." 
</p>
<p>
The little wife at this moment left her 
husband's side, and, advancing to where we stood, 
laid her hand timidly on that of my old friend. 
I looked at him once more, and then, beckoning 
the poor engraver to his father's side, I passed 
quietly from the room, where I felt that my 
presence was no longer needed. 
</p>
<hr/>
<p>
About an hour afterwards I was sitting 
disconsolately in my room, reflecting on the loneliness 
of my own position, and rather envying 
my opposite neighbours, when I heard my own 
name shouted in a cheery voice from without. 
</p>
<p>
I looked in the old direction, and saw my 
friend Mr. Pycroft standing at his son's open 
window. 
</p>
<p>
"We want you to come over," said the old 
gentleman, "and spend what is left of the evening 
with us." 
</p>
<p>
I assented gladly, and was just drawing in 
my head, when I heard myself called once more 
by name. 
</p>
<p>
"And I say," said Mr. Pycroft, in a stage 
whisper, "as we are rather short of liquor here, 
perhaps you wouldn't mind bringing a bottle of 
brandy in your pocket; and if you happen to 
have such a thing as a lemon--" 
</p>
<p>
In a few minutes I was sitting one of a 
comfortable party in the room opposite. 
</p>
<p>
"Do you know what is one of the first things 
we intend to do now," said the little wife, 
smiling as she looked at me. 
</p>
<p>
"I have not the least idea," was my answer. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, we are going to nail up the thickest 
curtain we can get, in order to prevent our opposite 
neighbour from seeing what we are about 
whenever our lamp happens to be alight." 
</p>
<p>
"You need not be afraid," I said; "and you 
may save yourself the trouble of putting up the 
curtain, for the opposite neighbour hopes henceforth 
to see so much of his new friends in their 
Substance, that he is not likely to trouble 
himself much more about--their Shadows." 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up Terrible Company."/>
<p>
WHILE the artist was still engaged in telling 
his story, another visitor had come in at the gate, 
and had politely remained in the background, so 
as not to interrupt the proceedings. When the story 
was over, he came forward, and presented himself 
(in excellent English) as a Frenchman on a visit 
to this country. In the course of an eventful 
life, opportunities had occurred to him of learning 
our language, on the Continent, and necessity 
had obliged him to turn them to good 
account. Many years had passed, since that time, 
and had allowed him no earlier chance of visiting 
England than the chance of which he had now 
availed himself. He was staying with some 
friends in the neighbourhood--the Hermit had 
been mentioned to him--and here he was, on 
the ground of Thomas Tiddler, to deposit his 
homage at the feet of that illustrious landed 
proprietor. 
</p>
<p>
Was the French visitor surprised? Not the 
least in the world. His face showed deep marks 
of former care and trouble--perhaps he was past 
feeling surprised at anything? By no means. 
If he had seen Mr. Mopes on French ground, 
he would have been petrified on the spot. But 
Mr. Mopes on English ground was only a new 
development of the dismal national character. 
Given British spleen, as the cause--followed 
British suicide, as the effect. Quick suicide (of 
which the works of his literary countrymen had 
already informed him) by throwing yourself into 
the water. Slow suicide (of which his own eyes 
now informed him) by burying yourself among 
soot and cinders, in a barred kitchen. Curious 
either way--but nothing to surprise a well-read 
Frenchman. 
</p>
<p>
Leaving our national character to assert itself 
to better advantage, when time had given this 
gentleman better opportunities of studying it, 
Mr. Traveller politely requested him to follow 
the relation of the artist's experience with an 
experience of his own. After a moment's grave 
consideration, the Frenchman said that his early 
life had been marked by perils and sufferings 
of no ordinary kind. He had no objection to 
relate one of his adventures--but he warned 
his audience beforehand that they must expect 
to be a little startled; and he begged that they 
would suspend their opinions of himself and his 
conduct, until they had heard him to the end. 
</p>
<p>
After those prefatory words, he began as follows: 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
I AM a Frenchman by birth, and my name is 
François Thierry. I need not weary you with 
my early history. Enough, that I committed a 
political offence--that I was sent to the galleys 
for it--that I am an exile for it to this day. 
The brand was not abolished in my time. If I 
chose, I could show you the fiery letters on my 
shoulder. 
</p>
<p>
I was arrested, tried, and sentenced, in Paris. 
I went out of the court with my condemnation 
ringing in my ears. The rumbling wheels of the 
prison-van repeated it all the way from Paris to 
Bicêtre that evening, and all the next day, and 
the next, and the next, along the weary road 
from Bicêtre to Toulon. When I look back 
upon that time, I think I must have been stupified 
by the unexpected severity of my sentence; 
for I remember nothing of the journey, nor of 
the places where we stopped--nothing but the 
eternal repetition of "travaux forcés--travaux 
forcés--travaux forcés à perpétuité," over and 
over, and over again. Late in the afternoon of 
the third day, the van stopped, the door was 
thrown open, and I was conducted across a 
stone yard, through a stone corridor, into a huge 
stone hall, dimly lighted from above. Here I was 
interrogated by a military superintendent, and 
entered by name in a ponderous ledger bound 
and clasped with iron, like a book in fetters. 
</p>
<p>
"Number Two Hundred and Seven," said the 
superintendent. "Green." 
</p>
<p>
They took me into an adjoining room, searched, 
stripped, and plunged me into a cold bath. 
When I came out of the bath, I put on the 
livery of the galleys--a coarse canvas shirt, 
trousers of tawny serge, a red serge blouse, and 
heavy shoes clamped with iron. Last of all, a 
green woollen cap. On each leg of the trousers, 
and on the breast and back of the blouse, were 
printed the fatal letters "T. F." On a brass 
label in the front of the cap, were engraved the 
figures "207." From that moment I lost my 
individuality. I was no longer François Thierry. 
I was Number Two Hundred and Seven. The 
superintendent stood by and looked on. 
</p>
<p>
"Come, be quick," said he, twirling his long 
moustache between his thumb and forefinger. 
"It grows late, and you must be married before 
supper." 
</p>
<p>
"Married!" I repeated. 
</p>
<p>
The superintendent laughed, and lighted a 
cigar, and his laugh was echoed by the guards 
and jailers. 
</p>
<p>
Down another stone corridor, across another 
yard, into another gloomy hall, the very counterpart 
of the last, but filled with squalid figures, 
noisy with the clank of fetters, and pierced at 
each end with a circular opening, through which 
a cannon's mouth showed grimly. 
</p>
<p>
"Bring Number Two Hundred and Six," said 
the superintendent, "and call the priest." 
</p>
<p>
Number Two Hundred and Six came from a 
farther corner of the hall, dragging a heavy 
chain, and along with him a blacksmith, bare-
armed and leather-aproned. 
</p>
<p>
"Lie down," said the blacksmith, with an 
insulting spurn of the foot. 
</p>
<p>
I lay down. A heavy iron ring attached to a 
chain of eighteen links was then fitted to my 
ankle, and riveted with a single stroke of the 
hammer. A second ring next received the 
disengaged ends of my companion's chain and mine, 
and was secured in the same manner. The echo 
of each blow resounded through the vaulted roof 
like a hollow laugh. 
</p>
<p>
"Good," said the superintendent, drawing a 
small red book from his pocket. "Number 
Two Hundred and Seven, attend to the prison 
code. If you attempt to escape without 
succeeding, you will be bastinadoed. If you 
succeed in getting beyond the port, and are then 
taken, you will receive three years of double-
chaining. As soon as you are missed, three cannon 
shots will be fired, and alarm flags will be 
hoisted on every bastion. Signals will be 
telegraphed to the maritime guards, and to the 
police of the ten neighbouring districts. A price 
will be set upon your head. Placards will be 
posted upon the gates of Toulon, and sent to 
every town throughout the empire. It will be 
lawful to fire upon you, if you cannot be 
captured alive." 
</p>
<p>
Having read this with grim complacency, the 
superintendent resumed his cigar, replaced the 
book in his pocket, and walked away. 
</p>
<p>
All was over--now all the incredulous wonder, 
the dreamy dulness, the smouldering hope, of 
the past three days. I was a felon, and (slavery 
in slavery!) chained to a fellow-felon. I looked 
up, and found his eyes upon me. He was a 
swart heavy-browed sullen-jawed man of about 
forty; not much taller than myself, but of 
immensely powerful build. 
</p>
<p>
"So," said he, "you're for life, are you? So 
am I." 
</p>
<p>
"How do you know I am for life?" I asked, wearily. 
</p>
<p>
"By that." And he touched my cap roughly 
with the back of his hand. "Green, for life. Red, 
for a term of years. What are you in for?" 
</p>
<p>
"I conspired against the government." 
</p>
<p>
He shrugged his shoulders contemptuously. 
</p>
<p>
"Devil's mass! Then you're a gentleman-
convict, I suppose! Pity you've not a berth to 
yourselves--we poor forçats hate such fine 
company." 
</p>
<p>
"Are there many political prisoners?" I 
asked, after a moment's pause. 
</p>
<p>
"None, in this department." 
</p>
<p>
Then, as if detecting my unspoken thought, 
"I am no innocent," he added with an oath. 
"This is the fourth time I have been here. Did 
you ever hear of Gasparo?" 
</p>
<p>
"Gasparo the forger?" 
</p>
<p>
He nodded. 
</p>
<p>
"Who escaped three or four months since, and--" 
</p>
<p>
"And flung the sentinel over the ramparts, 
just as he was going to give the alarm. I'm 
the man." 
</p>
<p>
I had heard of him, as a man who, early in 
his career, had been sentenced to a long solitary 
imprisonment in a gloomy cell, and who had 
come forth from his solitude hardened into an 
absolute wild beast. I shuddered, and, as I 
shuddered, found his evil eye taking vindictive 
note of me. From that moment he hated me. 
From that moment I loathed him. 
</p>
<p>
A bell rang, and a detachment of convicts 
came in from labour. They were immediately 
searched by the guard, and chained up, two and 
two, to a sloping wooden platform that reached 
all down the centre of the hall. Our afternoon 
meal was then served out. consisting of a mess 
of beans, an allowance of bread and ship-
biscuit, and a measure of thin wine. I drank the 
wine; but I could eat nothing. Gasparo took 
what he chose from my untouched allowance, 
and those who were nearest, scrambled for 
the rest. The supper over, a shrill whistle 
echoed down the hall, each man took his narrow 
mattress from under the platform which made 
our common bedstead, rolled himself in a piece 
of seaweed matting, and lay down for the night. 
In less than five minutes, all was profoundly 
silent. Now and then I heard the blacksmith 
going round with his hammer, testing the gratings, 
and trying the locks, in all the corridors. 
Now and then, the guard stalked past with his 
musket on his shoulder. Sometimes, a convict 
moaned, or shook his fetters in his sleep. Thus 
the weary hours went by. My companion slept 
heavily, and even I lost consciousness at last. 
</p>
<p>
I was sentenced to hard labour. At Toulon 
the hard labour is of various kinds: such as 
quarrying, mining, pumping in the docks, lading 
and unlading vessels, transporting ammunition, 
and so forth. Gasparo and I were employed 
with about two hundred other convicts in a 
quarry a little beyond the port. Day after day, 
week after week, from seven in the morning 
until seven at night, the rocks echoed with our 
blows. At every blow, our chains rang and 
rebounded on the stony soil. In that fierce 
climate, terrible tempests and tropical droughts 
succeed each other throughout the summer and 
autumn. Often and often, after toiling for 
hours under a burning sky, have I gone back 
to prison and to my pallet, drenched to the skin. 
Thus the last days of the dreary spring ebbed 
slowly past; and then the more dreary summer, 
and then the autumn-time, came round. 
</p>
<p>
My fellow-convict was a Piedmontese. He 
had been a burglar, a forger, an incendiary. In 
his last escape, he had committed manslaughter. 
Heaven alone knows how my sufferings were 
multiplied by that abhorred companionship--
how I shrank from the touch of his hand--how 
I sickened, if his breath came over me as we lay 
side by side at night. I strove to disguise my 
loathing; but in vain. He knew it as well as I 
knew it, and he revenged himself upon me by 
every means that a vindictive nature could 
devise. That he should tyrannise over me was 
not wonderful; for his physical strength was 
gigantic, and he was looked upon as an 
authorised despot throughout the port; but simple 
tyranny was the least part of what I had to 
endure. I had been fastidiously nurtured; he 
purposely and continually offended my sense of 
delicacy. I was unaccustomed to bodily labour; 
he imposed on me the largest share of our daily 
work. When I needed rest, he would insist on 
walking. When my limbs were cramped, he 
would lie down obstinately, and refuse to stir. 
He delighted to sing blasphemous songs, and 
relate hideous stories of what he had thought 
and resolved on in his solitude. He would 
even twist the chain in such wise that it should 
gall me at every step. I was at that time 
just twenty-two years of age, and had been 
sickly from boyhood. To retaliate, or to defend 
myself, would have been alike impossible. To 
complain to the superintendent, would only have 
been to provoke my tyrant to greater cruelty. 
</p>
<p>
There came a day, at length, when his hatred 
seemed to abate. He allowed me to rest when 
our hour of repose came round. He abstained 
from singing the songs I abhorred, and fell into 
long fits of abstraction. The next morning, 
shortly after we had begun work, he drew near 
enough to speak to me in a whisper. 
</p>
<p>
"François, have you a mind to escape?" 
</p>
<p>
I felt the blood rush to my face. I clasped 
my hands. I could not speak. 
</p>
<p>
"Can you keep a secret?" 
</p>
<p>
"To the death." 
</p>
<p>
"Listen, then. To-morrow, a renowned 
marshal will visit the port. He will inspect the docks, 
the prisons, the quarries. There will be plenty 
of cannonading from the forts and the shipping, 
and if two convicts escape, a volley more or less 
will attract no attention round about Toulon. 
Do you understand?" 
</p>
<p>
"You mean that no one will recognise the 
signals?" 
</p>
<p>
"Not even the sentries at the town-gates--
not even the guards in the next quarry. Devil's 
mass! What can be easier than to strike off 
each other's fetters with the pickaxe when the 
superintendent is not looking, and the salutes 
are firing? Will you venture?" 
</p>
<p>
"With my life!'" 
</p>
<p>
"A bargain. Shake hands on it." 
</p>
<p>
I had never touched his hand in fellowship 
before, and I felt as if my own were blood-
stained by the contact. I knew by the sullen 
fire in his glance, that he interpreted my faltering 
touch aright. 
</p>
<p>
We were roused an hour earlier than usual 
the following morning, and went through a 
general inspection in the prison-yard. Before 
going to work, we were served with a double 
allowance of wine. At one o'clock, we heard 
the first far-off salutes from the ships of war in 
the harbour. The sound ran through me like a 
galvanic shock. One by one, the forts took up 
the signal. It was repeated by the gun-boats 
closer in shore. Discharge followed discharge, 
all along the batteries on both sides of the port, 
and the air grew thick with smoke. 
</p>
<p>
"As the first shot is fired yonder," whispered 
Gasparo, pointing to the barracks behind the 
prison, "strike at the first link of my chain, 
close to the ankle." 
</p>
<p>
A rapid suspicion flashed across me. 
</p>
<p>
"If I do, how can I be sure that you will 
free me afterwards? No, Gasparo; you must 
deal the first blow." 
</p>
<p>
"As you please," he replied, with a laugh 
and an imprecation. 
</p>
<p>
At the same instant, came a flash from the 
battlements of the barrack close by, and then a 
thunderous reverberation, multiplied again and 
again by the rocks around. As the roar burst 
over our heads, I saw him strike, and felt the 
fetters fall. Scarcely had the echo of the first 
gun died away, when the second was fired. It 
was now Gasparo's turn to be free. I struck; 
but less skilfully, and had twice to repeat the 
blow before breaking the stubborn link. We 
then went on, apparently, with our work, standing 
somewhat close together, with the chain 
huddled up between us. No one had observed 
us, and no one, at first sight, could have 
detected what we had done. At the third shot, 
a party of officers and gentlemen made their 
appearance at the bend of the road leading up to 
the quarry. In an instant, every head was 
turned in their direction; every felon paused in 
his work; every guard presented arms. At 
that moment we flung away our caps and pick-
axes, scaled the rugged bit of cliff on which we 
had been toiling, dropped into the ravine below, 
and made for the mountain passes that lead into 
the valley. Encumbered still with the iron 
anklets to which our chains had been fastened, 
we could not run very swiftly. To add to our 
difficulties, the road was uneven, strewn with 
flints and blocks of fallen granite, and tortuous 
as the windings of a snake. Suddenly, on turning 
a sharp angle of projecting cliff, we came 
upon a little guard-house and a couple of 
sentries. To retreat was impossible. The 
soldiers were within a few yards of us. They 
presented their pieces, and called to us to 
surrender. Gasparo turned upon me like a wolf at 
bay. 
</p>
<p>
"Curse you!" said he, dealing me a 
tremendous blow, "stay and be taken! I have 
always hated you!" 
</p>
<p>
I fell, as if struck down by a sledge hammer, 
and, as I fell, saw him dash one soldier to the 
ground, dart past the other, heard a shot, and 
then ... all became dark, and I know no more. 
</p>
<p>
When I next opened my eyes, I found myself 
lying on the floor of a small unfurnished room, 
dimly lighted by a tiny window close against 
the ceiling. It seemed as if weeks had gone by, 
since I lost consciousness. I had scarcely 
strength to rise, and, having risen, kept my feet 
with difficulty. Where my head had lain, the 
floor was wet with blood. Giddy and perplexed, 
I leaned against the wall, and tried to think. 
</p>
<p>
In the first place, where was I? Evidently 
in no part of the prison from which I had escaped. 
There, all was solid stone and iron grating; here, 
was only whitewashed lath and plaster. I must 
be in a chamber of the little guard-house: 
probably in an upper chamber. Where, then, were 
the soldiers? Where was Gasparo? Had I 
strength to clamber up to that window, and if 
so, in what direction did that window look out? 
I stole to the door, and found it locked. I 
listened, breathlessly, but could hear no sound 
either below or above. Creeping back again, I 
saw that the little window was at least four 
feet above my head. The smooth plaster offered 
no projections by which I could raise myself, 
and there was not even a fireplace in the room 
from which I could have wrenched a bar to dig 
out holes in the wall for my feet and hands. 
Stay! There was my leathern belt, and on the 
belt, the iron hook which used to sustain my 
chain when I was not at work. I tore off the 
hook, picked away the lath and plaster in three 
or four places, climbed up, opened the window, 
and gazed out eagerly. Before me, at a distance 
of not more than thirty-five or forty feet, rose the 
rugged cliff under whose shelter the guard-house 
was built; at my feet, lay a little kitchen-garden, 
divided from the base of the rock by a muddy 
ditch which seemed to run through the ravine; 
to the right and left, as well as I could judge, 
lay the rocky path along which our course had 
been directed. My decision was taken at once. 
To stay was certain capture; to venture, at all 
hazards, would make matters no worse. Again 
I listened, and again all was quiet. I drew 
myself through the little casement, dropped 
as gently as I could upon the moist earth, 
and, crouching against the wall, asked myself 
what I should do next. To climb the cliff 
would be to offer myself as a target to the first 
soldier who saw me. To venture along the 
ravine would be, perhaps, to encounter Gasparo 
and his captors face to face. Besides, it was 
getting dusk, and, under cover of the night, if I 
could only conceal myself till then, I might yet 
escape. But where was that concealment to be 
found? Heaven be thanked for the thought! 
There was the ditch. 
</p>
<p>
Only two windows looked out upon the garden 
from the back of the guard-house. From one 
of those windows I had just now let myself down, 
and the other was partly shuttered up. I did 
not dare, however, openly to cross the garden. 
I dropped upon my face, and crawled in the 
furrows between the rows of vegetables, until I 
came to the ditch. Here, the water rose nearly 
to my waist, but the banks on either side were 
considerably higher, and, by stooping, I found 
that I could walk without bringing my head to 
the level of the road. I thus followed the course 
of the ditch for some two or three hundred yards 
in the direction of Toulon, thinking that my 
pursuers would be less likely to suspect me of 
doubling back towards prison, than of pushing 
forward towards the country. Half lying, half 
crouching under the rank grasses that fringed 
the bank above, I then watched the gathering 
shadows. By-and-by I heard the evening gun, 
and a moment after, something like a distant 
sound of voices. Hark! was that a shout? 
Unable to endure the agony of suspense, I lifted 
my head, and peeped cautiously out. There 
were lights moving in the windows of the guard-
house--there were dark figures in the garden--
there were hasty tramplings of feet upon the 
road above! Presently a light flashed over the 
water only a few yards from my hiding-place! 
I slid gently down at full length, and suffered 
the foul ooze to close noiselessly over me. Lying 
thus, I held my breath till the very beatings of 
my heart seemed to suffocate me, and the veins 
in my temples were almost bursting. I could 
bear it no longer--I rose to the surface--I 
breathed again--I looked--I listened. All 
was darkness and silence. My pursuers were 
gone by! 
</p>
<p>
I suffered an hour to go by, too, before I 
ventured to move again. By that time it was 
intensely dark, and had begun to rain heavily. 
The water in the ditch became a brawling 
torrent, through which I waded, unheard, past the 
very windows of the guard-house. 
</p>
<p>
After toiling through the water for a mile or 
more, I ventured out upon the road again: and 
so, with the rain and wind beating in my face, 
and the scattered boulders tripping me up 
continually, I made my way through the whole 
length of the winding pass, and came out 
upon the more open country about midnight. 
With no other guide than the wind, which was 
blowing from the north-east, and without even a 
star to help me, I then struck off to the right, 
following what seemed to be a rough by-road, 
lying through a valley. By-and-by the rain 
abated, and I discerned the dark outlines of a 
chain of hills extending all along to the left of 
the road. These, I concluded, must be the 
Maures. All was well, so far. I had taken 
the right direction, and was on the way to 
Italy. 
</p>
<p>
Excepting to sit down now and then for a few 
minutes by the wayside, I never paused in my 
flight the whole night through. Fatigue and 
want of food prevented me, it is true, from walking 
very fast; but the love of liberty was strong 
within me, and, by keeping steadily on, I 
succeeded in placing about eighteen miles between 
myself and Toulon. At five o'clock, just as the 
day began to dawn, I heard a peal of chimes, 
and found that I was approaching a large town. 
In order to avoid this town, I was forced to 
turn back for some distance, and take to the 
heights. The sun had now risen, and I dared 
go no farther; so, having pulled some turnips in 
a field as I went along, I took refuge in a little 
lonely copse in a hollow among the hills, and 
there lay all day in safety. When night again 
closed in, I resumed my journey, keeping always 
among the mountains, and coming now and then 
on grand glimpses of moonlit bays, and tranquil 
islands lying off the shore; now and then, on 
pastoral hamlets nestled up among the palmy 
heights; or on promontories overgrown with 
the cactus and the aloe. I rested all the second 
day in a ruined shed at the bottom of a deserted 
sand-pit, and, in the evening, feeling that I could 
no longer sustain life without some fitting 
nourishment, made my way down towards a tiny 
fishing village on the coast below. It was quite 
dark, by the time I reached the level ground. I 
walked boldly past the cottages of the fishermen, 
meeting only an old woman and a little child on 
the way, and knocked at the curé's door. He 
opened it himself. I told my story in half a 
dozen words. The good man believed and pitied 
me. He gave me food and wine, an old 
handkerchief to wrap about my head, an old coat to 
replace my convict's jacket, and two or three 
francs to help me on my way. I parted from 
him with tears. 
</p>
<p>
I walked all that night again, and all the 
next, keeping somewhat close upon the coast, 
and hiding among the cliffs during the daytime. 
On the fifth morning, having left Antibes behind 
me during the night's march, I came to the 
banks of the Var; crossed the torrent about 
half a mile below the wooden bridge; plunged 
into the pine-woods on the Sardinian side of the 
frontier; and lay down to rest on Italian ground 
at last! 
</p>
<p>
How, though comparatively safe, I still 
pursued my journey by the least frequented ways--
how I bought a file at the first hamlet to which 
I came, and freed myself from the iron anklet--
how, having lurked about Nice till my hair and 
beard had grown, I begged my way on to Genoa--
how, at Genoa, I hung about the port, earning 
a scanty livelihood by any chance work that I 
could get, and so struggled, somehow, through 
the inclement winter--how, towards the early 
spring, I worked my passage on board a small 
trader from Genoa to Fiumicino, touching at 
all the ports along the coast--and how, coming 
slowly up the Tiber in a barge laden with oil 
and wine, I landed one evening in March on the 
Ripetta quay, in Rome;--how all these things 
happened, and what physical hardships I endured 
in the mean while, I have no time here to relate 
in detail. My object had been, to get to Rome, 
and that object was at last attained. In so 
large a city, and at so great a distance from the 
scene of my imprisonment, I was personally safe. 
I might hope to turn my talents and education 
to account. I might even find friends among the 
strangers who would flock thither to the Easter 
festivals. Full of hope, therefore, I sought a 
humble lodging in the neighbourhood of the 
quay, gave up a day or two to the enjoyment of 
my liberty and of the sights of Rome, and then 
set myself to find some regular employment. 
</p>
<p>
Regular employment, or, indeed, employment 
of any kind, was not, however, so easily to be 
obtained. It was a season of distress. The 
previous harvest had been a failure, and the 
winter unusually severe. There had also been 
disturbances in Naples, and the travellers this 
spring were fewer by some thousands than  the 
ordinary average. So dull a carnival had not 
been known for years. The artists had sold no 
paintings, and the sculptors no statues. The 
cameo-cutters and mosaicists were starving. The 
tradesmen, the hotel-keepers, the professional 
ciceroni, were all complaining bitterly. Day 
by day, my hopes faded and my prospects 
darkened. Day by day, the few scudi I had 
scraped together on the passage melted away. 
I had thought to obtain a clerkship, or a 
secretaryship, or a situation in some public 
library. Before three weeks were over, I would 
gladly have swept a studio. At length there 
came a day when I saw nothing before me but 
starvation; when my last bajocco was expended; 
when my padrone (or landlord) shut the door in 
my face, and I knew not where to turn for a meal 
or a shelter. All that afternoon, I wandered 
hopelessly about the streets. It was Good Friday, 
of all days in the year. The churches were 
hung with black; the bells were tolling; the 
thoroughfares were crowded with people in 
mourning. I went into the little church of 
Santa Martina. They were chanting a miserere, 
probably with no great skill, but with a pathos 
that seemed to open up all the sources of my 
despair. 
</p>
<p>
Outcast that I was, I slept that night under a 
dark arch near the theatre of Marcellus. The 
morning dawned upon a glorious day, and I crept 
out, shivering, into the sunshine. Lying crouched 
against a bit of warm wall, I caught myself 
wondering more than once how long it would 
be worth while to endure the agonies of hunger, 
and whether the brown waters of the Tiber 
were deep enough to drown a man. It seemed 
hard to die so young. My future might 
have been so pleasant, so honourable. The 
rough life that I had been leading of late, too, 
had strengthened me in every way, physically 
and mentally. I had grown taller. My muscles 
were more developed. I was twice as active, as 
energetic, as resolute, as I had been a year before. 
And of what use were these things to me? I 
must die, and they could only serve to make me 
die the harder. 
</p>
<p>
I got up and wandered about the streets, as I 
had wandered the day before. Once I asked for 
alms, and was repulsed. I followed mechanically 
in the stream of carriages and foot passengers, 
and found myself, by-and-by, in the midst of the 
crowd that ebbs and flows continually about 
Saint Peter's during Easter week. Stupified and 
weary, I turned aside into the vestibule of the 
Sagrestia, and cowered down in the shelter of a 
doorway. Two gentlemen were reading a 
printed paper wafered against a pillar close by. 
</p>
<p>
"Good Heavens!" said one to the other, 
"that a man should risk his neck for a few 
pauls!" 
</p>
<p>
"Ay, and with the knowledge that out of 
eighty workmen, six or eight are dashed to 
pieces every time," added his companion. 
</p>
<p>
"Shocking! Why, that is an average of ten 
per cent!" 
</p>
<p>
"No less. It is a desperate service." 
</p>
<p>
"But a fine sight," said the first speaker, 
philosophically; and with this they walked 
away. 
</p>
<p>
I sprang to my feet, and read the placard 
with avidity. It was headed "Illumination of 
Saint Peter's," and announced that, eighty 
workmen being required for the lighting of the 
dome and cupola, and three hundred for the 
cornices, pillars, colonnade, and so forth, the 
amministratore was empowered, &amp;c. &amp;c. In 
conclusion, it stated that every workman 
employed on the dome and cupola should receive 
in payment, a dinner and twenty-four pauls, the 
wages of the rest being less than a third of that 
sum. 
</p>
<p>
A desperate service, it was true; but I was a 
desperate man. After all, I could but die, and 
I might as well die after a good dinner as from 
starvation. I went at once to the amministratore, 
was entered in his list, received a couple 
of pauls as earnest of the contract, and engaged 
to present myself punctually at eleven o'clock 
on the following morning. That evening I 
supped at a street stall, and, for a few bajocchi, 
obtained leave to sleep on some straw, in a loft 
over a stable at the back of the Via del Arco. 
</p>
<p>
At eleven o'clock on the morning of Easter 
Sunday, April the sixteenth, I found myself, 
accordingly, in the midst of a crowd of poor 
fellows, most of whom, I dare say, were as 
wretched as myself, waiting at the door of the 
administrator's office. The piazza in front of 
the cathedral was like a moving mosaic of life 
and colour. The sun was shining, the 
fountains were playing, the flags were flying over 
Saint Angelo. It was a glorious sight; but I 
saw it for only a few moments. As the clocks 
struck the hour, the folding-doors were thrown 
open, and we passed, in a crowd, into a hall, 
where two long tables were laid for our 
accommodation. A couple of sentinels stood at the 
door; an usher marshalled us, standing, round 
the tables; and a priest read grace. 
</p>
<p>
As he began to read, a strange sensation came 
upon me. I felt impelled to look across to the 
opposite table, and there . . . yes, by Heaven! 
there I saw Gasparo. 
</p>
<p>
He was looking full at me, but his eyes dropped 
on meeting mine. I saw him turn lividly white. 
The recollection of all he had made me suffer, 
and of the dastardly blow that he had dealt me 
on the day of our flight, overpowered for the 
moment even my surprise at seeing him in this 
place. Oh that I might live to meet him yet, 
under the free sky, where no priest was praying, 
and no guards were by! 
</p>
<p>
The grace over, we sat down, and fell to. 
Not even anger had power to blunt the edge of 
my appetite just then. I ate like a famishing 
wolf, and so did most of the others. We were 
allowed no wine, and the doors were locked upon 
us, that we might not procure any elsewhere. 
It was a wise regulation, considering the task 
we had to perform; but it made us none the 
less noisy. Under certain circumstances, danger 
intoxicates like wine; and on this Easter Sunday, 
we eighty sanpietrini, any one of whom 
might have his brains dashed about the leads 
before supper-time, ate, talked, jested, and 
laughed, with a wild gaiety that had in it 
something appalling. 
</p>
<p>
The dinner lasted long, and when no one 
seemed disposed to eat more, the tables were 
cleared. Most of the men threw themselves on 
the floor and benches, and went to sleep; 
Gasparo among the number. Seeing this, I could 
refrain no longer. I went over, and stirred him 
roughly with my foot. 
</p>
<p>
"Gasparo! You know me?" 
</p>
<p>
He looked up, sullenly. 
</p>
<p>
"Devil's mass! I thought you were at 
Toulon." 
</p>
<p>
"It is not your fault that I am not at Toulon! 
Listen to me. If you and I survive 
this night, you shall answer to me for your 
treachery!" 
</p>
<p>
He glared at me from under his deep brows, 
and, without replying, turned over on his face 
again, as if to sleep. 
</p>
<p>
"Ecco un maladetto!" (There's an accursed 
fellow!), said one of the others, with a 
significant shrug, as I came away. 
</p>
<p>
"Do you know anything of him?" I asked, 
eagerly. 
</p>
<p>
"Cospetto! I know nothing of him; but that 
solitude is said to have made him a Wolf." 
</p>
<p>
I could learn no more, so I also stretched 
myself upon the floor, as far as possible from my 
enemy, and fell profoundly asleep, 
</p>
<p>
At seven, the guards roused those who still 
slept, and served each man with a small mug of 
thin wine. We were then formed into a double 
file, marched round by the back of the cathedral, 
and conducted up an inclined plane to the roof 
below the dome. From this point, a long series 
of staircases and winding passages carried us up 
between the double walls of the dome; and, at 
different stages in the ascent, a certain number 
of us were detached and posted ready for work. 
I was detached about half way up, and I saw 
Gasparo going higher still. When we were all 
posted, the superintendents came round and 
gave us our instructions. At a given signal, 
every man was to pass out through the loophole 
or window before which he was placed, and 
seat himself astride upon a narrow shelf of wood 
hanging to a strong rope just below. This rope 
came through the window, was wound round a 
roller, and secured from within. At the next 
signal, a lighted torch would be put into his right 
hand, and he was to grasp the rope firmly with 
his left. At the third signal, the rope was to be 
unwound from within by an assistant placed 
there for the purpose, he was to be allowed to 
slide rapidly down, over the curve of the dome, 
and, while thus sliding, was to apply his torch 
to every lamp he passed in his downward 
progress. 
</p>
<p>
Having received these instructions, we waited, 
each man at his window, until the first signal 
should be given. 
</p>
<p>
It was fast getting dark, and the silver 
illumination had been lighted since seven. All the 
great ribs of the dome, as far as I could see; all 
the cornices and friezes of the façade below; all 
the columns and parapets of the great colonnade 
surrounding the piazza four hundred feet below, 
were traced out in lines of paper lanterns, the 
light from which, subdued by the paper, gleamed 
with a silvery fire which had a magical and 
wondrous look. Between and among these 
lanternoni, were placed, at different intervals all 
over the cathedral on the side facing the piazza, 
iron cups called padelle, ready filled with tallow 
and turpentine. To light those on the dome and 
cupola, was the perilous task of the sanpietrini; 
when they were all lighted, the golden illumination 
would be effected. 
</p>
<p>
A few moments of intense suspense elapsed. 
At every second the evening grew darker, the 
lanternoni burned brighter, the surging hum of 
thousands in the piazza and streets below, rose 
louder to our ears. I felt the quickening breath 
of the assistant at my shoulder--I could almost 
hear the beating of my heart. Suddenly, like 
the passing of an electric current, the first 
signal flew from lip to lip. I got out, and 
crossed my legs firmly round the board--with the 
second signal, I seized the blazing torch--with 
the third, I felt myself launched, and, lighting 
every cup as I glided past, saw all the 
mountainous dome above and below me spring into 
lines of leaping flame. The clock was now striking 
eight, and when the last stroke sounded, the whole 
cathedral was glowing in outlines of fire. A 
roar, like the roar of a great ocean, rose up from 
the multitude below, and seemed to shake the 
very dome against which I was clinging. I 
could even see the light upon the gazing faces, 
the crowd upon the bridge of St. Angelo, 
and the boats swarming along the Tiber. 
</p>
<p>
Having dropped safely to the full length of 
my rope, and lighted my allotted share of lamps, 
I was now sitting in secure enjoyment of this 
amazing scene. All at once, I felt the rope 
vibrate. I looked up, saw a man clinging by 
one hand to the iron rod supporting the padelle, 
and with the other .... Merciful Heaven! It 
was the Piedmontese firing the rope above me 
with his torch! 
</p>
<p>
I had no time for thought--I acted upon 
instinct. It was done in one fearful moment. I 
clambered up like a cat, dashed my torch full in 
the solitary felon's face, and grasped the rope 
an inch or two above the spot where it was 
burning! Blinded and baffled, he uttered a 
terrible cry, and dropped like a stone. Through all 
the roar of the living ocean below, I could hear 
the dull crash with which he came down upon 
the leaded roof--resounding through all the 
years that have gone by since that night, I hear 
it now! 
</p>
<hr/>
<p>
I had scarcely drawn breath, when I found 
myself being hauled up. The assistance came 
not a moment too soon, for I was sick and 
giddy with horror, and fainted as soon as I was 
safe in the corridor. The next day I waited on 
the amministratore, and told him all that had 
happened. My statement was corroborated by 
the vacant rope from which Gasparo had 
descended, and the burnt fragment by which I had 
been drawn up. The amministratore repeated 
my story to a prelate high in office; and while 
none, even of the sanpietrini, suspected that my 
enemy had come by his death in any unusual 
manner, the truth was whispered from palace to 
palace until it reached the Vatican. I received 
much sympathy, and such pecuniary assistance 
as enabled me to confront the future without 
fear. Since that time my fortunes have been 
various, and I have lived in many countries. 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up Waifs At Sea."/>
<p>
SOME little time elapsed, after the French 
gentleman's narrative was over, before any more 
visitors made their appearance. At last, there 
sauntered in slowly a light-haired melancholy 
man; very tall, very stout; miserably dressed 
in cast-off garments; carrying a carpenter's 
basket, and looking as if he never expected any 
such windfall of luck as a chance of using the 
tools inside it. Surveying Mr. Traveller with 
watery light-blue eyes, this dismal individual 
explained (in better language than might have 
been expected from his personal appearance) 
that he was in search of work; and that, finding 
none, he had come in to stare at Mr. Mopes for 
want of anything better to do. His name was 
Heavysides; his present address was the Peal 
of Bells down in the village; if Mr. Traveller 
had the means of putting a job in his hands, he 
would be thankful for the same; if not, he would 
ask leave to sit down and rest himself agreeably 
by looking at Mr. Mopes. 
</p>
<p>
Leave being granted, he sat down, and stared 
to his heart's content. He was not astonished, 
as the artist had been; he was not complacently 
impenetrable to surprise, like the Frenchman--
he was simply curious to know why the Hermit 
had shut himself up. "When he first skewered 
that blanket round him, what had he got to 
complain of?" asked Heavysides. "Whatever 
his grievance is, I could match it, I think." 
</p>
<p>
"Could you?" said Mr. Traveller. "By all 
means let us hear it." 
</p>
<p>
There has never yet been discovered a man 
with a grievance, who objected to mention it. 
The carpenter was no exception to this general 
human rule. He entered on his grievance, 
without a moment's hesitation, in these 
words: 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
I SHALL consider it in the light of a personal 
favour, at starting, if you will compose your 
spirits to hear a pathetic story, and if you will 
kindly picture me in your own mind as a baby 
five minutes old. 
</p>
<p>
Do I understand you to say that I am too big 
and too heavy to be pictured in anybody's mind 
as a baby? Perhaps I may be--but don't 
mention my weight again, if you please. My weight 
has been the grand misfortune of my life. It 
spoilt all my prospects (as you will presently 
hear) before I was two days old. 
</p>
<p>
My story begins thirty-one years ago, at 
eleven o'clock in the forenoon; and starts with 
the great mistake of my first appearance in this 
world, at sea, on board the merchant ship 
Adventure, Captain Gillop, five hundred tons 
burden, coppered, and carrying an experienced 
surgeon. 
</p>
<p>
In presenting myself to you (which I am now 
about to do) at that eventful period of my life, 
when I was from five to ten minutes old; and 
in withdrawing myself again from your notice 
(so as not to trouble you with more than a short 
story), before the time when I cut my first tooth, 
I need not hesitate to admit that I speak on 
hearsay knowledge only. It is knowledge, 
however, that may be relied on, for all that. My 
information comes from Captain Gillop, 
commander of The Adventure (who sent it to me in 
the form of a letter); from Mr. Jolly, 
experienced surgeon of The Adventure (who wrote 
it for me--most unfeelingly, as I think--in the 
shape of a humorous narrative); and from Mrs. 
Drabble, stewardess of The Adventure (who 
told it me by word of mouth). Those three 
persons were, in various degrees, spectators--I 
may say, astonished spectators--of the events 
which I have now to relate. 
</p>
<p>
The Adventure, at the time I speak of, was 
bound out from London to Australia. I 
suppose you know, without my telling you, that 
thirty years ago was long before the time of the 
gold-finding and the famous clipper ships. Building 
in the new colony, and sheep-farming far 
up inland, were the two main employments of 
those days; and the passengers on board our 
vessel were consequently builders or sheep-
farmers, almost to a man. 
</p>
<p>
A ship of five hundred tons, well loaded with 
cargo, doesn't offer first-rate accommodation to 
a large number of passengers. Not that the 
gentlefolks in the cabin had any great reason to 
complain. There, the passage-money, which 
was a good round sum, kept them what you call 
select. One or two berths, in this part of the 
ship, were even empty and going a begging, in 
consequence of there being only four cabin 
passengers. These are their names and 
descriptions: 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Sims, a middle-aged man, going out on 
a building speculation. Mr. Purling, a weakly 
young gentleman, sent on a long sea-voyage for 
the benefit of his health. Mr. and Mrs. 
Smallchild, a young married couple with a little 
independence, which Mr. Smallchild proposed to 
make a large one by sheep-farming. This 
gentleman was reported to the captain, as being 
very good company when on shore, But the 
sea altered him to a certain extent. When Mr. 
Smallchild was not sick, he was eating and 
drinking; and when he was not eating and 
drinking, he was fast asleep. He was perfectly 
patient and good-humoured, and wonderfully 
nimble at running into his cabin when the 
qualms took him on a sudden--but, as for his 
being good company, nobody heard him say ten 
words together all through the voyage. And 
no wonder. A man can't talk in the qualms; 
a man can't talk while he is eating and drinking; 
and a man can't talk when he is asleep. 
And that was Mr. Smallchild's life. As for Mrs. 
Smallchild, she kept her cabin from first to last. 
But you will hear more of her presently. 
</p>
<p>
These four cabin passengers, as I have already 
remarked, were well enough off for their 
accommodation. But the miserable people in the 
steerage--a poor place, at the best of times, on 
board The Adventure--were all huddled together, 
men and women and children, higgledy-piggledy, 
like sheep in a pen; except that they hadn't got 
the same quantity of fine fresh air to blow over 
them. They were artisans and farm-labourers 
who couldn't make it out in the old country. 
I have no information either of their exact 
numbers or of their names. It doesn't matter: 
there was only one family among them which 
need be mentioned particularly--namely, the 
family of the Heavysides. To wit, Simon 
Heavysides, intelligent and well educated, a 
carpenter by trade; Martha Heavysides, his 
wife; and seven little Heavysides, their 
unfortunate offspring.--My father and mother and 
brothers and sisters, did I understand you to 
say? Don't be in a hurry; I recommend you 
to wait a little before you make quite sure of 
that circumstance. 
</p>
<p>
Though I myself had not, perhaps--strictly 
speaking--come on board when the vessel left 
London, my ill-luck, as I firmly believe, had 
shipped in The Adventure to wait for me--and 
decided the nature of the voyage accordingly. 
Never was such a miserable time known. Stormy 
weather came down on us from all points of the 
compass, with intervals of light baffling winds, 
or dead calms. By the time The Adventure 
had been three months out, Captain Gillop's 
naturally sweet temper began to get soured. I 
leave you to say whether it was likely to be 
much improved by a piece of news which 
reached him from the region of the cabin, on 
the morning of the ninety-first day. It had 
fallen to a dead calm again; and the ship was 
rolling about helpless with her head all round 
the compass, when Mr. Jolly (from whose 
unfeeling narrative I repeat all conversations, 
exactly as they passed) came on deck to the 
captain, and addressed him in these words: 
</p>
<p>
"I've got some news that will rather surprise 
you," said Mr. Jolly, smiling and rubbing his 
hands. (Although the experienced surgeon has 
not shown much sympathy for my troubles, I 
won't deny that his disposition was as good as 
his name. To this day, no amount of bad 
weather or hard work can upset Mr. Jolly's 
temper.) 
</p>
<p>
"If it's news of a fair wind coming," grumbled 
the captain, "that would surprise me, on 
board this ship, I can promise you!" 
</p>
<p>
"It's not exactly a wind coming," said Mr. 
Jolly. "It's another cabin passenger." 
</p>
<p>
The captain looked round at the empty sea, 
with the land thousands of miles away, and with 
not a ship in sight--turned sharply on the 
experienced surgeon--eyed him hard--changed 
colour suddenly and asked what he meant. 
</p>
<p>
"I mean, there's a fifth cabin passenger 
coming on board," persisted Mr. Jolly, grinning 
from ear to ear--"introduced by Mrs. Smallchild--
likely to join us, I should say, towards evening--
size, nothing to speak of--sex, not known 
at present--manners and customs, probably 
squally." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you really mean it?" asked the captain, 
backing away, and turning paler and paler. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes; I do," answered Mr. Jolly, nodding 
hard at him. 
</p>
<p>
"Then, I'll tell you what," cried Captain 
Gillop, suddenly flying into a violent passion, 
"I won't have it! The infernal weather has 
worried me out of my life and soul already--
and I won't have it! Put it off, Jolly--tell her 
there isn't room enough for that sort of thing on 
board my vessel. What does she mean by taking 
us all in in this way? Shameful! shameful!" 
</p>
<p>
"No! no!" remonstrated Mr. Jolly. "Don't 
look at it in that light. It's her first child, 
poor thing. How should she know? Give her 
a little more experience, and I dare say--" 
</p>
<p>
"Where's her husband?" broke in the 
captain, with a threatening look. "I'll speak my 
mind to her husband, at any rate." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Jolly consulted his watch before he 
answered. 
</p>
<p>
"Half-past eleven," he said. "Let me 
consider a little. It's Mr. Smallchild's regular time 
just now for squaring accounts with the sea. 
He'll have done in a quarter of an hour. In five 
minutes more, he'll be fast asleep. At one o'clock, 
he'll eat a hearty lunch, and go to sleep again. At 
half-past two, he'll square accounts as before--
and so on, till night. You'll make nothing of Mr. 
Smallchild, captain. Extraordinary man--wastes 
tissue, and repairs it again perpetually, in the 
most astonishing manner. If we are another 
month at sea, I believe we shall bring him into 
port totally comatose.--Hallo! What do you  
want?" 
</p>
<p>
The steward's mate had approached the quarter 
deck while the doctor was speaking. Was 
it a curious coincidence? This man also was 
grinning from ear to ear, exactly like Mr. Jolly. 
</p>
<p>
"You're wanted in the steerage, sir," said 
the steward's mate to the doctor. "A woman 
taken bad, name of Heavysides." 
</p>
<p>
"Nonsense!" cried Mr. Jolly. "Ha! ha! ha! 
 You don't mean--Eh?" 
</p>
<p>
"That's it, sir, sure enough," said the 
steward's mate, in the most positive manner. 
</p>
<p>
Captain Gillop looked all round him, in 
silent desperation, lost his sea-legs for the 
first time these twenty years, staggered back 
till he was brought up all standing by the side 
of his own vessel, dashed his fist on the 
bulwark, and found language to express himself in, 
at the same moment. 
</p>
<p>
"This ship is bewitched," said the captain, 
wildly. "Stop!" he called out, recovering 
himself a little, as the doctor bustled away to the 
steerage. "Stop! If it's true, Jolly, send her 
husband here aft to me. Damme, I'll have it 
out with one of the husbands!" said the captain, 
shaking his fist viciously at the empty air. 
</p>
<p>
Ten minutes passed; and then, there came 
staggering towards the captain, tottering this 
way and that with the rolling of the becalmed 
vessel, a long, lean, melancholy, light-haired 
man, with a Roman nose, a watery blue eye, and 
a complexion profusely spotted with large 
brown freckles. This was Simon Heavysides, 
the intelligent carpenter, with the wife and the 
family of seven small children on board. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh! you're the man, are you?" said the 
captain. 
</p>
<p>
The ship lurched heavily; and Simon Heavysides 
staggered away with a run to the opposite 
side of the deck, as if he preferred going straight 
overboard into the sea, to answering the 
captain's question. 
</p>
<p>
"You're the man--are you?" repeated the 
captain, following him, seizing him by the collar, 
and pinning him up fiercely against the bulwark. 
"It's your wife--is it? You infernal rascal!  
what do you mean by turning my ship into a 
Lying-in Hospital? You have committed an act 
of mutiny; or, if it isn't mutiny, it's next door 
to it. I've put a man in irons for less! I've 
more than half a mind to put you in irons! 
Hold up, you slippery lubber! What do you 
mean by bringing passengers I don't bargain 
for on board my vessel? What have you got 
to say for yourself, before I clap the irons on 
you?" 
</p>
<p>
"Nothing, sir," answered Simon Heavysides, 
with the meekest connubial resignation in his 
looks and manners. "As for the punishment 
you mentioned just now, sir," continued Simon, 
"I wish to say--having seven children more  
than I know how to provide for, and an eighth 
coming to make things worse--I respectfully  
wish to say, sir, that my mind is in irons 
already; and I don't know as it will make much 
difference if you put my body in irons along 
with it." 
</p>
<p>
The captain mechanically let go of the 
carpenter's collar: the mild despair of the man 
melted him in spite of himself. 
</p>
<p>
"Why did you come to sea? Why didn't 
you wait ashore till it was all over?" asked the 
captain, as sternly as he could. 
</p>
<p>
"It's no use waiting, sir," remarked Simon. 
"In our line of life as soon as it's over, it begins 
again. There's no end to it that I can see," 
said the miserable carpenter, after a moment's 
meek consideration--"except the grave." 
</p>
<p>
"Who's talking about the grave?" cried Mr. 
Jolly, coming up at that moment. "It's births 
we've got to do with on board this vessel--not 
burials. Captain Gillop, this woman, Martha 
Heavysides, can't be left in your crowded 
steerage, in her present condition. She must be 
moved off into one of the empty berths--and 
the sooner the better, I can tell you!" 
</p>
<p>
The captain began to look savage again. A 
steerage passenger in one of his "state-rooms" 
was a nautical anomaly subversive of all discipline. 
He eyed the carpenter once more, as 
if he was mentally measuring him for a set of 
irons. 
</p>
<p>
"I'm very sorry, sir," Simon remarked, 
politely--"very sorry that any inadvertence of mine 
or Mrs. Heavyside's--" 
</p>
<p>
"Take your long carcase and your long tongue 
forward!" thundered the captain. "When 
talking will mend matters, I'll send for you 
again. Give your own orders, Jolly," he went on, 
resignedly, as Simon staggered off. "Turn the 
ship into a nursery as soon as you like!" 
</p>
<p>
Five minutes later--so expeditious was Mr. 
Jolly--Martha Heavysides appeared horizontally 
on deck, shrouded in blankets, and 
supported by three men. When this interesting 
procession passed the captain, he shrank aside 
from it with as vivid an appearance of horror 
as if a wild bull was being carried by him 
instead of a British matron. The sleeping berths 
below opened on either side out of the main 
cabin. On the left-hand side (looking towards 
the ship's bowsprit) was Mrs. Smallchild. On 
the right-hand side, opposite to her, the doctor 
established Mrs. Heavysides. A partition of 
canvas was next run up, entirely across the 
main cabin. The smaller of the two temporary 
rooms thus made, lay nearest the stairs leading 
on deck, and was left free to the public. The 
larger was kept sacred to the doctor and his 
mysteries. When an old clothes-basket, emptied, 
cleaned, and comfortably lined with blankets (to 
serve for a make-shift cradle), had been, in due 
course of time, carried into the inner cabin, 
and had been placed midway between the two 
sleeping-berths, so as to be easily producible 
when wanted, the outward and visible preparations 
of Mr. Jolly were complete; the male 
passengers had all taken refuge on deck; and 
the doctor and the stewardess were left in 
undisturbed possession of the lower regions. 
</p>
<p>
While it was still early in the afternoon, the 
weather changed for the better. For once in a 
way, the wind came from the fair quarter; and 
The Adventure bowled along pleasantly before it 
almost on an even keel. Captain Gillop mixed 
with the little group of male passengers on the 
quarter-deck, restored to his sweetest temper; 
and set them his customary example, after dinner, 
of smoking a cigar. 
</p>
<p>
"If this fine weather lasts, gentlemen," he 
said, "we shall make out very well with our 
meals up here; and we shall have our two small 
extra cabin passengers christened on dry land in a 
week's time, if their mothers approve of it. 
How do you feel in your mind, sir, about your 
good lady?" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Smallchild (to whom the inquiry was 
addressed) had his points of external personal 
resemblance to Simon Heavysides. He was 
neither so tall, nor so lean certainly--but he, 
too, had a Roman nose, and light hair, and 
watery blue eyes. With careful reference to his 
peculiar habits at sea, he had been placed 
conveniently close to the bulwark, and had been 
raised on a heap of old sails and cushions, so 
that he could easily get his head over the ship's 
side when occasion required. The food and 
drink which assisted in "restoring his tissue," 
when he was not asleep and not "squaring 
accounts with the sea," lay close to his hand. It 
was then a little after three o'clock; and the 
snore with which Mr. Smallchild answered the 
captain's inquiry showed that he had got round 
again, with the regularity of clockwork, to the 
period of the day when he recruited himself with 
sleep. 
</p>
<p>
"What an insensible blockhead that man is!" 
said Mr. Sims, the middle-aged passenger; looking 
across the deck contemptuously at Mr. 
Smallchild. 
</p>
<p>
"If the sea had the same effect on you 
that it has on him," retorted the invalid 
passenger, Mr. Purling, "you would be just as 
insensible yourself." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Purling (who was a man of sentiment) 
disagreed with Mr. Sims (who was a man of 
business), on every conceivable subject, all 
through the voyage. Before, however, they 
could continue the dispute about Mr. Smallchild, 
the doctor surprised them by appearing from the 
cabin. 
</p>
<p>
"Any news from below, Jolly?" asked the 
captain, anxiously. 
</p>
<p>
"None whatever," answered the doctor. 
"I've come to idle the afternoon away up here, 
along with the rest of you." 
</p>
<p>
As events turned out, Mr. Jolly idled away 
an hour and a half exactly. At the end of that 
time, Mrs. Drabble the stewardess appeared 
with a face of mystery, and whispered nervously 
to the doctor: 
</p>
<p>
"Please to step below directly, sir." 
</p>
<p>
"Which of them is it?" asked Mr. Jolly. 
</p>
<p>
"Both of them," answered Mrs. Drabble, 
emphatically. 
</p>
<p>
The doctor looked grave; the stewardess 
looked frightened. The two immediately 
disappeared together. 
</p>
<p>
"I suppose, gentlemen," said Captain Gillop, 
addressing Mr. Purling, Mr. Sims, and the first 
mate, who had just joined the party, "I 
suppose it's only fit and proper, in the turn things 
have taken, to shake up Mr. Smallchild? And 
I don't doubt but what we ought to have the 
other husband handy, as a sort of polite attention 
under the circumstances. Pass the word 
forward, there, for Simon Heavysides. Mr. 
Smallchild, sir! rouse up! Here's your good 
lady--Hang me, gentlemen, if I know exactly 
how to put it to him." 
</p>
<p>
"Yes. Thank you," said Mr. Smallchild, 
opening his eyes drowsily. "Biscuit and cold 
bacon, as usual--when I'm ready. I'm not 
ready yet. Thank you. Good afternoon." Mr. 
Smallchild closed his eyes again, and became, in 
the doctor's phrase, "totally comatose." 
</p>
<p>
Before Captain Gillop could hit on any new 
plan for rousing this imperturbable passenger, 
Simon Heavysides once more approached the 
quarter-deck. 
</p>
<p>
"I spoke a little sharp to you, just now, my 
man," said the captain, "being worried in my 
mind by what's going on on board this vessel. 
But I'll make it up to you, never fear. Here's 
your wife in, what they call, an interesting situation. 
It's only right you should be within easy 
hail of her. I look upon you, Heavysides, as a 
steerage-passenger in difficulties; and I freely 
give you leave to stop here along with us till 
it's all over." 
</p>
<p>
"You are very good, sir," said Simon; "and 
I am indeed thankful to you and to these 
gentlemen. But, please to remember, I have seven 
children already in the steerage--and there's 
nobody left to mind 'em but me. My wife has 
got over it uncommonly well, sir, on seven 
previous occasions--and I don't doubt but what 
she'll conduct herself in a similar manner on the 
eighth. It will be a satisfaction to her mind, 
Captain Gillop and gentlemen, if she knows I'm 
out of the way, and minding the children. For 
which reason, I respectfully take my leave." 
With those words, Simon made his bow, and 
returned to his family. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, gentlemen, these two husbands take 
it easy enough, at any rate!" said the captain. 
"One of them is used to it, to be sure; and the 
other is--" 
</p>
<p>
Here a banging of cabin doors below, and a 
hurrying of footsteps, startled the speaker and his 
audience into momentary silence and attention. 
</p>
<p>
"Ease her with the helm, Williamson!" said 
Captain Gillop, addressing the man who was 
steering the vessel. "In my opinion, gentlemen, 
the less the ship pitches the better, in the 
turn things are taking now." 
</p>
<p>
The afternoon wore on into evening, and 
evening into night. Mr. Smallchild performed 
the daily ceremonies of his nautical existence as 
punctually as usual. He was aroused to a 
sense of Mrs. Smallchild's situation when 
he took his biscuit and bacon; lost the sense 
again when the time came round for "squaring 
his accounts;" recovered it in the interval 
which ensued before he went to sleep; lost it 
again, as a matter of course, when his eyes 
closed once more--and so on through the evening 
and early night. Simon Heavysides received 
messages occasionally (through the captain's 
care), telling him to keep his mind easy; 
returned messages mentioning that his mind was 
easy, and that the children were pretty quiet, 
but never approached the deck in his own 
person. Mr. Jolly now and then showed 
himself--said "All right,--no news," took a little 
light refreshment, and disappeared again, as 
cheerful as ever. The fair breeze still held; 
the captain's temper remained unruffled; the 
man at the helm eased the vessel, from time to 
time, with the most anxious consideration. Ten 
o'clock came: the moon rose and shone 
superbly; the nightly grog made its appearance 
on the quarter-deck; the captain gave the 
passengers the benefit of his company; and still 
nothing happened. Twenty minutes more of 
suspense slowly succeeded each other--and then, 
at last, Mr. Jolly was seen suddenly to ascend 
the cabin stairs. 
</p>
<p>
To the amazement of the little group on the 
quarter-deck, the doctor held Mrs. Drabble 
the stewardess fast by the arm, and, without 
taking the slightest notice of the captain or the 
passengers, placed her on the nearest seat he 
could find. As he did this, his face became 
visible in the moonlight, and displayed to the 
startled spectators an expression of blank 
consternation. 
</p>
<p>
"Compose yourself, Mrs. Drabble," said the 
doctor, in tones of unmistakable alarm. "Keep 
quiet, and let the air blow over you. Collect 
yourself, ma'am--for Heaven's sake, collect 
yourself!" 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Drabble made no answer. She beat her 
hands vacantly on her knees, and stared straight 
before her, like a woman panic-stricken. 
</p>
<p>
"What's wrong?" asked the captain, setting 
down his glass of grog in dismay. "Anything 
amiss with those two unfortunate women?" 
</p>
<p>
"Nothing," said the doctor. "Both doing 
admirably well." 
</p>
<p>
"Anything queer with their babies?" 
continued the captain. "Are there more than you 
bargained for, Jolly? Twins, for instance?" 
</p>
<p>
"No! no!" replied Mr. Jolly, impatiently. 
"A baby apiece--both boys--both in first-rate 
condition. Judge for yourselves," added the 
doctor, as the two new cabin-passengers tried 
their lungs, below, for the first time, and found 
that they answered their purpose in the most 
satisfactory manner. 
</p>
<p>
"What the devil's amiss then with you and 
Mrs. Drabble?" persisted the captain, beginning 
to lose his temper again. 
</p>
<p>
"Mrs. Drabble and I are two innocent people, 
and we have got into the most dreadful scrape 
that ever you heard of!" was Mr. Jolly's 
startling answer. 
</p>
<p>
The captain, followed by Mr. Purling and Mr. 
Sims, approached the doctor with looks of horror. 
Even the man at the wheel stretched himself 
over it as far as he could to hear what was 
coming next. The only uninterested person 
present was Mr. Smallchild. His time had come 
round for going to sleep again, and he was 
snoring peacefully, with his biscuit and bacon 
close beside him, 
</p>
<p>
"Let's hear the worst of it at once, Jolly," 
said the captain, a little impatiently. 
</p>
<p>
The doctor paid no heed to this request. His 
whole attention was absorbed by Mrs. Drabble. 
"Are you better now, ma'am?" he asked, 
anxiously. 
</p>
<p>
"No better in my mind," answered Mrs. 
Drabble, beginning to beat her knees again. 
"Worse, if anything." 
</p>
<p>
"Listen to me," said Mr. Jolly, coaxingly. 
"I'll put the whole case over again to you, in a 
few plain questions. You'll find it all come 
back to your memory, if you only follow me 
attentively, and if you take time to think and 
collect yourself before you attempt to answer." 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Drabble bowed her head in speechless 
submission--and listened. Everybody else on 
the quarter-deck listened, except the impenetrable 
Mr. Smallchild. 
</p>
<p>
"Now, ma'am!" said the doctor. "Our 
troubles began in Mrs. Heavyside's cabin, 
which is situated on the starboard side of the ship?" 
</p>
<p>
"They did, sir," replied Mrs. Drabble. 
</p>
<p>
"Good! We went backwards and forwards, 
an infinite number of times, between Mrs. 
Heavysides (starboard) and Mrs. Smallchild 
(larboard)--but we found that Mrs. Heavysides, 
having got the start, kept it--and when I called 
out, 'Mrs. Drabble! here's a chopping boy for 
you: come and take him!'--I called out 
starboard, didn't I?" 
</p>
<p>
"Starboard, sir--I'll take my oath of it," said 
Mrs. Drabble. 
</p>
<p>
"Good, again! 'Here is a chopping boy,' 
I said. 'Take him, ma'am, and make him 
comfortable in the cradle.' And you took him, and 
made him comfortable in the cradle, accordingly? 
Now, where was the cradle?" 
</p>
<p>
"In the main cabin, sir," replied Mrs. 
Drabble. 
</p>
<p>
"Just so! In the main cabin, because we 
hadn't got room for it in either of the sleeping-
cabins. You put the starboard baby (otherwise 
Heavysides) in the clothes-basket cradle in the 
main cabin. Good, once more. How was the 
cradle placed?" 
</p>
<p>
"Crosswise to the ship, sir," said Mrs. Drabble. 
</p>
<p>
"Crosswise to the ship? That is to say, 
with one side longwise towards the stern of the 
vessel, and one side longwise towards the bows. 
Bear that in mind--and now follow me a little 
farther. No! no! don't say you can't, and 
your head's in a whirl. My next question will 
steady it. Carry your mind on half an hour, 
Mrs. Drabble. At the end of half an hour, you 
heard my voice again; and my voice called out--
'Mrs. Drabble! here's another chopping boy 
for you: come and take him!'--and you came 
and took him larboard, didn't you?" 
</p>
<p>
"Larboard, sir, I don't deny it," answered Mrs. 
Drabble. 
</p>
<p>
"Better and better! 'Here is another 
chopping boy,' I said. 'Take him, ma'am, and make 
him comfortable in the cradle, along with 
number one.' And you took the larboard baby 
(otherwise Smallchild), and made him 
comfortable in the cradle along with the starboard 
baby (otherwise Heavysides), accordingly? 
Now, what happened after that?" 
</p>
<p>
"Don't ask me, sir!" exclaimed Mrs. Drabble, 
losing her self-control, and wringing her 
hands desperately. 
</p>
<p>
"Steady, ma'am! I'll put it to you as plain 
as print. Steady! and listen to me. Just as 
you had made the larboard baby comfortable, I 
had occasion to send you into the starboard (or 
Heavysides) cabin, to fetch something which I 
wanted in the larboard (or Smallchild) cabin; I 
kept you there a little while along with me; I 
left you, and went into the Heavysides cabin, 
and called to you to bring me something I wanted 
out of the Smallchild cabin, but before you 
got half way across the main cabin, I said 'No; 
stop where you are, and I'll come to you;' 
immediately after which, Mrs. Smallchild alarmed 
you, and you came across to me of your own 
accord; and, thereupon, I stopped you in the 
main cabin, and said, 'Mrs. Drabble, your 
mind's getting confused, sit down and collect 
your scattered intellects; and you sat down, 
and tried to collect them--?" 
</p>
<p>
("And couldn't, sir," interposed Mrs. Drabble, 
parenthetically. "Oh, my head! my head!") 
</p>
<p>
--"And tried to collect your scattered 
intellects, and couldn't?" continued the doctor. 
"And the consequence was, when I came out 
from the Smallchild cabin to see how you were 
getting on, I found you with the clothes-basket 
cradle hoisted up on the cabin table, staring 
down at the babies inside with your mouth 
dropped open, and both your hands twisted in 
your hair? And when I said, 'Anything wrong 
with either of those two fine boys, Mrs. Drabble?' 
you caught me by the coat-collar, and whispered 
in my right ear these words: 'Lord save us 
and help us, Mr. Jolly, I've confused the two 
babies in my mind, and I don't know which is 
which!'" 
</p>
<p>
"And I don't know now!" cried Mrs. Drabble, 
hysterically. "Oh, my head! my head! I 
don't know now!" 
</p>
<p>
"Captain Gillop and gentlemen," said Mr. 
Jolly, wheeling round and addressing his audience 
with the composure of sheer despair, "that is 
the Scrape--and, if you ever heard of a worse 
one, I'll trouble you to compose this miserable 
woman by mentioning it immediately." 
</p>
<p>
Captain Gillop looked at Mr. Purling and Mr. 
Sims. Mr. Purling and Mr. Sims looked at 
Captain Gillop. They were all three thunder-
struck--and no wonder. 
</p>
<p>
"Can't you throw any light on it, Jolly?" 
inquired the captain, who was the first to recover 
himself. 
</p>
<p>
"If you knew what I have had to do below, 
you wouldn't ask me such a question as that," 
replied the doctor. "Remember that I have 
had the lives of two women and two children to 
answer for--remember that I have been cramped 
up in two small sleeping-cabins, with hardly 
room to turn round in, and just light enough 
from two miserable little lamps to see my hand 
before me--remember the professional difficulties 
of the situation, the ship rolling about under 
me all the while, and the stewardess to compose 
into the bargain;--bear all that in mind, will you, 
and then tell me how much spare time I had on 
my hands for comparing two boys together inch 
by inch--two boys born at night, within half an 
hour of each other, on board a ship at sea. Ha! 
ha! I only wonder the mothers and the boys 
and the doctor are all five of them alive to tell 
the story!" 
</p>
<p>
"No marks on one or other of them, that 
happened to catch your eye?" asked Mr. Sims. 
</p>
<p>
"They must have been strongish marks to 
catch my eye in the light I had to work by, 
and in the professional difficulties I had to 
grapple with," said the doctor. "I saw they 
were both straight, well-formed children--and 
that's all I saw!" 
</p>
<p>
"Are their infant features sufficiently 
developed to indicate a family likeness?" inquired 
Mr. Purling. "Should you say they took after 
their fathers or their mothers?" 
</p>
<p>
"Both of them have light eyes, and light 
hair--such as it is," replied Mr. Jolly, doggedly. 
"Judge for yourself." 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Smallchild has light eyes and light hair," 
remarked Mr. Sims. 
</p>
<p>
"And Simon Heavysides has light eyes and 
light hair," rejoined Mr. Purling. 
</p>
<p>
"I should recommend waking Mr. Smallchild, 
and sending for Heavysides, and letting the two 
fathers toss up for it," suggested Mr. Sims. 
</p>
<p>
"The parental feeling is not to be trifled with 
in that heartless manner," retorted Mr. Purling. 
"I should recommend trying the Voice of 
Nature." 
</p>
<p>
"What may that be, sir?" inquired Captain 
Gillop, with great curiosity. 
</p>
<p>
"The maternal instinct," replied Mr. Purling. 
"The mother's intuitive knowledge of her own 
child." 
</p>
<p>
"Ay, ay!" said the captain. "Well 
thought of. What do you say, Jolly, to the 
Voice of Nature?" 
</p>
<p>
The doctor held up his hand impatiently. He 
was engaged in resuming the effort to rouse 
Mrs. Drabble's memory by a system of amateur 
cross-examination, with the unsatisfactory 
result of confusing her more hopelessly than ever. 
Could she put the cradle back, in her own mind, 
into its original position? No. Could she 
remember whether she laid the starboard baby 
(otherwise Heavysides) on the side of the cradle 
nearest the stern of the ship, or nearest the bows? 
No. Could she remember any better about the 
larboard baby (otherwise Smallchild)? No. 
Why did she move the cradle on to the cabin 
table, and so bewilder herself additionally, when 
she was puzzled already? Because it came over 
her, on a sudden, that she had forgotten, in the 
dreadful confusion of the time, which was which; 
and of course she wanted to look closer at them, 
and see; and she couldn't see; and to her dying 
day she should never forgive herself; and let 
them throw her overboard, for a miserable wretch, 
if they liked,--and so on, till the persevering 
doctor was wearied out at last, and gave up 
Mrs. Drabble, and gave up, with her, the whole 
case. 
</p>
<p>
"I see nothing for it but the Voice of 
Nature," said the captain, holding fast to Mr. 
Purling's idea. "Try it, Jolly--you can but 
try it." 
</p>
<p>
"Something must be done,' said the doctor. 
"I can't leave the women alone any longer; 
and the moment I get below they will both ask 
for their babies. Wait here, till you're fit to be 
seen, Mrs. Drabble, and then follow me. Voice 
of Nature!" added Mr. Jolly, contemptuously, 
as he descended the cabin stairs. "Oh yes, 
I'll try it--much good the Voice of Nature will 
do us, gentlemen. You shall judge for 
yourselves." 
</p>
<p>
Favoured by the night, Mr. Jolly cunningly 
turned down the dim lamps in the sleeping 
cabins to a mere glimmer, on the pretext that 
light was bad for his patients' eyes. He then 
took up the first of the two unlucky babies that 
came to hand, marked the clothes in which it 
was wrapped with a blot of ink, and carried it 
in to Mrs. Smallchild, choosing her cabin 
merely because he happened to be nearest to it. 
The second baby (distinguished by having no 
mark) was taken by Mrs. Drabble to Mrs. 
Heavysides. For a certain time, the two mothers and 
the two babies were left together. They were 
then separated again by medical order; and 
were afterwards reunited, with the difference 
that the marked baby went on this occasion to 
Mrs. Heavysides, and the unmarked baby to 
Mrs. Smallchild--the result, in the obscurity of 
the sleeping cabins, proving to be that one baby 
did just as well as the other, and that the Voice 
of Nature was (as Mr. Jolly had predicted) 
totally incompetent to settle the existing 
difficulty. 
</p>
<p>
"While night serves us, Captain Gillop, we 
shall do very well," said the doctor, after he had 
duly reported the failure of Mr. Purling's 
suggested experiment. "But when morning comes, 
and daylight shows the difference between the 
children, we must be prepared with a course of 
some kind. If the two mothers, below, get the 
slightest suspicion of the case as it really stands, 
the nervous shock of the discovery may do 
dreadful mischief. They must be kept deceived, 
till they're up and well again, in the interests of 
their own health. We must choose a baby for 
each of them when to-morrow comes, and then 
hold to the choice, till the mothers are up 
again. The question is, who's to take the 
responsibility. I don't usually stick at trifles--
but I candidly admit that I'm afraid of it." 
</p>
<p>
"I decline meddling in the matter, on the 
ground that I am a perfect stranger," said Mr. 
Sims. 
</p>
<p>
"And I object to interfere, from precisely 
similar motives," added Mr. Purling; agreeing 
for the first time with a proposition that 
emanated from his natural enemy all through the 
voyage. 
</p>
<p>
"Wait a minute, gentlemen," said Captain 
Gillop. "I've got this difficult matter, as I 
think, in its right bearings. We must make a 
clean breast of it to the husbands, and let them 
take the responsibility." 
</p>
<p>
"I believe they won't accept it," observed 
Mr. Sims. 
</p>
<p>
"And I believe they will," asserted Mr. 
Purling, relapsing into his old habits. 
</p>
<p>
"If they won't," said the captain, firmly, 
"I'm master on board this ship--and, as sure 
as my name's Thomas Gillop, I'll take the 
responsibility!" 
</p>
<p>
This courageous declaration settled all 
difficulties for the time being; and a council was 
held to decide on future proceedings. It 
was resolved to remain passive until the next 
morning, on the last faint chance that a few 
hours' sleep might compose Mrs. Drabble's 
bewildered memory. The babies were to be 
moved into the main cabin before the daylight 
grew bright--or, in other words, before Mrs. 
Smallchild or Mrs. Heavysides could identify the 
infant who had passed the night with her for 
the time being. The doctor and the captain 
were to be assisted by Mr. Purling, Mr. Sims, 
and the first mate, in the capacity of witnesses; 
and the assembly so constituted was to meet, in 
consideration of the emergency of the case, at 
six o'clock in the morning, punctually. 
</p>
<p>
At six: o'clock accordingly, with the weather 
fine, and the wind still fair, the proceedings 
began. For the last time Mr. Jolly cross-
examined Mrs. Drabble, assisted by the 
captain, and supervised by the witnesses. Nothing 
whatever was elicited from the unfortunate 
stewardess. The doctor pronounced her confusion 
to be chronic, and the captain and the 
witnesses unanimously agreed with him. 
</p>
<p>
The next experiment tried was the revelation 
of the true state of the case to the husbands. 
Mr. Smallchild happened, on this occasion, to be 
"squaring his accounts" for the morning; and 
the first articulate words which escaped him 
in reply to the disclosure, were: "Devilled 
biscuit and anchovy paste." Further perseverance 
merely elicited an impatient request that they 
would "pitch him overboard at once, and the 
two babies along with him." Serious 
remonstrance was tried next, with no better effect. 
"Settle it how you like," said Mr. Smallchild, 
faintly. "Do you leave it to me, sir, as 
commander of this vessel?" asked Captain Gillop. 
(No answer.) "Nod your head, sir, if you 
can't speak." Mr. Smallchild nodded his head 
roundwise on his pillow--and fell asleep. 
Does that count for leave to me to act?" 
asked Captain Gillop of the witnesses. And the 
witnesses answered, decidedly, Yes. 
</p>
<p>
The ceremony was then repeated with Simon 
Heavysides, who responded, as became so 
intelligent a man, with a proposal of his own, for 
solving the difficulty. 
</p>
<p>
"Captain Gillop and gentlemen," said the 
carpenter, with fluent and melancholy politeness, 
"I should wish to consider Mr. Smallchild 
before myself in this matter. I am quite willing 
to part with my baby (whichever he is); and I 
respectfully propose that Mr. Smallchild should 
take both the children, and so make quite sure 
that he has really got possession of his own 
son." 
</p>
<p>
The only immediate objection to this ingenious 
proposition was started by the doctor; who 
sarcastically inquired of Simon "what he thought 
Mrs. Heavysides would say to it?" The 
carpenter confessed that this consideration had 
escaped him; and that Mrs. Heavysides was 
only too likely to be an irremovable obstacle in 
the way of the proposed arrangement. The 
witnesses all thought so too; and Heavysides and 
his idea were dismissed together, after Simon 
had first gratefully expressed his entire readiness 
to leave it all to the captain. 
</p>
<p>
"Very well, gentlemen," said Captain Gillop. 
"As commander on board, I reckon next after 
the husbands in the matter of responsibility--
I've considered this difficulty in all its bearings--
and I'm prepared to deal with it. The Voice of 
Nature (which you proposed, Mr. Purling) 
has been found to fail. The tossing up for it 
(which you proposed, Mr. Sims) doesn't square 
altogether with my notions of what's right in a 
very serious business. No, sir! I've got my 
own plan; and I'm now about to try it. Follow 
me below, gentlemen, to the steward's 
pantry." 
</p>
<p>
The witnesses looked round on one another 
in the profoundest astonishment--and followed. 
</p>
<p>
"Saunders," said the captain, addressing the 
steward. "Bring out the scales." 
</p>
<p>
The scales were of the ordinary kitchen sort, 
with a tin tray, on one side, to hold the 
commodity to be weighed, and a stout iron slab on 
the other to support the weights. Saunders 
placed these scales upon a neat little pantry 
table, fitted on the ball-and-socket principle, so 
as to save the breaking of crockery by swinging 
with the motion of the ship. 
</p>
<p>
"Put a clean duster in the tray," said the 
captain. "Doctor," he continued, when this 
had been done, "shut the doors of the sleeping-
berths (for fear of the women hearing anything); 
and oblige me by bringing those two babies in 
here." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, sir!" exclaimed Mrs. Drabble, who had 
been peeping guiltily at the proceedings--"oh, 
don't hurt the little dears! If anybody suffers, 
let it be me!" 
</p>
<p>
"Hold your tongue, if you please, ma'am," 
said the captain. "And keep the secret of 
these proceedings, if you wish to keep your 
place. If the ladies ask for their children, say 
they will have them in ten minutes' time." 
</p>
<p>
The doctor came in, and set down the clothes-
basket cradle on the pantry floor. Captain 
Gillop immediately put on his spectacles, and 
closely examined the two unconscious innocents 
who lay beneath him. 
</p>
<p>
"Six of one and half a dozen of the other," 
said the captain. "I don't see any difference 
between them. Wait a bit, though! Yes, I do. 
One's a bald baby. Very good. We'll begin 
with that one. Doctor, strip the bald baby, 
and put him in the scales." 
</p>
<p>
The bald baby protested--in his own language--
but in vain. In two minutes he was flat on 
his back in the tin tray, with the clean duster 
under him to take the chill off. 
</p>
<p>
"Weigh him accurately, Saunders," continued 
the captain. "Weigh him, if necessary, to an 
eighth of an ounce. Gentlemen! watch this 
proceeding closely: it's a very important one." 
</p>
<p>
While the steward was weighing and the 
witnesses were watching, Captain Gillop asked his 
first mate for the log-book of the ship, and for 
pen and ink. 
</p>
<p>
"How much, Saunders?" asked the captain, 
opening the book. 
</p>
<p>
"Seven pounds, one ounce, and a quarter," 
answered the steward. 
</p>
<p>
"Right, gentlemen?" pursued the captain. 
</p>
<p>
"Quite right," said the witnesses. 
</p>
<p>
"Bald child--distinguished as Number One--
weight, seven pounds, one ounce, and a quarter 
(avoirdupois)," repeated the captain, writing 
down the entry in the log-book. "Very good. 
We'll put the bald baby back now, doctor; and 
try the hairy one next." 
</p>
<p>
The hairy one protested--also in his own 
language--and also in vain. 
</p>
<p>
"How much, Saunders?" asked the captain. 
</p>
<p>
"Six pounds, fourteen ounces, and three-
quarters," replied the steward. 
</p>
<p>
"Right, gentlemen?" inquired the captain. 
</p>
<p>
"Quite right," answered the witnesses. 
</p>
<p>
"Hairy child--distinguished as Number Two, 
weight six pounds, fourteen ounces, and three-
quarters (avoirdupois)," repeated, and wrote, the 
captain. "Much obliged to you, Jolly--that 
will do. When you have got the other baby 
back in the cradle, tell Mrs. Drabble neither of 
them must be taken out of it, till further orders; 
and then be so good as to join me and these 
gentlemen on deck. If anything of a discussion 
rises up among us, we won't run the risk of 
being heard in the sleeping-berths." With these 
words Captain Gillop led the way on deck, and 
the first mate followed with the log-book and 
the pen and ink. 
</p>
<p>
"Now, gentlemen," began the captain, when 
the doctor had joined the assembly, "my first 
mate will open these proceedings by reading 
from the log a statement which I have written 
myself, respecting this business, from beginning 
to end. If you find it all equally correct with 
the statement of what the two children weigh, 
I'll trouble you to sign it, in your quality of 
witnesses, on the spot." 
</p>
<p>
The first mate read the narrative, and the 
witnesses signed it, as perfectly correct. 
Captain Gillop then cleared his throat, and 
addressed his expectant audience in these words: 
</p>
<p>
"You'll all agree with me, gentlemen, that 
justice is justice; and that like must to like. 
Here's my ship of five hundred tons, fitted with 
her spars accordingly. Say, she's a schooner of 
a hundred and fifty tons, the veriest landsman 
among you, in that case, wouldn't put such 
masts as these into her. Say, on the other hand, 
she's an Indiaman of a thousand tons, would 
our spars (excellent good sticks as they are, 
gentlemen) be suitable for a vessel of that 
capacity? Certainly not. A schooner's spars to 
a schooner, and a ship's spars to a ship, in fit 
and fair proportion. In this serious difficulty, 
I take my stand on that principle. And my 
decision is: give the heaviest of the two babies 
to the heaviest of the two women; and let the 
lightest then fall, as a matter of course, to the 
other. In a week's time, if this weather holds, 
we shall all (please God) be in port; and if there's 
a better way out of this mess than my way, the 
parsons and lawyers ashore may find it, and 
welcome." 
</p>
<p>
With those words the captain closed his 
oration; and the assembled council immediately 
sanctioned the proposal submitted to them, with 
all the unanimity of men who had no idea of 
their own to set up in opposition. Mr. Jolly 
was next requested (as the only available 
authority) to settle the question of weight 
between Mrs. Smallchild and Mrs. Heavysides, 
and decided it, without a moment's hesitation, 
in favour of the carpenter's wife, on the 
indisputable ground that she was the tallest and the 
stoutest woman of the two. Thereupon, the 
bald baby, "distinguished as Number One," 
was taken into Mrs. Heavysides' cabin; and the 
hairy baby, "distinguished as Number Two," 
was accorded to Mrs. Smallchild; the Voice of 
Nature, neither in the one case nor in the other, 
raising the slightest objection to the captain's 
principle of distribution. Before seven o'clock, 
Mr. Jolly reported that the mothers and sons, 
larboard and starboard, were as happy and 
comfortable as any four people on board ship could 
possibly wish to be; and the captain thereupon 
dismissed the council with these parting 
words: 
</p>
<p>
"We'll get the studding-sails on the ship now, 
gentlemen, and make the best of our way to 
port. Breakfast, Saunders, in half an hour, and 
plenty of it! I doubt if that unfortunate Mrs. 
Drabble has heard the last of this business yet. 
We must all lend a hand, gentlemen, and pull 
her through if we can. In other respects, the 
job's over, so far as we are concerned; and 
the parsons and the lawyers must settle it 
ashore." 
</p>
<p>
But, the parsons and the lawyers did nothing 
of the sort, for the plain reason that nothing was 
to be done. In ten days the ship was in port, 
and the news was broken to the two mothers. 
Each one of the two adored her baby, after ten 
days' experience of it--and each one of the two 
was in Mrs. Drabble's condition of not knowing 
which was which. Every test was tried. First, 
the test by the doctor, who only repeated what 
he had told the captain. Secondly, the test by 
personal resemblance; which failed in 
consequence of the light hair, blue eyes, and Roman 
noses, shared in common by the fathers, and the 
light hair, blue eyes, and no noses worth 
mentioning, shared in common by the children. 
Thirdly, the test of Mrs. Drabble, which began 
and ended in fierce talking on one side and floods 
of tears on the other. Fourthly, the test by 
legal decision, which broke down through the 
total absence of any instructions for the law to 
act on. Fifthly, and lastly, the test by appeal 
to the husbands, which fell to the ground in 
consequence of the husbands knowing nothing about 
the matter in hand. The captain's barbarous 
test by weight remained the test still--and here 
am I, a man of the lower order, without a penny 
to bless myself with, in consequence. 
</p>
<p>
Yes! I was the bald baby of that memorable 
period. My excess in weight settled my 
destiny in life. The fathers and mothers on either 
side kept the babies according to the 
captain's principle of distribution, in despair of 
knowing what else to do. Mr. Smallchild--who 
was sharp enough, when not sea-sick--made his 
fortune. Simon Heavysides persisted in increasing 
his family, and died in the workhouse. Judge 
for yourself (as Mr. Jolly might say) how the 
two boys born at sea have fared in after-life. I, 
the bald baby, have seen nothing of the hairy 
baby for years past. He may be short, like Mr. 
Smallchild--but I happen to know that he is 
wonderfully like Heavysides, deceased, in the 
face. I may be tall like the carpenter--but I 
have the Smallchild eyes, hair, and expression, 
notwithstanding. Make what you can of that! 
You will find it come in the end to the same 
thing. Smallchild, junior, prospers in the world, 
because he weighed six pounds, fourteen ounces, 
and three-quarters. Heavysides, junior, fails in 
the world, because he weighed seven pounds, one 
ounce, and a quarter. There is the end of it, 
anyhow; and, if Mr. Hermit's outer crust will 
only let him, I recommend him to blush for his 
own grievance, whatever it is. As for Mr. 
Traveller, if he happens to have any loose silver 
about him, I'm not above taking it--and so I 
leave you, gentlemen, to settle the argument 
between you. 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up A Pocket-Book."/>
<p>
SEVERAL people came in at the gate, not only 
when the last speaker had withdrawn, but at 
various times throughout the day, from whom 
nothing could be extracted by the utmost 
ingenuity of Mr. Traveller, save what their calling 
was (when they had any), whence they came, 
and whither they were going. But, as those who 
had nothing to tell, clearly could tell nothing in 
justification of Mr. Mopes the Hermit, Mr. 
Traveller was almost as well satisfied with them 
as with any of the rest. Some of the many 
visitors came of a set purpose, attracted by 
curiosity; some, by chance, looking in to explore 
so desolate a place; many had often been there 
before, and came for drink and halfpence. These 
regular clients were all of the professed vagrant 
order; "and, as I observed to you," Mr. 
Traveller invariably remarked with coolness 
when they were gone, "are part of the Nuisance." 
</p>
<p>
When any one approached, either purposely 
or accidentally, to whom the figure in the blanket 
was new, Mr. Traveller, acting as a self-
constituted showman, did the honours of the place: 
referring to the Hermit as "our friend in there," 
and asking the visitor, without further explanation--
lest his own impartiality should be called in 
question--if he could favour our friend in there 
with any little experience of the living and 
moving world? It was in answer to this 
inquiry, that a sunburnt gentleman of middle age, 
with fine bright eyes, and a remarkable air of 
determination and self-possession (he had come 
over from the assize-town, he said, to see the 
sight in the soot and cinders), spake thus: 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
OFFICE-HOURS were over, and we were all 
 taking down our straw-hats from the pegs 
on which they dangled; ledgers were clasped, 
papers put away, desks locked, and the work of 
the day was at an end, when the white-haired 
cashier came sidling towards me. "Mr. 
Walford, sir, would you stay a moment? Would 
you step this way? The firm wish to speak to 
you." 
</p>
<p>
Good old Job Wiginton always described 
his employers, collectively, as "the firm." They 
were sacred beings in his eyes, were Spalding 
and Hausermann, and he had served them for a 
quarter of a century, with exemplary fidelity 
and respect. Job Wiginton, like myself, and like 
the senior partner in that great mercantile 
house, was an Englishman born and bred. He 
had kept the books of Spalding and Hausermann 
for twenty years at Philadelphia, and had 
cheerfully followed them to California, when 
they decided on settling in San Francisco City, 
five years before. The younger clerks, French 
or American for the most part, were rather 
disposed to make a butt of the simple honest old 
cashier; but he and I had been very good friends 
during the four years of my employment, and I 
always entertained a sincere respect for the old 
man's sterling good qualities. Now, however, 
for a reason I will presently explain, I was 
considerably taken aback by the communication 
which Mr. Wiginton made in his own 
formal way. 
</p>
<p>
"The firm wish to see me?" I 
stammered, with a tell-tale colour rising in my 
face. Old Job nodded assent, coughed, and 
carefully wiped his gold-rimmed spectacles. I 
had noticed, in spite of my own confusion, that 
the cashier was dejected and nervous; his voice 
was husky, his hand trembled as he rubbed the 
dim glasses, and there was an unwonted moisture 
in his round blue eyes. As I followed Job 
into the inner parlour, where the merchants 
usually sat during business hours, I marvelled 
much what this wholly unexpected summons 
might portend. I had formerly been on terms 
of great and cordial intimacy with my 
employers; but for the last three months, my 
intercourse, with the senior partner in especial, 
had been strictly confined to business matters 
and dry routine. It was not that I had done 
anything to forfeit the good opinion of the 
firm. My employers had still the same confidence 
in me, the same regard for me, as heretofore; 
but there was an end, if not of friendship, 
at least of cordiality. This partial estrangement 
dated from the day when, with Emma Spalding 
smiling through tears and blushes at my side, I 
had ventured to tell the rich merchant that I 
loved his only daughter, and that my love was 
returned. It is an old, old story. We were 
two young persons of the same country and 
creed, alike in tastes and education, and in other 
respects, wealth excepted, not so ill matched; 
and we were together on a foreign shore, among 
strange people. We had been suffered to 
associate familiarly together, to read poetry, sing 
duets, and so forth; for Emma had no mother to 
watch against the approach of poverty-stricken 
suitors, and Mr. Spalding was a proud man, and 
not given to suspicion. Hence we glided--as 
millions of couples have done before, and will 
again--down the smooth rose-strewn path that 
leads from friendship to love. I am sure of 
one thing: it was not my employer's wealth, or 
the idea of Emma's probable expectations from 
her father--who had but two children, a son and 
a daughter, between whom to divide the 
accumulations of a life spent in honourable toil--which 
allured me. But the time came when soft words 
and fond looks had to give place to an avowal 
of attachment. I spoke out to Emma, without 
premeditation; and, once across the Rubicon, 
other considerations, undreamed of as yet, came 
to beset me, mockingly. What would Mr. Spalding 
think of me? Surely, he could form but one 
judgment of the poor clerk, with no property 
beyond his pitiful savings, who had dared to 
entangle the affections of his master's daughter? 
My course was clear. I must tell him the truth, 
at whatever cost to myself. 
</p>
<p>
I did so. The disclosure was hurried on by 
some slight unforeseen circumstance, as my 
proposal had been, but I was at least candid in my 
avowals. To do Mr. Spalding justice, he 
rejected my suit in as gentle and courteous a 
fashion as the harsh operation would admit of. 
But, cut to the heart, I withdrew from his 
presence, very very wretched, and had for many 
days afterwards, serious thoughts of excluding 
myself from observation, becoming a solitary 
man, and leading a gloomy and moody life. 
Better thoughts, however, lying deeper within 
me, admonished me of the utter worthlessness of 
a purposeless existence, and of the utter 
contemptibility of the soul that can sink into it. 
And thus it fell out that I ceased to visit my 
employer as a private friend, and yet remained 
in his employ. 
</p>
<p>
Was I mean-spirited for staying on thus? I 
cannot pretend to decide so nice a point, but 
I know that it was a great stimulant to me to 
have obtained a moral victory over myself, and 
some relief to the disappointment of my dearest 
hopes that I was still allowed to breathe the same 
air as Emma Spalding, to catch a glimpse of her 
sweet saddened face, were it but on the way to 
church, though for three weary months we never 
interchanged a word. 
</p>
<p>
So I was not a little surprised when Job 
Wiginton summoned me to the presence of 
"the firm." My heart beat quickly as the 
old cashier turned the handle of the door. 
What could Mr. Spalding want of me? I had 
kept the promise he had wrung from me; I had 
abstained from any intrusion, any unlicensed 
correspondence. Surely, surely he could not send 
for me merely to say that a rejected suitor was 
ineligible even as a servant, and that our 
connexion must cease? In the larger of the two 
adjacent rooms, a room hung in Spanish fashion 
with stamped and gilded leather, and heavily 
furnished with dark mahogany from Honduras, 
I found the firm. Mr. Spalding, a tall thin 
grey-headed gentleman, was pacing up and down 
the apartment in great agitation. Mr. Hausermann, 
a German, as his name implies, sat before 
a table covered with papers, ejaculating guttural 
exclamations of wonder from time to time, and 
with a look of hopeless perplexity in his fat pink 
face. The cashier entered along with me, and 
closed the door. 
</p>
<p>
"Ach, mein Himmel!" muttered the junior 
partner: a hale, portly man, but of a flabby 
nature, morally and physically, compared with the 
energetic chief of the house: "ach! we were 
petter to have never peen porn, than live to see 
this!" 
</p>
<p>
Job Wiginton gave a groan of sincere sympathy. 
I quickly perceived that something had gone 
wrong, and as quickly did I see that this mysterious 
something had no direct reference to my audacity 
in winning the heart of Emma Spalding. 
What was amiss? There is one grisly ghost that 
always haunts the imagination of the more 
intelligent subordinates of a commercial firm--
Bankruptcy. But the house had been such a 
prudent house, so steady and well ballasted, had 
glided so demurely along in safe old-world 
groove, that it was rather ridiculed in 
consequence by the mushroom firms that daily arose 
or collapsed around us. But I had little time 
to think, for Mr. Spalding stopped in his walk, 
came abruptly up to me, and took me by both 
hands. "George Walford," said the old 
merchant, with more emotion in his voice and 
features than he had ever shown before, "I have 
not been kind to you lately. You were a good 
friend to me--before--before--" and here he 
reddened somewhat, and ceased speaking. 
</p>
<p>
I glanced towards Mr. Hausermann, but 
he looked so fat and helpless as he sat in 
his arm-chair, murmuring phrases in his 
native tongue, that I saw no explanation was to 
be looked for in that quarter. So I told Mr. 
Spalding, in as firm a tone as possible, that 
our mutual esteem had, I hoped, survived our 
intimacy, and that I still felt myself a faithful 
friend to him and his, and would gladly prove 
myself one. 
</p>
<p>
"I thought so--I thought so," said the 
merchant, looking pleased for a moment; "you 
are a good lad, George, and that's why I come 
to you for help in my sore need, hard and harsh 
as you may have thought me the other day--
when--Never mind!" 
</p>
<p>
"I was first to say it," exclaimed Mr. 
Hausermann. "'Let us call Shorge Walford,' 
say I. 'He has got ver goot prains; ver goot 
young man.'" 
</p>
<p>
A quarter of a century spent among Anglo-
Saxons had never taught Mr. Hausermann the 
English language in its purity. Indeed, his life, 
out of office hours, was spent entirely with 
Teutons like himself, who swarm all over 
America, and with whom he could enjoy German 
conversation, Rhine wine, and the black coffee 
of the fatherland. I should never get to the 
end of the interview if I described it verbatim, 
chronicling the broken sentences and vague talk 
of the junior partner, and the comments of Job 
Wiginton. The confidential cashier 
sympathised with the distress of his employers as a 
faithful dog might have done, and was about 
as likely to suggest a practical remedy. Mr. 
Wiginton was worthy of all trust; he was as 
close as wax and as honest as the day, but he was 
a mere machine for the casting up of sums, the 
balancing of books, and locking of safes. Mr. 
Hausermann was not much cleverer than the cashier; 
he was an admirable arithmetician, could detect 
an error of a halfpenny in a problem involving 
billions, and his penmanship was magnificent. 
But, with these attainments, he owed his 
present position in commerce, not to his abilities, 
but to the florins he had inherited, and to the 
talent and keenness of his English partner. It 
was from the chief of the house himself that 
I heard the following tale:--Mr. Spalding, as I 
have said, had but two children, Emma, and 
her brother Adolphus; his wife had died on 
the voyage from Philadelphia, and his affection 
centred in his boy and girl. Unluckily, 
Adolphus did not turn out well, was wild 
and extravagant, and squandered his liberal 
allowance among horse jockeys and gamblers. 
Mr. Spalding, strict with all the world besides, 
was rather lax and indulgent where his son 
was concerned. The young man was very 
good-looking and of pleasing address; he had 
been the darling of his dead mother; and the 
father was very patient and forbearing with 
him, for her sake. The youth went from bad to 
worse, got deeper into debt and evil company, 
seldom came home, and seriously impaired his 
health by a long course of excesses. All this I 
knew, for Adolphus was a clerk in the house, 
nominally at least, though he hardly ever 
occupied his stool in the office. But what I did 
not know was, that Adolphus Spalding, in his 
eagerness to settle a number of so-called debts 
of honour, had been led to rob his father. He 
had forged the signatures of Spalding and 
Hausermann to a cheque for thirty thousand 
dollars, payable at sight, and purporting to be 
drawn by the merchants on their bankers in New 
York. More than this: he had abstracted from 
his father's desk a Russia-leather pocket-book, 
containing bills and securities to a great amount, 
and this he had placed in the hands of the 
same vile associate who had undertaken to 
present the cheque at the counter of the New York 
bank. 
</p>
<p>
"The scoundrel is gone northward already. 
He started last Tuesday, by the way of Panama, 
along with the mail," said Mr. Spalding. "You 
know the man, I dare say, for he was very 
notorious in the town--Joram Heckler." 
</p>
<p>
"Dr. Joram Heckler!" I exclaimed, as I 
recalled to mind the dark clever face of the young 
man alluded to: a plausible, well-mannered person, 
who had been sub-editor of a San Francisco 
newspaper. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, Doctor, or Colonel, Heckler," responded 
Mr. Spalding, with a bitter smile, "for it appears 
that he has assumed a military title on the 
journey back to the north. He possessed great 
influence over the mind of my misguided son; 
he was the tempter in this accursed robbery; and 
I doubt not that he intends to appropriate the 
entire spoil to himself." 
</p>
<p>
I now asked Mr. Spalding, as delicately as I 
could, how he had obtained his information. 
</p>
<p>
It appeared that Adolphus, whose feeble 
frame, exhausted by hard living, was ill fitted 
to sustain the fierce excitement of the felonious 
act he had committed, had sickened of a fever, 
immediately after the departure of his 
accomplice. 
</p>
<p>
"The wretched boy lies on his bed up-stairs, 
quivering betwixt life and death," said the 
father, with a faltering voice, "and in his 
delirium he has betrayed his guilt. His sister, 
who has watched at his bedside like an angel as 
she is, dear girl, she was frightened at his 
ravings of self-accusation. She called me, and 
with my own ears I heard the son I was so 
proud of--my petted boy--tell how he had 
cheated and plundered me." 
</p>
<p>
The old merchant staggered to a chair, and I 
saw the tears trickle between the fingers with 
which he tried to hide the workings of his 
wrinkled face. 
</p>
<p>
After a time he grew more calm. Then he 
developed his plan, in which broke out his 
habitual decision and force of character. Before 
all things, the honour of the house must be 
saved. The value of the money at stake (though 
a large sum) was trifling, compared to the 
disgrace, the loss of credit, the blot upon the name 
of Spalding. Yes, at any cost, the young 
man's shameful act must be hidden in darkness. 
The cheque must not be presented, the bills 
must not be negotiated. But how to prevent 
he tempter from realising the benefits of his 
ill-gotten booty? He was off--he was speeding 
towards New York by the quick Panama route; 
in a few weeks he would be there. No pursuit 
seemed possible. The delay till the start of the 
next mail would be fatal. I remembered the 
Pony Express, the swift overland mail whereby 
we Californian residents can most rapidly 
communicate with the civilised world, and I 
suggested this resource. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Spalding shook his head. "No, that 
would never do; I might send a despatch, no 
doubt, to stop the payment of the cheque. I 
might perhaps procure Heckler's arrest on his 
arrival in New York, but thence would spring 
inquiry, doubt, suspicion, and the whole black 
affair would creep into the journals before a week 
was out. No. I have but one hope, one chance: 
I must send a trustworthy person--I am too old 
to go myself--a trustworthy person to hasten to 
New York by the perilous route across the Rocky 
Mountains, and he must arrive before Heckler, 
and must get the papers from him by violence or 
stratagem. George Walford, you are the man I 
have selected." 
</p>
<p>
"I, sir?" 
</p>
<p>
I was stupified. Before my fancy rose, like a 
panorama, the long route, then but lately 
explored, that traversed the enormous continent 
from sea to sea: a route teeming with dangers. 
All I had ever heard or read of prairie travel, of 
famine, fire, the assaults of wild beasts, and of 
human foes more pitiless still, crowded on my 
memory at once. I thought of the vast 
distance, of the almost herculean fatigues to be 
undergone, of the icy barrier which the Rocky 
Mountains stretched across the track, as if to 
bar the progress of presumptuous man; and 
though I am no fainter of heart than my 
neighbours, I dare say my countenance expressed 
dismay and repugnance. Indeed, I am sure it 
did, for Mr. Hausermann groaned, and said, 
"Donner! what shall we to now?" 
</p>
<p>
"Walford," said Mr. Spalding, "I don't 
wish to dissemble with you. I am asking you 
to incur the certainty of very great fatigue, 
hardship, and danger. I am asking you to risk 
life itself to save the honour of the house and 
that of my own family. I do not make such a 
request without proposing a proportionate 
reward.--There, hear me out! I don't offer you 
money for such a service. Come back successful, 
and you shall be a partner in the house of 
Spalding and Hausermann; and if you and 
Emma are still of the same mind three months 
hence--" 
</p>
<p>
I trembled with joy as I interrupted my 
employer. "I'll go, sir, gladly and most 
willingly." 
</p>
<p>
"That's a prave poy. I knew he would!" 
ejaculated the German; and the cashier rubbed 
his hands joyfully. 
</p>
<p>
"When can you be ready to start?" asked 
Mr. Spalding. 
</p>
<p>
"Directly. In half an hour, if you please." 
</p>
<p>
"An hour will do," said Mr. Spalding, 
with a smile at my eagerness. "Bodesson shall be 
at the door by that time, with his carriage and 
his best horses. You must save your strength 
as much as you can for the prairie. You have 
a six-shooter, I know. Get ready what requisites 
for the journey will go into small compass. 
You shall have an ample supply of money--
spend it freely, lavishly, and don't spare horse-
flesh or gold upon the way. I would give half 
my fortune to place you speedily on the pavement 
of New York. You are an ambassador 
with full powers, George, and your own wit and 
courage must carry you through. Now, you 
had better prepare for the road." 
</p>
<p>
I lingered. 
</p>
<p>
"Anything more to say?" asked the 
merchant, good humouredly. 
</p>
<p>
"If I could speak tor a moment--just an 
instant--to Miss Spalding?" 
</p>
<p>
"She is at her brother's bedside," replied the 
old man, hurriedly. "But--yes, you are right. 
You shall see her before you start." 
</p>
<p>
I seemed to make but one step to the house 
where I lodged. I spent ten minutes in hastily 
arranging my belongings--and it is wonderful 
how much a man can condense into ten minutes 
when he is under the influence of strong excitement--
charged my revolver, packed a few things 
in a small bag, and ran back like a greyhound. 
Mr. Spalding gave me some fuller instructions, and 
handed to me a heavy parcel of gold and silver, as 
well as a bundle of bank-notes. I was to keep the 
bank-paper until I reached the civilised world; 
in the desert, my only hope would be to bribe in 
specie the half-tamed wanderers of the west. 
Mr. Spalding was still talking when Bodesson, 
one of the principal liverymen of San Francisco, 
drove his spanking pair of Spanish horses up to 
the door. Then the merchant went up-stairs, 
and returned with his daughter. Dear Emma! 
she was pale, and thinner than of old, but her 
eyes were bright and loving, and her words, full 
of hope and constancy, gave me fresh courage, 
and a resolve to do or die. Our parting was 
very brief. A few hurried whispers--a hasty 
renewal of the old vows and troth-plight--
and for a moment I caught her in my arms 
and kissed her cheek, and in the next I was 
gone. I sat by Bodesson's side; the whip 
cracked; off flew the foaming horses along the 
street; and I looked back and waved a farewell 
in answer to Mr. Spalding's waving hand and 
Emma's handkerchief. Then we turned the 
corner, and darted along the road. 
</p>
<p>
Bodesson was well paid, and he kept the 
mettled horses at their work over many a mile 
of ground. I seemed to start cheerfully, and 
under good auspices. My heart was full of 
hope. The gay French Creole by my side was a 
merry companion; he sang Canadian songs, 
whistled, chirruped to the bounding bays, and 
chattered incessantly. 
</p>
<p>
"Monsieur was going to the prairies! Ah, 
très bien! The prairies were ver intéressantes, 
ver moch so. But monsieur must take care when 
he got there--must not stir from the protection 
of ze dragoons, or les sauvages, ze ferocious 
Indians, would carry off monsieur's cheveux--
what you call scalp!" 
</p>
<p>
So the Frenchman prattled on. He believed 
I was going to Salt Lake City on business, and 
never doubted that I should voyage with a 
caravan under escort of the States dragoons. 
What would he have said had he known 
that I was to traverse that land of danger 
and hunger alone? 
</p>
<p>
My journey to the eastern border of 
California was not remarkable enough to justify 
me in dwelling here on its details. Spending 
money freely, I was able to proceed 
almost entirely in wheeled carriages more or 
less rude, and I contrived to push along over 
sorry roads at a respectable pace. I slept in 
the vehicles during the dark hours, snatching a 
broken slumber as best I could, in the midst of 
jolting and swaying. Sometimes even a bribe 
could not induce my Mexican or American 
drivers to risk the perils of a stony road at 
night, and then I recruited my strength by rest, 
but was always ready to start at cock-crow. I 
knew well what was before me, and that all the 
fatigue I endured was child's play to what was 
in store. I had been on the prairies before--
those, at least, which lie east of the Rocky 
Mountains. Mr. Spalding was well aware that 
I was a good horseman, expert in the use of 
fire-arms, and of a robust constitution. These 
are not the common attributes of a clerk, but I 
had not been bred to the desk. My father had 
been esteemed rich, till at his death, in 
embarrassed circumstances, I had been left to battle 
with poverty as I might; I had kept hunters 
at Oxford, and had been passionately fond of 
field sports. I had kept up the habit of taking 
brisk exercise, and now I was about to find the 
benefit of trained muscles and robust health. I 
did not disguise from myself that I was embarking 
on an enterprise full of risks. I might 
starve in the desert, whitened as it was by the 
bones of many an emigrant. I might perish 
miserably in one of those fires that rush like 
flaming serpents through the boundless sea of 
grass. And if my scalp did not blacken in the 
smoke of some Indian wigwam, fever or sheer 
fatigue might make an end of my life and hopes 
at once. Or, I might reach New York too late. 
It was gall and wormwood to me to think that 
Joram Heckler was pressing on towards the 
north with all the speed of a fast steamer. The 
very thought made me bound and stamp my foot 
on the floor of the rude mail-cart, as if I could 
quicken my progress by such a gesture. How 
I prayed that contrary winds might delay the 
packet on its passage from Aspinwall to the 
Empire City! 
</p>
<p>
I reached Carson City, on the border of 
the desert, and there I made a brief halt that 
I might prepare for the coming effort. I 
was perfectly well aware that the most 
dangerous and difficult part of the road was that 
lying between California and the Mormon 
settlements. Once beyond the Utah territory, I 
might well hope to escape the arrows and 
tomahawk of the savage. I found Carson full of 
returning emigrants, diggers going back with their 
pelf to the Atlantic states, Mormon converts, 
and traders who had emptied their waggons in 
Californian markets. These good folks were all 
waiting for the regular escort of national 
dragoons, under whose guard they were to travel. 
It was impossible for me to move so slowly, 
and I accordingly bought a bag of sun-dried 
beef, another of parched corn, some blankets, 
and such matters, and a powerful horse 
handsomely accoutred with a bridle and saddle 
of Mexican make. I bought the latter from an 
American dealer, who was mightily tickled at 
the idea of my making my way alone over the 
prairies. "I give you credit for your grit, 
sartainly, mister," said he: "it is good, and no 
mistake; but I guess you'd better sleep upon 
the idea a few times more. Them  Indian 
scalpers will lift your ha'r, sure as hogs yield 
bacon. Won't you believe me? Come along, 
then, and ax another man's opinion!" And he 
dragged me towards a sort of tavern, the porch 
of which was crowded by men and women, 
French, Spanish, German, Yankee, and mulatto, 
all of whom were gathered round a lathy dark-
haired young fellow in a trim half-military dress, 
that would have passed for that of a policeman 
but for the red flannel shirt and Mexican 
sombrero he wore. This man had keen 
mobile features, and was hardened by 
constant work and weather into little more than 
muscle and bone; he wore spurred boots 
and thick "savers," and was cracking a whip 
as he gaily chatted with the crowd, who 
laughed at his wit in a way that proved him a 
prime favourite. He was, in fact, one of the 
salaried riders of the "Pony Express," ready 
to start with the bag of despatches, the instant 
the courier from San Francisco should arrive 
with it. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, colonel; yes, gals," I heard him say; 
"I'm downright sorry to leave, but duty is 
duty, ain't it? If the Indians don't rub me 
out--" 
</p>
<p>
"Rub you out, Shem? Catch a racoon 
asleep!" cried one of the rider's admiring 
friends. 
</p>
<p>
"Waal!" said Shem, with a modest voice, 
but a boastful twinkle in his restless eye, "the 
varmints have tried a time or two, but they've 
found Shem Grindrod rather a tough nut to 
crack, they have. When a chap's Kentucky 
bred, real right down hard hickory, 'taint so 
easy to lift his ha'r as--Service to ye, stranger!" 
</p>
<p>
For his eye had lighted on me. 
</p>
<p>
"Shem," cried the horse-dealer, "here's a 
gentleman wants to cross the parara, all alone, 
on hossback, Broadway fashion. What do you  
say to that?" 
</p>
<p>
There was a general laugh. Shem took off 
his hat with mock respect. 
</p>
<p>
"Whoop!" he cried. "If that ain't clear grit 
in the down-easter dandy! You'll see snakes, 
mister, I reckon. There's no accommodation 
for gen-teel persons, and you'll jest get your 
hoss stole, or chawed up by the wolves, and 
you'll lose yourself and die for want of a dinner, 
if you don't fall in with the Injuns--and if you 
do, Jehoshaphat!" 
</p>
<p>
All this would have been provoking to some 
men, but I knew the American character too well 
to be out of temper. Shem evidently took me for 
a presumptuous townsman, plunging wantonly 
into the lion's mouth, and was good naturedly 
discouraging my rashness. With some trouble, 
I drew him apart, and commenced a private 
conversation. I told him that I was bound for 
the eastern states, that my business was imperative, 
but that if he could help me I would 
pay him most liberally for the aid rendered. 
For I had formed a crude idea that, if I could 
procure the privilege of using the relays of 
spare horses kept at the different stations on 
the route, for the use of the mail-bag riders, I 
might accomplish the most awkward part of the 
journey with great rapidity. Shem, however, 
though not ill natured, dashed my hopes to the 
ground. Such a concession would be "agin all 
rule." The servants of the Express Company 
"darn't do it." It was not to be thought of. 
I must wait for the caravan. 
</p>
<p>
I did not wait for the caravan, but set forth 
that very day. The people gave me a half ironical 
cheer as I rode out of the straggling street of 
Carson, but I saw the Yankee dealer shake his 
head and screw up the corners of his mouth, as 
if he considered me little better than a suicide. 
</p>
<p>
There was no use in letting the grass grow 
under my feet, so I pushed briskly ahead. I 
was riding a powerful horse, one of those bred 
in Kentucky or Tennessee, and which will sell 
for a high price on the western border of 
prairieland. To find the way in broad daylight 
was easy. There was a broad track made by 
the passage of countless waggons and beasts of 
burden. I had a compass, but I really did not 
need it. I covered many a weary league of 
ground in the course of that day's ride. Here 
and there, among the forked streamlets which 
were feeders of the Carson, I came to farms 
where I easily procured corn for my horse and 
food for myself. I had come to two resolutions: 
one, to economise my little store of jerked 
beef as much as possible; the other, to refuse 
all hospitable proffers of whisky, being convinced 
that on water only could such trying work as 
that before me be accomplished. I kept on, 
with brief pauses, through the day, and held 
to the track as long as the moonlight served 
me, urging on my flagging steed to the very 
limits of his strength. Then, in the dark, 
I dismounted, took off saddle and bridle, 
hobbled my horse, and tethered him so that 
he had ample space to graze. Then, I lay 
down, wrapped in my blankets, pillowed my 
head upon my saddle, and fell asleep with my 
weapons by my side. 
</p>
<p>
I awoke with a start, in the pitch dark night, 
and could not well remember where I was. My 
horse was uneasy, and his abrupt motions had 
disturbed me. I heard a rustling in the long 
grass, a scratching, a pawing of light feet 
amongst the herbage, and a whining sound as 
of hungry dogs whimpering for food. Dogs? 
There were no dogs there. Wolves! And 
my horse, on whose security my life might 
depend, was trembling and bathed in 
perspiration. I had kindled no fire, apprehensive 
lest the light should attract some band of 
prowling savages; and now the coyotés were 
gathering around us like flies about honey. For 
myself, I felt no fear: the wolf of America is 
very different from the "grey beast" of German 
forests or Pyrenean snows. But my poor nag 
was in danger, and his very tremors were adding 
perilously to the exhaustion of the long and 
hurried ride. I rose, and began groping about 
for brushwood. Luckily I was still in a well-
watered region, where shrubs and undergrowth 
abounded, and where the gigantic cotton-wood 
trees reared their majestic forms beside the 
streamlets. I soon came upon a clump of 
brush, and cutting with my sharp and heavy 
knife as much as I could carry in both arms, I 
returned with it, and cleared a little space of the 
grass, which was long enough to be dangerous 
in the event of its catching fire. I then took out 
my tin box of lucifers, struck a light, and kindled 
a fire: though not very easily, for the heavy dew 
stood in great glistening beads on grass and 
shrub, and the moistened wood emitted many a 
cloud of pungent and dark smoke, before I could 
coax the sullen embers to burst forth in the 
required blaze. All this time, I had to give an 
occasional halloo, rattling a tin cup against the 
barrel of my revolver, for the purpose of 
intimidating the wolves; while it was necessary to 
pat and soothe by voice and hand the poor horse 
itself, which was tugging at the tethering-rope 
in a way that threatened to break it every 
instant. At last, to my great joy, the fire leaped 
up, red and cheery, its bright beams illumined 
a little radiant patch of prairie, and, hovering in 
the shadows on the edge of this illuminated 
spot, I saw the slinking coyotés, the smallest 
and most timid, but also the most cunning, 
variety of the wolf of America. Presently 
I flung a firebrand among the pack, and 
they vanished into the darkness, but for half an 
hour I could hear their howls of disappointment, 
growing fainter and fainter, as the distance 
increased. My horse was quieter after the 
disappearance of the wolves, and in about an hour I 
ventured to return to my blankets and my 
repose, after piling a fresh heap of brush on the 
steadily glowing fire. Not very long afterwards, 
a feeling of intense cold awoke me by slow 
degrees. I opened my eyes. The fire was low; 
its embers glowed crimson, fading gradually into 
blackness. Overhead was the dim sky, the vast 
host of stars having the peculiar pale and sickly 
hue which heralds the dawn. It was very cold. 
There was a rushing sound in the air, and the 
grass of the prairie was tossed to and fro in wild 
confusion; a strong wind was blowing--the 
norther. This was the first blast of the chilly 
north wind that annually sets in at the close of 
the unhealthy season in the south. It had a 
piercing and glacial effect, coming, as it did, 
from the Polar ice-fields, and across the Rocky 
Mountain range; but I gladly hailed it, for I 
remembered that it would be dead against the mail 
steamer that was breasting the waters of the 
Mexican Gulf with Joram Heckler and his 
plunder on board. I might beat him yet! 
</p>
<p>
But the wind increased in force; it was blowing 
like a hurricane, and I shivered in spite of my 
warm poncho and blankets. My horse had lain 
down, and was trembling with cold. I was obliged 
to spare him a blanket; he was a "States" horse, 
swifter, but not so hardy and useful for prairie 
travel as the mustangs of the plains. The wind 
did not diminish as the sun rose, red and angry, 
and a new cause of alarm began to haunt me. I 
had heard of travellers utterly weatherbound for 
days among the prairies, on account of the fury 
of the resistless wind. And time was so valuable 
to me! I felt sick at heart as the chilly 
hours of early morning crept on, and almost 
despaired of success. I was benumbed and 
stiff; the dew had been turned to icicles by 
the sudden cold; and now every waving blade 
of grass seemed crested with a diamond, glittering 
and flashing in the level sunshine. By 
nine o'clock the wind began to abate; it 
slackened very gradually, and at half-past 
ten I considered that I might resume my 
journey. My breakfast was not a luxurious one; 
a mouthful of beef and parched maize, swallowed 
in the intervals of saddling my horse and rolling 
up my blankets. Then, I drew up the iron peg 
to which the halter was attached, rolled up the 
halter, lasso fashion, at my saddle bow, and 
mounted. I was less awkward in the every-day 
routine of prairie life than might be supposed. 
Years ago, before I entered Spalding and 
Hausermann's employ, I had spent some weeks in a 
frontier fort, as the guest of the officers of a 
United States Ranger regiment. I had 
accompanied my hosts on several hunts and scouting 
expeditions against hostile Indians, and had 
found some amusement in picketing my steed, 
lighting camp fires, and so forth: little dreaming 
that my whole earthly happiness would 
ever depend on my proficiency in such arts. 
As the sun rose in the pale blue sky, nature 
assumed a more cheerful appearance; the icicles 
and hoar-frost melted, and the air became merely 
bracing and agreeable, as the bitter cold passed 
away. On we went, following the plain trail of 
the waggon trains, up and down the gently rolling 
slopes of the undulating prairie. I noticed 
with some dismay that my horse was no longer 
the mettled creature that had pranced so gaily out 
of Carson the day before. At first he certainly 
answered my voice and the pressure of my knee, 
by stepping out gallantly; but after a while he 
began to flag, bore heavily on the bit, and required 
a frequent touch of the spur. It was clear I 
had taxed his powers too severely on the 
previous day. He was going weakly under me, in 
a spiritless way that spoke volumes. What was 
I to do? I had plenty of money, but money 
cannot prove a talisman in the wilderness. 
There was not a farm between the place where I 
stood and the Great Salt Lake itself. My only 
chance in procuring a remount lay in meeting 
some one who would sell me a steed, and this 
was far from a certainty. I was chewing the 
cud of bitter reflections when I heard the light 
tramp of a galloping horse behind me. Quickly 
I turned my head, and saw a booted rider 
dashing gaily along over the swells of the prairie; 
his trim coat, half opened, showed a red flannel 
shirt; and his Mexican sombrero was bound 
with a cord of tarnished gold. He had a 
revolving carbine pistol at his saddle-bow, and 
at his side hung from his shoulder-belt his 
leathern despatch-bag. It was my acquaintance 
of yesterday--Shem Grindrod. 
</p>
<p>
"Mornin', stranger!" he called out, cheerily; 
"I didn't skear you, yesterday, it seems, by my 
yarns about Injuns. 'Twas Gospel truth, for 
all that. Camped out, I reckon? Your hoss 
does look a little the wuss for wear, mister, 
though. You've pushed him a goodish stretch, 
you have." 
</p>
<p>
We rode on for some distance side by side. 
My poor horse was inspired to do his best by the 
presence of the other horse, and together we 
sped over the country: my steed trotting, Shem's 
mustang galloping, for Spanish-American horses 
have but one pace when urged beyond a walk. 
Shem was much more kind and even polite in 
his manner than on the previous day. He told 
me, bluntly, that he respected a fellow that 
proved himself a man, but that what he hated 
worse than copperhead snakes was a Broadway 
dandy giving himself adventurous airs. My 
horsemanship had won Shem's esteem, and he 
sympathised heartily with me when he saw 
that I was really bent on crossing the desert at 
any risk. 
</p>
<p>
"Your hoss is a good bit of stuff, mister," 
said he, "but I'm afraid he's pretty nigh used 
up for one while. Now you listen to me. The 
best thing you can do, is to buy a mustang fust 
chance you get. There'll be hunters passing 
south, and p'raps they'll trade. When you get 
right out among the plains, you stick to the 
trail well, and if a grass fire blinds it, you take 
your compass and bear up for east by north. 
Keep that pistol of yourn ready, and if you do 
see Injuns, keep cool. Don't waste a shot. 
Every round bit of lead is worth a life on the 
parara. Good-by, wish you luck." 
</p>
<p>
Shem headed his horse for one of the 
Express stations, a little lonely block-house, with 
a stockaded yard, which was garrisoned by 
a few of his comrades, and where a relay of 
fresh horses was kept. I looked wistfully at 
the block-house and the well-stocked corral, and 
then turned away with my tired steed to resume 
my weary travel. I knew that early in the 
afternoon I should reach another station of the 
same kind, and there I meant to apply for 
refreshment and shelter, in case my horse should 
knock up altogether. Before I had gone a mile, 
I saw my friend Shem, on a fresh steed, scouring 
the plain. He waved his hand, and gave me 
a cheer of recognition, and I looked after him 
enviously as he flew like an arrow up the 
slope, and vanished in the distance. By good 
luck, however, I almost instantly encountered a 
party of white men, the first travellers I had 
seen. These turned out to be three trappers 
returning from Oregon, with a fair stock of 
peltry loaded on two mules. They were all 
well mounted on "Indian ponies," and one of 
them led by a lariat a powerful and shapely 
mustang, whose bright eye and wide nostrils 
matched well with his wiry limbs. He had been 
captured on the plains, not two months before, 
one of a wild herd; but he was sufficiently 
broken in to be useful in prairie fashion. I 
struck a bargain with the trapper, by which my 
exhausted but more valuable quadruped was 
bartered for the half-wild mustang; the trapper 
also receiving four gold eagles. The arrangement 
was mutually satisfactory, and as the tall 
Kentuckian helped me to shift my saddle and 
bridle to the spotted nag I had just acquired, I 
saw his eyes twinkle with self-congratulation. 
</p>
<p>
"One word of advice, colonel," said the 
trapper, as I placed the gold in his hard brown 
hand; "keep your eyes skinned as you go along, 
and don't let the cussed Redskins double upon 
you. There's Indian sign about, there is. I 
saw the print of a moccassin, down yonder by 
the spring, where the Indians never come for 
any good, mister. You mind--Utahs ain't to 
be trusted, and Shoshonies are worse. As for 
Rapshoes, Heaven help you, colonel, if they 
ketch you alone! There's Indians about. I 
smell 'em." 
</p>
<p>
"I wish you'd got a good rifle on your 
shoulder, mister," said another, as I mounted; 
"six shooters is very handy tools, but nothing 
sickens the Indians like a good five-foot bit of 
holler iron, that air true." 
</p>
<p>
I took leave of these good fellows, who 
wished me a safe journey in the heartiest way, 
though evidently disbelieving in the likelihood 
that a "greenhorn" could carry his property and 
scalp safe across the desert. The mustang was 
fresh, and darted along at that untiring though 
not very speedy gallop which animals of that hardy 
race can maintain for a very considerable time. 
We made capital progress: the country grew 
drier, and the grass shorter, and the swampy 
bottoms and trickling brooks were fewer. I met with 
no adventure, except that my new purchase put 
his foot into an outlying burrow, as we skirted 
a "village" of prairie dogs, and gave us both a 
roll on the turf; but we were unhurt, and I had 
luckily kept my grasp of the bridle, or I should 
have lost my horse. Once I thought I saw 
something hovering on the edge of the horizon, 
but whether savages, buffaloes, or wild horses, I 
could not determine. After riding several miles 
I came to a place where the trail dipped suddenly 
into a low tract of alluvial earth, intersected by 
a stream of some magnitude, and shaded by a 
belt of lofty cotton-wood trees. I traced here the 
fresh footprints of a horse which must just have 
passed, for the bruised grass had but partially 
risen around the edges. "Crack, bang!" went 
the sharp report of fire-arms ringing from the 
thicket below, and with the reports mingled the 
horrid war-whoop of the savage. Grasping my 
pistol, I dashed in among the trees, and beheld 
poor Shem Grindrod, bleeding, reeling in his 
saddle, and beset by a party of six or seven 
Indians, mounted, and in their hideous panoply of 
war. Shem had been pierced by three arrows: he 
was fainting with loss of blood; but he fronted 
the savages boldly, and one Indian lay at his 
feet, rolling in the agonies of death. My arrival 
changed the current of the fight; two rounds 
from my revolver, the second of which laid low 
a muscular barbarian, smeared with yellow 
ochre, who was pressing on Shem with an 
uplifted tomahawk, sufficed for their discomfiture. 
Probably they took me for the advanced guard 
of a party of whites. At any rate, they fled at 
speed across the plain. 
</p>
<p>
I was just in time to break Shem's fall, as the 
poor fellow dropped from his saddle, feebly 
murmuring, "Thank ye, mister. You've saved my 
scalp, any way, if 'twas just too late to save--" 
His voice was hushed here, and he fainted in my 
arms. 
</p>
<p>
There was a metal flask of whisky dangling 
at the mail-bag rider's saddle-bow, along with his 
blanket and havresack; I hastily unscrewed the 
stopper, and contrived to force a few drops into 
the mouth of the wounded man. Then, I tore 
my cravat into strips, and with it and my 
handkerchief tried to bind up the hurts Shem had 
received, after vainly attempting to withdraw the 
barbed arrows. Two of the injuries were mere 
flesh wounds, more painful than dangerous; 
but the third was of a serious character: the 
shaft was imbedded in Shem's side, though the 
hemorrhage was trifling in appearance when 
compared with the abundant flow of blood from 
the other injuries. In about a couple of minutes 
Shem revived sufficiently to look up. I was 
touched by the gratitude his eyes expressed. 
Probably, poor lad, he had received but a scanty 
share of kindness in his scrambling life. 
</p>
<p>
"Do you suffer much pain from the arrow 
wounds?'" I asked. "Take a drop more of the 
whisky; it will give you strength, and if I can 
once help you to proceed as far as the 
blockhouse--" 
</p>
<p>
"'Tain't no manner of use, stranger, my duty 
to ye, all the same," replied the rider, after 
swallowing a small quantity of spirits. "I've 
got my finish at last. A chap that's fit in the 
border fights ever since he could squint along a 
gun, don't need no doctor to tell him when he's 
got goss, he don't." 
</p>
<p>
I could not disguise from myself that Shem 
was right. His face showed a ghastly change; 
it was ashen white, pinched, and thin; while 
the lips twitched, and the eyes had acquired 
that peculiar eager glance, and restless craving 
brightness, which we never notice except in 
those over whom death hovers. But I tried to 
cheer the poor fellow; succeeded in stanching 
the blood that flowed from his arm, 
transpierced by two of the iron-tipped reeds; and 
begged him to keep up his hope and courage. 
</p>
<p>
"'Tain't worth wasting words upon, mister," 
gasped Shem; "I knowed I'd my call; onst I 
felt the cold and the rankling pain that follered 
the smart of that cussed arrow in my ribs. I'm 
jest bleeding to death, inwardly, I am, and all 
the surgeon chaps in the States couldn't help 
me, no, nor yet the cleverest bonesetter in the 
pararas. But you cheated the curs out of my 
scalp, stranger. They had a hanker to get this 
child's ha'r, they had, to dance round in their 
darned village, them Shoshonies. My! How 
the squaws will jeer and mock 'em when 
they go back empty-fisted, and leavin' two of 
the pack behind 'em, too!" And Shem, with 
death in his face and at his heart, actually 
laughed. He had to catch painfully at his 
breath before he spoke again. "Stranger, 
it's an ill wind blows nobody any good. You 
hark to me. What I couldn't give you, nouther 
for dollars nor axin', you'll get now. Go on to 
the station; take this here mail-bag along; give 
it 'em, and tell 'em the rights of what's chanced. 
They'll turn out fast enough, I'll warrant, and 
they'll put me under the turf afore the wolves 
pick my bones. And another rider must go on 
with the bag. And tell 'em 'twere my dyin' 
wish, they'd give you a fresh hoss at each block, 
and so let you go with the rider, and push 
ahead. The Co. won't be riled at the breach of 
rules--seein' you saved the bag, let alone my 
scalp, and--" 
</p>
<p>
He broke down here. I was quite melted at 
the unselfish thoughtfulness of this poor dying 
creature, this untaught, half-wild frontiers-man, 
who could care for my speedy journey while his 
own vital breath was trembling on his livid lips. 
I gave him a third sup of whisky, begging him 
to let me know if I could communicate his last 
wishes to any distant friend or relation? 
</p>
<p>
"There a gal that lives to Hampton Town," 
said Shem, almost in a whisper, "the darter of 
a dealer that trades in mules, she be; and Ruth 
and I--Oh, 'tis a pity the wedding day were 
put off, cause the Co. gives pensions to wives, 
but none to sweethearts, and Ruth's father met 
with misfortins in trade, and she'd ha' been glad 
of a few dollars a year, poor thing!" 
</p>
<p>
I asked his sweetheart's name, for, as I 
assured him, I felt certain that the house of 
Spalding and Hausermann would befriend her for 
his sake, if through the service I had rendered 
Shem I were really enabled to do my errand with 
a success otherwise unattainable. 
</p>
<p>
"Ruth Moss," said Shem, in his weak voice; 
"that's her surname and given name. She's a 
good girl, pretty and good, is Ruth, and only 
too tender a flower for a rough borderman like 
me; goes to chapel reg'lar, and writes like a 
print book." 
</p>
<p>
He then begged that I would send to Ruth a 
certain knot of ribbon which he had received 
from her as a keepsake, or merely snatched in a 
lover's whim, I do not know which; at any rate, 
I found it carefully wrapped in deerskin, in the 
bosom of his dress, but ah! with a deep dark 
stain of blood marring the gay blue of the silk. 
The arrow had passed nearly through that 
humble love-token. Shem further prayed me, 
that as I passed by the Round Pond Station, 
between Port Bridge and Red Creek, I would 
tell his old father, Amos Grindrod, that he, 
Shem, had "died like a man." 
</p>
<p>
"The old man'll be cut up, I'm afraid," 
murmured Shem, whose eyes were getting dim; 
"but he'll be glad to know my ha'r warn't lifted. 
Tell him I were wiped out by the band of Mad 
Buffalo, the Shoshonie.''T'war Mad Buffalo 
hisself that sent the arrow through me, just as 
I kivered him with the carbine. The shunk! 
Many a noggin of drink I've given him when he 
come tradin' to the fort. But there war a grudge 
atween him and me, and he's ped it; but let him 
mind how he ever comes within range of old 
Amos Grindrod's rifle!" 
</p>
<p>
Shem was anxious to know whether the 
Indian I had shot was quite dead, and what 
painted device his half-naked body bore. His 
own glazing eyes could not distinguish; but 
when I described the yellow ochre barred with 
white, he said it must be the "Little Owl," 
one of Mad Buffalo's best warriors. The other 
Indian was of slighter make, and daubed with 
black and vermilion. Both were stone dead. 
Shem asked me, half timidly, if I would be 
so good as repeat "a bit of Scripture." He 
had not been much of a chapel-goer, but Ruth 
had "got religion," and his mother, too, had 
been "a Christian woman," as he quaintly 
observed. I knelt beside him and held up his head 
as I uttered aloud the words of a brief and 
simple prayer, such as little children are taught 
to lisp with their innocent lips; and once or 
twice I heard the husky tones of the dying man 
repeat the words. But there was a strong shiver 
through his frame, and poor Shem Grindrod was 
dead before the prayer was prayed out. 
</p>
<p>
About an hour later, I rode up to the station, 
mounted on my own horse, and leading Shem's 
by the bridle. 
</p>
<p>
"Halloa! pull up, pull up, or I'll plug ye, 
sure as my name's Bradshaw!" shouted a stern 
voice through a loophole of the lonely blockhouse. 
And I saw the long clouded barrel of a 
frontier rifle pointing in my direction. I halted, 
of course. 
</p>
<p>
"That's one of our hosses," cried a second 
voice; "the critter's stole it, I reckon. What 
is he?" 
</p>
<p>
"I am a friend," I called out; "a traveller 
from California. Let me come in, and I will 
explain all." 
</p>
<p>
The garrison held a short but animated 
debate. One man avowed his belief in the truth 
of my story, another broadly hinted that I 
might turn out a "renegade" or "white 
Indian," that I merely wanted to open the doors 
of the fortress to my ferocious allies, ambushed 
somewhere hard by, and that it would be as 
well to shoot me, as a provisional act of 
prudence. But the majority carries the day in 
America; and, luckily for me, the majority 
decreed my admission. Loud was the surprise, 
and sincere the sorrow, with which the little 
garrison received the news of their comrade's 
murder. Three of the men caught up such rude 
tools as they possessed, and, slinging their rifles, 
prepared to take the "back trail" to the spot 
where the unfortunate young man's body lay, 
and where his remains would be hastily laid in 
earth, after the custom of the frontiers. 
Another hurried, with all the instinct of discipline, 
to saddle a horse for the purpose of carrying 
forward the mail-bag which poor Shem had resigned 
only with his life. This rider was the most 
affected of the group, by the melancholy tidings 
I had brought. He would have preferred to be 
one of those who were to lay his old associate 
beneath the prairie turf, but this could not be. 
He was "next for duty," he said, simply, with 
tears standing in his hardy eyes. So, he hurried 
to equip himself and steed for the perilous road. 
I now ventured, rather timidly and awkwardly, 
to prefer my request for the accommodation of 
fresh relays of horses along the rest of the route, 
speaking as modestly as I could of my own 
preservation of the despatches. The men looked 
puzzled as they scrutinised me and weighed my 
demand. One of them, he who had taken me 
for a renegade white in the Indian interest, gave 
me a piercing glance, and gruffly said, "How do 
we know he ain't been bamfoozling us with a 
pack of lies? He may have murdered Shem, 
ye see, jest to get a remount, and--" 
</p>
<p>
"You jest shut up!" thundered, in tones of 
deep indignation, the rider who was to carry on 
the mails. "You oughter to be ashamed of that 
tongue o' yourn, Jethro Summers. Here's a 
gentleman, and what's more, an honest chap, 
has fit by poor Shem's side, has saved his scalp 
from them Shoshonies, and brought on the bag 
for us, and you're to insult him with your mean 
talk. See! his hoss is fresh, and he's brought 
in Shem's hoss; and you to go telling him he'd 
murder a white Christian to get a lift. It's a 
burnin' shame, Jeth Summers!" 
</p>
<p>
"'Tis, 'tis!" exclaimed the other two men. 
</p>
<p>
"Did ye ever know a darned renegade look a 
chap in the face, bold and honest, like the 
colonel, there? He's a good chap, is mister; 
and if ever he wants a friend in a rough-and-
tumble fight, we're his men, sure as minks can 
swim." 
</p>
<p>
The trio shook hands with me with genuine 
warmth. Now, when the iron was hot, was 
the time to strike. I therefore made an 
energetic appeal to them to supply me with 
horses, assuring them that my whole prospects 
and happiness, as well as those of others, 
depended on my speed. They listened with 
interest; but when I concluded with the words, 
"Shem Grindrod wished it; he bade me ask it 
of you, as he lay dying," the game was won. 
To be sure, the one ill-conditioned member of 
the community grumbled out something about 
"soft sawder, breach of rules, cunning Yankees, 
and dismissal." But the tall rider cut, him 
short, by affirming with an oath, that "if the 
Co. chose to ride nasty on such a point, after 
the stranger's services, why the Co. was a mean 
scamp, and he wouldn't serve 'em, for one." 
I did not at first exactly comprehend this 
frequently-recurring phrase of the "Co.," and was 
disposed to regard it as the name of some over-
looker, or superintendent, but afterwards 
discovered that this monosyllabic impersonation 
meant the Express Company. 
</p>
<p>
"Look sharp, mister. You shall have a 
mount, but there's time lost a'ready, and we 
shall have to ride whip and spur. Come and 
pick a nag out of the corral. There's a brindled 
mustang your saddle will fit like his skin. The 
roan's best, but his back's rubbed raw. Ask Jonas 
to give you some beef and biscuit: we shan't 
pass many hot-els, that air positive. Charge 
that revolver o' yourn, colonel; I see two 
bullets a-missing. Have a horn of whisky--old 
Monongahela? No! Do be spry with the 
saddle, you Jeth--a man should help in a case 
like this. Easy, mister, with the bridle--the 
mustang bites--so! We'll take care of your 
nag, and you'll find him as sleek as a slug, if 
you come back our way. Good-by, boys!" 
</p>
<p>
So saying, the impatient rider finished his 
preparations, sprang to his saddle, waved his 
repeating carbine over his head, and set off 
at furious speed. I followed as rapidly as I 
could, shouting a farewell to those left behind, 
who were on the point of starting for the place 
where poor Shem was lying beside the corpses 
of his copper-hued foes, stiff and stark. 
</p>
<p>
The brindled mustang was fat and lazy, 
compared with the nimble cream-coloured pony on 
which my guide was mounted. It took all my 
exertions to overtake 'Demus Blake, whose 
name was probably Aristodemus, though thus 
curtailed by usage. We rode at a tremendous 
pace. 
</p>
<p>
"Larrup your beast, colonel," cried the 
rider, "we're woful behind. Don't be stingy 
with the spur-iron, for that brindle does allays 
shirk when he can. Mind--'ware the sappy 
ground, where you see them clubby mosses! 
Jordan! they'd take a hoss up to the girths, 
and there you'd stop, like a tree'd coon. Push 
on, sir. Rattle him across them riv'lets: not 
that a parara hoss can jump like the critters 
from the U-nited States." 
</p>
<p>
It struck me that 'Demus Blake was bawling 
and flogging in this excited way, for no other 
purpose than to quiet his own nerves, and 
drown care. I was confirmed in this view by 
the fact that, after six or seven miles had been 
swallowed up by the rapid career of our foam-
flecked steeds, the rider reined his horse into a 
steady hand-gallop. 
</p>
<p>
"There, mister," said he, "we'll go quiet 
now. I feels kiender easier under my left ribs. 
Tell'ee, colonel, little as you think it, to look at 
such as me, I was as near making the biggest 
baby of myself--there, I was! Poor boy Shem! 
I knowed him, sir, oncommon well, and 
oncommon long. We played about together, when we 
were as high as a ramrod, in Pequottie 
village, nigh to Utica, in old Kentuck. And 
when old Amos and my daddy, Jonathan Blake, 
calculated to move west, they chose the same 
location. Sad news for old Amos--a white-
haired old chap now, but pretty tough, too. He's 
at Brown's Hole--no, at Round Pond--trading 
for peltry. I wouldn't care to have the tellin' 
on him." 
</p>
<p>
The rider was silent for a good while after 
this. He did not speak again till I paid a 
merited tribute to Shem's courage. I had found 
him, I said, fronting seven Indians like a stag at 
bay. The frontiers-man's eye glittered proudly: 
</p>
<p>
"A brave boy, sir. I was with him, first 
fight--that is, Shem's first, cause I'm two year 
an older man. 'Twarn't hereaway. South of 
Fremont's Pass it wur, and bloody Blackfoot 
Indians war the inimy, three to one, on'y they'd 
no fire-arms. 'Twarn't child's play that day, 
mister!" The backwoodsman expanded his 
broad chest, while his nostrils dilated, and his 
lips tightened, as he recalled the arduous 
struggle long past. 
</p>
<p>
He was a much stronger man than Shem, of 
a spirit less gay and lightsome, but not without 
a certain amount of rude practical poetry in his 
disposition. He knew Shem's sweetheart: a 
very nice-looking girl, of rather a quiet, subdued, 
and pious nature. "Not too common on the 
border, nouther, where even gals mostly has a 
spice of the wild-cat, but, mebbe, that pleased 
Shem." 
</p>
<p>
Of the distress in store for old Amos Grindrod: 
a hunter, once renowned for his prowess 
and skill, whether in warfare of the chase: 
Blake spoke feelingly and with deep conviction. 
</p>
<p>
"'Twill shorten the old man's days, sir, 
but it's lucky the old woman's not alive to 
hear it: she was that tender of Shem, if his 
finger ached she'd flutter like a robbed hen. 
Good old soul she was, Mrs. Grindrod, and 
nursed my old mother when she took the fever 
in that murderin' swamp." 
</p>
<p>
Honest 'Demus had too much innate good-
breeding to be inquisitive as to the purpose of my 
unusual journey. In this respect, as in some 
others, he far surpassed in tact and politeness 
many an accomplished citizen in varnished boots 
and satin vest. But he offered me some well-
meant advice. 
</p>
<p>
"Take it coolly," said he, "and don't flurry 
yourself, colonel. You've got more colour in 
your cheeks than need be, and your hand was 
as hot, when I shook it, as a bit of deer-meat 
toastin' over the fire. I don't know as you 
ain't right, shirking the whisky, though 'tis food 
and comfort to such as me. But a smart touch 
of fever would tie you by the leg, stranger, so 
don't fret overly, and sleep all you can. As for 
Injuns, they'll hardly trouble two white men, 
when there's nouthin' to be got but a kipple of 
nags that can be bought for a cast of the lasso, 
or larist. The emigrant trains is different, for 
the Red devils scent plunder in the waggons, 
and only the dragoons skear 'em. Twar spite 
med the Mad Buffalo fall on Shem Grindrod. 
Shem give him a coat o' tar and turkey feathers 
one night, at Bridger's Fort, when the Injun 
got so drunk with whisky some rascal sold him, 
he lay like a hog on the ground. They never 
forgive, them Injuns. Shoshonies have no pity, 
compared to the savages east of the Rocky 
Mountains. Keep a look out for outlying war 
parties, mister, when you get to the mountain 
parks. Crows will take hoss and clothes; 
Blackfeet allays hanker arter ha'r!" 
</p>
<p>
I took my guide's well-meant advice, and 
endeavoured to get through the journey as 
phlegmatically as might be. I snatched every 
opportunity of repose, if only for a few minutes, 
while the reeking saddles were being shifted to 
the backs of fresh horses; and it is wonderful 
how much refreshment I at times derived 
from a nap so brief as not much to exceed 
the traditional "forty winks." More than once, 
my companion said to me, "Colonel, you're 
about dropping with sleep. Shut your eyes, if 
you like, and give me your reins. I'll guide 
both hosses, and you can't hardly roll out of 
that cradle o' yourn." And, indeed, the deep 
Mexican saddle of demipique cut, which I had 
luckily provided on starting, was admirably 
adapted, with its lofty pommel and cantel, to 
the use of a dozing equestrian. Curious spells 
of slumber those were, when my head would nod 
like that of a porcelain mandarin, and my eyelids 
droop as if weighted with lead, and when, after 
a few minutes, I would start up, broad awake, 
as my mustang stumbled over broken ground. 
</p>
<p>
Once--it was while 'Demus Blake was still with 
me--I had a long and most delicious period 
of slumber, an interrupted by jerks or concussions; 
and when I awoke, quite a new man, and 
revived to an extent at which I now wonder, I 
found myself supported by the strong patient 
arm of my conductor, who had been galloping 
by my side for miles, managing both 
bridles with his disengaged hand. "I thought it 
would fresh you up, colonel!" said the brave 
fellow. 
</p>
<p>
Not all my mentors throughout that phantom 
ride across prairieland were as frank as Blake, nor 
as merry as Shem. But the mail-bag riders turned 
out good fellows in all main points, and I can safely 
say that I found but two or three surly or ill-
natured persons among all those who garrisoned 
the block-houses: while fortunately it fell to my 
lot on no occasion to be accompanied by one of 
these. In the prairie, as in the world at large, 
I found good-feeling the rule, cynicism or malice 
the exception, though I am bound to say that 
the ill-conditioned individuals made twice as 
much noise and stir as their more amiable mates. 
The first start had been difficult, but at each 
succeeding station I received my remount without 
much delay or parley. The "privilege of the 
post" was conceded to me, while I was always 
welcome to a share of the rations in each little 
community. On the whole, I found the men 
cheerful in their strange isolation. They were 
liberally paid and not ill-fed, and they looked 
forward to a pension in the event of becoming 
crippled by some Indian hatchet-stroke or arrow-
shot. Planted in the wilderness, with the 
prospect of being presently encompassed by deep 
drifts of snow, over whose frozen surface the 
wolves would come to howl and scratch at their 
doors, like dogs seeking admittance, they were 
in fair spirits and undismayed. Their habitual 
talk was of the wild adventures that formed the 
every-day life of that frontier of Christendom; 
of Indian stratagems and cruelty, of panthers 
and "grizzlies," pronghorns and buffaloes. 
Several of them had consorted familiarly with the 
painted tribes of the desert, and spoke sundry 
Indian dialects as fluently as their mother tongue. 
I found these hardy men kind hosts enough; 
they would hush their talk, not to disturb me 
as I lay down on a heap of skins and blankets, 
to sleep, while the guide saddled the horses; 
and they soon ceased to ridicule my apparently 
capricious refusal of whisky. "Mebbe the 
colonel's right!" (Colonel is the Western title 
of courtesy), they would say in their blunt politeness. 
Once I found the inmates of a station, 
built on swampy ground, quite helpless and 
prostrate with fever. The fever had abated when 
the healthy norther began to blow, but the poor 
fellows were cramped with pains, and very 
feeble, and only one of the party could crawl 
about to cook and feed the fire. I had need to 
fix my mind on the reward of success, on the 
distant goal glittering far ahead, for it was no 
light task that I had undertaken. The thought 
of Emma nerved me, and I felt an Englishman's 
dogged resolve to win, to fight on, and 
to break sooner than bend. But the fatigues 
of that journey surpassed all my conceptions. 
By day and night, under a glaring sun or through 
the frost and cutting northerly winds, on we 
pressed, fording streams, threading the way 
through marshes, stumbling among the burrows 
of prairie dogs, or dashing across boundless 
plains. I almost learned to hate the long 
terraces of turf, the illimitable sweeps of dark 
green surface, the blue horizons, the swells of 
gently sloping earth, smooth enough for the 
passage of wheeled carriages. On we went, till 
the long grass, mixed with flowers and wild 
tufts of the flax-cotton, gave place to a shorter 
and crisper herbage, the true "buffalo grass" 
that the bisons love; or till water became 
scarce, and the sage plant replaced the 
blossomed shrubs of the west, and the springs were 
brackish, and here and there our horses' hoofs 
went cranching over a white stretch of desert, 
strewn with crystals of salt that glittered in the 
sun. We saw little of Indians, and of game 
still less. The latter, my guides told me, had 
been chiefly scared away, by the constant 
passage of emigrants. As for the savages, we 
sometimes saw the plumed heads, the tapering 
lances, and the fluttering robes, of a troop of 
wild horsemen, against the crimson sky of evening; 
but they offered us no molestation, and the 
riders said they were Utahs on the look-out for 
"buffler droves" returning from the south. Of 
the fatigue of that interminable ride, the aching 
joints, the stiffened sinews, the pains that 
racked my overstrained muscles, I can give no 
just idea. Still less can I convey any sense 
of the continual strain upon the intellect and 
the perceptive faculties, or how my brain grew 
as weary as my limbs. 
</p>
<p>
I shall never forget the evening of my arrival 
in Salt Lake City, the capital of Utah territory, 
and New Jerusalem of the Mormons. I had 
been encouraged by the guides, to look upon this 
town in the deserts as a turning-point in the 
journey, beyond which I should be in less peril 
from Indians, and after which a comparatively 
short ride would carry me to more civilised 
regions. But, to my surprise, I found the 
inmates of the station at Salt Lake City quite 
as lonely as, and more suspicious and moody than, 
in the far-off posts among the prairies. They 
were Gentiles in the midst of a fanatic 
population, wholly swayed by the hierarchy of that 
strange creed whose standard had been set up 
in the lawless wastes of the west. Nor was it 
long before I heard the cause of their dark 
looks and low spirits. 
</p>
<p>
"Where's Josh Hudson?" asked the rider 
who had come with me, when the first greetings 
had been exchanged. 
</p>
<p>
"Who knows?" answered the man 
addressed; "I don't. Seth said he went to the 
town, while I were in the corral with the hosses. 
If so, all I can say is, he never come back." 
</p>
<p>
"When was that, Seth?" asked the newly-
arrived rider. 
</p>
<p>
"Two days agone," answered Seth, as he 
scraped the surface of a half-exhausted quid of 
tobacco with his long sharp bowie-knife, "jest 
afore sundown." 
</p>
<p>
"He's not desarted. Josh was too honourable 
to make tracks, that way," said the rider, 
confidently. 
</p>
<p>
"Desarted! Not he. But that's what'll have 
to be put in the report--leastways, missin'," 
said Seth. 
</p>
<p>
The rider looked Seth in the face, and drew 
his forefinger, with a meaning look, slowly 
across his own throat. Seth nodded. 
</p>
<p>
"Least said, safest," said Seth, looking 
dubiously at me. 
</p>
<p>
"Colonel's safe. You may speak afore him, 
same as myself, boys!" cried the mail-bag rider, 
who had come with me; "do ye mean them 
bloodthirsty Mormons--?" 
</p>
<p>
"Whist, Jem! Whew! You'll get all our 
throats cut," cried the oldest man, starting up 
in great alarm; "there may be one of the brutes 
within earshot." He looked through the window, 
and opened the door, to satisfy himself that no 
eavesdroppers were near. 
</p>
<p>
"I forgot," apologised Jem; "but about Josh 
Hudson?" 
</p>
<p>
"I'm afeard," answered Seth, in a voice 
dropped almost to a whisper, "that he's gone 
for good. Josh was troubled about his sister, 
Nell Hudson, that jined the Mormons last 
winter, up in Illinoy, and was coaxed off, and is 
here, somewhere." 
</p>
<p>
"Ah," said the listener, "I heerd as much." 
</p>
<p>
"It's my belief," continued Seth, "that Josh 
got on this station a purpose to seek the gal 
out, and get her to go home to the old folks and 
the Church she were bred in. Mormons won't 
stand that." 
</p>
<p>
"Ah!" said the guide Jem again. 
</p>
<p>
"So, in short, Seth and me some think, we 
do," said the oldest of the group, "that Josh 
has been at his scoutin' onst too often, and met 
'shanpip.'" 
</p>
<p>
"Shanpip!" I repeated; "what is that?" 
</p>
<p>
The man eyed me curiously. "Never heerd 
of 'Shanpip brethren,' then, harn't ye, mister? 
So much the best for you. P'raps you've 
heerd tell of Danites?" 
</p>
<p>
I had heard, vaguely and obscurely, of that 
spiritual police of Mormondom, of those fierce 
zealots who obey their Prophet blindly. 
</p>
<p>
"Then you have reason to fear that your 
comrade is--" 
</p>
<p>
"Is lyin' under the salt mud of one o' them 
briny pools nigh to hand," interrupted the man, 
"and not alone, nouther. Theer's been a many 
missin', that never went back to settlements nor 
on to Californey. And theer they'll lie hid, I 
reckon, till the Day of Judgment, when Great 
Salt Lake shall give up its dead, like the rest 
of the airth and waters." 
</p>
<p>
I asked if an appeal could not be made to the 
Mormon elders themselves? 
</p>
<p>
"'Twouldn't answer, colonel. Suppose I goes 
to-morrow to Brigham's own house, or Kimball's, 
or any of their big men--elders, or angels, or 
high priests, or what not--and asks after Josh 
Hudson. Brigham's very mealy-mouthed, afraid 
the man's run away; what could be expected 
from a benighted Gentile, and that; gives 
his own account of it in preachment next Sabbath. 
P'raps one of 'em gives me a glass of wine or a 
julep, and mebbe it disagrees with me, and I 
die of it. You may stare, but didn't the States 
treasurer die that way, arter takin' refreshment at 
Angel Badger's house? And a pretty angel he be. 
P'raps I don't drink under a Mormon roof, and 
then, mebbe, I walk home late, and lose my way, 
or some other accident happens me--true as 
death, mister, on'y last week, as I passed Big 
Lick, I saw a dead woman's face looking up at 
me, all white and still, at bottom, of the salt 
pool." 
</p>
<p>
Thus far the elder man had spoken, but now 
Seth, who had evinced great uneasiness, jumped 
up with an oath, and cautiously opened the door. 
No one was listening. 
</p>
<p>
"Tell'ee what," said Seth, "we'd best keep 
this discoorse close, till we're outside the territory. 
They're that sharp, Mormons, blessed if 
I don't think they're all ear. And if they get's 
a notion what we're sayin', the colonel won't 
never see New York, and I shan't never happen 
home to Montgomery agin. Indian Walker and 
his pesky Utahs mostly got a knack of 
tomahawking them as Mormons don't much like. 
And mebbe we'd meet other Indians, with 
blankets and red paint on their faces, jest like 
the real Utahs, and pretty sharp knives in their 
belts." 
</p>
<p>
"Seth's right," said my former guide; "we 
don't want to set up any chaps to paint Injun 
on our account, as Angel Brown and Young 
Harris and the Danites did, when Martha 
Styles and Rachel Willis chose to go home to 
Illinoy--so, colonel, you get a snooze, and Seth, 
you needn't hurry about saddlin'--we've rode 
awful quick." 
</p>
<p>
I was not sorry when day-dawn found me, 
after a hard gallop by moonlight, approaching 
the confines of the Mormon territory. The 
rest of the journey was unmarked by adventure. 
Hardships there were, but no great perils. We 
traversed a route on which the bleached bones 
of many horses and mules lay white and ghastly, 
and on which many a low turfen mound marked 
the last resting-place of an emigrant, or his wife 
or child, never to reach the Promised Land of 
Hope. 
</p>
<p>
But provisions were more plentiful now, and 
water more regularly stored and easy of access, 
than when the expelled Mormons made their 
famous march across the desert, marking the 
untrodden route with graves. We narrowly 
escaped being smothered in the snow, in passing 
the outlet in the Rocky Mountains, and this 
was our last semblance of peril. 
</p>
<p>
Previous to this, it had been my sad duty to 
tell old Amos Grindrod, whom I found at the 
Round Pond Station, of his son's death, and to 
commit to his care the bit of ensanguined ribbon 
that was to be returned to poor Shem's 
sweetheart. The old man tried to bear the 
tidings with the stoicism of those Indians 
among whom he had passed much of his life, 
and expressed great pleasure at hearing that 
Shem had "died like a Kentucky man, clear 
grit," and that I had come up in time to save 
his scalp. But in a few minutes, nature 
conquered. The old man's bronzed features worked 
and twitched, and tears trickled from his aged 
eyes, as he sobbed out, "Shem! dear boy 
Shem! 'twas I that oughter be dead, not he." 
</p>
<p>
At last the weary ride was over: we had 
passed outlying farms guarded by a strong 
stockade, then the farms grew thicker and the 
stockades were dispensed with, and at last the 
roofs of a village, called by courtesy a town, 
came in view. Gladly did I dismount, gladly 
did I shake the hard hand of the last rider of 
the Express Company! Leaving that honest 
fellow puzzling over the cabalistic flourishes 
of a ten-dollar note I presented to him, I 
hired a pair-horse waggon of light build, and 
set off at once. The waggon bore me on 
until I exchanged it for a coach, the coach did 
me the same good office until I heard the snort 
of the steam-horse, and took my ticket by railway. 
How delicious, how snug and luxurious was 
such a mode of travel, after so much hard 
saddlework! Corduroy roads seemed smooth, and 
American railroads not in the least addicted to 
cause the trains to jerk or rock. The gliding 
motion was charming, and I made amends for 
lost time, by sleeping in a manner which 
provoked more than one fellow-traveller, eager to 
know my business and station in life. 
</p>
<p>
I had already telegraphed to New York briefly 
thus: 
</p>
<p>
"Has the Californian mail, via Panama, arrived?" 
</p>
<p>
Briefer still was the answer: 
</p>
<p>
"No." 
</p>
<p>
That was right, so far. My toil was not 
yet purposeless. I might hope to be in New 
York before Dr., or Colonel, Joram Heckler. 
The victory, to be sure, was not yet won. 
The valuable papers remained in the scoundrel's 
keeping. But my presence in New York 
would be unsuspected by him, and any overt act 
on my part would have the effect of a surprise. 
I was too exhausted, to devote myself to spinning 
air-drawn schemes for outwitting the 
intriguer. I should have need of all my faculties 
when the tug of war began, and I must sleep now. 
Sleep I did, over miles and miles, over leagues 
and leagues, of the iron way: resting obstinately, 
and being as passive as possible. 
</p>
<p>
"Massa get out? Dis New York, sare." 
</p>
<p>
Some one was shaking me by the arm: some 
one else held a lantern to my face. A black 
man and a white. The conductor, and a negro 
porter. 
</p>
<p>
"I'm going to the Metropolitan Hotel. I 
want a hack: no luggage. Has the Californian 
mail arrived?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, it has," said a newsvendor, who stood 
by, with aheap of journals under his arm; "got 
all the news here. Herald, Tribune, Times. 
Which will you have?" 
</p>
<p>
I bought one of the papers, and glanced at the 
list of arrivals viâ Panama. So much gold dust, 
so much bullion, distinguished European 
traveller, postmaster-general, Signora Cantatini, 
Colonels Thom, Heckler, &amp;c. The driver of the 
hack-carriage was an Irishman, as usual, and, 
luckily, not a new arrival. He readily conducted 
me (at that late hour all other stores and shops 
were closed) to the emporium of a Jew dealer in 
ready-made clothes, who was willing to turn a 
cent even at irregular time. I purchased a new 
suit, linen, a portmanteau, and so forth, and 
shaved off my stubbly beard with razors 
supplied by the Jew, and before the Jew's private 
looking-glass. My driver drove quite a trim, 
ordinary-looking gentleman to the Metropolitan 
Hotel, instead of the shaggy fiannel-shirted 
Californian who had first engaged him. 
</p>
<p>
Before I engaged a room, I civilly asked the 
bookkeeper to let me look at the addresses of 
guests: I was expecting my brother, I said, 
from Albany. I took good care to say nothing 
of Heckler or California, and the bookkeeper 
had no suspicion that my voyages had 
commenced at any more remote spot than 
Philadelphia or Baltimore. Yes--Heckler's name 
was down. 
</p>
<p>
I had guessed he would put up at the 
Metropolitan, for I had heard him mention the house 
approvingly in conversation. I hung about the 
bar and the staircases until I happened to hear 
that he had gone to bed. Then, I withdrew to 
think over my own plan of operations. I own I 
was puzzled. I tossed and tumbled uneasily on 
my pillow. While hurrying onward it had 
appeared as if I had but to arrive in time, and the 
difficulty was at an end; but now, what was I 
to do? The battle had yet to be fought. What 
should I do? In the morning, no doubt, 
Heckler would repair to the bank, to present 
the forged cheque, if not to get the bills 
discounted. I must stop him. But how? 
Should I go to the police, and return with 
the police myrmidons? Not to be thought 
of! Scandal, exposure, must follow such a step; 
nay, in the eyes of the law, Heckler might seem 
an innocent man, and I a false accuser. I next 
thought of confronting him boldly, and forcing 
from him, with a pistol at his head, if need be, 
the property of the firm. But this was too 
Quixotic a proceeding to be adopted in a first-
rate hotel in New York. I was at my wits' 
end. 
</p>
<p>
Heavens! What a smell of burning, and how 
stifling and thick the air! Smoke! The house 
is on fire. Up I sprang, and flung on my clothes 
in hot haste. "It's an ill wind that blows no 
one any good." I thought of Joram Heckler 
as I rang my bell to alarm the people. 
</p>
<p>
"Fire! fire!" The awful cry broke upon the 
ears of the sleepers, like the trump of doom. 
Dark clouds of volleying smoke poured along 
the corridors, flecked here and there by thin 
ribbons of flame that licked the walls and floors 
like the tongues of fiery serpents. Shrieks were 
heard; doors were burst open; men, women, 
children, rushed out, half-dressed and screaming. 
There was panic terror and wild confusion. 
The fire gained ground, the smoke was 
blindingly thick, and all fled before it--all but 
myself. I steadily groped my way towards 
Joram Heckler's room. I knew the number, 
and where to find it. I knew that I risked 
my life, but the stake was worth winning at 
such a risk. I was very nearly suffocated as I 
pushed on, holding by the wall, into the 
thickest of the smoke. Some man, half-dressed, 
and winged by fear, came rushing by with 
extended arms, and nearly overturned me. He 
uttered a savage oath; the red glare of the 
fire fell on his face; it was Joram Heckler. 
</p>
<p>
He did not recognise me, but dashed on, only 
mindful of his danger. Had he the papers with 
him? I thought not. I hoped not. That was 
his room then, the door of which was ajar, and 
into which the smoke was rolling. Not the 
smoke alone; I saw a thin red tongue of fire 
creeping in over the floor, beside the wainscot. 
I dashed in. My eyes smarted with the smoke, 
and I gasped for breath, but smoke and fire 
could not turn me now. Heckler's clothes 
and dressing-case were as he had laid them; 
the latter was open: no papers! His valise, 
too, lay open: no papers! I struck my forehead 
despairingly. He had them about him then! I 
was risking life idly. Emma was lost to me! 
The smoke choked me: the intolerably hot fire 
had gained the bed: valance and curtains were 
flaring high in a tall yellow pillar of flame. The 
subtle tongues of flame almost touched my feet. 
I must fly, if I would not perish. Outside, I 
heard the noise of the engines and the cheers of 
the mob, and then, the dash of water, as 
prodigious efforts were made to extinguish the fire. 
</p>
<p>
I was staggering away, when I saw, peeping 
from under the bolster of the bed, a Russia-
leather pocket-book. The rascal had forgotten it 
in his blind terror. The blazing curtains fell in 
fragments upon me, and my hands were a good 
deal scorched, but I rescued the precious prize. I 
tore it open. Yes, cheque and bills, all were 
there! Thrusting it into my breast-pocket, I 
left the room, and struggled as I best could 
down the passage. Dash after dash of water, 
flung from hand-buckets, had partially subdued 
the flames, and the firemen were gaining the 
victory. Half smothered, singed, blackened, 
but with a proudly beating heart, I forced my 
way down the heated and crowded staircase--
reached the outer air, and fainted. 
</p>
<p>
I have little more to tell. I am a partner in 
the firm: Emma is my wife; her brother 
recovered from his illness, and is now, in another 
land, an altered and penitent man. The house of 
Spalding, Hausermann, and Co. (I am Co.) 
have granted a pension to the poor girl who was 
to have been the bride of the luckless Shem 
Grindrod. Of Heckler we heard no more. 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up Miss Kimmeens."/>
<p>
THE day was by this time waning, when the 
gate again opened, and, with the brilliant golden 
light that streamed from the declining sun and 
touched the very bars of the sooty creature's 
den, there passed in a little child; a little girl 
with beautiful bright hair. She wore a plain 
straw hat, had a door-key in her hand, and 
tripped towards Mr. Traveller as if she were 
pleased to see him and were going to repose 
some childish confidence in him, when she caught 
sight of the figure behind the bars, and started 
back in terror. 
</p>
<p>
"Don't be alarmed, darling!" said Mr. 
Traveller, taking her by the hand. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, but I don't like it!" urged the shrinking 
child; "it's dreadful." 
</p>
<p>
"Well! I don't like it, either," said Mr. 
Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Who has put it there?" asked the little 
girl. "Does it bite?" 
</p>
<p>
"No,--only barks. But can't you make up 
your mind to see it, my dear?" For she was 
 covering her eyes. 
</p>
<p>
"O no no no!" returned the child. "I 
cannot bear to look at it!" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller turned his head towards his 
friend in there, as much as to ask him how he 
liked that instance of his success, and then took 
the child out at the still open gate, and stood 
talking to her for some half an hour in the 
mellow sunlight. At length he returned, 
encouraging her as she held his arm with both her 
hands; and laying his protecting hand upon her 
head and smoothing her pretty hair, he 
addressed his friend behind the bars as follows: 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
MISS PUPFORD'S establishment for six 
young ladies of tender years, is an 
establishment of a compact nature, an establishment 
in miniature, quite a pocket establishment. Miss 
Pupford, Miss Pupford's assistant with the 
Parisian accent, Miss Pupford's cook, and Miss 
Pupford's housemaid, complete what Miss Pupford 
calls the educational and domestic staff of her 
Lilliputian College. 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pupford is one of the most amiable of 
her sex; it necessarily follows that she possesses 
a sweet temper, and would own to the possession 
of a great deal of sentiment if she 
considered it quite reconcilable with her duty to 
parents. Deeming it not in the bond, Miss 
Pupford keeps it as far out of sight as she can--
which (God bless her!) is not very far. 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pupford's assistant with the Parisian 
accent, may be regarded as in some sort an 
inspired lady, for she never conversed with a 
Parisian, and was never out of England--except 
once in the pleasure-boat, Lively, in the foreign 
waters that ebb and flow two miles off Margate 
at high water. Even under those geographically 
favourable circumstances for the acquisition of 
the French language in its utmost politeness 
and purity, Miss Pupford's assistant did not fully 
profit by the opportunity; for, the pleasure-boat, 
Lively, so strongly asserted its title to its name 
on that occasion, that she was reduced to the 
condition of lying in the bottom of the boat 
pickling in brine as if she were being salted 
down, for the use of the Navy--undergoing at 
the same time great mental alarm, corporeal 
distress, and clear-starching derangement. 
</p>
<p>
When Miss Pupford and her assistant first 
foregathered, is not known to men, or pupils. 
But, it was long ago. A belief would hare 
established itself among pupils that the two once went 
to school together, were it not for the difficulty 
and audacity of imagining Miss Pupford born 
without mittens, and without a front, and without 
a bit of gold wire among her front teeth, and 
without little dabs of powder on her neat 
little face and nose. Indeed, whenever Miss 
Pupford gives a little lecture on the mythology 
of the misguided heathens (always carefully 
excluding Cupid from recognition), and tells how 
Minerva sprang, perfectly equipped, from the 
brain of Jupiter, she is half supposed to hint, 
"So I myself came into the world, completely 
up in Pinnock, Mangnall, Tables, and the use of 
the Globes." 
</p>
<p>
Howbeit, Miss Pupford and Miss Pupford's 
assistant are old old friends. And it is thought 
by pupils that, after pupils are gone to bed, they 
even call one another by their christian names in 
the quiet little parlour. For, once upon a time 
on a thunderous afternoon, when Miss Pupford 
fainted away without notice, Miss Pupford's 
assistant (never heard, before or since, to address 
her otherwise than as Miss Pupford) ran to her, 
crying out "My dearest Euphemia!" And 
Euphemia is Miss Pupford's christian name on 
the sampler (date picked out) hanging up in the 
College-hall, where the two peacocks, terrified 
to death by some German text that is waddling 
down hill after them out of a cottage, are 
scuttling away to hide their profiles in two 
immense bean-stalks growing out of flower-pots. 
</p>
<p>
Also, there is a notion latent among pupils, 
that Miss Pupford was once in love, and that the 
beloved object still moves upon this ball. Also, 
that he is a public character, and a personage of 
vast consequence. Also, that Miss Pupford's 
assistant knows all about it. For, sometimes of 
an afternoon when Miss Pupford has been reading 
the paper through her little gold eye-glass 
(it is necessary to read it on the spot, as the boy 
calls for it, with ill-conditioned punctuality, in 
an hour), she has become agitated, and has said 
to her assistant, "G!" Then Miss Pupford's 
assistant has gone to Miss Pupford, and Miss 
Pupford has pointed out, with her eye-glass, 
G in the paper, and then Miss Pupford's 
assistant has read about G, and has shown 
sympathy. So stimulated has the pupil-mind been 
in its time to curiosity on the subject of G, that 
once, under temporary circumstances favourable 
to the bold sally, one fearless pupil did actually 
obtain possession of the paper, and range all over 
it in search of G, who had been discovered therein 
by Miss Pupford not ten minutes before. But no 
G could be identified, except one capital offender 
who had been executed in a state of great hardihood, 
and it was not to be supposed that Miss 
Pupford could ever have loved him. Besides, 
he couldn't be always being executed. Besides, 
he got into the paper again, alive, within a 
month. 
</p>
<p>
On the whole, it is suspected by the pupil-mind 
that G is a short chubby old gentleman, with 
little black sealing-wax boots up to his knees, 
whom a sharply observant pupil, Miss Linx, when 
she once went to Tunbridge Wells with Miss 
Pupford for the holidays, reported on her return 
(privately and confidentially) to have seen come 
capering up to Miss Pupford on the Promenade, 
and to have detected in the act of squeezing Miss 
Pupford's hand, and to have heard pronounce the 
words, "Cruel Euphemia, ever thine!"--or 
something like that. Miss Linx hazarded a guess that 
he might be House of Commons, or Money 
Market, or Court Circular, or Fashionable 
Movements; which would account for his getting 
into the paper so often. But, it was fatally 
objected by the pupil-mind, that none of those 
notabilities could possibly be spelt with a G. 
</p>
<p>
There are other occasions, closely watched and 
perfectly comprehended by the pupil-mind, when 
Miss Pupford imparts with mystery to her 
assistant that there is special excitement in the 
morning paper. These occasions are, when Miss 
Pupford finds an old pupil coming out under the 
head of Births, or Marriages. Affectionate tears 
are invariably seen in Miss Pupford's meek little 
eyes when this is the case; and the pupil-mind, 
perceiving that its order has distinguished itself--
though the fact is never mentioned by Miss 
Pupford--becomes elevated, and feels that it 
likewise is reserved for greatness. 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pupford's assistant with the Parisian 
accent has a little more bone than Miss Pupford, 
but is of the same trim orderly diminutive cast, 
and, from long contemplation, admiration, and 
imitation of Miss Pupford, has grown like her. 
Being entirely devoted to Miss Pupford, and 
having a pretty talent for pencil-drawing, she 
once made a portrait of that lady: which was so 
instantly identified and hailed by the pupils, that 
it was done on stone at five shillings. Surely the 
softest and milkiest stone that ever was quarried, 
received that likeness of Miss Pupford! The lines 
of her placid little nose are so undecided in it that 
strangers to the work of art are observed to be 
exceedingly perplexed as to where the nose goes 
to, and involuntarily feel their own noses in a 
disconcerted manner. Miss Pupford being 
represented in a state of dejection at an open window, 
ruminating over a bowl of gold fish, the pupil-
mind has settled that the bowl was presented by 
G, and that he wreathed the bowl with flowers of 
soul, and that Miss Pupford is depicted as waiting 
for him on a memorable occasion when he was 
behind his time. 
</p>
<p>
The approach of the last Midsummer holidays 
had a particular interest for the pupil mind, by 
reason of its knowing that Miss Pupford was 
bidden, on the second day of those holidays, to 
the nuptials of a former pupil. As it was 
impossible to conceal the fact--so extensive were 
the dress-making preparations--Miss Pupford 
openly announced it. But, she held it due to 
parents to make the announcement with an air of 
gentle melancholy, as if marriage were (as indeed 
it exceptionally has been) rather a calamity. With 
an air of softened resignation and pity, therefore, 
Miss Pupford went on with her preparations; 
and meanwhile no pupil ever went up-stairs, or 
came down, without peeping in at the door of 
Miss Pupford's bedroom (when Miss Pupford 
wasn't there), and bringing back some surprising 
intelligence concerning the bonnet. 
</p>
<p>
The extensive preparations being completed on 
the day before the holidays, an unanimous 
entreaty was preferred to Miss Pupford by the 
pupil-mind--finding expression through Miss 
Pupford's assistant--that she would deign to 
appear in all her splendour. Miss Pupford 
consenting, presented a lovely spectacle. And 
although, the oldest pupil was barely thirteen, 
every one of the six became in two minutes 
perfect in the shape, cut, colour, price, and quality, 
of every article Miss Pupford wore. 
</p>
<p>
Thus delightfully ushered in, the holidays 
began. Five of the six pupils kissed little Kitty 
Kimmeens twenty times over (round total, one 
hundred times, for she was very popular), and so 
went home. Miss Kitty Kimmeens remained 
behind, for her relations and friends were all in 
India, far away. A self-helpful steady little child 
is Miss Kitty Kimmeens: a dimpled child too, and 
a loving. 
</p>
<p>
So, the great marriage-day came, and Miss 
Pupford, quite as much fluttered as any bride 
could be (G! thought Miss Kitty Kimmeens), 
went away, splendid to behold, in the carriage 
that was sent for her. But, not Miss Pupford 
only went away; for Miss Pupford's assistant 
went away with her, on a dutiful visit to an aged 
uncle--though surely the venerable gentleman 
couldn't live in the gallery of the church where 
the marriage was to be, thought Miss Kitty 
Kimmeens--and yet Miss Pupford's assistant had let 
out that she was going there. Where the cook 
was going, didn't appear, but she generally 
conveyed to Miss Kimmeens that she was bound, 
rather against her will, on a pilgrimage to 
perform some pious office that rendered new ribbons 
necessary to her best bonnet, and also sandals to 
her shoes. 
</p>
<p>
"So you see," said the housemaid, when they 
were all gone, "there's nobody left in the house 
but you and me, Miss Kimmeens." 
</p>
<p>
"Nobody else," said Miss Kitty Kimmeens, 
shaking her curls a little sadly. "Nobody!" 
</p>
<p>
"And you wouldn't like your Bella to go too; 
would you Miss Kimmeens?" said the housemaid. 
(She being Bella.) 
</p>
<p>
" N--no," answered little Miss Kimmeens. 
</p>
<p>
" Your poor Bella is forced to stay with you, 
whether she likes it or not; ain't she, Miss 
Kimmeens?" 
</p>
<p>
"Don't you like it?" inquired Kitty. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, you're such a darling, Miss, that it would 
be unkind of your Bella to make objections. Yet 
my brother-in-law has been took unexpected bad 
by this morning's post. And your poor Bella is 
much attached to him, letting alone her favourite 
sister, Miss Kimmeens." 
</p>
<p>
"Is he very ill?" asked little Kitty. 
</p>
<p>
"Your poor Bella has her fears so, Miss 
Kimmeens," returned the housemaid, with her apron 
at her eyes. "It was but his inside, it is true, 
but it might mount, and the doctor said that if it 
mounted he wouldn't answer." Here the housemaid 
was so overcome that Kitty administered 
the only comfort she had ready: which was a kiss. 
</p>
<p>
"If it hadn't been for disappointing Cook, dear 
Miss Kimmeens," said the housemaid, "your 
Bella would have asked her to stay with you. For 
Cook is sweet company, Miss Kimmeens; much 
more so than your own poor Bella." 
</p>
<p>
"But you are very nice, Bella." 
</p>
<p>
"Your Bella could wish to be so, Miss 
Kimmeens," returned the housemaid, "but she knows 
full well that it do not lay in her power this 
day." 
</p>
<p>
With which despondent conviction, the housemaid 
drew a heavy sigh, and shook her head, and 
dropped it on one side. 
</p>
<p>
"If it had been anyways right to disappoint 
Cook," she pursued, in a contemplative and 
abstracted manner, "it might have been so easy 
done! I could have got to my brother-in-law's, 
and had the best part of the day there, and got 
back, long before our ladies come home at night, 
and neither the one nor the other of them need 
never have known it. Not that Miss Pupford 
would at all object, but that it might put her out, 
being tender-hearted. Hows'ever, your own poor 
Bella, Miss Kimmeens," said the housemaid, 
rousing herself, "is forced to stay with you, and 
you're a precious love, if not a liberty." 
</p>
<p>
"Bella," said little Kitty, after a short silence. 
</p>
<p>
"Call your own poor Bella, your Bella, dear," 
the housemaid besought her. 
</p>
<p>
"My Bella, then." 
</p>
<p>
"Bless your considerate heart!" said the 
housemaid. 
</p>
<p>
"If you would not mind leaving me, I should 
not mind being left. I am not afraid to stay in 
the house alone. And you need not be uneasy on 
my account, for I would be very careful to do no 
harm." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh! As to harm, you more than sweetest, 
if not a liberty," exclaimed the housemaid, in a 
rapture, "your Bella could trust you anywhere, 
being so steady, and so answerable. The oldest 
head in this house (me and Cook says), but for 
its bright hair, is Miss Kimmeens. But no, I 
will not leave you; for you would think your 
Bella unkind." 
</p>
<p>
"But if you are my Bella, you must go," 
returned the child. 
</p>
<p>
"Must I?" said the housemaid, rising, on the 
whole with alacrity. "What must be, must be, 
Miss Kimmeens. Your own poor Bella acts 
according, though unwilling. But go or stay, 
your own poor Bella loves you, Miss Kimmeens." 
</p>
<p>
It was certainly go, and not stay, for within 
five minutes Miss Kimmeens's own poor Bella--so 
much improved in point of spirits as to have 
grown almost sanguine on the subject of her 
brother-in-law--went her way, in apparel that 
seemed to have been expressly prepared for some 
festive occasion. Such are the changes of this 
fleeting world, and so short-sighted are we poor 
mortals! 
</p>
<p>
When the house door closed with a bang and 
a shake, it seemed to Miss Kimmeens to be a 
very heavy house door, shutting her up in a 
wilderness of a house. But, Miss Kimmeens being, 
as before stated, of a self-reliant and methodical 
character, presently began to parcel out the long 
summer-day before her. 
</p>
<p>
And first she thought she would go all over 
the house, to make quite sure that nobody with 
a great-coat on and a carving-knife in it, had got 
under one of the beds or into one of the 
cupboards. Not that she had ever before been 
troubled by the image of anybody armed with a 
great-coat and a carving-knife, but that it seemed 
to have been shaken into existence by the shake 
and the bang of the great street door, reverberating 
through the solitary house. So, little Miss 
Kimmeens looked under the five empty beds of 
the five departed pupils, and looked under her 
own bed, and looked under Miss Pupford's bed, 
and looked under Miss Pupford's assistant's bed. 
And when she had done this, and was making 
the tour of the cupboards, the disagreeable 
thought came into her young head, What a very 
alarming thing it would be to find somebody 
with a mask on, like Guy Fawkes, hiding bolt 
upright in a corner and pretending not to be 
alive! However, Miss Kimmeens having finished 
her inspection without making any such 
uncomfortable discovery, sat down in her tidy little 
manner to needlework, and began stitching away 
at a great rate. 
</p>
<p>
The silence all about her soon grew very 
oppressive, and the more so because of the odd 
inconsistency that the more silent it was, the more 
noises there were. The noise of her own needle 
and thread as she stitched, was infinitely louder 
in her ears than the stitching of all the six 
pupils, and of Miss Pupford, and of Miss 
Pupford's assistant, all stitching away at once on a 
nighly emulative afternoon. Then, the schoolroom 
clock conducted itself in a way in which it had 
never conducted itself before--fell lame, somehow, 
and yet persisted in running on as hard and 
as loud as it could: the consequence of which 
behaviour was, that it staggered among the 
minutes in a state of the greatest confusion, and 
knocked them about in all directions without 
appearing to get on with its regular work. 
Perhaps this alarmed the stairs; but be that as it 
might, they began to creak in a most unusual 
manner, and then the furniture began to crack, 
and then poor little Miss Kimmeens, not liking 
the furtive aspect of things in general, began to 
sing as she stitched. But, it was not her own 
voice that she heard--it was somebody else 
making believe to be Kitty, and singing 
excessively flat, without any heart--so as that would 
never mend matters, she left off again. 
</p>
<p>
By-and-by, the stitching became so palpable 
a failure that Miss Kitty Kimmeens folded her 
work neatly, and put it away in its box, and gave 
it up. Then the question arose about reading. 
But no; the book that was so delightful 
when there was somebody she loved for her 
eyes to fall on when they rose from the page, 
had not more heart in it than her own singing 
now. The book went to its shelf as the 
needlework had gone to its box, and, since 
something must be done--thought the child, "I'll go 
put my room to rights." 
</p>
<p>
She shared her room with her dearest little 
friend among the other five pupils, and why then 
should she now conceive a lurking dread of the 
little friend's bedstead? But, she did. There 
was a stealthy air about its innocent white 
curtains, and there were even dark hints of a dead 
girl lying under the coverlet. The great want of 
human company, the great need of a human face, 
began now to express itself in the facility with 
which the furniture put on strange exaggerated 
resemblances to human looks. A chair with a 
menacing frown was horribly out of temper in a 
corner; a most vicious chest of drawers snarled 
at her from between the windows. It was no relief 
to escape from those monsters to the looking-
glass, for the reflexion said, "What? Is that you 
all alone there? How you stare!" And the 
background was all a great void stare as well. 
</p>
<p>
The day dragged on, dragging Kitty with it 
very slowly by the hair of her head, until it was 
time to eat. There were good provisions in the 
pantry, but their right flavour and relish had 
evaporated with the five pupils, and Miss 
Pupford, and Miss Pupford's assistant, and the cook 
and housemaid. Where was the use of laying 
the cloth symmetrically for one small guest, who 
had gone on ever since the morning growing 
smaller and smaller, while the empty house had 
gone on swelling larger and larger? The very 
Grace came out wrong, for who were "we" who 
were going to receive and be thankful? So, Miss 
Kimmeens was not thankful, and found herself 
taking her dinner in very slovenly style--gobbling 
it up, in short, rather after the manner of the 
lower animals, not to particularise the pigs. 
</p>
<p>
But, this was by no means the worst of the 
change wrought out in the naturally loving and 
cheery little creature as the solitary day wore on. 
She began to brood and be suspicious. She 
discovered that she was full of wrongs and injuries. 
All the people she knew, got tainted by her 
lonely thoughts and turned bad. 
</p>
<p>
It was all very well for Papa, a widower in 
India, to send her home to be educated, and to 
pay a handsome round sum every year for her to 
Miss Pupford, and to write charming letters to 
his darling little daughter; but what did he care 
for her being left by herself, when he was (as no 
doubt he always was) enjoying himself in 
company from morning till night? Perhaps he only 
sent her here, after all, to get her out of the way. 
It looked like it--looked like it to-day, that is, 
for she had never dreamed of such a thing before. 
</p>
<p>
And this old pupil who was being married. It 
was insupportably conceited and selfish in the old 
pupil to be married. She was very vain, and very 
glad to show off; but it was highly probable that 
she wasn't pretty; and even if she were pretty 
(which Miss Kimmeens now totally denied), she 
had no business to be married; and, even if 
marriage were conceded, she had no business to ask 
Miss Pupford to her wedding. As to Miss Pupford, 
she was too old to go to any wedding. She ought 
to know that. She had much better attend to 
her business. She had thought she looked nice 
in the morning, but she didn't look nice. She 
was a stupid old thing. G was another stupid 
old thing. Miss Pupford's assistant was another. 
They were all stupid old things together. 
</p>
<p>
More than that: it began to be obvious that 
this was a plot. They had said to one another, 
"Never mind Kitty; you get off, and I'll get 
off; and we'll leave Kitty to look after herself. 
Who cares for her?" To be sure they were right 
in that question; for who did care for her, a poor 
little lonely thing against whom they all planned 
and plotted? Nobody, nobody! Here Kitty 
sobbed. 
</p>
<p>
At all other times she was the pet of the whole 
house, and loved her five companions in return 
with a child's tenderest and most ingenuous 
attachment; but now, the five companions put on 
ugly colours, and appeared for the first time 
under a sullen cloud. There they were, all at 
their homes that day, being made much of, being 
taken out, being spoilt and made disagreeable, 
and caring nothing for her! It was like their 
artful selfishness always to tell her when they came 
back, under pretence of confidence and friendship, 
all those details about where they had been, 
and what they had done and seen, and how often 
they had said "O! If we had only darling little 
Kitty here!" Here indeed! I dare say! When 
they came back after the holidays, they were 
used to being received by Kitty, and to saying 
that coming to Kitty was like coming to another 
home. Very well then, why did they go away? 
If they meant it, why did they go away? Let 
them answer that. But they didn't mean it, and 
couldn't answer that, and they didn't tell the 
truth, and people who didn't tell the truth were 
hateful. When they came back next time, they 
should be received in a new manner; they should 
be avoided and shunned. 
</p>
<p>
And there, the while she sat all alone revolving 
how ill she was used, and how much better she 
was than the people who were not alone, the 
wedding breakfast was going on: no question of 
it! With a nasty great bride-cake, and with 
those ridiculous orange-flowers, and with that 
conceited bride, and that hideous bridegroom, 
and those heartless bridesmaids, and Miss 
Pupford stuck up at the table! They thought they 
were enjoying themselves, but it would come 
home to them one day to have thought so. They 
would all be dead in a few years, let them enjoy 
themselves ever so much. It was a religious 
comfort to know that. 
</p>
<p>
It was such a comfort to know it, that little 
Miss Kitty Kimmeens suddenly sprang from the 
chair in which she had been musing in a corner, 
and cried out, "O those envious thoughts are 
not mine, this wicked creature isn't me! Help 
me somebody! I go wrong, alone by my 
weak self. Help me anybody!" 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
"--Miss Kimmeens is not a professed 
philosopher, sir," said Mr. Traveller, presenting her 
at the barred window, and smoothing her shining 
hair, "but I apprehend there was some tincture 
of philosophy in her words, and in the 
prompt action with which she followed them. 
That action was, to emerge from her unnatural 
solitude, and look abroad for wholesome 
sympathy, to bestow and to receive. Her footsteps 
strayed to this gate, bringing her here by chance, 
as an apposite contrast to you. The child came 
out, sir. If you have the wisdom to learn from a 
child (but I doubt it, for that requires more 
wisdom than one in your condition would seem 
to possess), you cannot do better than imitate 
the child, and come out too--from that very 
demoralising hutch of yours." 
</p>
</chapter>
 
<chapter>
<info title="Picking Up The Tinker."/>
<p>
IT was now sunset. The Hermit had 
betaken himself to his bed of cinders half an hour 
ago, and lying on it in his blanket and skewer 
with his back to the window, took not the 
smallest heed of the appeal addressed to him. 
</p>
<p>
All that had been said for the last two hours, 
had been said to a tinkling accompaniment 
performed by the Tinker, who had got to work 
upon some villager's pot or kettle, and was 
working briskly outside. This music still 
continuing, seemed to put it into Mr. Traveller's 
mind to have another word or two with the 
Tinker. So, holding Miss Kimmeens (with 
whom he was now on the most friendly terms) 
by the hand, he went out at the gate to where 
the Tinker was seated at his work on the 
patch of grass on the opposite side of the road, 
with his wallet of tools open before him, and 
his little fire smoking. 
</p>
<p>
"I am glad to see you employed," said Mr. 
Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"I am glad to be employed," returned the 
Tinker, looking up as he put the finishing 
touches to his job. "But why are you glad?" 
</p>
<p>
"I thought you were a lazy fellow when I 
saw you this morning." 
</p>
<p>
"I was only disgusted," said the Tinker. 
</p>
<p>
"Do you mean with the fine weather?" 
</p>
<p>
"With the fine weather?" repeated the 
Tinker, staring. 
</p>
<p>
"You told me you were not particular as to 
weather, and I thought--" 
</p>
<p>
"Ha, ha! How should such as me get on, 
if we was partickler as to weather? We must 
take it as it comes, and make the best of it. 
There's something good in all weathers. If it 
don't happen to be good for my work to-day, 
it's good for some other man's to-day, and will 
come round to me to-morrow. We must all 
live." 
</p>
<p>
"Pray shake hands!" said Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Take care, sir," was the Tinker's caution, 
as he reached up his hand in surprise; "the 
black comes off." 
</p>
<p>
"I am glad of it," said Mr. Traveller. "I 
have been for several hours among other black 
that does not come off." 
</p>
<p>
"You are speaking of Tom in there?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes." 
</p>
<p>
"Well now," said the Tinker, blowing the 
dust off his job: which was finished. "Ain't it 
enough to disgust a pig, if he could give his 
mind to it?" 
</p>
<p>
"If he could give his mind to it," returned 
the other, smiling, "the probability is that he 
wouldn't be a pig." 
</p>
<p>
"There you clench the nail," returned the 
Tinker. "Then what's to be said for Tom?" 
</p>
<p>
"Truly, very little." 
</p>
<p>
"Truly nothing you mean, sir," said the 
Tinker, as he put away his tools. 
</p>
<p>
"A better answer, and (I freely acknowledge) 
my meaning. I infer that he was the cause of 
your disgust?" 
</p>
<p>
"Why, look'ee here, sir," said the Tinker, 
rising to his feet, and wiping his face on the 
corner of his black apron energetically; "I 
leave you to judge!--I ask you!--Last night 
I has a job that needs to be done in 
the night, and I works all night. Well, 
there's nothing in that. But this morning I 
comes along this road here, looking for a sunny 
and soft spot to sleep in, and I sees this desolation 
and ruination. I've lived myself in 
desolation and ruination; I knows many a fellow-
creetur that's forced to live, life long, in desolation 
and ruination; and I sits me down and 
takes pity on it, as I casts my eyes about. Then 
comes up the long-winded one as I told you 
of, from that gate, and spins himself out like 
a silkworm concerning the Donkey (if my 
Donkey at home will excuse me) as has made it 
all--made it of his own choice! And tells me, 
if you please, of his likewise choosing to go 
ragged and naked, and grimy--maskerading, 
mountebanking, in what is the real hard lot of 
thousands and thousands! Why, then I say it's 
a unbearable and nonsensical piece of 
inconsistency, and I'm disgusted. I'm ashamed and 
disgusted!" 
</p>
<p>
"I wish you would come and look at him," 
said Mr. Traveller, clapping the Tinker on the 
shoulder. 
</p>
<p>
"Not I, sir," he rejoined. "I ain't a going 
to flatter him up, by looking at him!" 
</p>
<p>
"But he is asleep." 
</p>
<p>
"Are you sure he is asleep?" asked the 
Tinker, with an unwilling air, as he shouldered 
his wallet. 
</p>
<p>
"Sure." 
</p>
<p>
"Then I'll look at him for a quarter of a 
minute," said the Tinker, "since you so much 
wish it; but not a moment longer." 
</p>
<p>
They all three went back across the road; 
and, through the barred window, by the dying 
glow of the sunset coming in at the gate--
which the child held open for its admission--he 
could be pretty clearly discerned lying on his 
bed. 
</p>
<p>
"You see him?" asked Mr. Traveller. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes," returned the Tinker, "and he's worse 
than I thought him." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Traveller then whispered in few words 
what he had done since morning; and asked the 
Tinker what he thought of that? 
</p>
<p>
"I think," returned the Tinker, as he turned 
from the window, "that you've wasted a day on 
him." 
</p>
<p>
"I think so too; though not, I hope, upon 
myself. Do you happen to be going anywhere 
near the Peal of Bells?" 
</p>
<p>
"That's my direct way, sir," said the Tinker. 
</p>
<p>
"I invite you to supper there. And as I 
learn from this young lady that she goes some 
three-quarters of a mile in the same direction, 
we will drop her on the road, and we will 
spare time to keep her company at her garden 
gate until her own Bella comes home." 
</p>
<p>
So, Mr. Traveller, and the child, and the 
Tinker, went along very amicably in the sweet-
scented evening; and the moral with which the 
Tinker dismissed the subject was, that he said 
in his trade that metal that rotted for want of 
use, had better be left to rot, and couldn't rot 
too soon, considering how much true metal 
rotted from over-use and hard service. 
</p>
<section>THE END.</section>
</chapter>
</book>
