<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>The Holly-Tree Inn</title>
<subtitle>(Household Words Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1855</date>
<option name="chapter.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="chapter.number_style" value="NONE"/>
</info>

<prefix>
<info title="The Holly-Tree Inn."/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1855.</centre>
</prefix>

<chapter>
<title>THE GUEST.</title>
<p>
I HAVE kept one secret in the course of my 
life. I am a bashful man. Nobody would 
suppose it, nobody ever does suppose it, 
nobody ever did suppose it. But, I am naturally 
a bashful man. This is the secret which I 
have never breathed until now. 
</p>
<p>
I might greatly move the reader, by some 
account of the innumerable places I have not 
been to, the innumerable people I have not 
called upon or received, the innumerable social 
evasions I have been guilty of, solely because 
I am by original constitution and character, 
a bashful man. But, I will leave the reader 
unmoved, and proceed with the object 
before me. 
</p>
<p>
That object is, to give a plain account of my 
travels and discoveries in the Holly-Tree 
Inn; in which place of good entertainment 
for man and beast, I was once snowed up. 
</p>
<p>
It happened in the memorable year when 
I parted for ever from Angela Leath whom 
I was shortly to have married, on making 
the discovery that she preferred my bosom 
friend. From our school days I had freely 
admitted Edwin, in my own mind, to be far 
superior to myself, and, though I was grievously 
wounded at heart, I felt the preference to be 
natural, and tried to forgive them both. It 
was under these circumstances that I 
resolved to go to America--on my way to the 
Devil. 
</p>
<p>
Communicating my discovery neither to 
Angela nor to Edwin, but resolving to write 
each of them an affecting letter conveying my 
blessing and forgiveness, which the steam-tender 
for shore should carry to the post 
when I myself should be bound for the New 
World, far beyond recall;--I say, locking up 
my grief in my own breast, and consoling 
myself as I could, with the prospect of being 
generous, I quietly left all I held dear, and 
started on the desolate journey I have 
mentioned. 
</p>
<p>
The dead winter-time was in full dreariness 
when I left my chambers for ever, at 
five o'clock in the morning. I had shaved by 
candle-light, of course, and was miserably 
cold, and experienced that general all-pervading 
sensation of getting up to be hanged, 
which I have usually found inseparable from 
untimely rising under such circumstances. 
</p>
<p>
How well I remember the forlorn aspect of 
Fleet Street when I came out of the Temple! 
The street-lamps flickering in the gusty 
north-east wind, as if the very gas were 
contorted with cold; the white-topped houses; 
the bleak, star-lighted sky; the market 
people and other early stragglers, trotting, 
to circulate their almost frozen blood; the 
hospitable light and warmth of the few coffee-shops 
and public-houses that were open for 
such customers; the hard, dry, frosty rime 
with which the air was charged (the wind 
had already beaten it into every crevice), and 
which lashed my face like a steel whip. 
</p>
<p>
It wanted nine days to the end of the 
month, and end of the year. The Post-office 
packet for the United States was to 
depart from Liverpool, weather permitting, 
on the first of the ensuing month, and I 
had the intervening time on my hands. I 
had taken this into consideration, and had 
resolved to make a visit to a certain spot 
(which I need not name), on the further 
borders of Yorkshire. It was endeared to 
me by my having first seen Angela at a farm-house 
in that place, and my melancholy was 
gratified by the idea of taking a wintry leave 
of it before my expatriation. I ought to 
explain, that to avoid being sought out before 
my resolution should have been rendered 
irrevocable by being carried into full effect, I 
had written to Angela overnight, in my usual 
manner, lamenting that urgent business of 
which she should know all particulars by-and-by--
took me unexpectedly away from 
her for a week or ten days. 
</p>
<p>
There was no Northern Railway at that 
time, and in its place there were stage-coaches: 
which I occasionally find myself, in 
common with some other people, affecting to 
lament now, but which everybody dreaded as 
a very serious penance then. I had secured 
the box-seat on the fastest of these, and my 
business in Fleet Street was, to get into a cab 
with my portmanteau, so to make the best of 
my way to the Peacock at Islington, where I 
was to join this coach. But, when one of our 
Temple watchmen who carried my portmanteau 
into Fleet Street for me, told me about the 
huge blocks of ice that had for some days 
past been floating in the river, having closed 
up in the night and made a walk from the 
Temple Gardens over to the Surrey shore, I 
began to ask myself the question, Whether the 
box-seat would not be likely to put a sudden 
and a frosty end to my unhappiness? I was 
heart-broken, it is true, and yet I was not 
quite so far gone as to wish to be frozen to 
death. 
</p>
<p>
When I got up to the Peacock--where I 
found everybody drinking hot purl, in self-preservation--
I asked, if there were an inside 
seat to spare? I then discovered that, inside 
or out, I was the only passenger. This gave 
me a still livelier idea of the great inclemency 
of the weather, since that coach always loaded 
particularly well. However, I took a little 
purl (which I found uncommonly good), and 
got into the coach. When I was seated, 
they built me up with straw to the waist, 
and, conscious of making a rather ridiculous 
appearance, I began my journey. 
</p>
<p>
It was still dark when we left the Peacock. 
For a little while, pale uncertain ghosts of houses 
and trees appeared and vanished, and then it 
was hard, black, frozen day. People were 
lighting their fires; smoke was mounting 
straight up, high into the rarefied air; and 
we were rattling for Highgate Archway 
over the hardest ground I have ever heard 
the ring of iron shoes on. As we got into 
the country, everything seemed to have grown 
old and grey. The roads, the trees, thatched 
roofs of cottages and homesteads, the ricks in 
farmers' yards. Out-door work was 
abandoned, horse-troughs at roadside Inns were 
frozen hard, no stragglers lounged about, doors 
were close shut, little turnpike-houses had 
blazing fires inside, and children (even turnpike-people 
have children, and seem to like 
them), rubbed the frost from the little panes 
of glass with their chubby arms, that their 
bright eyes might catch a glimpse of the 
solitary coach going by. I don't know when 
the snow began to set in; but, I know 
that we were changing horses somewhere 
when I heard the guard remark, "That the 
old lady up in the sky was picking her geese 
pretty hard to-day." Then, indeed, I found 
the white down falling fast and thick. 
</p>
<p>
The lonely day wore on, and I dozed it out 
as a lonely traveller does. I was warm and 
valiant after eating and drinking--particularly 
after dinner; cold and depressed at all other 
times. I was always bewildered as to time 
and place, and always more or less out of my 
senses. The coach and horses seemed to 
execute in chorus, Auld Lang Syne, without 
a moment's intermission. They kept the time 
and tune with the greatest regularity, and 
rose into the swell at the beginning of the 
Refrain, with a precision that worried me to 
death. While we changed horses, the guard 
and coachman went stumping up and down 
the road, printing off their shoes in the snow, 
and poured so much liquid consolation into 
themselves without being any the worse for 
it, that I began to confound them, as it 
darkened again, with two great white casks 
standing on end. Our horses tumbled down 
in solitary places, and we got them up--
which was the pleasantest variety I had, for 
it warmed me. And it snowed and snowed, 
and still it snowed, and never left off snowing. 
All night long, we went on in this manner. 
Thus, we came round the clock, upon the Great 
North Road, to the performance of Auld Lang 
Syne by day again. And it snowed and 
snowed, and still it snowed, and never left off 
snowing. 
</p>
<p>
I forget now, where we were at noon on the 
second day, and where we ought to have 
been; but, I know that we were scores of miles 
behindhand, and that our case was growing 
worse every hour. The drift was becoming 
prodigiously deep; landmarks were getting 
snowed out; the road and the fields were all 
one; instead of having fences and hedgerows 
to guide us, we went crunching on, over an 
unbroken surface of ghastly white that 
might sink beneath us at any moment and 
drop us down a whole hill-side. Still, the 
coachman and guard--who kept together on 
the box, always in council, and looking well 
about them--made out the track with 
astonishing sagacity. 
</p>
<p>
When we came in sight of a town, it looked, 
to my fancy, like a large drawing on a slate, 
with abundance of slate-pencil expended on 
the churches and houses where the snow lay 
thickest. When we came within a town, and 
found the church clocks all stopped, the 
dial-faces choked with snow, and the Inn-signs 
blotted out, it seemed as if the whole 
place were overgrown with white moss. As 
to the coach, it was a mere snowball; 
similarly, the men and boys who ran along 
beside us to the town's end, turning our 
clogged wheels and encouraging our horses, 
were men and boys of snow; and the bleak 
wild solitude to which they at last dismissed 
us, was a snowy Saharah. One would have 
thought this enough; notwithstanding which, 
I pledge my word that it snowed and snowed, 
and still it snowed, and never left off snowing. 
</p>
<p>
We performed Auld Lang Syne the whole 
day; seeing nothing, out of towns and 
villages, but the track of stoats, hares, and 
foxes, and sometimes of birds. At nine 
o'clock at night, on a Yorkshire moor, a 
cheerful burst from our horn, and a welcome 
sound of talking, with a glimmering and 
moving about of lanterns, roused me from my 
drowsy state. I found that we were going to 
change. 
</p>
<p>
They helped me out, and I said to a 
waiter, whose bare head became as white as 
King Lear's in a single minute: "What Inn 
is this?" 
</p>
<p>
"The Holly-Tree, sir," said he. 
</p>
<p>
"Upon my word, I believe," said I, 
apologetically to the guard and coachman, "that 
I must stop here." 
</p>
<p>
Now, the landlord, and the landlady, and 
the ostler, and the postboy, and all the stable 
authorities, had already asked the coachman, 
to the wide-eyed interest of all the rest of the 
establishment, if he meant to go on? The 
coachman had already replied, "Yes, he'd 
take her through it"--meaning by Her, the 
coach--"if so be as George would stand 
by him." George was the guard, and he had 
already sworn that he would stand by him. 
So, the helpers were already getting the 
horses out. 
</p>
<p>
My declaring myself beaten, after this parley, 
was not an announcement without preparation. 
Indeed, but for the way to the announcement 
being smoothed by the parley, I more 
than doubt whether, as an innately bashful 
man, I should have had the confidence 
to make it. As it was, it received the 
approval, even of the guard and coachman. 
Therefore, with many confirmations of my 
inclining, and many remarks from one 
bystander to another, that the gentleman could 
go for'ard by the mail to-morrow, whereas 
to-night he would only be froze, and where 
was the good of a gentleman being froze--
ah, let alone buried alive (which latter clause 
was added by a humorous helper as a joke 
at my expense, and was extremely well 
received), I saw my portmanteau got out 
stiff, like a frozen body; did the handsome 
thing by the guard and coachman; wished 
them good night and a prosperous journey; 
and, a little ashamed of myself after all, for 
leaving them to fight it out alone, followed 
the landlord, landlady, and waiter of the 
Holly-Tree, up-stairs. 
</p>
<p>
I thought I had never seen such a large 
room as that into which they showed me. It 
had five windows, with dark red curtains that 
would have absorbed the light of a general 
illumination; and there were complications 
of drapery at the top of the curtains, that 
went wandering about the wall in a most 
extraordinary manner. I asked for a smaller room, 
and they told me there was no smaller room. 
They could screen me in, however, the landlord 
said. They brought a great old japanned 
screen, with natives (Japanese, I suppose), 
engaged in a variety of idiotic pursuits all 
over it; and left me, roasting whole before 
an immense fire. 
</p>
<p>
My bedroom was some quarter of a mile 
off, up a great staircase, at the end of a long 
gallery; and nobody knows what a misery 
this is to a bashful man who would rather 
not meet people on the stairs. It was the 
grimmest room I have ever had the nightmare 
in; and all the furniture, from the four 
posts of the bed to the two old silver candlesticks, 
was tall, high-shouldered, and spindle-waisted. 
Below, in my sitting-room, if I looked 
round my screen, the wind rushed at me like 
a mad bull; if I stuck to my arm-chair, the 
fire scorched me to the colour of a new brick. 
The chimney-piece was very high, and there 
was a bad glass--what I may call a wavy 
glass--above it, which, when I stood up, just 
showed me my anterior phrenological 
developments--and these never look well, in any 
subject, cut short off at the eyebrow. If I 
stood with my back to the fire, a gloomy 
vault of darkness above and beyond the 
screen insisted on being looked at; and, in 
its dim remoteness, the drapery of the ten 
curtains of the five windows went twisting 
and creeping about, like a nest of gigantic 
worms. 
</p>
<p>
I suppose that what I observe in myself 
must be observed by some other men of 
similar character in themselves; therefore I 
am emboldened to mention, that when I 
travel, I never arrive at a place but I 
immediately want to go away from it. Before I 
had finished my supper of broiled fowl and 
mulled port, I had impressed upon the 
waiter in detail, my arrangements for departure 
in the morning. Breakfast and bill at 
eight. Fly at nine. Two horses, or, if needful, 
even four. 
</p>
<p>
Tired though I was, the night appeared 
about a week long. In cases of nightmare, I 
thought of Angela, and felt more depressed 
than ever by the reflection that I was on the 
shortest road to Gretna Green. What had <em>I</em> 
to do with Gretna Green? I was not going 
<em>that</em> way to the Devil, but by the American 
route, I remarked, in my bitterness. 
</p>
<p>
In the morning I found that it was snowing 
still, that it had snowed all night, and that I 
was snowed up. Nothing could get out of 
that spot on the moor, or could come at it, 
until the road had been cut out by laborers 
from the market-town. When they might 
cut their way to the Holly-Tree, nobody could 
tell me. 
</p>
<p>
It was now Christmas Eve. I should have 
had a dismal Christmas-time of it anywhere, 
and, consequently, that did not so much 
matter; still, being snowed up, was, like 
dying of frost, a thing I had not bargained 
for. I felt very lonely. Yet I could no more 
have proposed to the landlord and landlady 
to admit me to their society (though I should 
have liked it very much), than I could have 
asked them to present me with a piece of 
plate. Here my great secret, the real 
bashfulness of my character, is to be observed. 
Like most bashful men, I judge of other 
people as if they were bashful too. Besides 
being far too shame-faced to make the 
proposal myself, I really had a delicate 
misgiving that it would be in the last degree 
disconcerting to them. 
	 
Trying to settle down, therefore, in my 
solitude, I first of all asked what books there 
were in the house? The waiter brought me a 
Book of Roads, two or three old Newspapers, 
a little Song-book terminating in a collection 
of Toasts and Sentiments, a little Jest-book, 
an odd volume of Peregrine Pickle, and the 
Sentimental Journey. I knew every word of 
the two last already, but I read them through 
again; then tried to hum all the songs (Auld 
Lang Syne was among them); went entirely 
through the jokes--in which I found a fund 
of melancholy adapted to my state of mind; 
proposed all the toasts, enunciated all the 
sentiments, and mastered the papers. The 
latter had nothing in them but Stock advertisements, 
a meeting about a county rate, and a 
highway robbery. As I am a greedy reader, 
I could not make this supply hold out until 
night; it was exhausted by tea-time. Being 
then entirely cast upon my own resources, I 
got through an hour in considering what to 
do next. Ultimately, it came into my head 
(from which I was anxious by any means to 
exclude Angela and Edwin), that I would 
endeavour to recall my experience of Inns, and 
would try how long it lasted me. I stirred 
the fire, moved my chair a little to one side 
of the screen--not daring to go far, for I 
knew the wind was waiting to make a rush 
at me--I could hear it growling--and began. 
</p>
<p>
My first impressions of an Inn, dated from 
the Nursery; consequently, I went back to the 
Nursery for a starting-point, and found 
myself at the knee of a sallow woman with a 
fishy eye, an aquiline nose, and a green 
gown, whose speciality was a dismal narrative 
of a landlord by the roadside, whose visitors 
unaccountably disappeared for many years, 
until it was discovered that the pursuit of 
his life had been to convert them into pies. 
For the better devotion of himself to this 
branch of industry, he had constructed a secret 
door behind the head of the bed; and when 
the visitor (oppressed with pie), had fallen 
asleep, this wicked landlord would look softly 
in with a lamp in one hand and a knife in the 
other, would cut his throat, and would make 
him into pies; for which purpose he had 
coppers underneath a trap-door, always 
boiling; and rolled out his pastry in the dead 
of the night. Yet even he was not insensible 
to the stings of conscience, for he never went 
to sleep without being heard to mutter, "Too 
much pepper!"--which was eventually the 
cause of his being brought to justice. I had 
no sooner disposed of this criminal than there 
started up another, of the same period, whose 
profession was, originally, housebreaking; in 
the pursuit of which art he had had his right 
ear chopped off one night as he was burglariously 
getting in at a window, by a brave and 
lovely servant-maid (whom the aquiline-nosed 
woman, though not at all answering the 
description, always mysteriously implied to be 
herself). After several years, this brave and 
lovely servant-maid was married to the landlord 
of a country Inn: which landlord had this 
remarkable characteristic, that he always 
wore a silk nightcap, and never would, on 
any consideration, take it off. At last, one 
night, when he was fast asleep, the brave and 
lovely woman lifted up his silk nightcap on 
the right side, and found that he had no ear 
there; upon which, she sagaciously perceived 
that he was the clipped housebreaker, who 
had married her with the intention of putting 
her to death. She immediately heated the 
poker and terminated his career, for which 
she was taken to King George upon his 
throne, and received the compliments of royalty 
on her great discretion and valour. This 
same narrator, who had a Ghoulish pleasure, 
I have long been persuaded, in terrifying me to 
the utmost confines of my reason, had another 
authentic anecdote within her own experience, 
founded, I now believe, upon Raymond and 
Agnes or the Bleeding Nun. She said it 
happened to her brother-in-law, who was 
immensely rich--which my father was not; and 
immensely tall--which my father was not. 
It was always a point with this Ghoule to 
present my dearest relations and friends to 
my youthful mind, under circumstances of 
disparaging contrast. The brother-in-law 
was riding once, through a forest, on a 
magnificent horse (we had no magnificent horse at 
our house), attended by a favourite and 
valuable Newfoundland dog (we had no dog), 
when he found himself benighted, and came to 
an Inn. A dark woman opened the door, and 
he asked her if he could have a bed there? 
She answered yes, and put his horse in the 
stable, and took him into a room where there 
were two dark men. While he was at supper, 
a parrot in the room began to talk, saying, 
"Blood, blood! Wipe up the blood!" Upon 
which, one of the dark men wrung the parrot's 
neck, and said he was fond of roasted parrots, 
and he meant to have this one for breakfast in 
the morning. After eating and drinking 
heartily, the immensely rich tall brother-in-law 
went up to bed; but, he was rather 
vexed, because they had shut his dog in 
the stable, saying that they never allowed 
dogs in the house. He sat very quiet for 
more than an hour, thinking and thinking, 
when, just as his candle was burning out, he 
heard a scratch at the door. He opened the 
door, and there was the Newfoundland dog! 
The dog came softly in, smelt about him, 
went straight to some straw in a corner 
which the dark men had said covered apples, 
tore the straw away, and disclosed two sheets 
steeped in blood. Just at that moment the 
candle went out, and the brother-in-law, 
looking through a chink in the door, saw the 
two dark men stealing up-stairs; one armed 
with a dagger, that long (about five feet); 
the other carrying a chopper, a sack, and a 
spade. Having no remembrance of the close 
of this adventure, I suppose my faculties to 
have been always so frozen with terror at 
this stage of it, that the power of listening 
stagnated within me for some quarter of an 
hour. 
</p>
<p>
These barbarous stories carried me, sitting 
there on the Holly-Tree hearth, to the Roadside 
Inn, renowned in my time in a sixpenny 
book with a folding plate, representing in a 
central compartment of oval form the portrait 
of Jonathan Bradford, and in four corner 
compartments four incidents of the tragedy with 
which the name is associated--coloured with 
a hand at once so free and economical, that 
the bloom of Jonathan's complexion passed 
without any pause into the breeches of the 
ostler, and, smearing itself off into the next 
division, became rum in a bottle. Then, I 
remembered how the landlord was found at 
the murdered traveller's bedside, with his own 
knife at his feet, and blood upon his hand; 
how he was hanged for the murder, notwithstanding 
his protestation, that he had indeed 
come there to kill the traveller for his saddlebags, 
but had been stricken motionless on 
finding him already slain; and how the ostler, 
years afterwards, owned the deed. By this 
time I had made myself quite uncomfortable. 
I stirred the fire, and stood with my back to 
it, as long as I could bear the heat, looking up 
at the darkness beyond the screen, and at the 
wormy curtains creeping in and creeping out, 
like the worms in the ballad of Alonzo the 
Brave and the fair Imogene. 
</p>
<p>
There was an Inn in the cathedral town 
where I went to school, which had pleasanter 
recollections about it than any of these. I 
took it next. It was the Inn where friends 
used to put up, and where we used to go to 
see parents, and to have salmon and fowls, 
and be tipped. It had an ecclesiastical sign--
the Mitre--and a bar that seemed to be 
the next best thing to a bishopric, it was so 
snug. I loved the landlord's youngest 
daughter to distraction--but let that pass. 
It was in this Inn that I was cried over by 
my rosy little sister, because I had acquired 
a black eye in a fight. And though she 
had been, that Holly-Tree night, for many 
a long year where all tears are dried, the 
Mitre softened me yet. 
</p>
<p>
"To be continued, to-morrow," said I, when 
I took my candle to go to bed. But, my bed 
took it upon itself to continue the train of 
thought that night. It carried me away, like 
the enchanted carpet, to a distant place 
(though still in England), and there, alighting 
from a stage-coach at another Inn in the 
snow, as I had actually done some years 
before, I repeated in my sleep, a curious 
experience I had really had there. More than 
a year before I made the journey in the course 
of which I put up at that Inn, I had lost a 
very near and dear friend by death. Every 
night since, at home or away from home, I 
had dreamed of that friend; sometimes, as 
still living; sometimes, as returning from 
the world of shadows to comfort me; always 
as being beautiful, placid, and happy; never 
in association with any approach to fear or 
distress. It was at a lonely Inn in a wide 
moorland place, that I halted to pass the 
night. When I had looked from my 
bedroom window over the waste of snow on 
which the moon was shining, I sat down 
by my fire, to write a letter. I had always, 
until that hour, kept it within my own 
breast that I dreamed every night of the 
dear lost one. But, in the letter that I 
wrote, I recorded the circumstance, and 
added that I felt much interested in proving 
whether the subject of my dream would still 
be faithful to me, travel-tired, and in that 
remote place. No. I lost the beloved figure 
of my vision in parting with the secret. My 
sleep has never looked upon it since, in sixteen 
years, but once. I was in Italy, and 
awoke (or seemed to awake), the well-remembered 
voice distinctly in my ears, conversing 
with it. I entreated it, as it rose above my 
bed and soared up to the vaulted roof of the 
old room, to answer me a question I had asked, 
touching the Future Life. My hands were still 
outstretched towards it as it vanished, when 
I heard a bell ringing by the garden wall, 
and a voice, in the deep stillness of the night, 
caling on all good Christians to pray for the 
souls of the dead; it being All Souls Eve. 
</p>
<p>
To return to the Holly-Tree. When I 
awoke next day, it was freezing hard, and the 
lowering sky threatened more snow. My 
breakfast cleared away, I drew my chair into 
its former place, and, with the fire getting so 
much the better of the landscape that I sat 
in twilight, resumed my Inn remembrances. 
</p>
<p>
That was a good Inn down in Wiltshire 
where I put up once, in the days of the hard 
Wiltshire ale, and before all beer was bitterness. 
It was on the skirts of Salisbury Plain, 
and the midnight wind that rattled my 
lattice window, came moaning at me from 
Stonehenge. There was a hanger-on at that 
establishment (a supernaturally-preserved 
Druid, I believe him to have been, and to be 
still), with long white hair, and a flinty blue 
eye always looking afar off: who claimed to 
have been a shepherd, and who seemed to be 
ever watching for the re-appearance on the 
verge of the horizon, of some ghostly flock of 
sheep that had been mutton for many ages. 
He was a man with a weird belief in him 
that no one could count the stones of Stonehenge 
twice, and make the same number of 
them; likewise, that any one who counted 
them three times nine times, and then stood 
in the centre and said "I dare!" would 
behold a tremendous apparition, and be stricken 
dead. He pretended to have seen a bustard 
(I suspect him to have been familiar with 
the dodo), in manner following: He was 
out upon the plain at the close of a late 
autumn day, when he dimly discerned, going 
on before him at a curious fitfully bounding 
pace, what he at first supposed to be a gig-umbrella 
that had been blown from some 
conveyance, but what he presently believed 
to be a lean dwarf man upon a little pony. 
</p>
<p>
Having followed this object for some distance 
without gaining on it, and having called to 
it many times without receiving any answer, 
he pursued it for miles and miles, when, at 
length coming up with it, he discovered it to 
be the last bustard in Great Britain, degenerated 
into a wingless state, and running along 
the ground. Resolved to capture him or 
perish in the attempt, he closed with the 
bustard; but, the bustard, who had formed a 
counter-resolution that he should do neither, threw 
him, stunned him, and was last seen making 
off due west. This weird man at that stage 
of metempsychosis, may have been a sleep-walker, 
or an enthusiast, or a robber; but, I 
awoke one night to find him in the dark at 
my bedside, repeating the Athanasian Creed 
in a terrific voice. I paid my bill next day, 
and retired from the county with all possible 
precipitation. 
</p>
<p>
That was not a common-place story which 
worked itself out at a little Inn in Switzerland, 
while I was staying there. It was a 
very homely place, in a village of one narrow, 
zig-zag street among mountains, and you 
went in at the main door through the cow-house, 
and among the mules and the dogs and 
the fowls, before ascending a great bare staircase 
 to the rooms: which were all of unpainted 
wood, without plastering or papering--like 
rough packing-cases. Outside, there was 
nothing but the straggling street, a little toy 
church with a copper-coloured steeple, a pine 
forest, a torrent, mists, and mountain-sides. 
A young man belonging to this Inn, had 
disappeared eight weeks before (it was winter-time), 
and was supposed to have had some 
undiscovered love affair, and to have gone 
for a soldier. He had got up in the night, 
and dropped into the village street from the 
loft in which he slept with another man; and 
he had done it so quietly, that his companion 
and fellow-laborer had heard no movement 
when he was awakened in the morning, and 
they said "Louis, where is Henri?" They 
looked for him high and low, in vain, and 
gave him up. Now, outside this Inn there 
stood, as there stood outside every dwelling in 
the village, a stack of firewood; but, the 
stack belonging to the Inn was higher than any 
of the rest, because the Inn was the richest 
house and burnt the most fuel. It began to 
be noticed, while they were looking high and 
low, that a Bantam cock, part of the 
livestock of the Inn, put himself wonderfully out 
of his way to get to the top of this wood-stack; 
and that he would stay there for 
hours and hours, crowing, until he appeared 
in danger of splitting himself. Five weeks 
went on--six weeks--and still this terrible 
Bantam, neglecting his domestic affairs, was 
always on the top of the wood-stack, crowing 
the very eyes out of his head. By this time 
it was perceived that Louis had become 
inspired with a violent animosity towards the 
terrible Bantam, and one morning he was 
seen by a woman who sat nursing her goitre 
at a little window in a gleam of sun, to catch 
up a rough billet of wood, with a great oath, 
hurl it at the terrible Bantam crowing on 
the wood-stack, and bring him down dead. 
Hereupon, the woman, with a sudden light in 
her mind, stole round to the back of the 
wood-stack, and, being a good climber, as all 
those women are, climbed up, and soon was 
seen upon the summit, screaming, looking 
down the hollow within, and crying, "Seize 
Louis, the murderer! Ring the church bell! 
Here is the body!" I saw the murderer 
that day, and I saw him as I sat by my fire at 
the Holly-Tree Inn, and I see him now, lying 
shackled with cords on the stable litter, among 
the mild eyes and the smoking breath of the 
cows, waiting to be taken away by the police, 
and stared at by the fearful village. A heavy 
animal--the dullest animal in the stables--
with a stupid head, and a lumpish face 
devoid of any trace of sensibility, who had 
been, within the knowledge of the murdered 
youth, an embezzler of certain small moneys 
belonging to his master, and who had taken 
this hopeful mode of putting a possible accuser 
out of his way. All of which he confessed 
next day, like a sulky wretch who couldn't 
be troubled any more, now that they had got 
hold of him and meant to make an end of 
him. I saw him once again, on the day of 
my departure from the Inn. In that Canton 
the headsman still does his office with a 
sword; and I came upon this murderer 
sitting bound to a chair, with his eyes 
bandaged, on a scaffold in a little market-place. 
In that instant, a great sword (loaded 
with quicksilver in the thick part of the 
blade), swept round him like a gust of wind, 
or fire, and there was no such creature in the 
world. My wonder was--not that he was so 
suddenly dispatched, but that any head was 
left unreaped, within a radius of fifty yards 
of that tremendous sickle. 
</p>
<p>
That was a good Inn, too, with the kind, 
cheerful landlady and the honest landlord, 
where I lived in the shadow of Mont Blanc, 
and where one of the apartments has a 
zoological papering on the walls, not so 
accurately joined but that the elephant occasionally 
rejoices in a tiger's hind legs and 
tail; while the lion puts on a trunk and 
tusks; and the bear, moulting as it were, 
appears as to portions of himself like a 
leopard. I made several American friends at 
that Inn, who all called Mont Blanc, Mount 
Blank--except one good-humored gentleman, 
of a very sociable nature, who became 
on such intimate terms with it that he spoke 
of it familiarly as "Blank;" observing at 
breakfast, "Blank looks pretty tall this 
morning;" or considerably doubting in the 
court-yard in the evening, whether there 
warn't some go-ahead naters in our country, 
sir, that would make out the top of Blank 
in a couple of hours from first start--now! 
</p>
<p>
Once, I passed a fortnight at an Inn in the 
North of England, where I was haunted by 
the ghost of a tremendous pie. It was a 
Yorkshire pie, like a fort--an abandoned 
fort with nothing in it; but the waiter had a 
fixed idea that it was a point of ceremony at 
every meal, to put the pie on the table. After 
some days, I tried to hint, in several delicate 
ways, that I considered the pie done with; 
as, for example, by emptying fag-ends of 
glasses of wine into it; putting cheese-plates 
and spoons into it, as into a basket; putting 
wine-bottles into it, as into a cooler; but 
always in vain, the pie being invariably 
cleaned out again and brought up as before. 
At last, beginning to be doubtful whether I 
was not the victim of a spectral illusion, and 
whether my health and spirits might not 
sink under the horrors of an imaginary pie, 
I cut a triangle out of it, fully as large as the 
musical instrument of that name in a power 
orchestra. Human prevision could not 
have foreseen the result--but the waiter 
mended the pie. With some effectual species 
of cement, he adroitly fitted the triangle in 
again, and I paid my reckoning and fled. 
</p>
<p>
The Holly-Tree was getting rather dismal. 
I made an overland expedition beyond the 
screen, and penetrated as far as the fourth 
window. Here, I was driven back by stress 
of weather. Arrived at my winter quarters 
once more, I made up the fire, and took 
another Inn. 
</p>
<p>
It was in the remotest part of Cornwall. 
A great annual Miners' Feast was being 
holden at the Inn, when I and my travelling 
companions presented ourselves at night 
among the wild crowd that were dancing 
before it by torchlight. We had had a 
break-down in the dark, on a stony morass 
some miles away; and I had the honor of 
leading one of the unharnessed post-horses. 
If any lady or gentleman on perusal of 
the present lines, will take any very tall 
post-horse with his traces hanging about 
his legs, and will conduct him by the bearing-rein 
into the heart of a country dance of a 
hundred and fifty couples, that lady or gentleman 
will then, and only then, form an 
adequate idea of the extent to which that 
post-horse will tread on his conductor's toes. 
Over and above which, the post-horse, finding 
three hundred people whirling about 
him, will probably rear, and also lash out 
with his hind legs, in a manner 
incompatible with dignity or self-respect on his 
conductor's part. With such little drawbacks 
on my usually impressive aspect, I appeared 
at this Cornish Inn, to the unutterable wonder 
of the Cornish Miners. It was full, and 
twenty times full, and nobody could be 
received but the post-horse--though to get rid 
of that noble animal was something. While 
my fellow-travellers and I were discussing 
how to pass the night and so much of the 
next day as must intervene before the jovial 
blacksmith and the jovial wheelwright would 
be in a condition to go out on the morass and 
mend the coach, an honest man stepped forth 
from the crowd and proposed his unlet floor 
of two rooms, with supper of eggs and bacon, 
ale and punch. We joyfully accompanied 
him home to the strangest of clean houses, 
where we were well entertained to the 
satisfaction of all parties. But, the novel feature 
of the entertainment was, that our host 
was a chairmaker, and that the chairs 
assigned to us were mere frames, altogether 
without bottoms of any sort; so that we 
passed the evening on perches. Nor was this 
the absurdest consequence; for when we 
unbent at supper, and any one of us gave way 
to laughter, he forgot the peculiarity of his 
position, and instantly disappeared. I 
myself, doubled up into an attitude from which 
self-extrication was impossible, was taken out 
of my frame, like a Clown in a comic pantomime 
who has tumbled into a tub, five times 
by the taper's light during the eggs and bacon. 
</p>
<p>
The Holly-Tree was fast reviving within me 
a sense of loneliness. I began to feel conscious 
that my subject would never carry me on 
until I was dug out. I might be a week here--
weeks! 
</p>
<p>
There was a story with a singular idea in 
it, connected with an Inn I once passed a 
night at, in a picturesque old town on the 
Welch border. In a large, double-bedded 
room of this Inn, there had been a suicide 
committed by poison, in one bed, while a 
tired traveller slept unconscious in the other. 
After that time, the suicide bed was never 
used, but the other constantly was; the 
disused bedstead remaining in the room empty, 
though as to all other respects in its old state. 
The story ran, that whosoever slept in this 
room, though never so entire a stranger, from 
never so far off, was invariably observed to 
come down in the morning with an impression 
that he smelt Laudanum; and that his 
mind always turned upon the subject of 
suicide; to which, whatever kind of man he 
might be, he was certain to make some reference 
if he conversed with any one. This 
went on for years, until it at length induced 
the landlord to take the disused bedstead 
down, and bodily burn it--bed, hangings, and 
all. The strange influence (this was the 
story), now changed to a fainter one, but 
never changed afterwards. The occupant of 
that room, with occasional but very rare 
exceptions, would come down in the morning, 
trying to recall a forgotten dream he had had 
in the night. The landlord, on his mentioning 
his perplexity, would suggest various common-place 
subjects, not one of which, as he 
very well knew, was the true subject. But 
the moment the landlord suggested "Poison," 
the traveller started, and cried "Yes!" He 
never failed to accept that suggestion, and he 
never recalled any more of the dream. 
</p>
<p>
This reminiscence brought the Welch Inns 
in general, before me; with the women in 
their round hats, and the harpers with their 
white beards (venerable, but humbugs, I am 
afraid), playing outside the door while I took 
my dinner. The transition was natural to 
the Highland Inns, with the oatmeal 
bannocks, the honey, the venison steaks, the trout 
from the loch, the whiskey, and perhaps 
(having the materials so temptingly at hand) 
the Athol brose. Once, was I coming south 
from the Scottish Highlands in hot haste, 
hoping to change quickly at the station at the 
bottom of a certain wild historical glen, 
when these eyes did with mortification see 
the landlord come out with a telescope and 
sweep the whole prospect for the horses: 
which horses were away picking up their own 
living, and did not heave in sight under four 
hours. Having thought of the loch-trout I 
was taken by quick association to the Anglers' 
Inns of England (I have assisted at innumerable 
feats of angling, by lying in the bottom 
of the boat, whole summer days, doing 
nothing with the greatest perseverance: which 
I have generally found to be as effectual 
towards the taking of fish as the finest tackle 
and the utmost science); and to the pleasant 
white, clean, flower-pot-decorated bed-rooms 
of those inns, overlooking the river, and the 
ferry, and the green ait, and the church-spire, 
and the country bridge; and to the peerless 
Emma with the bright eyes and the pretty 
smile, who waited, bless her! with a natural 
grace that would have converted Blue 
Beard. Casting my eyes upon my Holly-Tree 
fire, I next discerned among the glowing 
coals, the pictures of a score or more of those 
wonderful English posting-inns which we are 
all so sorry to have lost, which were so large 
and so comfortable, and which were such 
monuments of British submission to rapacity 
and extortion. He who would see 
these houses pining away, let him walk from 
Basingstoke or even Windsor to London, 
by way of Hounslow, and moralise on 
their perishing remains; the stables 
crumbling to dust; unsettled laborers and 
wanderers bivouacing in the outhouses; grass 
growing in the yards; the rooms where erst 
so many hundred beds of down were made 
up, let off to Irish lodgers at eighteen-pence 
a-week; a little ill-looking beer-shop shrinking 
in the tap of former days, burning 
coach-house gates for fire-wood, having one 
of its two windows bunged up, as if it had 
received punishment in a fight with the 
Railroad; a low, bandy-legged, brick-making 
bulldog standing in the door-way. What 
could I next see in my fire, so naturally, 
as the new railway- house of these times 
near the dismal country station; with 
nothing particular on draught but cold 
air and damp, nothing worth mentioning in 
the larder but new mortar, and no business 
doing, beyond a conceited affectation of 
luggage in the hall? Then, I came to the Inns 
of Paris, with the pretty appartement of four 
pieces up one hundred and seventy-five 
waxed stairs, the privilege of ringing the 
bell all day long without influencing 
anybody's mind or body but your own, and 
the not-too-much-for-dinner, considering 
the price. Next, to the provincial Inns of 
France, with the great church-tower rising 
above the courtyard, the horse-bells jingling 
merrily up and down the street beyond, and 
the clocks of all descriptions in all the rooms, 
which are never right, unless taken at the 
precise minute when by getting exactly twelve 
hours too fast or too slow, they unintentionally 
become so. Away I went, next, to the lesser 
road-side Inns of Italy; where all the dirty 
clothes in the house (not in wear) are always 
lying in your ante-room; where the mosquitoes 
make a raisin pudding of your face in summer, 
and the cold bites it blue in winter; where you 
get what you can, and forget what you can't; 
where I should again like to be boiling my 
tea in a pocket-handkerchief dumpling, for 
want of a tea-pot. So, to the old palace Inns 
and old monastery Inns, in towns and 
cities of the same bright country; with 
their massive quadrangular stair-cases 
whence you may look from among 
clustering pillars high into the blue vault of 
Heaven; with their stately banqueting-rooms, 
and vast refectories; with their 
labyrinths of ghostly bed-chambers, and their 
glimpses into gorgeous streets that have no 
appearance of reality or possibility. So, to the 
close little Inns of the Malaria districts, with 
their pale attendants, and their peculiar 
smell of never letting in the air. So, to the 
immense fantastic Inns of Venice, with the 
cry of the gondolier below, as he skims the 
corner; the grip of the watery odors on one 
particular little bit of the bridge of your 
nose (which is never released while you stay 
there); and the great bell of St. Mark's Cathedral 
tolling midnight. Next, I put up for a 
minute at the restless Inns upon the Rhine, where 
your going to bed, no matter at what hour, 
appears to be the tocsin for everybody else's 
getting up; and where, in the table d'hôte 
room at the end of the long table (with several 
Towers of Babel on it at the other end, all 
made of white plates), one knot of stoutish men, 
entirely drest in jewels and dirt, and having 
nothing else upon them, will remain all night, 
clinking glasses, and singing about the river 
that flows and the grape that grows and 
Rhine wine that beguiles and Rhine woman 
that smiles and hi drink drink my friend and 
ho drink drink my brother, and all the rest of 
it. I departed thence, as a matter of course, to 
other German Inns, where all the eatables are 
sodden down to the same flavor, and where 
the mind is disturbed by the apparition of 
hot puddings, and boiled cherries sweet and 
slab, at awfully unexpected periods of the 
repast. After a draught of sparkling beer from 
a foaming glass jug, and a glance of recognition 
through the windows of the student 
beer-houses at Heidelberg and elsewhere, I 
put out to sea for the Inns of America, with 
their four hundred beds a-piece, and their 
eight or nine hundred ladies and gentlemen at 
dinner every day. Again, I stood in the bar-rooms 
bar-rooms thereof, taking my evening cobbler, 
julep, sling, or cocktail. Again, I listened to 
my friend the General--whom I had known for 
five minutes, in the course of which period 
he had made me intimate for life with 
two Majors, who again had made me intimate 
for life with three Colonels, who again had 
made me brother to twenty-two civilians--
again, I say, I listened to my friend the 
General, leisurely expounding the resources of 
the establishment, as to gentlemen's morning-room, 
sir; ladies' morning-room, sir; gentlemen's 
evening-room, sir; ladies' evening-room, 
sir; ladies' and gentlemen's evening 
reuniting-room, sir; music-room, sir; reading 
room, sir; over four-hundred sleeping-rooms, 
sir; and the entire planned and finited within 
twelve calendar months from the first clearing 
off of the old incumbrances on the plot, 
at a cost of five hundred thousand dollars, sir. 
Again I found, as to my individual way of 
thinking, that the greater, the more gorgeous, 
and the more dollarous, the establishment 
was, the less desirable it was. 
Nevertheless, again I drank my cobbler, julep, 
sling, or cocktail, in all good-will, to my 
friend the General, and my friends the 
Majors, Colonels, and civilians, all; full-well 
knowing that whatever little motes my 
beamy eyes may have descried in theirs, they 
belong to a kind, generous, large-hearted, and 
great people. 
</p>
<p>
I had been going on lately, at a quick pace, 
to keep my solitude out of my mind; but, 
here I broke down for good, and gave up the 
subject. What was I to do? What was to 
become of me? Into what extremity was I 
submissively to sink? Supposing that, like 
Baron Trenck, I looked out for a mouse or 
spider, and found one, and beguiled my 
imprisonment by training it? Even that might 
be dangerous with a view to the future. I 
might be so far gone when the road did come 
to be cut through the snow, that, on my way 
forth, I might burst into tears, and beseech, 
like the prisoner who was released in his old 
age from the Bastille, to be taken back again 
to the five windows, the ten curtains, and the 
sinuous drapery. 
</p>
<p>
A desperate idea came into my head. 
Under any other circumstances I should have 
rejected it; but, in the strait at which I was, I 
held it fast. Could I so far overcome the inherent 
bashfulness which withheld me from the 
landlord's table and the company I might find 
there, as to make acquaintance, under various 
pretences, with some of the inmates of the 
house, singly--with the object of getting from 
each, either a whole autobiography, or a passage 
or experience in one, with which I could 
cheat the tardy time: first of all by seeking 
out, then by listening to, then by remembering 
and writing down? Could I, I asked 
myself, so far overcome my retiring nature as 
to do this. I could. I would. I did. 
</p>
<p>
The results of this conception I proceed to 
give, in the exact order in which I attained 
them. I began my plan of operations at 
once, and, by slow approaches and after overcoming 
many obstacles (all of my own 
making, I believe), reached the story of: 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE OSTLER.</title>
<p>
I FIND an old man, fast asleep, in one of the 
stalls of the stable. It is mid-day, and rather 
a strange time for an ostler to devote to sleep. 
Something curious, too, about the man's face. 
A withered woe-begone face. The eyebrows 
painfully contracted; the mouth fast set, and 
drawn down at the corners; the hollow cheeks 
sadly, and, as I cannot help fancying, 
prematurely wrinkled; the scanty, grizzled hair, 
telling weakly its own tale of some past sorrow 
or suffering. How fast he draws his breath, 
too, for a man asleep! He is talking in his 
sleep. 
</p>
<p>
"Wake up!" I hear him say, in a quick 
whisper through his fast-clenched teeth. 
"Wake up there! Murder! Lord help 
me! Lord help me, alone in this place!" 
</p>
<p>
He stops, and sighs again--moves one lean 
arm slowly, till it rests over his throat--
shudders a little, and turns on his straw--
the arm leaves his throat--the hand stretches 
itself out, and clutches at the side towards 
which he has turned, as if he fancies himself 
to be grasping at the edge of something. Is 
he waking? No--there is the whisper again; 
he is still talking in his sleep. 
</p>
<p>
"Light grey eyes," he says now, "and 
a droop in the left eyelid. Yes! yes!--
flaxen hair with a gold-yellow streak in" it--
all right, mother--fair, white arms with a 
down on them--little lady's hand, with a 
reddish look under the finger-nails--and the 
knife--always the cursed knife--first on 
one side, then on the other. Aha! you she-devil, 
where's the knife? Never mind, 
mother--too late now. I've promised to 
marry, and marry I must. Murder! wake 
up there! for God's sake, wake up!" 
</p>
<p>
At the last words his voice rises, and he 
grows so restless on a sudden, that I draw 
back quietly to the door. I see him shudder 
on the straw--his withered face grows 
distorted--he throws up both his hands with a 
quick, hysterical gasp; they strike against 
the bottom of the manger under which he 
lies; the blow awakens him; I have just 
time to slip through the door, before his eyes 
are fairly open and his senses are his own 
again. 
</p>
<p>
What I have seen and heard has so startled 
and shocked me, that I feel my heart beating 
fast, as I softly and quickly retrace my steps 
across the inn-yard. The discomposure that 
is going on within me, apparently shows itself 
in my face; for, as I get back to the covered 
way leading to the Inn stairs, the landlord, 
who is just coming out of the house to ring 
some bell in the yard, stops astonished, and 
asks what is the matter with me? I tell him 
what I have just seen. 
</p>
<p>
"Aha!" says the landlord, with an air of 
relief. "I understand now. Poor old chap! 
He was only dreaming his old dream over 
again. There's the queerest story--of a dreadful 
kind, too, mind you--connected with him 
and his dream, that ever was told." 
</p>
<p>
I entreat the landlord to tell me the story 
After a little hesitation, he complies with my 
request. 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
Some years ago, there lived in the suburbs 
of a large sea-port town, on the west coast of 
England, a man in humble circumstances, by 
name Isaac Scatchard. His means of subsistence 
were derived from any employment that 
he could get, as an ostler; and, occasionally, 
when times went well with him, from 
temporary engagements in service, as stable-helper 
in private houses. Though a faithful, 
steady, and honest man, he got on badly in 
his calling. His ill-luck was proverbial 
among his neighbours. He was always 
missing good opportunities, by no fault of 
his own; and always living longest in 
service with amiable people who were not 
punctual payers of wages. "Unlucky Isaac" 
was his nickname in his own neighbourhood--
and no one could say that he did not 
richly deserve it. 
</p>
<p>
With far more than one man's fair share 
of adversity to endure, Isaac had but one 
consolation to support him--and that was of the 
dreariest and most negative kind. He had 
no wife and children to increase his anxieties 
and add to the bitterness of his various 
failures in life. It might have been from 
mere insensibility, or it might have been 
from generous unwillingness to involve 
another in his own unlucky destiny--but 
the fact undoubtedly was, that he arrived 
at the middle term of life without marrying; 
and, what is much more remarkable, without 
once exposing himself, from eighteen to 
eight and thirty, to the genial imputation of 
ever having had a sweetheart. When he was 
out of service, he lived alone with his widowed 
mother. Mrs. Scatchard was a woman 
above the average in her lowly station, as 
to capacities and manners. She had seen 
better days, as the phrase is; but she never 
referred to them in the presence of curious 
visitors; and, though perfectly polite to 
every one who approached her, never 
cultivated any intimacies among her neighbours. 
She contrived to provide, hardly enough, 
for her simple wants, by doing rough work 
for the tailors; and always managed to 
keep a decent home for her son to return 
to, whenever his ill-luck drove him out helpless 
into the world. 
</p>
<p>
One bleak autumn, when Isaac was getting on 
fast towards forty, and when he was, as usual, 
out of place, through no fault of his own, he 
set forth from his mother's cottage on a long 
walk inland to a gentleman's seat, where he 
had heard that a stable-helper was required. 
It wanted then but two days of his birthday; 
and Mrs. Scatchard, with her usual fondness, 
made him promise, before he started, 
that he would be back in time to keep that 
anniversary with her, in as festive a way as 
their poor means would allow. It was easy 
for him to comply with this request, even 
supposing he slept a night each way on the 
road. He was to start from home on Monday 
morning; and, whether he got the new 
place or not, he was to be back for his birthday 
dinner on Wednesday at two o'clock. 
</p>
<p>
Arriving at his destination too late on the 
Monday night to make application for the 
stable-helper's place, he slept at the village-inn, 
and, in good time on the Tuesday morning, 
presented himself at the gentleman's house, 
to fill the vacant situation. Here, again, his 
ill-luck pursued him as inexorably as ever. 
The excellent written testimonials, as to 
character, which he was able to produce, availed 
him nothing; his long walk had been taken 
in vain--only the day before, the stable-helper's 
place had been given to another 
man. 
</p>
<p>
Isaac accepted this new disappointment 
resignedly, and as a matter of course. 
Naturally slow in capacity, he had the bluntness 
of sensibility and phlegmatic patience of 
disposition which frequently distinguish 
men with sluggishly-working mental 
powers. He thanked the gentleman's 
steward, with his usual quiet civility, for 
granting him an interview, and took his 
departure with no appearance of unusual 
depression in his face or manner. Before 
starting on his homeward walk, he made some 
inquiries at the inn, and ascertained that he 
might save a few miles, on his return, by 
following a new road. Furnished with full 
instructions, several times repeated, as to the 
various turnings he was to take, he set forth 
for his homeward journey, and walked on all 
day with only one stoppage for bread and 
cheese. Just as it was getting towards dark, 
the rain came on and the wind began to rise; 
and he found himself, to make matters worse, 
in a part of the country with which he was 
entirely unacquainted, though he knew 
himself to be some fifteen miles from home. The 
first house he found to inquire at was a lonely 
road-side inn, standing on the outskirts of a 
thick wood. Solitary as the place looked, it 
was welcome to a lost man who was also 
hungry, thirsty, footsore, and wet. The landlord 
was a civil, respectable-looking man; and 
the price he asked for a bed was reasonable 
enough. Isaac, therefore, decided on stopping 
comfortably at the inn for that night. 
</p>
<p>
He was constitutionally a temperate man. 
His supper simply consisted of two rashers of 
bacon, a slice of home-made bread, and a pint of 
ale. He did not go to bed immediately after this 
moderate meal, but sat up with the landlord 
talking about his bad prospects and his long 
run of ill-luck, and diverging from these 
topics to the subject of horse-flesh and racing. 
Nothing was said either by himself, his host, 
or the few labourers who strayed into the 
tap-room, which could, in the slightest 
degree, excite the very small and very dull 
imaginative faculty which Isaac Scatchard 
possessed. 
</p>
<p>
At a little after eleven the house was 
closed. Isaac went round with the landlord 
and held the candle while the doors and 
lower-windows were being secured. He 
noticed with surprise the strength of the 
bolts, bars, and iron-sheathed shutters. 
</p>
<p>
"You see, we are rather lonely here," said 
the landlord. "We never have had any at 
tempts made to break in yet, but it's always 
as well to be on the safe side. When nobody 
is sleeping here, I am the only man in the 
house. My wife and daughter are timid, and 
the servant-girl takes after her missusses. 
Another glass of ale, before you turn in? 
No!--Well, how such a sober man as you 
comes to be out of place is more than I can 
make out, for one. Here's where you're to 
sleep. You're our only lodger to-night, and I 
think you'll say my missus has done her best 
to make you comfortable. You're quite sure 
you won't have another glass of ale?--Very 
well. Good night." 
</p>
<p>
It was half-past eleven by the clock in the 
passage as they went up-stairs to the bedroom, 
the window of which looked on to the 
wood at the back of the house. Isaac locked the 
door, set his candle on the chest of drawers, 
and wearily got ready for bed. The bleak 
autumn wind was still blowing, and the 
solemn, monotonous, surging moan of it in 
the wood was dreary and awful to hear 
through the night-silence. Isaac felt strangely 
wakeful, and resolved, as he lay down in bed, 
to keep the candle a-light until he began to 
grow sleepy; for there was something unen 
durably depressing in the bare idea of lying 
awake in the darkness, listening to the 
dismal, ceaseless moaning of the wind in 
the wood. 
</p>
<p>
Sleep stole on him before he was aware of 
it. His eyes closed, and he fell off insensibly 
to rest, without having so much.as thought of 
extinguishing the candle. 
</p>
<p>
The first sensation of which he was conscious 
after sinking into slumber, was a strange 
shivering that ran through him suddenly 
from head to foot, and a dreadful sinking 
pain at the heart, such as he had never felt 
before. The shivering only disturbed his 
slumbers--the pain woke him instantly. In 
one moment he passed from a state of sleep 
to a state of wakefulness his eyes wide open--
his mental perceptions cleared on a sudden 
as if by a miracle. 
</p>
<p>
The caudle had burnt down nearly to the 
last morsel of tallow; but the top of the 
unsnuffed wick had just fallen off, and the light 
in the little room was, for the moment, fair 
and full. Between the foot of his bed and 
the closed door there stood a woman with a 
knife in her hand, looking at him. He was 
stricken speechless with terror, but he did not 
lose the preternatural clearness of his faculties; 
and he never took his eyes off the 
woman. She said not one word as they 
stared each other in the face; but she began 
to move slowly towards the left-hand side of 
the bed. 
</p>
<p>
His eyes followed her. She was a fair, 
fine woman, with yellowish flaxen hair, and 
light grey eyes, with a droop in the left eye-lid. 
He noticed those things and fixed them 
on his mind, before she was round at the side 
of the bed. Speechless, with no expression in 
her face, with no noise following her footfall,--
she came closer and closer--stopped--and 
slowly raised the knife. He laid his right 
arm over his throat to save it; but, as he 
saw the knife coming down, threw his hand 
across the bed to the right side, and jerked 
his body over that way, just as the knife 
descended on the mattress within an inch of his 
shoulder. 
</p>
<p>
His eyes fixed on her arm and hand, as she 
slowly drew the knife out of the bed. A 
white, well-shaped arm, with a pretty down 
lying lightly over the fair skin. A delicate, 
lady's hand, with the crowning beauty of a 
pink flush under and round the finger-nails. 
</p>
<p>
She drew the knife out, and passed back 
again slowly to the foot of the bed; stopped 
there for a moment looking at him; then 
came on--still speechless, still with no 
expression on the blank, beautiful face, still 
with no sound following the stealthy footfalls--
came on to the right side of the bed where 
he now lay. As she approached, she raised 
the knife again, and he drew himself away to 
the left side. She struck, as before, right into 
the mattress, with a deliberate, perpendicularly-
downward action of the arm. This 
time his eyes wandered from her to the 
knife. It was like the large clasp knives 
which he had often seen labouring men use 
to cut their bread and bacon with. Her 
delicate little fingers did not conceal more 
than two thirds of the handle; he noticed 
that it was made of buck-horn, clean and 
shining as the blade was, and looking like 
new. 
</p>
<p>
For the second time she drew the knife 
out, concealed it in the wide sleeve of her 
gown, then stopped by the bedside, watching 
him. For an instant he saw her standing in 
that position--then the wick of the spent 
candle fell over into the socket. The flame 
diminished to a little blue point, and the room 
grew dark. A moment, or less, if possible, 
passed so--and then the wick flamed up, 
smokily, for the last time. His eyes were still 
looking eagerly over the right-hand side of 
the bed when the final flash of light came, 
but they discerned nothing. The fair woman 
with the knife was gone. 
</p>
<p>
The conviction that he was alone again, 
weakened the hold of the terror that had 
struck him dumb up to this time. The 
preternatural sharpness which the very intensity 
of his panic had mysteriously imparted 
to his faculties, left them suddenly. His 
brain grew confused--his heart bent wildly--
his ears opened for the first time since 
the appearance of the woman, to a sense 
of the woful, ceaseless moaning of the wind 
among the trees. With the dreadful 
conviction of the reality of what he had seen, 
still strong within him, he leapt out of bed, 
and screaming--" Murder!--Wake up, there, 
wake up! "--dashed headlong through the 
darkness to the door. 
</p>
<p>
It was fast locked, exactly as he had left it 
on going to bed. 
</p>
<p>
His cries on starting up, had alarmed 
the house. He heard the terrified, 
 confused, exclamations of women; he saw the 
master of the house approaching along the 
passage, with his burning rush-candle in one 
hand and his gun in the other. 
</p>
<p>
"What is it?" asked the landlord, breathlessly. 
</p>
<p>
Isaac could only answer in a whisper: 
"A woman, with a knife in her 
hand," he gasped out. "In my room a fair, 
yellow-haired woman; she jabbed at me 
with the knife, twice over." 
</p>
<p>
The landlord's pale cheeks grew paler. He 
looked at Isaac eagerly by the flickering 
light of his candle; and his face began to get 
red again--his voice altered, too, as well as 
his complexion. 
</p>
<p>
"She seems to have missed you twice," he 
said. 
</p>
<p>
"I dodged the knife as it came down," 
Isaac went on, in the same scared whisper. 
"It struck the bed each time." 
</p>
<p>
The landlord took his candle into the bedroom 
immediately. In less than a minute he 
came out again into the passage in a violent 
passion. 
</p>
<p>
"The devil fly away with you and your 
woman with the knife! What do you mean 
by coming into a man's place and frightening 
his family out of their wits about a dream?" 
</p>
<p>
"I'll leave your house," said Isaac, faintly. 
"Better out on the road, in rain and dark, on 
my way home, than back again in that room 
after what I've seen in it. Lend me a light 
to get on my clothes by, and tell me what I'm 
to pay." 
</p>
<p>
"Pay!" cried the landlord, leading the 
way with his light sulkily into the bedroom. 
"You'll find your score on the slate when you 
go down stairs. I wouldn't have taken you 
in for all the money you've got about you, if 
I'd known your dreaming, screeching ways 
beforehand. Look at the bed. Where's the 
cut of a knife in it? Look at the window--
is the lock bursted? Look at the door 
(which I heard you fasten myself)--is it 
broke in? A murdering woman with a 
knife in my house! You ought to be 
ashamed of yourself!" 
</p>
<p>
Isaac answered not a word. He huddled 
on his clothes; and then they went down 
stairs together. 
</p>
<p>
"Nigh on twenty minutes past two!" said 
the landlord, as they passed the clock. "A 
nice time in the morning to frighten honest 
people out of their wits!" 
</p>
<p>
Isaac paid his bill, and the landlord let 
him out at the front door, asking, with a grin 
of contempt, as he undid the strong fastenings, 
whether "the murdering woman got in 
that way?" They parted without a word 
on either side. The rain had ceased; but 
the night was dark, and the wind bleaker 
than ever. Little did the darkness, or the 
cold, or the uncertainty about his way home, 
matter to Isaac. If he had been turned out 
into a wilderness in a thunder-storm, it would 
have been a relief, after what he had suffered 
in the bedroom of the inn. 
</p>
<p>
What was the fair woman with the knife? 
The creature of a dream, or that other 
creature from the unknown world called 
among men by the name of ghost? He could 
make nothing of the mystery--had made 
nothing of it, even when it was mid-day on 
Wednesday, and when he stood, at last, after 
many times missing his road, once more on 
the doorstep of home. 
</p>
<p>
His mother came out eagerly to receive 
him. His face told her in a moment that 
something was wrong. 
</p>
<p>
"I've lost the place; but that's my luck. 
I dreamed an ill dream last night, mother--
or, may be, I saw a ghost. Take it either 
way, it scared me out of my senses, and I'm 
not my own man again yet." 
</p>
<p>
"Isaac! your face frightens me. Come in 
to the fire. Come in, and tell mother all 
about it." 
</p>
<p>
He was as anxious to tell as she was to 
hear; for it had been his hope, all the way 
home, that his mother, with her quicker 
capacity and superior knowledge, might be 
able to throw some light on the mystery 
which he could not clear up for himself. 
His memory of the dream was still 
mechanically vivid, though his thoughts were 
entirely confused by it. 
</p>
<p>
His mother's face grew paler and paler as 
he went on. She never interrupted him by 
so much as a single word; but when he had 
done, she moved her chair close to his, put 
her arm round his neck, and said to him: 
</p>
<p>
"Isaac, you dreamed your ill dream on this 
Wednesda'y morning. What time was it 
when you saw the fair woman with the knife 
in her hand?" 
</p>
<p>
Isaac reflected on what the landlord had 
said when they passed by the clock on his 
leaving the inn--allowed as nearly as he 
could for the time that must have elapsed 
between the unlocking of his bedroom door 
and the paying of his bill just before going 
away, and answered: 
</p>
<p>
"Somewhere about two o'clock in the 
morning." 
</p>
<p>
His mother suddenly quitted her hold of 
his neck, and struck her hands together with 
a gesture of despair. 
</p>
<p>
"This Wednesday is your birthday Isaac; 
and two o'clock in the morning was the time 
when you were born!" 
</p>
<p>
Isaac's capacities were not quick enough to 
catch the infection of his mother's 
superstitious dread. He was amazed and a little 
startled also, when she suddenly rose from 
her chair, opened her old writing-desk, took 
out pen and ink and paper, and then said to 
him: 
</p>
<p>
"Your memory is but a poor one, Isaac, 
and now I'm an old woman, mine's not much 
better. I want all about this dream of yours 
to be as well known to both of us, years 
hence, as it is now. Tell me over again all 
you told me a minute ago, when you spoke of 
what the woman with the knife looked like." 
</p>
<p>
Isaac obeyed, and marvelled much as he 
saw his mother carefully set down on paper 
the very words that he was saying. "Light 
grey eyes," she wrote, as they came to the 
descriptive part, "with a droop in the left 
eyelid. Flaxen hair, with a gold-yellow 
streak in it. White arms, with a down on 
them. Little lady's hand, with a reddish 
look about the finger-nails. Clasp knife with 
a buck-horn handle, that seemed as good as 
new." To these particulars, Mrs. Scatchard 
added the year, month, day of the week, and 
time in the morning, when the woman of the 
dream appeared to her son. She then locked 
up the paper carefully in her writing-desk. 
</p>
<p>
Neither on that day, nor on any day after, 
could her son induce her to return to the 
matter of the dream. She obstinately kept 
her thoughts about it to herself, and even 
refused to refer again to the paper in her 
writing-desk. Ere long, Isaac grew weary of 
attempting to make her break her resolute 
silence; and time, which sooner or later, 
wears out all things, gradually wore out the 
impression produced on him by the dream. 
He began by thinking of it carelessly, and he 
ended by not thinking of it at all. This 
result was the more easily brought about by 
the advent of some important changes for the 
better in his prospects, which commenced 
not long after his terrible night's experience 
at the inn. He reaped at last the reward of 
his long and patient suffering under adversity, 
by getting an excellent place, keeping it 
for seven years, and leaving it, on the death 
of his master, not only with an excellent 
character, but also with a comfortable 
annuity bequeathed to him as a reward for 
saving his mistress's life in a carriage 
accident. Thus it happened that Isaac 
Scatchard returned to his old mother, seven 
years after the time of the dream at the inn, 
with an annual sum of money at his disposal, 
sufficient to keep them both in ease and 
independence for the rest of their lives. 
</p>
<p>
The mother, whose health had been bad 
of late years, profited so much by the 
care bestowed on her and by freedom from 
money anxieties, that when Isaac's next 
birthday came round, she was able to sit up 
comfortably at table and dine with him. 
</p>
<p>
On that day, as the evening drew on, Mrs. 
Scatchard discovered that a bottle of tonic 
medicine--which she was accustomed to take, 
and in which she had fancied that a dose or 
more was still left--happened to be empty. 
Isaac immediately volunteered to go to the 
chemist's, and get it filled again. It was as 
rainy and bleak an autumn night as on the 
memorable past occasion when he lost his 
way and slept at the roadside inn. 
</p>
<p>
On going into the chemist's shop, he was 
passed hurriedly by a poorly-dressed woman 
coming out of it. The glimpse he had of her 
face struck him, and he looked back after her 
as she descended the door-steps. 
</p>
<p>
"You're noticing that woman?" said the 
chemist's apprentice behind the counter. 
"It's my opinion there's something wrong 
with her. She's been asking for laudanum to 
put to a bad tooth. Master's out for half an 
hour; and I told her I wasn't allowed to sell 
poison to strangers in his absence. She laughed 
in a queer way, and said she would come back 
in half an hour. If she expects master to 
serve her, I think she'll be disappointed. 
It's a case of suicide, sir, if ever there was 
one yet." 
</p>
<p>
These words added immeasurably to the 
sudden interest in the woman which Isaac 
had felt at the first sight of her face. After 
he had got the medicine-bottle filled, he 
looked about anxiously for her, as soon as he 
was out in the street. She was walking 
slowly up and down on the opposite side of 
the road. With his heart, very much to his 
own surprise, beating fast, Isaac crossed over 
and spoke to her. 
</p>
<p>
He asked if she was in any distress. She 
pointed to her torn shawl, her scanty dress, 
her crushed, dirty bonnet--then moved under 
a lamp so as to let the light fall on her stern, 
pale, but still most beautiful face. 
</p>
<p>
"I look like a comfortable, happy woman--
don't I?" she said with a bitter laugh. 
</p>
<p>
She spoke with a purity of intonation 
which Isaac had never heard before from 
other than ladies' lips. Her slightest actions 
seemed to have the easy negligent grace of a 
thorough-bred woman. Her skin, for all its 
poverty-stricken paleness, was as delicate as 
if her life had been passed in the enjoyment 
of every social comfort that wealth can 
purchase. Even her small, finely-shaped hands, 
gloveless as they were, had not lost their 
whiteness. 
</p>
<p>
Little by little, in answer to his question, 
the sad story of the woman came out. There 
is no need to relate it here; it is told 
over and over again in Police Reports and 
paragraphs about Attempted Suicides. 
</p>
<p>
"My name is Rebecca Murdoch," said the 
woman, as she ended. "I have ninepence 
left, and I thought of spending it at the 
chemist's over the way in securing a passage 
to the other world. Whatever it is, it can't 
be worse to me than this--so why should I 
stop here?" 
</p>
<p>
Besides the natural compassion and sadness 
moved in his heart by what he heard, Isaac 
felt within him some mysterious influence 
att work all the time the woman was speaking, 
which utterly confused his ideas and almost 
deprived him of his powers of speech. All 
that he could say in answer to her last reckless 
words was, that he would prevent her 
from attempting her own life, if he followed 
her about all night to do it. His rough, 
trembling earnestness seemed to impress 
her. 
</p>
<p>
"I won't occasion you that trouble," she 
answered, when he repeated his threat. 
"You have given me a fancy for living by 
speaking kindly to me. No need for the 
mockery of protestations and promises. You 
may believe me without them. Come to 
Fuller's Meadow to-morrow at twelve, and 
you will find me alive, to answer for myself. 
No!--no money. My ninepence will do to 
get me as good a night's lodging as I want." 
</p>
<p>
She nodded and left him. He made no 
attempt to follow--he felt no suspicion that 
she was deceiving him. 
</p>
<p>
"It's strange, but I can't help believing 
her," he said to himself--and walked away, 
bewildered, towards home. 
</p>
<p>
On entering the house his mind was still 
so completely absorbed by its new subject of 
interest, that he took no notice of what his 
mother was doing when he came in with the 
bottle of medicine. She had opened her old 
writing-desk in his absence, and was now 
reading a paper attentively that lay inside it. 
On every birthday of Isaac's since she had 
written down the particulars of his dream 
from his own lips, she had been accustomed 
to read that same paper, and ponder over it 
in private. 
</p>
<p>
The next day he went to Fuller's Meadow. 
He had done only right in believing her so 
implicitly--she was there, punctual to a 
minute, to answer for herself. The last-left 
faint defences in Isaac's heart against the 
fascination which a word or look from her 
began inscrutably to exercise over him, sank 
down and vanished before her for ever on 
that memorable morning. 
</p>
<p>
When a man, previously insensible to the 
influence of women, forms an attachment in 
middle life, the instances are rare indeed, let 
the warning circumstances be what they may, 
in which he is found capable of freeing 
himself from the tyranny of the new ruling 
passion. The charm of being spoken to 
familiarly, fondly, and gratefully by a woman 
whose language and manners still retained 
enough of their early refinement to hint at 
the high social station that she had lost, 
would have been a dangerous luxury to a 
man of Isaac's rank at the age of twenty. 
But it was far more than that--it was certain 
ruin to him--now that his heart was opening 
unworthily to a new influence, at that middle 
time of life when strong feelings of all kinds, 
once implanted, strike root most stubbornly 
 in a man's moral nature. A few more stolen 
interviews after that first morning in Fuller's 
Meadow completed his infatuation. In 
less than a month from the time when he 
first met her, Isaac Scatchard had consented 
to give Rebecca Murdoch a new interest in 
existence, and a chance of recovering the 
character she had lost, by promising to make 
her his wife. 
</p>
<p>
She had taken possession, not of his passions 
only, but of his faculties as well. All arrangements 
for the present and all plans for the 
future were of her devising. All the mind 
he had he put into her keeping. She directed 
him on every point; even instructing him 
how to break the news of his approaching 
marriage in the safest manner to his mother. 
</p>
<p>
"If you tell her how you met me and who 
I am at first," said the cunning woman, "she 
will move heaven and earth to prevent our 
marriage. Say I am the sister of one of your 
fellow-servants--ask her to see me before 
you go into any more particulars--and leave 
it to me to do the rest. I want to make her 
love me next best to you, Isaac, before she 
knows anything of who I really am." 
</p>
<p>
The motive of the deceit was sufficient to 
sanctify it to Isaac. The stratagem proposed 
relieved him of his one great anxiety, and 
quieted his uneasy conscience on the subject 
of his mother: Still, there was something 
wanting to perfect his happiness, something 
that he could not realise, something 
mysteriously untraceable, and yet, something 
that perpetually made itself felt; not when 
he was absent from Rebecca Murdoch, but, 
strange to say, when he was actually in 
her presence! She was kindness itself 
with him; she never made him feel his 
inferior capacities, and inferior manners,--she 
showed the sweetest anxiety to please him in 
the smallest trifles; but, in spite of all these 
attractions, he never could feel quite at his 
ease with her. At their first meeting, there 
had mingled with his admiration when he 
looked in her face, a faint involuntary feeling 
of doubt whether that face was entirely 
strange to him. No after familiarity had 
the slightest effect on this inexplicable, 
wearisome uncertainty. 
</p>
<p>
Concealing the truth as he had been 
directed, he announced his marriage engagement 
precipitately and confusedly to his 
mother, on the day when he contracted it. 
Poor Mrs. Scatchard showed her perfect 
confidence in her son by flinging her arms 
round his neck, and giving him joy of 
having found at last, in the sister of one of 
his fellow-servants, a woman to comfort 
and care for him after his mother was 
gone. She was all eagerness to see the 
woman of her son's choice; and the next day 
was fixed for the introduction. 
</p>
<p>
It was a bright sunny morning, and the 
little cottage parlour was full of light, as 
Mrs. Scatchard, happy and expectant, 
dressed for the occasion in her Sunday gown, 
sat waiting for her son and her future 
daughter-in-law. Punctual to the appointed 
time, Isaac hurriedly and nervously led his 
promised wife into the room. His mother 
rose to receive her--advanced a few steps, 
smiling--looked Rebecca full in the eyes--
and suddenly stopped. Her face, which 
had been flushed the moment before, turned 
white in an instant--her eyes lost their 
expression of softness and kindness, and assumed 
a blank look of terror--her outstretched 
hands fell to her sides, and she staggered 
back a few steps with a low cry to her son. 
</p>
<p>
"Isaac!" she whispered, clutching him 
fast by the arm, when he asked alarmedly if 
she was taken ill. "Isaac! Does that 
woman's face remind you of nothing?" 
</p>
<p>
Before he could answer; before he could 
look round to where Rebecca, astonished and 
angered by her reception, stood, at the lower 
end of the room; his mother pointed 
impatiently to her writing-desk, and gave him the 
key. 
</p>
<p>
"Open it," she said, in a quick, breathless 
whisper. 
</p>
<p>
"What does this mean? Why am I 
treated as if I had no business here? Does 
your mother want to insult me?" asked 
Rebecca, angrily. 
</p>
<p>
"Open it, and give me the paper in 
the left-hand drawer. Quick! quick, for 
Heaven's sake!" said Mrs. Scatchard, shrinking 
further back in terror. Isaac gave her the 
paper. She looked it over eagerly for a 
moment--then followed Rebecca, who was now 
turning away haughtily to leave the room, 
and caught her by the shoulder--abruptly 
raised the long, loose sleeve of her gown, and 
glanced at her hand and arm. Something 
like fear began to steal over the angry 
expression of Rebecca's face as she shook 
herself free from the old woman's grasp. "Mad!" 
she said to herself; "and Isaac never told 
me." With these few words she left the 
room. 
</p>
<p>
Isaac was hastening after her when his 
mother turned and stopped his further 
progress. It wrung his heart to see the misery 
and terror in her face as she looked at him. 
</p>
<p>
"Light grey eyes," she said, in low, mournful, 
awe-struck tones, pointing towards the 
open door. "A droop in the left eyelid. 
Flaxen hair with a gold-yellow streak in it. 
White arms with a down on them. Little, 
lady's hand, with a reddish look under the 
finger-nails. The woman of the dream!--Oh, 
Heaven! Isaac, the woman of the dream!" 
</p>
<p>
That faint cleaving doubt which he had 
never been able to shake off in Rebecca 
Murdoch's presence, was fatally set at rest 
for ever. He had seen her face, then, before--
seven years before, on his birthday, in the 
bedroom of the lonely inn. "The woman of 
the dream!" 
</p>
<p>
"Be warned, Oh, my son! be warned! 
Isaac! Isaac! let her go, and do you stop 
with me!" 
</p>
<p>
Something darkened the parlour window, as 
those words were said. A sudden chill ran 
through him; and he glanced sidelong at the 
shadow. Rebecca Murdoch had come back. 
She was peering in curiously at them over the 
low window blind. 
</p>
<p>
"I have promised to marry, mother," he 
said, "and marry I must." 
</p>
<p>
The tears came into his eyes as he spoke, 
and dimmed his sight; but he could just 
discern the fatal face outside moving away 
again from the window. 
</p>
<p>
His mother's head sank lower. 
</p>
<p>
"Are you faint?" he whispered. 
</p>
<p>
"Broken-hearted, Isaac." 
</p>
<p>
He stooped down and kissed her. The 
shadow, as he did so, returned to the window; 
and the fatal face peered in curiously once 
more. 
</p>
<p>
Three weeks after that day, Isaac and 
Rebecca were man and wife. All that was 
hopelessly dogged and stubborn in the man's 
moral nature, seemed to have closed round 
his fatal passion, and to have fixed it 
unassailably in his heart. 
</p>
<p>
After that first interview in the cottage 
parlour, no consideration would induce Mrs. 
Scatchard to see her son's wife again, or even 
to talk of her when Isaac tried hard to plead 
her cause after their marriage. This course of 
conduct was not in any degree occasioned by a 
discovery of the degradation in which Rebecca 
had lived. There was no question of that 
between mother and son. There was no question 
of anything but the fearfully exact 
resemblance between the living breathing woman 
and the spectre woman of Isaac's dream. 
Rebecca, on her side, neither felt nor 
expressed the slightest sorrow at the estrangement 
between herself and her mother-in-law. 
Isaac, for the sake of peace, had 
never contradicted her first idea that age and 
long illness had affected Mrs. Scatchard's 
mind. He even allowed his wife to upbraid 
him for not having confessed this to her at 
the time of their marriage engagement, rather 
than risk anything by hinting at the truth. 
The sacrifice of his integrity before his one 
all-mastering delusion, seemed but a small 
thing, and cost his conscience but little, after 
the sacrifices he had already made. 
</p>
<p>
The time of waking from his delusion--the 
cruel and the rueful time--was not far off. 
After some quiet months of married life, as 
the summer was ending, and the year was 
getting on towards the month of his birthday, 
Isaac found his wife altering towards 
him. She grew sullen and contemptuous--
she formed acquaintances of the most 
dangerous kind, in defiance of his objections, his 
entreaties, and his commands,--and, worst of 
all, she learnt, ere long, after every fresh 
difference with her husband, to seek the 
deadly self-oblivion of drink. Little by little, 
after the first miserable discovery that his 
wife was keeping company with drunkards, 
the shocking certainty forced itself on Isaac 
that she had grown to be a drunkard herself. 
</p>
<p>
He had been in a sadly desponding state 
for some time before the occurrence of these 
domestic calamities. His mother's health, as 
he could but too plainly discern every time 
he went to see her at the cottage, was failing 
fast; and he upbraided himself in secret 
as the cause of the bodily and mental suffering 
she endured. When, to his remorse 
on his mother's account, was added the 
shame and misery occasioned by the discovery 
of his wife's degradation, he sank under 
the double trial--his face began to alter 
fast, and he looked what he was, a spirit-broken 
man. His mother, still struggling 
bravely against the illness that was hurrying 
her to the grave, was the first to notice 
the sad alteration in him, and the first to 
hear of his last bitterest trouble with his 
wife. She could only weep bitterly, on the 
day when he made his humiliating confession; 
but on the next occasion when he went to 
see her, she had taken a resolution, in 
reference to his domestic afflictions, which 
astonished, and even alarmed him. He found 
her dressed to go out, and on asking the 
reason, received this answer: 
</p>
<p>
"I am not long for this world, Isaac," 
said she; "and I shall not feel easy on 
my death-bed, unless I have done my best 
to the last, to make my son happy. I mean 
to put my own fears and my own feelings out 
of the question, and to go with you to your 
wife, and try what I can do to reclaim her. 
Give me your arm, Isaac; and let me do the 
last thing I can in this world to help my son 
before it is too late." 
</p>
<p>
He could not disobey her: and they 
walked together slowly towards his miserable 
home. It was only one o'clock in the 
afternoon when they reached the cottage where 
he lived. It was their dinner hour, and Rebecca 
was in the kitchen. He was thus able to take 
his mother quietly into the parlour, and then 
prepare his wife for the interview. She had 
fortunately drank but little at that early 
hour, and she was less sullen and capricious 
than usual. He returned to his mother, with 
his mind tolerably at ease. His wife soon 
followed him into the parlour, and the meeting 
between her and Mrs. Scatchard passed 
off better than he had ventured to anticipate: 
though he observed, with secret apprehension, 
that his mother, resolutely as she 
controlled herself in other respects, could not 
look his wife in the face when she spoke to 
her. It was a relief to him, therefore, when 
Rebecca began to lay the cloth. 
</p>
<p>
She laid the cloth--brought in the bread-tray, 
and cut a slice from the loaf for her 
husband--then returned to the kitchen. At 
that moment, Isaac, still anxiously watching 
his mother, was startled by seeing the same 
ghastly change pass over her face, which had 
altered it so awfully on the morning when 
Rebecca and she first met. Before he could 
say a word she whispered with a look of 
horror:--
</p>
<p>
"Take me back!--home, home, again, 
Isaac! Come with me, and never come back 
again." 
</p>
<p>
He was afraid to ask for an explanation,--
he could only sign to her to be silent, arid 
help her quickly to the door. As they passed 
the bread-tray on the table she stopped and 
pointed to it. 
</p>
<p>
"Did you see what your wife cut your 
bread with?" she asked, in a low, still 
whisper. 
</p>
<p>
"No, mother,--I was not noticing--what 
was it?" 
</p>
<p>
"Look!" 
</p>
<p>
He did look. A new clasp-knife, with a 
buck-horn handle lay with the loaf in the 
bread-tray. He stretched out his hand, shudderingly, 
to possess himself of it; but, at 
the same time, there was a noise in the 
kitchen, and his mother caught at his 
arm. 
</p>
<p>
"The knife of the dream!--Isaac, I'm 
faint with fear--take me away! before she 
comes back!" 
</p>
<p>
He was hardly able to support her--the 
visible, tangible reality of the knife struck 
him with a panic, and utterly destroyed any 
faint doubts that he might have entertained 
up to this time, in relation to the mysterious 
dream-warning of nearly eight years before. 
By a last desperate effort, he summoned self-possession 
enough to help his mother quietly 
out of the house,--so quietly, that the "dream-woman" 
(he thought of her by that name, 
now!) did not hear them departing, from 
the kitchen. 
</p>
<p>
"Don't go back, Isaac,--don't go back!" 
implored Mrs. Scatchard, as he turned 
to go away, after seeing her safely seated 
again in her own room. 
</p>
<p>
"I must get the knife," he answered, under 
his breath. She tried to stop him again; 
but he hurried out without another word. 
</p>
<p>
On his return, he found that his wife had 
discovered their secret departure from the 
house. She had been drinking, and was in 
a fury of passion. The dinner in the kitchen 
was flung under the grate; the cloth was off 
the parlour-table. Where was the knife? 
Unwisely, he asked for it. She was only too 
glad of the opportunity of irritating him, 
which the request afforded her. "He wanted 
the knife, did he? Could he give her a reason 
why?--No!--Then he should not have 
it,--not if he went down on his knees to ask 
for it." Further recriminations elicited the 
fact that she had bought it a bargain--and 
that she considered it her own especial 
property. Isaac saw the uselessuess of attempting 
to get the knife by fair means, and 
determined to search for it, later in the day, 
in secret. The search was unsuccessful. Night 
came on, and he left the house to walk about 
the streets. He was afraid now to sleep in the 
same room with her. 
</p>
<p>
Three weeks passed. Still sullenly enraged 
with him, she would not give up the knife; 
and still that fear of sleeping in the same 
room with her, possessed him. He walked 
about at night, or dozed in the parlour, or sat 
watching by his mother's bed-side. Before the 
expiration of the first week in the new month 
his mother died. It wanted then but ten 
days' of her son's birthday. She had longed 
to live till that anniversary. Isaac was 
present at her death; and her last words in this 
world were addressed to him: "Don't go 
back, my son, don't go back!" 
</p>
<p>
He was obliged to go back, if it were only to 
watch his wife. Exasperated to the last 
degree by his distrust of her, she had revengefully 
sought to add a sting to his grief, during 
the last days of his mother's illness, by 
declaring that she would assert her right to 
attend the funeral. In spite of all that he 
could do, or say, she held with wicked 
pertinacity to her word; and, on the day 
appointed for the burial, forced herself--
inflamed and shameless with drink--into her 
husband's presence, and declared that she 
would walk in the funeral procession to his 
mother's grave. 
</p>
<p>
This last worst outrage, accompanied by all 
that was most insulting in word and look, 
maddened him for the moment. He struck her. 
The instant the blow was dealt, he repented 
it. She crouched down, silent in a corner 
of the room, and eyed him steadily; it was a 
look that cooled his hot blood, and made him 
tremble. But there was no time now to 
think of a means of making atonement. 
Nothing remained, but to risk the worst till 
the funeral was over. There was but one way 
of making sure of her. He locked her into 
her bed-room. 
</p>
<p>
When he came back some hours after, he 
found her sitting, very much altered in look 
and bearing, by the bedside, with a bundle on 
her lap. She rose, and faced him quietly, and 
spoke with a strange stillness in her voice, a 
strange repose in her eyes, a strange composure 
in her manner. 
</p>
<p>
"No man has ever struck me twice," she 
said, "and my husband shall have no second 
opportunity. Set the door open and let me 
go. From this day forth we see each other 
no more." 
</p>
<p>
Before he could answer she passed him, 
and left the room. He saw her walk away up 
the street. 
</p>
<p>
Would she return? All that night he 
watched and waited; but no footstep came 
near the house. The next night, overpowered 
by fatigue, he lay down in bed, in his clothes, 
with the door locked, the key on the table, 
and the candle burning. His slumber was not 
disturbed. The third night, the fourth, 
the fifth, the sixth, passed, and nothing 
happened. He lay down on the seventh, 
still in his clothes, still with the door locked, 
the key on the table, and the candle burning; 
but easier in his mind. 
</p>
<p>
Easier in his mind, and in perfect health of 
body, when he fell off to sleep. But his rest 
was disturbed. He woke twice, without any 
sensation of uneasiness. But the third time 
it was that never-to-be-forgotten shivering of 
the night at the lonely inn, that dreadful 
sinking pain at the heart, which once more 
aroused him in an instant. 
</p>
<p>
His eyes opened towards the left hand side 
of the bed, and there stood--The woman 
</p>
<p>
of the dream, again?--No! His wife; the 
living reality, with the dream-spectre's face--
in the dream-spectre's attitude; the fair 
arm up--the knife clasped in the delicate, 
white hand. 
</p>
<p>
He sprang upon her, almost at the instant 
of seeing her, and yet not quickly enough to 
prevent her from hiding the knife. Without 
a word from him--without a cry from her--
he pinioned her in a chair. With one hand 
he felt up her sleeve--and, there, where the 
dream-woman had hidden the knife, she had 
hidden it,--the knife with the buck-horn 
handle, that looked like new. 
</p>
<p>
In the despair of that fearful moment his 
brain was steady, his heart was calm. He 
looked at her fixedly, with the knife in his 
hand, and said these last words: 
</p>
<p>
"You told me we should see each other no 
more, and you have come back. It is my 
turn, now, to go, and to go for ever. I say 
that we shall see each other no more; and 
my word shall not be broken." 
</p>
<p>
He left her, and set forth into the night. 
There was a bleak wind abroad, and the 
smell of recent rain was in the air. The 
distant church-clocks chimed the quarter as 
he walked rapidly beyond the last 
houses in the suburb. He asked the first 
policeman he met, what hour that was, of 
which the quarter past had just struck. 
</p>
<p>
The man referred sleepily to his watch, 
and answered: "Two o'clock." Two in the 
morning. What day of the month was this 
day that had just begun? He reckoned it 
up from the date of his mother's funeral. 
The fatal parallel was complete--it was his 
birthday! 
</p>
<p>
Had he escaped the mortal peril which his 
dream foretold? or had he only received a 
second warning? As that ominous doubt 
forced itself on his mind, he stopped, 
reflected, and turned back again towards the 
city. He was still resolute to hold to his 
word, and never to let her see him more; but 
there was a thought now in his mind of having 
her watched and followed. The knife 
was in his possession--the world was before 
him; but a new distrust of her--a vague, unspeakable, 
superstitious dread--had overcome 
him. 
</p>
<p>
"I must know where she goes, now she 
thinks I have left her," he said to himself, 
as he stole back wearily to the precincts of 
his house. 
</p>
<p>
It was still dark. He had left the candle 
burning in the bedchamber: but when he 
looked up at the window of the room now, 
there was no light in it. He crept cautiously 
to the house-door. On going away, he 
remembered to have closed it: on trying it 
now, he found it open. 
</p>
<p>
He waited outside, never losing sight of the 
house, till daylight. Then he ventured 
indoors--listened, and heard nothing--looked 
into kitchen, scullery, parlour; and found 
nothing: went up, at last, into the bedroom--
it was empty. A pick-lock lay on the 
floor, betraying how she had gained entrance 
in the night; and that was the only trace 
of her. 
</p>
<p>
Whither had she gone? That no mortal 
tongue could tell him. The darkness had 
covered her flight; and when the day broke, 
no man could say where the light found her. 
</p>
<p>
Before leaving the house and the town for 
ever, he gave instructions to a friend and 
neighbour to sell his furniture for anything 
that it would fetch, and apply the proceeds 
to employing the police to trace her. The 
directions were honestly followed, and the 
money was all spent; but the enquiries led 
to nothing. The pick-lock on the bedroom 
floor remained the one last useless trace of 
her. 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
 At this point of the narrative the landlord 
paused, and looked towards the stable-door. 
</p>
<p>
"So far," he said, "I tell you what was 
told to me. The little that remains to be 
added lies within my own experience. 
between two and three months after the events 
I have just been relating, Isaac Scatchard 
came to me, withered and old-looking before 
his time, just as you saw him to-day. He 
had his testimonials to character with him, 
and he asked for employment here. I gave 
him a trial, and liked him in spite of his queer 
habits. He is as sober, honest, and willing a 
man as there is in England. As for his 
restlessness at night, and his sleeping away his 
leisure time in the day, who can wonder at 
it after hearing his story? Besides, he never 
objects to being roused up, when he's wanted, 
so there's not much inconvenience to 
complain of, after all." 
</p>
<p>
"I suppose he is afraid of waking out of 
that dreadful dream in the dark?" said I. 
</p>
<p>
"No," returned the landlord. "The dream 
comes back to him so often, that he has got 
to bear with it by this time resignedly 
enough. It's his wife keeps him waking at 
night, as he has often told me." 
</p>
<p>
"What! Has she never been heard of 
yet?" 
</p>
<p>
"Never. Isaac himself has the one 
perpetual thought about her, that she is alive 
and looking for him. I believe he wouldn't 
let himself drop off to sleep towards two 
in the morning for a king's ransom. Two 
in the morning, he says, is the time when 
she will find him, one of these days. Two in 
the morning is the time all the year round, 
when he likes to be most certain that he has 
got that clasp-knife safe about him. He 
does not mind being alone, as long as he is 
awake, except on the night before his birthday, 
when he firmly believes himself to be 
in peril of his life. The birthday has only 
come round once since he has been here; 
and then he sat up, along with the night-porter. 
'She's looking for me,' he always 
says, when I speak to him on the one theme 
of his life; ' she's looking for me.' He may 
be right. She may be looking for him. Who 
can tell?" 
</p>
<p>
"Who can tell!" said I. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BOOTS.</title>
<p>
WHERE had he been in his time? he 
repeated when I asked him the question. Lord, 
he had been everywhere! And what had he 
been? Bless you, he had been everything 
you could mention a'most. 
</p>
<p>
Seen a good deal? Why, of course he had. 
I should say so, he could assure me, if I only 
knew about a twentieth part of what had 
come in his way. Why, it would be easier 
for him, he expected, to tell what he hadn't 
seen, than what he had. Ah! A deal, it 
would. 
</p>
<p>
What was the curiousest thing he had 
seen? Well! He didn't know. He couldn't 
momently name what was the curiousest thing 
he had seen--unless it was a Unicorn--and 
he see him once, at a Fair. But, supposing a 
young gentleman not eight year old, was to 
run away with a fine young woman of seven, 
might I think that a queer start? Certainly? 
Then, that was a start as he himself had had 
his blessed eyes on--and he had cleaned 
the shoes they run away in--and they was 
so little that he couldn't get his hand 
into 'em. 
</p>
<p>
Master Harry Walmers's father, you see, 
he lived at the Elmses, down away by Shooter's 
Hill there, six or seven mile from Lunnon. 
He was a gentleman of spirit, and good looking, 
and held his head up when he walked, and 
had what you may call Fire about him. He 
wrote poetry, and he rode, and he ran, and he 
cricketed, and he danced, and he acted, and 
he done it all equally beautiful. He was 
uncommon proud of Master Harry as was 
his only child; but he didn't spoil him, 
neither. He was a gentleman that had a 
will of his own and a eye of his own, and 
that would be minded. Consequently, though 
he made quite a companion of the fine bright 
boy, and was delighted to see him so fond of 
reading his fairy books, and was never tired 
of hearing him say my name is Norval, or 
hearing him sing his songs about Young May 
Moons is beaming love, and When he as adores 
thee has left but the name, and that: still he 
kept the command over the child, and the 
child was a child, and it's to be wished more 
of 'em was! 
</p>
<p>
How did Boots happen to know all this? 
Why, through being under-gardener. Of 
course he couldn't be under-gardener, and 
be always about, in the summer-time, near 
the windows on the lawn, a mowing, and 
sweeping, and weeding, and pruning, and this 
and that, without getting acquainted with 
the ways of the family.--Even supposing 
Master Harry hadn't come to him one morning 
early, and said, "Cobbs, how should you 
spell Norah, if you was asked?" and then 
begun cutting it in print, all over the fence. 
</p>
<p>
He couldn't say he had taken particular 
notice of children before that; but, really it 
was pretty to see them two mites a going 
about the place together, deep in love. And 
the courage of the boy! Bless your soul, he'd 
have throwed off his little hat, and tucked 
up his little sleeves, and gone in at a Lion, he 
would, if they had happened to meet one and 
she had been frightened of him. One day he 
stops, along with her, where Boots was hoeing 
weeds in the, gravel, and says--speaking up, 
"Cobbs," he says, "I like you." "Do you, 
sir? I'm proud to hear it." "Yes, I do, 
Cobbs. Why do I like you, do you think, 
Cobbs?" "Don't know, Master Harry, I am 
sure." "Because Norah likes you, Cobbs." 
Indeed, sir? That's very gratifying." 
"Gratifying, Cobbs? It's better than millions of 
the brightest diamonds, to be liked by Norah." 
"Certainly, sir." "You're going away, ain't 
you, Cobbs?" "Yes sir." "Would you 
like another situation, Cobbs?" "Well, sir, 
I shouldn't object, if it was a good 'un." 
"Then, Cobbs," says he, "you shall be our 
Head Gardener when we are married." And 
he tucks her, in her little sky blue mantle, 
under his arm, and walks away. 
</p>
<p>
Boots could assure me that it was better 
than a picter, and equal to a play, to see 
them babies with their long bright curling 
hair, their sparkling eyes, and their beautiful 
light tread, a rambling about the garden, 
deep in love. Boots was of opinion that the 
birds believed they was birds, and kept up 
with 'em, singing to please 'em. Sometimes, 
they would creep under the Tulip-tree, and 
would sit there with their arms round one 
another's necks, and their soft cheeks touching, 
a reading about the Prince, and the 
Dragon, and the good and bad enchanters, 
and the king's fair daughter. Sometimes, he 
would hear them planning about having a 
house in a forest, keeping bees and a cow, 
and living entirely on milk and honey. Once, 
he came upon them by the pond, and heard 
Master Harry say, "Adorable Norah, kiss 
me, and say you love me to distraction, or 
I'll jump in head-foremost." And Boots 
made no question he would have done it, if 
she hadn't complied. On the whole, Boots 
said it had a tendency to make him feel as 
if he was in love himself--only he didn't 
exactly know who with. 
</p>
<p>
"Cobbs," said Master Harry, one evening, 
when Cobbs was watering the flowers; "I 
am going on a visit, this present Midsummer, 
to my grandmamma's at York." 
</p>
<p>
"Are you indeed, sir? I hope you'll have 
a pleasant time. I am going into Yorkshire 
myself, when I leave here." 
</p>
<p>
"Are you going to your grandmamma's, 
Cobbs?" 
</p>
<p>
"No, sir. I haven't got such a thing." 
</p>
<p>
"Not as a grandmamma, Cobbs?" 
</p>
<p>
"No, sir." 
</p>
<p>
The boy looked on at the watering of the 
flowers, for a little while, and then said, "I 
shall be very glad indeed to go, Cobbs--
Norah's going." 
</p>
<p>
"You'll be all right then, sir," says Cobbs, 
"with your beautiful sweetheart by your 
side." 
</p>
<p>
"Cobbs," returned the boy, flushing. "I 
never let anybody joke about it, when I can 
prevent them." 
</p>
<p>
"It wasn't a joke, sir," says Cobbs with 
humility, "--wasn't so meant." 
</p>
<p>
"I am glad of that, Cobbs, because I like 
you, you know, and you're going to live with 
us.--Cobbs!" 
</p>
<p>
"Sir." 
</p>
<p>
"What do you think my grandmamma 
gives me, when I go down there?" 
</p>
<p>
"I couldn't so much as make a guess, sir." 
</p>
<p>
"A Bank of England five-pound note, 
Cobbs." 
</p>
<p>
"Whew!" says Cobbs, "that's a spanking 
sum of money, Master Harry." 
</p>
<p>
"A person could do a good deal with such 
a sum of money as that. Couldn't a person, 
Cobbs?" 
</p>
<p>
"I believe you, sir!" 
</p>
<p>
"Cobbs," said the boy, "I'll tell you a secret. 
At Norah's house, they have been joking her 
about me, and pretending to laugh at our 
being engaged. Pretending to make game 
of it, Cobbs!" 
</p>
<p>
"Such, sir," says Cobbs, "is the depravity 
of human natur." 
</p>
<p>
The boy, looking exactly like his father, 
stood for a few minutes with his glowing face 
towards the sunset, and then departed with 
"Good-night, Cobbs. I'm going in." 
</p>
<p>
If I was to ask Boots how it happened 
that he was a going to leave that place just 
at that present time, well, he couldn't rightly 
answer me. He did suppose he might have 
stayed there till now, if he had been anyways 
inclined. But, you see, he was younger then 
and he wanted change. That's what he 
wanted--change. Mr. Walmers, he said, 
to him when he give him notice of his 
intentions to leave, "Cobbs," he says, "have 
you anythink to complain of? I make the 
inquiry, because if I find that any of my 
people really has anythink to complain of, I 
wish to make it right if I can." "No, sir," 
says Cobbs; "thanking you, sir, I find myself 
as well sitiwated here as I could hope to be 
anywheres. The truth is, sir, that I'm a 
going to seek my fortun." "O, indeed, 
Cobbs?" he says; "I hope you may find it." 
And Boots could assure me--which he did, 
touching his hair with his boot-jack, as a 
salute in the way of his present--calling that 
he hadn't found it yet. 
</p>
<p>
Well, sir! Boots left the Elmses when his 
time was up, and Master Harry he went 
down to the old lady's at York, which old 
lady would have given that child the teeth out 
of her head (if she had had any), she was so 
wrapt up in him. What does that Infant do--
for Infant you may call him and be within 
the mark--but cut away from that old lady's 
with his Norah, on a expedition to go to 
Gretna Green and be married! 
</p>
<p>
Sir, Boots was at this identical Holly-Tree 
Inn (having left it several times since to 
better himself, but always come back through 
one thing or another), when, one summer 
afternoon, the coach drives up, and out of 
the coach gets them two children. The 
Guard says to our Governor, "I don't quite 
make out these little passengers, but the 
young gentleman's words was, that they was 
to be brought here." The young gentleman 
gets out; hands his lady out; gives the 
Guard something for himself; says to our 
Governor, "We're to stop here to-night, 
please. Sitting-room and two bed-rooms will 
be required. Chops and cherry-pudding for 
two!" and tucks her, in her little sky-blue 
mantle, under his arm, and walks into the 
house much bolder than Brass. 
</p>
<p>
Boots leaves me to judge what the 
amazement of that establishment was, when 
those two tiny creatures all alone by 
themselves was marched into the Angel;--much 
more so, when he, who had seen them without 
their seeing him, give the Governor his 
views of the expedition they was upon. 
"Cobbs," says the Governor, "if this is so, I 
must set off myself to York and quiet their 
friends' minds. In which case you must 
keep your eye upon 'em, and humour 'em, 
till I come back. But, before I take these 
measures, Cobbs, I should wish you to 
find from themselves whether your opinions 
is correct." "Sir to you," says Cobbs, 
"that shall be done directly." 
</p>
<p>
So, Boots goes upstairs to the Angel, and 
there he finds Master Harry on a e-normous 
sofa--immense at any time, but looking like 
the Great Bed of Ware, compared with him--
a drying the eyes of Miss Norah with 
his pocket hankecher. Their little legs was 
entirely off the ground, of course, and it 
really is not possible for Boots to express 
to me how small them children looked. 
</p>
<p>
"It's Cobbs! It's Cobbs!" cries Master 
Harry, and comes running to him and catching 
hold of his hand. Miss Norah comes 
running to him on t'other side and catching 
hold of his t'other hand, and they both jump 
for joy. 
</p>
<p>
"I see you a getting out, sir," says Cobbs. 
"I thought it was you. I thought I couldn't 
be mistaken in your height and figure. 
What's the object of your journey, sir?--
Matrimonial? 
</p>
<p>
"We are going to be married, Cobbs, at 
Gretna Green," returned the boy. "We 
have run away on purpose. Norah has been 
in rather low spirits, Cobbs; but she'll be 
happy, now we have found you to be our 
friend." 
</p>
<p>
"Thank you, sir, and thank you, miss," 
says Cobbs, "for your good opinion. Did 
you bring any luggage with you, sir?" 
</p>
<p>
If I will believe Boots when he gives me 
his word and honour upon it, the lady had 
got a parasol, a smelling-bottle, a round and a 
half of cold buttered toast, eight peppermint 
drops, and a hair-brush--seemingly, a doll's. 
The gentleman had got about half-a-dozen 
yards of string, a knife, three or four sheets 
of writing-paper folded up surprising small, 
a orange, and a Chaney mug with his name 
upon it. 
</p>
<p>
"What may be the exact natur of your 
plans, sir?" says Cobbs. 
</p>
<p>
"To go on," replied the boy--which the 
courage of that boy was something wonderful!--
"in the morning, and be married 
to-morrow." 
</p>
<p>
"Just so, sir," says Cobbs. "Would it 
meet your views, sir, if I was to accompany 
you?" 
</p>
<p>
When Cobbs said this, they both jumped 
for joy again, and cried out, "O yes, yes, 
Cobbs! Yes!" 
</p>
<p>
"Well, sir," say a Cobbs. "If you will 
excuse my having the freedom to give an 
opinion, what I should recommend would be 
this. I'm acquainted with a pony, sir, which, 
put in a pheayton that I could borrow, 
would take you and Mrs. Harry 
Walmers Junior (myself driving, if you approved), 
to the end of your journey in a very short 
space of time. I am not altogether sure, sir, 
that this pony will be at liberty to-morrow, 
but even if you had to wait over to-morrow 
for him, it might be worth your while. As 
to the small account here, sir, in case you 
was to find yourself running at all short, 
that don't signify; because I'm a part 
proprietor of this inn, and it could stand over." 
</p>
<p>
Boots assures me that when they clapped 
their hands, and jumped for joy again, and 
called him "Good Cobbs!" and "Dear 
Cobbs!" and bent across him to kiss one 
another in the delight of their confiding 
hearts, he felt himself the meanest rascal for 
deceiving 'em, that ever was born. 
</p>
<p>
"Is there anything you want just at 
present, sir?" says Cobbs, mortally ashamed 
of himself. 
</p>
<p>
"We should like some cakes after dinner," 
answered Master Harry, folding his arms, 
putting out one leg, and looking straight at 
him, "and two apples--and jam. With dinner 
we should like to have toast-and-water. But, 
Norah has always been accustomed to haIf a, 
glass of currant wine at dessert. And so 
have I." 
</p>
<p>
"It shall be ordered at the bar, sir," says 
Cobbs; and away he went. 
</p>
<p>
Boots has the feeling as fresh upon him at 
this minute of speaking, as he had then, that 
he would far rather have had it out in half-a-dozen 
rounds with the Governor, than have 
combined with him; and that he wished with 
all his heart there was any impossible place 
where those two babies could make an 
impossible marriage, and live impossibly happy 
ever afterwards. However, as it couldn't be, 
he went into the Governor's plans, and the 
Governor set off for York in half-an-hour. 
</p>
<p>
The way in which the women of that house--
without exception--every one of 'em--
married and single--took to that boy when 
they heard the story, Boots considers 
surprising. It was as much as he could do 
to keep 'em from dashing into the room and 
kissing him. They climbed up all sorts of 
places, at the risk of their lives, to look at him 
through a pane of glass. They was seven 
deep at the key-hole. They was out of their 
minds about him and his bold spirit. 
</p>
<p>
In the evening, Boots went into the room, 
to see how the runaway couple was getting 
on. The gentleman was on the window-seat, 
supporting the lady in his arms. She had 
tears upon her face, and was lying, very tired 
and half asleep, with her head upon his 
shoulder, 
</p>
<p>
"Mrs. Harry Walmers Junior, fatigued, 
sir?" says Cobbs. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, she is tired, Cobbs; but, she is not 
used to be away from home, and she has been 
in low spirits again. Cobbs, do you think 
you could bring a biffin, please?" 
</p>
<p>
"I ask your pardon, sir," says Cobbs. 
"What was it you?--" 
</p>
<p>
"I think a Norfolk biffin would rouse her, 
Cobbs. She is very fond of them." 
</p>
<p>
Boots withdrew in search of the required 
restorative, and, when he brought it in, the 
gentleman handed it to the lady, and fed her 
with a spoon, and took a little himself. The 
lady being heavy with sleep, and rather cross, 
"What should you think, sir," says Cobbs, 
"of a chamber candlestick?" The gentleman 
approved; the chambermaid went first, up 
the great staircase; the lady, in her sky-blue 
mantle, followed, gallantly escorted by the 
gentleman; the gentleman embraced her at 
her door, and retired to his own apartment, 
where Boots softly locked him up. 
</p>
<p>
Boots couldn't but feel with increased 
acuteness what a base deceiver he was, when 
they consulted him at breakfast (they had 
ordered sweet milk-and-water, and toast and 
currant jelly, overnight), about the pony. It 
really was as much as he could do, he don't 
mind confessing to me, to look them two 
young things in the face, and think what 
a wicked old father of lies he had grown 
up to be. Howsomever, he went on 
lying like a Trojan, about the pony. He told 
'em that it did so unfort'nately happen that 
the pony was half clipped, you see, and that 
he couldn't be taken out in that state, for fear 
it should strike to his inside. But, that he'd 
be finished clipping in the course of the day, 
and that to morrow morning at eight o'clock 
the pheayton would be ready. Boots's view 
of the whole case, looking back upon it in 
my room, is, that Mrs. Harry Walmers 
Junior was beginning to give in. She hadn't 
had her hair curled when she went to bed, 
and she didn't seem quite up to brushing it 
herself, and it's getting in her eyes put her 
out. But, nothing put out Master Harry. 
He sat behind his breakfast-cup, a tearing 
away at the jelly, as if he had been his own 
father. 
</p>
<p>
After breakfast, Boots is inclined to 
consider that they drawed soldiers--at least, he 
knows that many such was found in the fire-place, 
all on horseback. In the course of the 
morning, Master Harry rang the bell--it was 
surprising how that there boy did carry 
on--and said in a sprightly way, "Cobbs, is 
there any good walks in this neighbourhood?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, sir," says Cobbs. "There's Love 
Lane." 
</p>
<p>
"Get out with you, Cobbs! "--that was 
that there boy's expression--" you're joking." 
</p>
<p>
"Begging your pardon, sir," says Cobbs, 
"there really is Love Lane. And a pleasant 
walk it is, and proud shall I be to show it to 
yourself and Mrs. Harry Walmers Junior." 
</p>
<p>
"Norah, dear," said Master Harry, "this 
is curious. We really ought to see Love 
Lane. Put on your bonnet, my sweetest 
darling, and we will go there with Cobbs." 
</p>
<p>
Boots leaves me to judge what a Beast he 
felt himself to be, when that young pair told 
him, they all three jogged along together, 
that they had made up their minds to give 
him two thousand guineas a year as head 
gardener, on accounts of his being so true a 
friend to 'em. Boots could have wished at 
the moment that the earth would have opened 
and swallerd him up; he felt so mean, with 
their beaming eyes a-looking at him, and 
believing him. Well, sir, he turned the 
conversation as well as he could, and he took 
'em down Love Lane to the water-meadows, 
and there Master Harry would have drownded 
himself in half a moment more, a-getting out 
a water-lily for her--but nothing daunted 
that boy. Well, sir, they was tired out. All 
being so new and strange to 'em, they was 
tired as tired could be. And they laid down on 
a bank of daisies, like the children in the 
wood, leastways meadows, and fell asleep. 
</p>
<p>
Boots don't know--perhaps I do--but 
never mind, it don't signify either way--why 
it made a man fit to make a fool of himself, 
to see them two pretty babies a lying there 
in the clear still sunny day, not dreaming 
half so hard when they was asleep, as they 
done when they was awake. But, Lord! when 
you come to think of yourself, you know, and 
what a game you have been up to ever since 
you was in your own cradle, and what a poor 
sort of a chap you are, and how it's always 
either Yesterday with you, or else To-morrow, 
and never To-day, that's where it is! 
Well, sir, they woke up at last, and then 
one thing was getting pretty clear to Boots: 
namely, that Mrs. Harry Walmerses Junior's 
temper was on the move. When Master 
Harry took her round the waist, she said he 
"teased her so;" and when he says, "Norah, 
my young May Moon, your Harry tease you?" 
she tells him, "Yes; and I want to go home!" 
</p>
<p>
A biled fowl, and baked bread-and-butter 
pudding, brought Mrs. Walmers up a little; 
but Boots could have wished, he must 
privately own to me, to have seen her more 
sensible of the woice of love, and less 
abandoning of herself to currants. However, 
Master Harry he kept up, and his noble 
heart was as fond as ever. Mrs. Walmers 
turned very sleepy about dusk, and began to 
cry. Therefore, Mrs. Walmers went off to 
bed as per yesterday; and Master Harry 
ditto repeated. 
</p>
<p>
About eleven or twelve at night, comes 
back the Governor in a chaise, along with Mr 
Walmers and a elderly lady. Mr. Walmers 
looks amused and very serious, both at once, 
and says to our missis, "We are much 
indebted to you, ma'am, for your kind care of 
our little children, which we can never 
sufficiently acknowledge. Pray ma'am, where is 
my boy?" Our missis says, "Cobbs has 
the dear child in charge, sir. Cobbs, show 
Forty!" Then, he says to Cobbs, "Ah Cobbs! 
I am glad to see you. I understood you 
was here!" And Cobbs says, "Yes, sir 
Your most obedient, sir." 
</p>
<p>
I may be surprised to hear Boots say it 
perhaps; but, Boots assures me that his heart 
beat like a hammer, going up stairs. "I beg 
your pardon, sir," says he, while unlocking 
the door; "I hope you are not angry with 
Master Harry. For, Master Harry is a fine 
boy, sir, and will do you credit and honour." 
And Boots signifies to me, that if the fine 
boy's father had contradicted him in the 
daring state of mind in which he then was, 
he thinks he should have "fetched him a 
crack," and taken the consequences. 
</p>
<p>
But, Mr. Walmers only says, "No, Cobbs. 
No, my good fellow. Thank you!" And, 
the door being opened, goes in. 
</p>
<p>
Boots goes in too, holding the light, and 
he sees Mr. Walmers go up to the bedside, 
bend gently down, and kiss the little sleeping 
face. Then, he stands looking at it for 
a minute, looking wonderfully like it (they 
do say he ran away with Mrs. Walmers); 
and then he gently shakes the little 
shoulder. 
</p>
<p>
"Harry, my dear boy! Harry!" 
</p>
<p>
Master Harry starts up and looks at him. 
Looks at Cobbs too. Such is the honour of 
that mite, that he looks at Cobbs, to see 
whether he has brought him into trouble. 
</p>
<p>
"I am not angry, my child. I only want 
you to dress yourself and come home." 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, Pa." 
</p>
<p>
Master Harry dresses himself quickly. 
His breast begins to swell when he has 
nearly finished, and it swells more and more 
as he stands at last, a-looking at his father; 
his father standing a-looking at him, the 
quiet image of him. 
</p>
<p>
"Please may I"--the spirit of that litlle 
creatur, and the way he kept his rising 
tears down! "--Please dear Pa--may I--kiss 
Norah, before I go?" 
</p>
<p>
"You may, my child." 
</p>
<p>
So, he takes Master Harry in his hand, and 
Boots leads the way with the candle, and 
they come to that other bedroom: where the 
elderly lady is seated by the bed, and poor 
little Mrs. Harry Walmers Junior is fast 
asleep. There, the father lifts the child up 
to the pillow, and he lays his little face down 
for an instant by the little warm face of 
poor unconscious little Mrs. Harry Walmers 
Junior, and gently draws it to him--a sight 
so touching to the chambermaids who are 
peeping through the door, that one of them 
calls out "It's a shame to part 'em!" But 
this chambermaid was always, as Boots 
informs me, a soft-hearted one. Not that 
there was any harm in that girl. Far from it. 
</p>
<p>
Finally, Boots says, that's all about it. 
Mr. Walmers drove away in the chaise, 
having hold of Master Harry's hand. The 
elderly lady and Mrs. Harry Walmers 
Junior that was never to be, (she married 
a Captain, long afterwards, and died in 
India), went off next day. In conclusion, 
Boots puts it to me whether I hold with him 
in two opinions; firstly, that there are not 
many couples on their way to be married, 
who are half as innocent of guile as those 
two children; secondly, that it would be a jolly 
good thing for a great many couples on their 
way to be married, if they could only be 
stopped in time and brought back separately. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE LANDLORD.</title>
<p>
URIAH TATTENHALL is my elder brother 
by fifteen years. I am Sam Tattenhall. 
</p>
<p>
My brother Uriah rang at his gate at his 
snug retreat of Trumpington Cottage, Peckham, 
near London, exactly at a quarter to six--
his regular hour--when the omnibus from the 
city set him down at the end of the lane. 
It was December, but the weather was fine 
and frosty, and as it was within a few days 
of Christmas, his children--four in number--
two boys, just come home from school, and 
two girls who came home from school every 
day--were all on the alert to receive him, 
with a world of schemes for the delectation 
of the coming holiday-time. 
</p>
<p>
My brother Uriah was an especial family-man. 
He made himself the companion 
and play-fellow of his children on all 
occasions that his devotion to his business 
in the city would admit of. His 
hearty, cheery voice was heard as he entered 
the hall, and while he was busy pulling-off 
is over-coat, and hanging up his hat: 
"Well, my boys, well George, well Miss 
Lucy, there. What are you all about? 
</p>
<p>
How's the world used you since this morning? 
Where's mamma? The kettle boiling, eh?" 
The running fire of hilarity that always 
ANImated him seemed to throw sunshine and a 
new life into the house, when he came in. 
The children this evening rushed out into the 
hall, and crowded round him with such a 
number of "I say, pa's," and "Do you know, 
pa?" and "Don't tell him now, Mary,--let 
him guess. Oh! you'll never guess, pa!" 
that he could only hurry them all into the 
sitting-room before him like a little flock of 
sheep, saying, "Well, well, you rogues,--well, 
well,--let us have some tea, and then all 
about it." 
</p>
<p>
The fire blazed bonnily, as it was wont, in 
the bright grate, and that and the candles 
made the room, with light and warmth, the 
very paradise of comfort. Mrs. Tattenhall, 
a handsome woman of five and thirty or so--
she might be more, but she did not look it--
was just in the act of pouring the water from 
a very bright little kettle into the equally 
bright silver tea-pot, and with a sunny, rosy, 
youthful, and yet matronly face, turned 
smilingly at his entrance, and said, "Well, 
my dear, is it not a very cold night?" 
</p>
<p>
"Not in this room, certainly, my dear," 
said my brother Uriah, "and with such 
a snuggery before one, who cares for cold 
outside." 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Tattenhall gave him a brighter smile 
still, and the neat Harriet coming in with 
the toast, the whole family group was speedily 
seated round the tea-table, and the whole 
flood of anticipated pleasures and plans of 
the younger population let loose, and 
cordially entered into, and widened and 
IMproved by my brother Uriah. He promised 
them an early night at the very best 
pantomime, and they were to read all about all the 
pantomimes in the newspapers, and find out 
which was the best. He meant to take 
them to see all sorts of sights, and right 
off-hand on Christmas Eve he was going 
to set up a Christmas-tree, and have 
Christkindchen, and all sorts of gifts under 
it for everybody. He had got it all ready 
done by a German who came often to his 
warehouse, and it was somewhere, not far off 
just now. 
</p>
<p>
"Thank you, papa,--thank you a thousand 
times. Oh! what heaps of fun!" exclaimed 
the children, altogether. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, really, my dear," said Mrs. Tattenhall, 
delighted as the children, "what has 
come to you? You quite out-do yourself, 
good as you always are. You are quite 
magnificent in your projects." 
</p>
<p>
"To be sure," said Uriah, taking hold of 
the hands of little Lucy, and dancing round 
the room with her. "To be sure; we may 
just as well be merry as sad; it will be all the 
same a hundred years hence." 
</p>
<p>
Presently the tea-table was cleared, and, as 
they drew round the fire, my brother Uriah 
pulled out a book, and said, "George, there's a 
nice book--begin, and read it aloud: it will 
be a very pleasant book for these winter evenings 
before all the dissipation begins. It is 
Pringle's Adventures in South Africa, and is 
almost as good as Robinson Crusoe. I knew 
Pringle well; a lame, little man, that you 
never would dream could sit on a horse, 
much less ride after lions and elephants in 
that style." 
</p>
<p>
"Lions and elephants!" all were silent, 
and George read on. He read till eight 
o'clock, their bed-time, and the whole group--
parents and children--were equally 
delighted with it. As they closed the book--
"Now," said the father, "would it not be 
grand fun to live out there, and ride after 
the lions and elephants?" 
</p>
<p>
"Ah! grand fun!" said the boys, but the 
mother and the girls shuddered at the lions. 
"Well, you could stay in the house, you know," 
said Bob. 
</p>
<p>
"Right, my fine fellow," said the father, 
clapping him on the shoulder. "So now 
off to bed, and dream all about it." 
</p>
<p>
When the children were gone, my brother 
Uriah stretched out his feet on the fender 
and fell into a silence. When my brother's 
silence had lasted some time his wife said, 
"Are you sleepy, my dear?" 
</p>
<p>
"No; never was more wakeful," said 
Uriah; "really, my dear, I never was less 
inclined to be sprightly: but it won't 
do to dash the spirits of the children. Let 
them enjoy the Christmas as much as they 
can, they will never be young but once." 
</p>
<p>
"What is amiss?" asked Mrs. Tattenhall, 
with a quick apprehensive look. "Is there 
something amiss? Good gracious! you 
frighten me." 
</p>
<p>
"Why no, there is nothing exactly amiss; 
there is nothing new; but the fact is, I have 
just taken stock, and to-day finished casting 
all up, and struck the balance." 
</p>
<p>
"And is it bad? Is it less than you 
expected?" askqd Mrs. Tattenhall, fixing her 
eyes seriously on her husband's face. 
</p>
<p>
"Bad? No, not bad, nor good. I'll tell 
you what it is. You've heard of a toad in a 
mud wall. Well, that's me. Twenty years 
ago, I went into business with exactly three 
thousand pounds, and here I have been 
trading, and fagging, and caring, and getting, 
and losing, business extending, and profits 
getting less and less, making large sales, and 
men breaking directly after, and so the 
upshot is,--twenty years trade, and the 
balance the same to a pound as that I began 
with. Three thousand I started with, and 
three thousand is precisely my capital at this 
moment." 
</p>
<p>
"Is that all?" said Mrs. Tattenhall, 
wonderfully relieved. "Be thankful, my dear 
Uriah, that you have three thousand pounds. 
You have your health wonderfully, we have 
all our health; we have children, as good 
and promising children as anybody is blest 
with, and a happy home, and live as well and 
Comfortably as any one need to do, or as I 
wish, I am sure. What do we want more?" 
</p>
<p>
"What do we want more?" said Uriah, 
drawing up his legs suddenly, and clapping 
his hands in a positive sort of a way on his 
knees. "Why, I for one, want a great deal 
more. We've children, you say, and a home, 
and all that. Heaven be thanked, so we have! 
but I want our children to have a home after 
us. Three thousand pounds divided amongst 
four, leaves about seven hundred and fifty 
each. Is it worth while to fag a whole life, 
and leave them that and a like prospect? 
No," continued Uriah, in a considering 
manner, and shaking his head. "No, I want 
something more; more for myself; more for 
them; more room, more scope, a wider horizon, 
and a more proportionate result of a 
whole human existence. And do you know 
Maria what I have come to as the best 
conclusion? To go out to Australia." 
</p>
<p>
"To go out to Australia!" said Mrs. 
Tattenhall, in astonishment. "My dear 
Uriah, you are joking. You mean no such 
thing." 
</p>
<p>
"But that is just what I do mean," said 
Uriah, taking his wife's hand affectionately; 
"I have thought of it long, and the toad-in-the-wall 
balance has determined me. And now 
what I ask of you is to look at it calmly and 
earnestly. You know the Smiths, the Browns, 
and the Robinsons have gone out. They 
report the climate delicious, and that wonders 
are doing. A new country, if it be a good 
country, is the place to grow and thrive in, 
without doubt. Look at the trees in a wood. 
They grow up and look very fine in the mass. 
The wood, you say, is a very fine wood; but 
when you have looked at the individual trees, 
they are crowded and spindled up. They 
cannot put out a single bough beyond a 
certain distance; if they attempt it, their 
presuming twigs are poked back again by 
sturdy neighbours all round, that are all 
struggling for light and space like them. 
Look then at the tree on the open plain,--
how it spreads and hangs in grand amplitude 
its unobstructed boughs and foliage: a 
lordly object. Just so, this London. It is a 
vast, a glorious, a most imposing London, 
but thousands of its individuals in it are 
pressed and circumscribed to a few square 
yards and no more. Give me the open plain,--
the new country, and then see if I do not 
put out a better head, and our children 
too." 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Tattenhall, now she felt that her 
husband was in earnest, sat motionless and 
confounded. The shock had come too 
suddenly upon her. Her husband, it is true, 
had often told her that things did not move 
as he wished; that they seemed fixed, and 
stereotyped, and stagnant; but then, when 
are merchants satisfied? She never had 
entertained an idea but that they should go on 
to the end of the chapter as they had been 
going on ever since she was married. She 
was bound up heart and soul with her own 
country; she had her many friends and 
relations, with whom she lived on the most 
cordial terms; all her tastes, feelings, and ideas 
were English and metropolitan. At the very 
idea of quitting England, and for so new, and 
so distant a country, she was seized with an 
indescribable consternation. 
</p>
<p>
" My dear Maria!" said her husband; 
"mind, I don't ask you to go at first. You 
and the children can remain here till I have 
been and seen what the place and prospects 
are like. My brother Sam will look after 
business--he will soon be at home in it--and if 
all is pleasant, why, you will come then, if 
not I won't ask you. I'll work out a good 
round sum myself if possible, or open up 
some connection that will mend matters here. 
What can I say more?" 
</p>
<p>
"Nothing, dear Uriah, nothing. But those 
poor children----" 
</p>
<p>
"Those poor children!" said Uriah. "Why 
my dear Maria, if you were to ask them 
whether they would like a voyage to 
Australia, to go and see those evergreen woods, 
and gallop about all amongst gay parrots, 
and great kangaroos, they would jump off 
their seats with joy. The spirits of the 
young are ever on the wing for adventure 
and new countries. It is the prompting of 
that Great Power which has constructed all 
this marvellous universe, and bade mankind 
multiply and replenish the earth. Don't 
trouble yourself about them. You saw how 
they devoured the adventures at the Cape, 
and you'll see how they will kindle up in a 
wonderful enthusiasm at the promise of a 
voyage to Australia. What are pantomimes 
to that?" 
</p>
<p>
"Poor things!" said Mrs. Tattenhall. 
"They know nothing about the reality; all is 
fairyland and poetry to them." 
</p>
<p>
"The reality! the reality, Maria, will be 
all fairyland and poetry to them." 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Tatteuhall shook her head, and 
retired that night--not to sleep, but with a 
very sad heart to ruminate over this 
unexpected revelation. My brother's words were 
realised at the first mention of the 
project to the children. After the first shock of 
surprise and doubt whether it were really 
meant, they became unboundedly delighted. 
The end of it was, that by the middle of February, 
my brother Uriah, having had a handsome 
offer for his business and stock, had wound 
up all his affairs; and Mrs. Tattenhall having 
concluded, like a good wife and mother, to go 
with the whole family, they bade farewell to 
England, Mrs. Tattenhall with many tears, 
Uriah serious and thoughtful, the children 
full of delight and wonder at everything in 
the ship. 
</p>
<p>
They had a fine voyage, though with very 
few passengers, for the captain said there was 
a temporary damp on the Australian 
colonies. The order of the Government at home 
to raise the upset price of land to one 
pound per acre, had checked emigration, and 
as there had been a good deal of speculation 
in Melbourne in town allotments, things just 
now looked gloomy. This was in eighteen 
hundred and forty-three. "But it can't last 
long," said the Captain, "that silly order of 
raising the price of the land is so palpably 
absurd; while America is selling land so 
much nearer at a quarter of the price, that it 
must be repealed; and then all will be right 
again." 
</p>
<p>
It was the middle of May when our party 
arrived in Hobson's Bay. It was very rainy, 
gloomy weather--the very opposite to all 
that the climate had been represented in the 
accounts sent home--but then it was the 
commencement of winter, the November of 
our season. Uriah got a boat, and sailed up 
the winding river to the town. The sail was 
through a flat tract of land densely 
overgrown with a mass of close, dark bushes, of 
some ten feet high, somewhat resembling our 
sloe-tree, the tea-tree of that country. On 
reaching the foot of the town, which stood 
on a range of low hills, Uriah and his 
companions stepped out into a most appalling 
slough of black mud, through which they 
waded till they reached the town, which was 
of no great extent, scattered over a 
considerable space, however, for the number of 
houses, and with great intervals of woodland, 
and of places where the trees had been felled, 
and where the stumps, a yard high, remained 
in unsightly nakedness. 
</p>
<p>
Uriah walked on through a scene which, 
somehow in keeping with the weather, fell 
heavily on his spirits. There was nothing 
doing, or stirring; houses in various degrees 
of progress stood as they were. There were 
piles of timber, lime, shingles, posts, and 
rails, empty wagons and carts, but no 
people employed about them. On every 
hand he saw lots marked out for fencing 
or building upon, but there they remained 
all stationary. 
</p>
<p>
"Is it Sunday?" Uriah asked himself. 
No, it was Tuesday. Then why all this 
stagnation; this solitude? In a lane, or 
rather deep track of mud and ruts, since 
known as Flinders' Lane, but then without a 
name, and only just wide enough between the 
trees for a cart to pass, Uriah wading and 
plunging along, the rain meantime pouring, 
streaming, and drumming down on his 
umbrella, he came face to face with a large 
active man in a mackintosh cloak, and an 
oilskin hood over his head. Neither of 
them found it very convenient to step out of 
the middle mud track, because on each side 
of it rose a perfect bank of sludge raised 
by the wheels of drays, and stopping to have 
a look at each other, the strange man 
suddenly put out a huge red hand warm and 
wet, and exclaimed: 
</p>
<p>
"What! Tattenhall! You here! In the 
name of all wonders what could bring you 
here at this moment?" 
</p>
<p>
"What, Robinson! is that you?" cried 
Uriah. "Is this your climate? This your 
paradise?" 
</p>
<p>
"Climate--paradise--be hanged!" said 
Robinson. "They're well enough. If everything 
else were as well there would be nought 
to complain of. But tell me Uriah Tattenhall, 
with that comfortable Trumpington 
Cottage at Peckham, with that well-to-do 
warehouse in the Old Jewry, what could 
possess you to come here?" 
</p>
<p>
"What should I come for, but to settle?" 
asked Uriah, somewhat chagrined at this 
salutation. 
</p>
<p>
"To settle! ha, ha!" burst out Robinson. 
"Well, as for that, you could not come to a 
better place. It is a regular settler here. 
Everything and everybody are settled here 
out and out. This is a settlement, and no 
mistake; but it is like a many other settle 
the figures are all on the wrong side 
the ledger." 
</p>
<p>
"Good gracious!" said Uriah. 
</p>
<p>
"Nay, it is neither good nor gracious," 
replied Robinson. "Look round. What do 
you see? Ruin, desertion, dirt and the--
devil!" 
</p>
<p>
"Why, how is that?" asked Uriah. "I 
thought you, and Jones, and Brown, and all 
of you had made your fortunes." 
</p>
<p>
"So we had, or were just on the point of 
doing. We had purchased lots of land for 
building, and had sold it out again at five 
hundred per cent, when chop! down comes 
little Lord John with his pound an acre, 
and, heigh, presto! everything goes topsy-turvy. 
Our purchasers are either in the 
bankruptcy court, or have vanished. By 
jingo! I could show you such lots, fine lots 
for houses and gardens, for shops and 
warehouses; ay, and shops and warehouses upon 
them too, as would astonish you." 
</p>
<p>
"Well, and what then?" asked Uriah. 
</p>
<p>
"What then! why man don't you comprehend. 
Emigration is stopped, broken off as 
short as a pipe-shank, not a soul is coming 
out to buy and live in all these houses--not a 
soul except an odd--excuse me, Tattenhall, 
I was going to say, except you and another 
fool or two. But where do you hang out? 
Look! there is my house," pointing to a 
wooden erection near. "I'll come and see 
you as soon as I know where you fix 
yourself." 
</p>
<p>
"But mind one thing," cried Uriah, seizing 
him by the arm as he passed. "For heaven's 
sake, don't talk in this manner to my wife. 
It would kill her." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh no, mum's the word! There's no use 
frightening the women," said Robinson. "No, 
confound it, I won't croak any how. And, after 
all, bad as things are, why, they can't remain 
so for ever. Nothing ever does, that's one 
comfort. They'll mend sometime." 
</p>
<p>
"When?" said Uriah. 
</p>
<p>
"Well," said Robinson, pausing a little, 
"not before you and I meet again, so I may 
leave that answer to another opportunity;" 
and with a nod and very knowing look he 
stalked on. 
</p>
<p>
"Odd fellow!" said my brother Uriah. "He 
is very jocose for a ruined man. What is one to 
think?" and he waded on. After making a 
considerable circuit, and actually losing himself 
in the wood somewhere about where the 
Reverend Mr. Morrison's chapel now stands 
in Collins' Street, he again came across 
Robinson who stood at the door of a 
considerable erection of wattle-and-dab, that is, a 
building of boughs wattled on stakes, and 
dabbed over with mud; then not uncommon 
in Melbourne, and still common enough in 
the bush. It stood on the hill-side with a 
swift muddy torrent produced by the rains 
rushing down the valley below it, towards 
the river, as it has often done since it bore 
the name of Swanston Street. 
</p>
<p>
"Here, Tattenhall! here is a pretty go!" 
shouted Robinson; "a fellow has cut with 
bag and baggage to-night who owes me four 
thousand pounds, and has left me a lot more 
houses and land. That's the way every day. 
But look, here is a house ready for you. You 
can't have a better, and you can pay me any 
trifle you like, something is better than 
nothing." . 
</p>
<p>
He led Uriah in. The house was thoroughly 
and comfortably furnished; though, of course, 
very simply, with beds and everything. Uriah 
in less than a week, was safely established 
there, and had time to ramble about with his 
boys, and learn more fully the condition of 
the colony. It was melancholy beyond 
description. Wild, reckless speculation brought 
to a sudden close by the cessation of 
immigration, had gone like a hurricane over the 
place, and had left nothing but ruin and 
paralysis behind it. No words that Robinson 
had used, or that any man could use, 
could overpaint the real condition of 
prostration and of misery. Two hundred and 
eighty insolvencies in a population of ten 
thousand, told the tale of awful reality. 
Uriah was overwhelmed with consternation 
at the step he had taken. O! how pleasant 
seemed that Trumpington Cottage, Peckham, 
and that comfortable warehouse in the Old 
Jewry, as he viewed them from the Antipodes 
in the midst of rain and ruin. 
</p>
<p>
What, however, was my brother Uriah's 
astonishment to see Robinson stalk in the 
next day, his tall figure having to stoop at 
every door, and in his brusque, noisy way, go 
up to Mrs. Tattenhall, and shaking her hand 
as you would shake the handle of a pump, 
congratulate her on her arrival in the colony. 
</p>
<p>
"A lucky hit, madam, a most lucky, scientific 
hit! Ah! trust Tattenhall for knowing 
what he is about." 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Tattenhall stood with a singular 
expression of wonder and bewilderment on her 
countenance, for the condition of the place, 
and the condolings of several female neighbours 
who had dropped in in Uriah's absence, 
had induced her to believe that they had 
made a fatal move of it. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, sir," said she, "what can you mean, 
for as I hear, the place is utterly ruined, 
and certainly it looks like it?" 
</p>
<p>
"Ruined! to be sure it is, at least the 
people are, more's the pity for me, and the 
like of me who have lost everything; but 
for Tattenhall who has everything to gain, 
and money to win it with, why it is the 
golden opportunity, the very thing! If he 
had watched at all the four corners of the 
world, and for a hundred years, he could 
not have dropped into such a chance. Ah! 
trust Tattenhall, make me believe he did not 
plan it." Thrusting his knuckles into Uriah's 
side, and laughing with a thunder-clap of 
a laugh that seemed to come from lungs of 
leather. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, look here now," he continued, 
drawing a chair and seating himself on its 
front edge; "look here now, if you had come 
six months ago, you could have bought 
nothing except out of the fire. Town 
allotments, land, houses, bread, meat, sugar, 
everything ten times the natural price: 
and, now! cheap, dog cheap! of no value 
at all, you might have them for asking 
for; nay, I could go into a dozen deserted 
shops, and take any quantity for nothing. 
And property! why three thousand pounds 
cash would almost buy all the place--all the 
colony." 
</p>
<p>
'What is the use," asked Mrs. Tattenhall, 
"of buying a ruined colony?" 
</p>
<p>
"A ruined colony!" said Robinson, edging 
himself still more forward in his chair, and 
seeming actually to sit upon nothing, his 
huge figure and large ruddy face appearing 
still larger. "The colony, madam, is not 
ruined; never was ruined, never can be 
ruined. The people are ruined, a good lot 
of them; but the colony is a good and a 
grand colony. God made the colony, and 
let me tell you, madam," looking very serious, 
"Providence is no speculator, up to-day, down 
to-morrow. What he does he does. Well, the 
people have ruined themselves; but it is 
out of their power to ruin the colony; no, 
nor the town. The town and the colony 
are sound as a bell, never were sounder, 
never had more stuff in them; never had 
so much. There is the land still, not a yard 
of it is gone; no great fellow has put that 
on his back and gone off with it. The land 
is there, and the houses, and the merchandise, 
and the flocks, and herds, and horses: 
and--what concerns you--" 
</p>
<p>
He sate and looked at Mrs. Tattenhall, 
who stood there intently listening, and Uriah 
stood just behind her listening too, and all 
the children with their mouths open, gazing 
on the strange man. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, what--what concerns us?" said 
Mrs. Tattenhall. 
</p>
<p>
"To get a huge, almighty heap of 
something for nothing," said the large man, 
stretching out his arms in a circular shape, 
as if he would enclose a whole globe, and 
in a low, slow, deep tone, calculated to sink 
deep into the imaginations of the listeners. 
</p>
<p>
"If we did but know when things would 
mend;" said my brother Uriah, for the first 
time venturing to put in a word. 
</p>
<p>
"When!" said Robinson starting up so 
suddenly that his head struck against a beam 
in the low one-storeyed house. "Confound 
these low places," said he, turning fiery red, 
and rubbing his crown, "there will be better 
anon. When? say ye? Hark ye! this 
colony is--how old? Eight years! and in 
eight years what a town! what wealth! what 
buildings! what a power of sheep and cattle! 
The place is knocked down, won't it get up 
again? Ay, and quickly! Here are a pair 
of sturdy legs," he said, turning to Bob, who 
flushed up in surprise; "but, Mrs. Tattenhall, 
you did not teach him to walk without 
a few tumbles, eh? But he got up again, and 
how he stands now! what a sturdy young 
rogue it is! And what made him get up 
again? Because he was young and strong, 
and the colony is young and strong, madam. 
Eight years old! What shall I give you for 
a three thousand pounds purchase made 
now, three years hence? Just think of 
that," said the tall man, "just turn that over 
a time or two," nodding solemnly to my 
brother, and then to my sister-in-law, and 
then cautiously glancing at the menacing 
beam, and with a low duck diving out of 
the house. 
</p>
<p>
"What a strange fellow!" said Uriah. 
</p>
<p>
"But how true!" said Mrs. Tattenhall. 
</p>
<p>
"How true! What true?" asked Uriah, 
astonished. 
</p>
<p>
"Why," said Mrs. Tattenhall, "what he 
says. It is truth, Uriah; we must buy as 
much as we can." 
</p>
<p>
"But," said Uriah, "only the other day he 
said the clean contrary. He said everybody 
was ruined." 
</p>
<p>
"And he says so still," added Mrs. Tattenhall, 
enthusiastically, "but not the colony. 
We must buy! We must buy, and wait. 
One day we shall reap a grand harvest." 
</p>
<p>
"Ah!" said Uriah; "so you let yourself, 
my dear Maria, be thus easily persuaded, 
because Robinson wants to sell, and thinks 
we have money?" 
</p>
<p>
"Is it not common sense, however? Is it 
not the plainest sense?" asked Mrs. Tattenhall. 
"Do you think this colony is never to 
recover?" 
</p>
<p>
"Never is a long while," said Uriah. "But 
still--" 
</p>
<p>
"Well, we will think it over, and see how 
the town lies; and where the chief points of 
it will be, probably, hereafter; and if this 
Mr. Robinson has any land in such places, I 
would buy of him, because he has given us 
the first idea of it." 
</p>
<p>
They thought and looked, and the end of it 
was, that very soon they had bought up land 
and houses, chiefly from Robinson, to the 
amount of two thousand pounds. Robinson 
fain would not have sold, but have mortgaged; 
and that fact was the most convincing proof 
that he was sincere in his expectations of a 
revival. Time went on. Things were more 
and more hopeless. Uriah, who had nothing 
else to do, set on and cultivated a garden. 
He had plenty of garden ground, and his 
boys helped him, and enjoyed it vastly. As 
the summer went on, and melons grew ripe, 
and there were plenty of green peas and 
vegetables, by the addition of meat, which 
was now only one penny a-pound, they could 
live almost for nothing; and Uriah thought 
they could wait and maintain themselves for 
years, if necessary. So, from time to time, 
one tale of urgent staring distress or another 
lured him on to take fresh bargains, till he saw 
himself almost penniless. Things still remained 
as dead as the very stones or the stumps 
around them. My brother Uriah began to feel 
very melancholy; and Mrs. Tattenhall, who 
had so strongly advised the wholesale 
purchase of property, looked very serious. Uriah 
often thought: "Ah! she would do it; but--
Bless her! I will never say so, for she 
did it for the best." But his boys and girls 
were growing apace, and made him think. 
"Bless me! In a few years they will be 
shooting up into men and women; and if 
this speculation should turn out all moonshine!--
if the place should never revive!" 
</p>
<p>
He sate one day on the stump of a tree on 
a high ground, looking over the bay. His 
mind was in the most gloomy, dejected 
condition. Everything looked dark and hopeless. 
No evidence of returning life around; 
no spring in the commercial world; and his 
good money gone; as he sate thus, his eyes 
fixed on the distance, his mind sunk in the 
lowering present, a man came up, and asked 
him to take his land off his hands: to take it, 
for Heaven's sake, and save his starving family. 
</p>
<p>
"Man!" said Uriah, with a face and a 
voice so savage that it made the suppliant 
start even in his misery, "I have no 
money! I want no land! I have too 
much land. You shall have it all for as 
much as will carry me back to England, and 
set me down a beggar there!" 
</p>
<p>
The man shook his head. "If I had a 
single crown I would not ask you; but my 
wife is down of the fever, and my children 
are dying of dysentery. What shall I do? 
and my lots are the very best in the place." 
</p>
<p>
"I tell you!" said my brother Uriah, with 
a fierce growl, and an angry flash of the eye, 
"I have no money, and how can I buy?" 
</p>
<p>
He glanced at the man in fury; but a face 
so full of patient suffering and of sickness--
sickness of the heart, of the soul, and, as it 
were, of famine, met his gaze, that he stopped 
short, felt a pang of remorse for his anger, 
and, pointing to a number of bullocks grazing 
in the valley below, he said, in a softened 
tone, "Look there! The other day a man 
told me such a tale of horror--a sick family, 
and a gaol staring him in the face, that I gave 
him my last money--my carefully hoarded 
money, and of what use are those cattle to 
me? None whatever: You may have them 
for your land, if you like. I have nothing 
else." 
</p>
<p>
"I will have them," said the man. "On a 
distant station I know where I could sell 
them, if I could only leave my family. But 
they have no flour, no tea, nothing but meat, 
meat, meat." 
</p>
<p>
"Leave them to me," said Uriah, feeling 
the warm blood and the spirit of humanity 
beginning to circulate in his bosom at the 
sense of what was really suffering around 
him. "Leave them to me. I will care for 
them. Your wife and children shall have a 
doctor. I will find you some provisions for 
your journey, and if ever your land is worth 
anything, you shall have it again. This 
state of things makes monsters of us. It 
turns our blood into gall, our hearts into 
stones. We must resist it or we are ruined, 
indeed!" 
</p>
<p>
"Nay," said the man, "I won't impose 
upon you. Take that piece of land in the 
valley there; it will one day be valuable." 
</p>
<p>
"That!" said Uriah, looking. "That! 
"Why, that is a swamp! I will take that--
I shall not hurt you there!" And he laughed 
outright, the first time for two years. 
</p>
<p>
Years went on, and my brother Uriah lived 
on, but as it were in the valley of the shadow 
of death. It was a melancholy and dispiriting 
time. The buoyancy of his soul was gone. 
That jovial, sunny, ebullient spirit with 
which he used to come home from the city, 
in England, had fled, as a thing that had 
never been. He maintained himself chiefly 
out of his garden. His children were springing 
up into long, lanky lads and lasses. He 
educated them himself, as well as he could; 
and as for clothes! Not a navvy--not a beggar--
in the streets of London, but could 
have stood a comparison with them, to their 
infinite disparagement. Ah! those good three 
thousand pounds! How will the balance 
stand in my brother Uriah's books at the end 
of the next twenty years? 
</p>
<p>
But anon there awoke a slight motion in 
the atmosphere of life. It was a mere flutter 
of the air, that died out again. Then again 
it revived--it strengthened it--blew like a 
breath of life over the whole landscape. 
Uriah looked around him from the very place 
where he had sat on the stump in despair. 
It was bright and sunny. He heard a sound 
of an axe and a hammer. He looked, and 
saw a house, that had stood a mere skeleton, 
once more in progress. There were people 
passing to and fro with a more active air. 
What is that? A cart of goods? A dray of 
building materials. There was life and 
motion again! The discovery of converting 
sheep and oxen into tallow had raised the 
value of stock. The shops and the merchants 
were once more in action. The man to whom 
he had sold the oxen came up smiling--
</p>
<p>
"Things mend, sir. We shall soon be all 
right. And that piece of land in the swamp, 
that you were so merry over, will you sell it? 
It lies near the wharves, and is wanted for 
warehouses." 
</p>
<p>
"Bravo!" cried Uriah, and they descended 
the hill together. Part of the land was sold; 
and soon substantial warehouses, of the native 
trapstone, were rising upon it. Uriah's old 
attachment to a merchant's life came over him. 
With the purchase-money he built a 
warehouse too. Labour was extremely low, and 
he built a large and commodious one. 
</p>
<p>
Another year or two, and behold Uriah 
busy in his warehouse; his two boys clerking 
it gravely in the counting-house. Things 
grew rapidly better. Uriah and his family 
were once more handsomely clad, handsomely 
housed, and Uriah's jolly humour was again 
in the ascendant. Every now and then 
Robinson came hurrying in, a very busy man 
indeed he was now, in the town council, and 
moreover, mayor; and saying, "Well, Mrs. 
Tattenhall, didn't I say it, eh? Is not this 
boy of a colony on a fine sturdy pair of legs 
again? Not down? Not dead? Well, well, 
Tattenhall did me a kindness, then--by ready 
cash for my land--I don't forget it; but I 
don't know how I am to make him amends, 
unless I come and dine with him some day." 
And he was off again. 
</p>
<p>
Another year or two, and that wonderful 
crisis, the gold discovery, came. Then, what 
a sensation--what a stir--what a revolution! 
what running, and buying and bidding for 
land, for prime business situations!--what 
rolling in of people--capital--goods. Heaven 
and earth!--what a scene--what a place--
what a people. 
</p>
<p>
Ten years to a day from the last balance at 
the Old Jewry, Uriah Tattenhall balanced 
again, and his three thousand pounds was 
grown to seventy thousand pounds, and was 
still rolling up and on like a snow-ball. 
</p>
<p>
There were George and Bob grown into 
really tall and handsome fellows. George 
was the able merchant, Bob had got a 
station out at the Dundenong-hills, and 
told wonderful stories of riding after 
kangaroos, and wild bulls, and shooting splendid 
lyre-birds--all of which came of reading 
Pringle's Life in South Africa. There were 
Mary and Lucy, two handsome girls as any 
in the colony, and wonderfully attractive 
to a young Benson and a younger Robinson. 
Wonders were the next year to bring 
forth, and amongst them was to be a grand 
pic-nic at Bob's station, at the Dundenong, in 
which they were to live out in real tents in 
the forest, and cook, and bake, and brew, and 
the ladies were to join in a bull-hunt, and 
shoot with revolvers, and nobody was to 
be hurt, or thrown, or anything to happen, 
but all sorts of merriment and wild-wood 
life. 
</p>
<p>
And really my brother's villa on the 
Yarra River is a very fine place. The house 
is an Italian villa built of real stone, ample, 
with large, airy rooms, a broad verandah, 
and all in the purest taste. It stands on a high 
bank above the valley, in which the Yarra 
winds, taking a sweep there, its course marked 
by a dense body of acacia trees. In the spring 
these trees are of resplendent gold, loading 
the air with their perfume. Now they were 
thick and dark in their foliage, casting their 
shade on the river deep between its banks. 
From the house the view presented this deep 
valley with this curving track of trees, and 
beyond slopes divided into little farms, with 
their little homesteads upon them, where 
Uriah had a number of tenants making their 
fortunes on some thirty or forty acres each, 
by hay at forty pounds a ton, and potatoes 
and onions at one shilling a pound, and all 
other produce in proportion. 
</p>
<p>
On this side of the river you saw extensive 
gardens in the hollow blooming with 
roses and many tropical flowers, and along 
the hill sides on either hand vineyards 
and fruit orchards of the most vigorous 
vegetation, and loaded with young fruit. 
The party assembled at my brother Uriah's 
house on that hospitable Christmas day, 
descended amid a native shrubbery, and 
Uriah thrust a walking-stick to its very 
handle into the rich black soil, and when his 
friends expressed their surprise, he told them 
that the soil there was fourteen feet deep, and 
would grow any quantity of produce for ages 
without manuring. Indeed, they passed 
through green corn of the most luxuriant 
character, and, crossing the bridge of a brook 
which there fell into the river, they found 
themselves under the acacias; by the river 
side there lay huge prostrate trunks of ancient 
gum-trees, the patriarchs of the forest, which 
had fallen and given place to the acacia, and 
now reminded the spectators that they were 
still in the land of primitive woods. 
</p>
<p>
"Why, Tattenhall," said Robinson, to my 
brother Uriah, "Trumpington Cottage, my 
dear fellow, would cut a poor figure after 
this. I'd ask any lord or gentleman to 
show me a fertiler or more desirable place 
in the tight little island. Bigger houses 
there may be, and are, but not to my mind 
more desirable. Do you know, very large 
houses always seem to me a sort of asylums 
for supernumerary servants--the master 
can only occupy a corner--there he cuts 
out quite small in the bulk. And as to 
fertility, this beats Battersea Fields and 
Fulham hollow. Those market-gardeners might 
plant and plant to all eternity, always taking 
out and never putting in, and if they could 
grow peaches, apricots, grapes, figs twice a 
year, and all that as tine in the open air as 
they do in hot-houses, and sell their bunches 
of parsley at sixpence a-piece, and water-melons--
gathered from any gravel heap or 
dry open field--at five shillings a-piece, 
plentiful as pumpkins, wouldn't they astonish 
themselves! 
</p>
<p>
"But what makes you call this place 
Bowstead?" continued Robinson, breaking off a 
small wattle-bough to whisk the flies from 
his face. "Orr has named his Abbotsford--
that's because he's a Scotchman; and we've 
got Cremorne Gardens, and Richmond, and 
Hawthorne, and all sorts of English names 
about here;--but Bowstead! I can't make 
it out." 
</p>
<p>
"You can't?" said Uriah, smiling; "don't 
you see that the river curves in a bow here, 
and stead is a place?" 
</p>
<p>
"O! that's it," said Robinson; "I fancied 
it was to remind you of Bow Bells." 
</p>
<p>
"There you have it," said Bob, laughing. 
"Bow Bells! but, as there was a bow and no 
bells, my father put a stead to it, that's 
instead of the bells, you know." 
</p>
<p>
"Bless me!" said Robinson: "now I should 
never have thought of that--how very 
clever!" 
</p>
<p>
And he took the joke in such perfect 
simplicity, that all burst into a simultaneous 
laugh; for every one else knew that it was 
so called in honour of Maria Bowstead, now 
the univerally respected Mrs. Tattenhall. 
</p>
<p>
The whole party were very merry, for they 
had good cause to be. Mr. and Mrs. Tattenhall, 
still in their prime, spread out, enlarged 
every way, in body and estate, rosy, 
handsomely dressed, saw around them nothing but 
prosperity. A paradise of their own, in which 
they saw their children already developed 
into that manly and feminine beauty so 
conspicuous in our kindred of the south; their 
children already taking root in the land and 
twining their branches amongst those of other 
opulent families, they felt the full truth of 
Robinson's rude salutation, as he exclaimed, 
on coming to a fresh and more striking view 
of the house and grounds,--
</p>
<p>
"Ah! Tattenhall, Tattenhall!" giving him 
one of his jocose pokes in the side, "didn't 
I say you knew very well what you were 
about when you came here, eh? Mrs. 
Tattenhall, ma'am? Who said it? Robinson, 
wasn't it, eh?" 
</p>
<p>
When they returned to the house, and had 
taken tea in a large tent on the lawn, and the 
young people had played a lively game of 
romps or bo-peep amongst the bushes of the 
shrubbery, with much laughter, the great 
drawing-room was lighted up, and very soon 
there was heard the sounds of violins and 
dancing feet. My brother Uriah and his 
wife were at that moment sitting under the 
verandah, enjoying the fresh evening air, the 
scent of tropical trees and flowers which 
stole silently through the twilight, and the 
clear, deep blue of the sky, where the 
magnificent constellations of Orion and the 
Scorpion were growing momentarily into their 
full nocturnal splendour. As the music broke 
out my brother Uriah affectionately pressed 
the hand of his wife, faithful and wise 
and encouraging through the times of their 
difficulty and depression, and saying "Thank 
God for all this!" the pressure was as 
affectionately and gratefully returned. Then 
my brother and his wife rose up, and passed 
into the blaze of light which surrounded the 
gay and youthful company within. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BARMAID.</title>
<p>
SUE was a pretty, gentle girl--a farmer's 
orphan daughter, and the landlord's niece--
whom I strongly suspected of being engaged 
to be married very shortly, to the writer of 
the letter that I saw her reading at least 
twenty times, when I passed the bar, and 
which I more than believe I saw her kiss one 
night. She told me a tale of that country 
which went so pleasantly to the music of her 
voice, that I ought rather to say it turned 
itself into verse, than was turned into verse 
by me. 
</p>
<poem>
<poem1>A little past the village</poem1>
<poem2>The inn stood, low and white,</poem2>
<poem1>Green shady trees behind it,</poem1>
<poem2>And an orchard on the right,</poem2>
<poem1>Where over the green paling</poem1>
<poem2>The red-cheeked apples hung,</poem2>
<poem1>As if to watch how wearily</poem1>
<poem2>The sign-board creaked and swung.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The heavy-laden branches</poem1>
<poem2>Over the road hung low,</poem2>
<poem1>Reflecting fruit or blossom</poem1>
<poem2>In the wayside well below;</poem2>
<poem1>Where children, drawing water,</poem1>
<poem2>Looked up and paused to see,</poem2>
<poem1>Amid the apple branches,</poem1>
<poem2>A purple Judas Tree.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The road stretch'd winding onward</poem1>
<poem2>For many a weary mile</poem2>
<poem1>So dusty footsore wanderers</poem1>
<poem2>Would pause and rest awhile;</poem2>
<poem1>And panting horses halted,</poem1>
<poem2>And travellers loved to tell</poem2>
<poem1>The quiet of the wayside inn,</poem1>
<poem2>The orchard, and the well.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Here Maurice dwelt; and often</poem1>
<poem2>The sunburnt boy would stand</poem2>
<poem1>Gazing upon the distance,</poem1>
<poem2>And shading with his hand</poem2>
<poem1>His eyes, while watching vainly</poem1>
<poem2>For travellers, who might need</poem2>
<poem1>His aid to loose the bridle,</poem1>
<poem2>And tend the weary steed.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And once (the boy remember'd</poem1>
<poem2>That morning many a day--</poem2>
<poem1>The dew lay on the hawthorn,</poem1>
<poem2>The bird sang on the spray)</poem2>
<poem1>A train of horsemen, nobler</poem1>
<poem2>Than he had seen before,</poem2>
<poem1>Up from the distance gallopp'd,</poem1>
<poem2>And paused before the door.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Upon a milk-white pony,</poem1>
<poem2>Fit for a faery queen,</poem2>
<poem1>Was the loveliest little damsel</poem1>
<poem2>His eyes had ever seen;</poem2>
<poem1>A servant-man was holding</poem1>
<poem2>The leading rein, to guide</poem2>
<poem1>The pony and its mistress</poem1>
<poem2>Who cantered by his side.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Her sunny ringlets round her</poem1>
<poem2>A golden cloud had made,</poem2>
<poem1>While her large hat was keeping</poem1>
<poem2>Her calm blue eyes in shade;</poem2>
<poem1>One hand held firm the silken reins</poem1>
<poem2>To keep her steed in check,</poem2>
<poem1>The other pulled his tangled mane,</poem1>
<poem2>Or stroked his glossy neck.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And as the boy brought water,</poem1>
<poem2>And loosed the rein, he heard</poem2>
<poem1>The sweetest voice, that thank'd him</poem1>
<poem2>In one low gentle word;</poem2>
<poem1>She turned her blue eyes from him,</poem1>
<poem2>Look'd up, and smiled to see</poem2>
<poem1>The hanging purple blossoms</poem1>
<poem2>Upon the Judas Tree.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And show'd it with a gesture,</poem1>
<poem2>Half pleading, half command,</poem2>
<poem1>Till he broke the fairest blossom,</poem1>
<poem2>And laid it in her hand;</poem2>
<poem1>And she tied it to her saddle</poem1>
<poem2>With a ribbon from her hair,</poem2>
<poem1>While her happy laugh rang gaily,</poem1>
<poem2>Like silver on the air.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>But the champing steeds were rested--</poem1>
<poem2>The horsemen now spurr'd on,</poem2>
<poem1>And down the dusty highway</poem1>
<poem2>They vanish'd and were gone.</poem2>
<poem1>Years pass'd, and many a traveller</poem1>
<poem2>Paused at the old inn-door,</poem2>
<poem1>But the little milk-white pony</poem1>
<poem2>And the child return'd no more.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Years pass'd, the apple branches</poem1>
<poem2>A deeper shadow shed;</poem2>
<poem1>And many a time the Judas Tree,</poem1>
<poem2>Blossom and leaf lay dead;</poem2>
<poem1>When on the loitering western breeze</poem1>
<poem2>Came the bells' merry sound,</poem2>
<poem1>And flowery arches rose, and flags</poem1>
<poem2>And banners waved around.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And Maurice stood expectant,</poem1>
<poem2>The bridal train would stay</poem2>
<poem1>Some moments at the inn-door,</poem1>
<poem2>The eager watchers say;</poem2>
<poem1>They--come the cloud of dust draws near--</poem1>
<poem2>'Mid all the state and pride,</poem2>
<poem1>He only sees the golden hair</poem1>
<poem2>And blue eyes of the bride.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The same, yet, ah! still fairer,</poem1>
<poem2>He knew the face once more</poem2>
<poem1>That bent above the pony's neck</poem1>
<poem2>Years past at the inn-door:</poem2>
<poem1>Her shy and smiling eyes look'd round,</poem1>
<poem2>Unconscious of the place--</poem2>
<poem1>Unconscious of the eager gaze</poem1>
<poem2>He fix'd upon her face.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>He pluck'd a blossom from the tree--</poem1>
<poem2>The Judas Tree--and cast</poem2>
<poem1>Its purple fragrance towards the bride,</poem1>
<poem2>A message from the Past.</poem2>
<poem1>The signal came, the horses plunged--</poem1>
<poem2>Once more she smiled around:</poem2>
<poem1>The purple blossom in the dust</poem1>
<poem2>Lay trampled on the ground.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Again the slow years fleeted,</poem1>
<poem2>Their passage only known</poem2>
<poem1>By the height the Passion-flower</poem1>
<poem2>Around the porch had grown;</poem2>
<poem1>And many a passing traveller</poem1>
<poem2>Paused at the old inn-door,</poem2>
<poem1>But the bride, so fair and blooming</poem1>
<poem2>Return'd there never more.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>One winter morning, Maurice,</poem1>
<poem2>Watching the branches bare,</poem2>
<poem1>Rustling and waving dimly</poem1>
<poem2>In the grey and misty air,</poem2>
<poem1>Saw blazon'd on a carriage</poem1>
<poem2>Once more the well-known shield,</poem2>
<poem1>The azure fleurs-de-lis and stars</poem1>
<poem2>Upon a silver field.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>He looked--was that pale woman,</poem1>
<poem2>So grave, so worn, so sad,</poem2>
<poem1>The child, once young and smiling,</poem1>
<poem2>The bride, once fair and glad?</poem2>
<poem1>What grief had dimm'd that glory</poem1>
<poem2>And brought that dark eclipse</poem2>
<poem1>Upon her blue eyes' radiance,</poem1>
<poem2>And paled those trembling lips?</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>What memory of past sorrow,</poem1>
<poem2>What stab of present pain,</poem2>
<poem1>Brought that deep look of anguish,</poem1>
<poem2>That watch'd the dismal rain,</poem2>
<poem1>That watch'd (with the absent spirit</poem1>
<poem2>That looks, yet does not see)</poem2>
<poem1>The dead and leafless branches</poem1>
<poem2>Upon the Judas Tree.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The slow dark months crept onward</poem1>
<poem2>Upon their icy way,</poem2>
<poem1>'Till April broke in showers,</poem1>
<poem2>And Spring smiled forth in May,</poem2>
<poem1>Upon the apple-blossoms</poem1>
<poem2>The sun shone bright again,</poem2>
<poem1>When slowly up the highway</poem1>
<poem2>Came a long funeral train.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The bells toll'd slowly, sadly,</poem1>
<poem2>For a noble spirit fled;</poem2>
<poem1>Slowly, in pomp and honour,</poem1>
<poem2>They bore the quiet dead.</poem2>
<poem1>Upon a black-plumed charger</poem1>
<poem2>One rode, who held a shield,</poem2>
<poem1>Where azure fleurs-de-lis and stars</poem1>
<poem2>Shone on a silver field.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>'Mid all that homage given</poem1>
<poem2>To a fluttering heart at rest,</poem2>
<poem1>Perhaps an honest sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Dwelt only in one breast.</poem2>
<poem1>One by the inn-door standing</poem1>
<poem2>Watch'd with fast-dropping tears</poem2>
<poem1>The long procession passing,</poem1>
<poem2>And thought of bygone years.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The boyish, silent homage</poem1>
<poem2>To child and bride unknown,</poem2>
<poem1>The pitying tender sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Kept in his heart alone,</poem2>
<poem1>Now laid upon the coffin</poem1>
<poem2>With a purple ilower, might he</poem2>
<poem1>Told to the cold dead sleeper;</poem1>
<poem2>The rest could only see</poem2>
<poem1>A fragrant purple blossom</poem1>
<poem2>Pluck'd from a Judas Tree.</poem2>
</poem>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE POOR PENSIONER.</title>
<p>
I MET her in the corridor, walking to and 
fro, and muttering to herself with a down-looking 
aspect, and a severe economy of 
dress, the season considered. I wondered 
how she came there, and was, to say the 
least of it, decidedly startled when she 
stopped directly opposite me, and, lifting a 
pair of blank, brown eyes to my face, said, in 
a stern voice: 
</p>
<p>
"He was not guilty, my lord judge. God 
will right him yet. It will all come out 
some day. I can wait: yes, I can wait. I 
am more patient than death: I am more 
patient than injustice." 
</p>
<p>
I made a hasty and undignified retreat 
down stairs when she left the passage free, 
and, meeting the waiter, inquired who the 
woman was. The man touched his forehead 
significantly, and said that she was harmless 
(I was very glad to hear it); and that she 
lived on the broken victuals; and that his 
mistress always gave her a dinner on Christmas-day. 
While we were speaking together, 
she descended to where we stood, and 
repeated the exact formula of which she had 
made use before. She was a tall woman, 
strong-limbed, and thin to meagreness. She 
might be fifty, or perhaps fifty-five; her skin 
was withered, and tanned by exposure to all 
sorts of weather, and her uncovered hair was 
burnt to a rusty iron-grey. The waiter 
suggested to her to go to the kitchen fire; at 
which she broke into a scornful laugh, and 
reiterated, "I am more patient than death. 
I am more patient than injustice," and then 
walked out at the open door into the snow. 
</p>
<p>
"I don't think she feels it, sir," said the 
waiter, opening my door for me to enter. 
</p>
<p>
I do not think she did. I watched her 
from my window. She took up a handful of 
the newly-fallen snow and thrust it into her 
bosom, then hugged it close, as if it were a 
living thing, that could be warmed by that 
eager clasp; I saw also, as she turned her 
dark face up towards the sky, that the angry 
scowl left it. I should imagine that all 
sensation in her was dead, except in one 
corner of her heart, to which had gathered 
the memory of some miserable wrong, whose 
acuteness would bide with her to the day of 
her death. 
</p>
<p>
Her name, as I learnt on further inquiry, 
was Hester. She had been born and bred in 
the Yorkshire dales; her parents were of the 
yeoman class, and poor through improvidence 
rather than misfortune. As a girl, Hester 
was remarkable for her pride and her beauty, 
of which no more relics remained than are 
left of the summer rose-garden in drear and 
misty November. She received the scant 
education common to her condition half-a-century 
ago, and grew up a wild, wilful-tempered 
girl, impatient of all restraint, and 
eager for change and excitement. At 
sixteen she married, and very shortly afterwards 
her husband found it expedient to 
leave the dales, and to enlist in a regiment 
which was ordered on foreign service. Hester 
followed him to India, and led the life of 
camps for several years. During this 
interval her family lost sight of her completely; 
for, having parted in anger, no correspondence 
was kept up between them. This silence 
and separation lasted full nine years, during 
which time, Death dealt hardly with those left 
at home. Of all the large family of sons and 
daughters whom the old people had seen 
grow up to man's and woman's estate, not 
one survived. Their hearts began to soften 
towards the offending child, and they made 
efforts to learn if the regiment to which her 
husband belonged had returned to England. 
It had not. 
</p>
<p>
One bleak and wintry night, while the 
solitary and bereaved couple were sitting by 
their silent hearth--it was a very lonely and 
retired spot where the house stood--a heavy 
step came up the little garden path. Neither 
of them stirred. They thought it was one of 
the farm-servants returning from the village, 
whither he had been sent on some errand. 
The curtains had not been closed over the 
window, and all the room, filled with the 
shine of a yule-tide fire, was visible to the 
wayfarer without. The mother sat facing 
the window; lifting her slow, dull gaze from 
the white wood-ashes on the hearth, she 
looked across towards it, and uttered a low, 
frightened cry. She saw a dark face peering 
in at the glass, which wore the traits of 
her daughter Hester. She thought it was 
her wraith, and said so to the old man, who, 
taking a lantern, went out to see if anybody 
was lurking about. It was a very boisterous 
night: loud with wind, and black with clouds 
of sleety rain. At the threshold he stumbled 
over a dark form, which had crouched there 
for the slight shelter afforded by the porch. 
He lowered the lantern, and threw the light 
on the face of a woman. 
</p>
<p>
"Dame! dame! It is our bairn: it is lile 
Hester!" 
</p>
<p>
The mother appeared, and, with a great, 
gasping cry, recognised her daughter. 
</p>
<p>
They led her into the house, towards the 
glowing heat of the fire, and set her down by 
the hearth; for her limbs would scarcely 
support her. Hester wore a thin and ragged 
cloak, beneath the folds of which she had 
hidden her child from the storm. He had 
fallen asleep in her bosom; but as her mother 
removed the dripping garment from her 
shoulders, he woke up with a laugh of 
childish surprise and pleasure. He was a 
fine, well-grown boy, of from six to seven 
years old, and showed none of those signs of 
want and suffering which had graven premature 
age upon the wasted features and gaunt 
frame of his mother. It was some time 
before Hester recovered from her frozen 
exhaustion, and then her first and eager 
demand was for food for the child. 
</p>
<p>
"O Heaven, pity me!" cried the old woman, 
who was weeping over the pair. "Hester 
and her lad starving, while there was to spare 
at home!" 
</p>
<p>
She supplied their wants soon, and would 
have taken the boy; but Hester held him to 
her with a close and jealous grasp, chafing 
his limbs, warming his little hands in her 
bosom, and covering his hand with passionate 
kisses. 
</p>
<p>
He fell asleep in her arms at last; and 
then she told her brief story. She was 
widowed; her husband had died in India 
from wound-fever, and she had been sent 
home to England; on her arrival there she 
found herself destitute, and had traversed 
the country on foot, subsisting by the casual 
charity of strangers. Thus much she said, 
and no more. She indulged in no details of 
her own exquisite sufferings; perhaps they 
were forgotten, when she ended by saying, 
"Thank the Lord, the lad is saved!" 
</p>
<p>
Hester lived on at the farm with her 
parents; and, as the old man failed more and 
more daily, she took the vigorous management 
of it upon herself, and things throve 
with them. By degrees, her beauty was 
restored, and then she had repeated offers of 
marriage; for, the inheritance which would 
be hers at her father's death was by no 
means despicable. But, she kept herself 
single, for the lad's sake. Wilfred grew 
strong, handsome, and high-spirited--like 
his mother, indeed, with whom, much as 
they loved each other, he had many a 
fierce contention. He never could bear 
to be thwarted or checked by her, and 
often Hester, in the bitterness of her 
unbridled anger, would cry, "O Wilfred! it 
would have been better for thee and thy 
mother if we had died on the door-stone in 
the snow, that night we came home." 
</p>
<p>
Still, she had an intense pride in him; and 
always, after their quarrels, she allowed his 
extravagance to have freer scope, though 
that was what usually led to their disputes. 
As might have been expected, Wilfred, under 
such uncertain training, became reckless, 
wild, and domineering, though he preserved 
a certain rough generosity and frankness of 
character which redeemed his faults, and 
made him a favourite with the country folks, 
and a sort of king amongst his companions, 
whose superior in all rustic sports he was. 
</p>
<p>
His grandfather died when he was nineteen; 
his grandmother, eighteen months 
later. Then Hester was sole mistress of the 
little farm. Wilfred soon began to urge his 
mother to sell the property and leave the 
dales, whose uneventful quiet fretted his 
restless disposition. This she absolutely 
refused to do; and was on one occasion so 
deeply irritated at his persistence as to say: 
</p>
<p>
"I would sell the Ings to save your life, 
Wilfred, but for nothing less!" 
</p>
<p>
There was at this time, living on a 
neighbouring farm, an old man of the name of 
Price, who had a grand-daughter to keep his 
house. She was called Nelly; and, besides 
being a small heiress, was a beauty, and 
something of a coquette. Nelly had a short, 
plump little figure; a complexion as soft and 
clear as a blush-rose, and auburn hair. 
Wilfred fell in love. He was a tall, hardy, 
self-willed, and proud young fellow; but in 
Nelly's hands he was plastic as wax, and 
weak as water. She encouraged him, teased 
him, caressed him, mocked him, set him 
beside himself. She played off all her 
little witcheries and fascinations upon him; 
looked sweetly unconscious of their 
mischievous influence; and , when Wilfred stormed 
and raved, she laughed in his face. He 
wanted to marry her immediately; she had 
played with him long enough, he thought; 
and one evening when she had been soft and 
coy, rather than teasing, he put his fortune 
to the proof. She told him flatly she did not 
like him--wherein Nelly told anything but 
the truth, as perhaps better women have 
done under like circumstance. 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred took her reply in earnest, and 
went away in a rage--mad, jealous, and burning 
with passionate disappointment. Hester 
hated Nelly, and gave her not a few hard 
words; for in her camp life, the mother had 
culled some epithets, more expressive than 
polite, which she used with vigorous truth 
when her wrath was excited. She kept her 
son's wound raw and sore by frequent scornful 
allusions to his "Nelly Graceless," and 
did her best to widen the breach between 
them with ample success. 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred stayed away from the Prices for 
ten whole days. 
</p>
<p>
This desertion did not suit the golden-headed 
but tinsel-hearted little coquette. 
She contrived to meet him in a shady wood-walk, 
where they had often loitered together. 
He was out with his dog and gun; very ill 
at ease in mind, for his handsome face looked 
sullen and dangerous, and he would not see 
her as she passed by. Mortified and angry, 
Nelly went home and cried herself ill. 
Wilfred heard she had caught a fever, and must 
needs go to ask. She met him at the garden 
gate, with a smile and a blush; whereat 
Wilfred was so glad, that he forgot to 
reproach her. There was, in consequence, a 
complete reconciliation, ratified by kisses and 
promises--light coin with beauty Nell, but 
real heart-gold with poor, infatuated Wilfred. 
Hester almost despised her son when she 
heard of it. 
</p>
<p>
"She is only fooling thee, lad!" said she, 
indignantly. "Come a richer suitor to the 
door, she'll throw thee over. She is only a 
light, false-hearted lass, not worth a whistle 
of thine." 
</p>
<p>
Therein Hester spake truth. 
</p>
<p>
Nelly played with her lover as a cat plays 
with a mouse. Wilfred urged their marriage. 
She would one day, and the next day she 
would not. Then arose other difficulties. 
Hester did not want an interloper by her 
fire-side, and would not give up the farm to 
her son; in fact, she was so jealous of his 
affection, that the thought of his marriage 
was hateful to her. Old Price said the 
young folks might settle with him, if they 
would; but Nelly liked the house at the Ings 
better, and thought Wilfred ought to take 
her there. When he explained that the 
property was his mother's for her life, she 
immediately accused him of not loving her, 
and assumed a decided coldness and repulsiveness 
of manner. Wilfred, both hurt and 
angry, tried to give her up, but his bonds 
were not so easily escaped. If he stayed 
away from her two days, on the third he was 
sure to be at her side, either winning her 
with tender words, or reproaching her with 
bitter ones. Nelly must have found the 
game a pleasant one, for she kept it up a long 
time, undergoing herself as many changes of 
hue and form as a bubble blown up into the 
sunshine. 
</p>
<p>
Frequently, during his lengthy visits at the 
Glebe Farm, Wilfred had encountered a man, 
Joseph Rigby by name, a dales-yeoman, and 
one of considerable wealth, but no education. 
This man was one of the last in the 
world to excite jealousy; but presently 
Wilfred was compelled to see that Nelly gave 
the coarse-mannered, middle-aged Rigby, 
more of her attentions than consorted with 
her position as his promised wife. He 
charged her with the fact. At first she 
denied it with blushes, and tears, and loud 
protestations; but at last confessed that 
Rigby had proposed to her--she did not dare 
to add that she had half-accepted him. They 
parted in mutual displeasure; and old Price 
said, as they agreed so badly, they had better 
break off the match, and Nelly should marry 
Joseph Rigby, who was well-to-do, and would 
know how to keep his wife in order. Wilfred 
went near her no more. 
</p>
<p>
Presently, it was rumoured in the countryside 
that Nelly Price and Mr. Rigby were to 
be married after the October fairs. Hester 
sneered, prophesied that the rich yeoman 
would repent his bargain before Saint Mark's, 
and rejoiced greatly at her son's escape. 
</p>
<p>
Meanwhile, Wilfred went about the farm 
and the house, silent, moody, and spiritless. 
He was quite changed, and, as his mother 
thought, for the better. Instead of associating 
with his former companions, he stayed much 
at home, and again renewed his entreaties 
that his mother would sell the Ings, and 
leave the dales altogether. He wanted to 
migrate. He did not care where they went, 
so that they got away from that hateful place. 
Hester was as reluctant as ever to comply; 
but she modified her refusal--they would try 
a year longer: if he were still in the same 
mind at the end of that period--well, perhaps 
she would yield to his urgent wishes. 
</p>
<p>
On the morning of the Leeford Fair he left 
home early, and returned towards dusk so--
it was said by Hester. No other person saw 
him until noon next day. Joseph Rigby 
was found murdered, and thrown into 
a gully by the Leeford road, that night. 
There were traces of a violent struggle upon 
the road, and the body had been dragged 
some distance. It had been rifled of money 
and watch, but a broad engraved ring which 
Rigby wore on the fourth finger of his left 
hand, was not removed. He was known to 
have left the market-hall at Leeford with a 
considerable sum in gold upon his person, for 
his brother-in-law had remonstrated with 
him about carrying so much; but the doomed 
man made light of his warnings. The whole 
country-side was up, for the murder was a 
barbarous one. Suspicion fell at once on 
Hester's son. His behaviour at Leeford had 
attracted observation. He had been seen to 
use angry gestures to Rigby, who had laughed 
at him, and had offered the young man his 
hand, as if wishing to be friends; the other 
had rejected it, and turned away, shaking his 
clenched fist. He had also been seen to 
mount his horse at the inn door, and ride off 
in the afternoon. Rigby started about an 
hour later, and alone. He was seen no more 
until his body was found in the ditch by 
some men going to their work in the morning. 
</p>
<p>
When Wilfred was taken, he and his 
mother were sitting by the fireside together: 
she sewing; he reading. It was towards 
twilight, and he had not been over the 
threshold all day. He was very downcast 
and gloomy; irritable when spoken to, 
and short in his answers. His mother said 
to him that he was very strange, and added 
that she wished he would give over hankering 
after Nelly Graceless. He laughed 
painfully, and did not lift his eyes from his book. 
There was a loud knock at the door. Hester 
rose and opened it. Three men pushed their 
way into the house, the foremost asking if 
her son was at home. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes; he is in there, by the fire. What 
do you want with him?" 
</p>
<p>
"You must come with us, Mr. Wilfred--
nay, it's no use showing fight," cried a burly, 
muscular fellow, laying his hand heavily on 
his shoulder; for Wilfred had turned deadly 
pale, and had attempted to shake off the 
man's grasp. 
</p>
<p>
"What is it for?" asked Hester, with her 
eyes on her son. 
</p>
<p>
"God knows.--I don't," said he, quietly. 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Rigby was robbed and murdered last 
night, as he came home from Leeford Fair, 
and suspicion points at your lad, mistress," 
said the man, who still held his hand on 
Wilfred's shoulder. 
</p>
<p>
Hester gave utterance to no frantic 
denials; she laughed, even. 
</p>
<p>
"Why he was at home by this hour yesterday, 
</p>
<p>
in this very room, at his tea. Wasn't 
he, Jessy?" said she, turning to the maid-servant; 
who, with a countenance of alarm, 
stood by the door. 
</p>
<p>
The girl said "Yes;" then hesitated, and 
added that she didn't see young master when 
she brought in tea. 
</p>
<p>
"I was up-stairs," said Wilfred. 
</p>
<p>
"You had better keep all that for another 
time and place: you must go with us 
now," observed the man. 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred made no resistance. His mother 
brought him his coat, and helped him to put 
it on. 
</p>
<p>
"Say thou didn't do it, Willy--only say 
so?" whispered she, fiercely. 
</p>
<p>
"I didn't mother: so help me, God!" was 
his fervent reply. 
</p>
<p>
"You hear him!" cried Hester, turning 
to the men; "you hear him! He never 
lied in his days. He might have killed 
Rigby in a fair fight, or in hot blood; but he 
is not the lad to lie in wait at night, to 
murder his enemy and rob him! He is not 
a thief, this son of mine!" 
</p>
<p>
The officers urged their departure. 
Wilfred was placed in the vehicle which had been 
brought for the purpose, and driven off. 
</p>
<p>
"I'll follow thee, Willy!" cried his 
mother. "Keep up thy heart; they can't 
touch thee! Good-bye, my poor lad!" 
</p>
<p>
They were out of hearing, and Hester 
turned back into the house, cursing Nelly 
Graceless in her heart. 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred was committed to take his trial at 
the winter gaol-delivery on a charge of wilful 
murder. The evidence against him was 
overwhelming. Hester sold the Ings and 
collected all the money she could, that, if 
gold would buy his redemption, it might be 
done; for herself, she had a perfect faith in 
his innocence, and was confident of his 
acquittal, but few persons, if any, shared her 
feelings. The best legal advice had been 
retained for the accused, and the trial came on 
shortly before Christmas. Hester was the 
only witness for her son. The woman Jessy's 
evidence damaged his cause considerably. 
She contradicted herself over and over again, 
and at last, flurried and confused, she burst 
into tears, crying out that she would say 
anything to get her young master off. There 
was nobody to speak with certainty as 
to the prisoner's having been at home by a 
certain hour but his mother; he had put his 
horse into the stable himself, the groom being 
absent at the fair, and Jessy could not swear 
that he was in to tea; she believed not; 
only one cup was used. 
</p>
<p>
Two witnesses, labourers on a farm near 
the Ings, swore to having seen and spoken to 
the prisoner after the hour stated; they said 
he was riding fast, and seemed agitated, but 
it was too dark to see his face. Nelly Price 
also had her word against him; it was drawn 
from her reluctantly, in the midst of shame-faced 
tears and noisy sobs, but it quite overthrew 
overthrew the attempt to prove an alibi. She 
stated that she had watched until dark, in the 
garden, for Wilfred's return from Leeford, and 
had not seen him go by. The prisoner never 
looked towards her, but murmured that he 
had gone home by the bridle-road and Low 
Lane to avoid passing the Glebe Farm. The 
former witnesses, on being recalled, said that 
it was on the highway, nearly a mile from 
the place where the lower road branched off, 
and nearer to the Ings, that they encountered 
the accused. These two decent men, 
being strictly cross-examined, never swerved 
from their first story an iota, and agreed in 
every particular. They were individuals 
of decent character; both had worked on the 
prisoner's farm, and acknowledged him to be 
a liberal and kind master. Their evidence 
was not to be shaken. As a final and damning 
proof of guilt, the watch of which the 
murdered man had been robbed was produced; 
it had been found concealed under the thatch 
of an out-house at the Ings. At this point of 
the evidence the prisoner was observed to 
draw himself up and look round defiantly,--
despair gave him a fictitious strength, 
perhaps, or, was it conscious innocence! 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred spoke in his own defence, briefly, 
but strongly. His life, he said, was sworn 
away, but he was as guiltless of the crime 
laid to his charge as any of those gentlemen 
who sat in judgment upon him. His mother, 
who had remained in court all the time and 
had never spoken except when called upon 
for her evidence, had preserved a stoical 
calmness throughout. When he ceased to speak 
however, she cried out in a quivering voice: 
</p>
<p>
"My lad, thy mother believes thee!" 
</p>
<p>
Some friend would have led her out, but 
she refused to go. The jury gave their 
verdict of guilty without any recommendation 
to mercy, and the sentence of death was 
pronounced. Then it was that Hester rose 
on her feet and faltered that formula of words 
with which she had startled me in the 
corridor: 
</p>
<p>
"He is not guilty, my lord judge. God 
will right him yet. It will all come out 
some day. I can wait; yes, I can wait. I 
am more patient than death. I am more 
patient than injustice." 
</p>
<p>
Wilfred died stubborn and unconfessing; 
on the scaffold, with his last breath, he 
persisted in asserting his innocence. His mother 
bade him farewell, and was carried to this inn, 
where she had stayed, raving in a frenzy-fit. 
For many months she was subject to restraint, 
but, recovering in some measure, she was at 
length set at liberty. Her mind was still 
distraught, however; she wandered back to 
the dales and to her old home, but the new 
owner had taken possession, and after enduring 
her intrusions for some time, he was 
compelled to apply for her removal. 
</p>
<p>
After this, her money being lost or 
exhausted, she strayed about the country in 
a purposeless way; begging or doing day's 
work in the field, until she strayed here 
again, and became the Pensioner of the 
Holly Tree. The poor demented creature 
is always treated kindly, but her son's 
sentence has not yet been reversed in men's 
judgment. Every morning during the time 
the judges are in the neighbouring Assize 
town she waits in one of the streets through 
which they must pass to reach the court; and 
as the gilt coach, the noisy trumpets, and the 
decrepit halberdiers, go by, she scowls at them 
from beneath her shaggy brows, and mutters 
her formula of defiance. She will die saying 
it: comforting her poor, worn, wounded heart 
with its smarting balm. 
</p>
<p>
Will she find, when she comes before the 
Tribunal of Eternal Decrees that she has 
leaned thus long upon a broken reed, or will 
she find her son there, free from the guilt of 
blood? 
</p>
<p>
The Great Judge only knows. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BILL.</title>
<p>
I COULD scarcely believe, when I came to 
the last word of the foregoing recital and 
finished it off with a flourish, as I am apt to 
do when I make an end of any writing, that 
I had been snowed up a whole week. The 
time had hung so lightly on my hands, and 
the Holly-Tree, so bare at first, had borne so 
many berries for me, that I should have 
been in great doubt of the fact but for a piece 
of documentary evidence that lay upon my 
table. 
</p>
<p>
The road had been dug out of the snow, on 
the previous day, and the document in question 
was my Bill. It testified, emphatically, 
to my having eaten and drunk, and warmed 
myself, and slept, among the sheltering 
branches of the Holly-Tree, seven days and 
nights. 
</p>
<p>
I had yesterday allowed the road twenty-four 
hours to improve itself, finding that I 
required that additional margin of time for the 
completion of my task. I had ordered my 
Bill to be upon the table, and a chaise to be 
at the door, "at eight o'clock to-morrow 
evening." It was eight o'clock to-morrow | 
evening, when I buckled up my travelling 
writing-desk in its leather case, paid my 
Bill, and got on my warm coats and 
wrappers. Of course, no time now 
remained for my travelling on, to add a frozen 
tear to the icicles which were doubtless hanging 
plentifully about the farm-house where I 
had first seen Angela. What I had to do, 
was, to get across to Liverpool by the shortest 
open road, there to meet my heavy baggage 
and embark. It was quite enough to do, and 
I had not an hour too much time to do it in. 
</p>
<p>
I had taken leave of all my Holly-Tree 
friends--almost, for the time being, of 
my bashfulness too--and was standing for 
half a minute at the Inn-door, watching the 
ostler as he took another turn at the cord 
which tied my portmanteau on the chaise, 
when I saw lamps coming down towards the 
Holly-Tree. The road was so padded with 
snow that no wheels were audible; but, all of 
us who were standing at the Inn-door, saw 
lamps coming on, and at a lively rate too, 
between the walls of snow that had been heaped 
up, on either side of the track. The chamber-maid 
instantly divined how the case stood, 
and called to the ostler: "Tom, this is a 
Gretna job!" The ostler, knowing that 
her sex instinctively scented a marriage or 
anything in that direction, rushed up the 
yard, bawling, "Next four out!" and in a 
moment the whole establishment was thrown 
into commotion. 
</p>
<p>
I had a melancholy interest in seeing the 
happy man who loved and was beloved; and, 
therefore, instead of driving off at once, I 
remained at the Inn-door when the fugitives 
drove up. A bright-eyed fellow, muffled in a 
mantle, jumped out so briskly that he almost 
overthrew me. He turned to apologise, and, 
by Heaven, it was Edwin! 
</p>
<p>
"Charley!" said he, recoiling. "Gracious 
powers, what do you do here?" 
</p>
<p>
"Edwin, "said I, recoiling, "Gracious powers, 
what do you do here!" I struck my forehead 
as I said it, and an insupportable blaze of light 
seemed to shoot before my eyes. 
</p>
<p>
He hurried me into the little parlor (always 
kept with a slow fire in it and no poker), 
where posting company waited while their 
horses were putting to; and, shutting the 
door, said: 
</p>
<p>
"Charley, forgive me!" 
</p>
<p>
"Edwin!" I returned. "Was this well? 
When I loved her so dearly! When I had 
garnered up my heart so long! "I could say 
no more. 
</p>
<p>
He was shocked when he saw how moved 
I was, and made the cruel observation, 
that he had not thought I should have taken 
it so much to heart. 
</p>
<p>
I looked at him. I reproached him no 
more. But I looked at him. 
</p>
<p>
"My dear, dear Charley," said he; "don't 
think ill of me, I beseech you! I know 
you have a right to my utmost confidence, 
and, believe me, you have ever had it 
until now. I abhor secresy. Its meanness is 
intolerable to me. But, I and my dear girl 
have observed it for your sake." 
</p>
<p>
He and his dear girl! It steeled me. 
</p>
<p>
"You have observed it for my sake, sir?" 
said I, wondering how his frank face could 
face it out so. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes!--and Angela's," said he. 
</p>
<p>
I found the room reeling round in an 
uncertain way, like a laboring humming-top. 
"Explain yourself," said I, holding on by one 
hand to an arm-chair. 
</p>
<p>
"Dear old darling Charley!" returned 
Edwin, in his cordial manner, "consider! When 
you were going on so happily with Angela, 
why should I compromise you with the old 
gentleman by making you a party to our 
engagement, and (after he had declined my 
proposals) to our secret intention? Surely it 
was better that you should be able honorably 
to say, ' He never took counsel with me, 
never told me, never breathed a word of it.' 
If Angela suspected it and showed me all 
the favor and support she could--God 
bless her for a precious creature and a priceless 
less wife!--I couldn't help that. Neither I 
nor Emmeline ever told her, any more than 
we told you. And for the same good reason, 
Charley; trust me, for the same good reason, 
and no other upon earth!" 
</p>
<p>
Emmeline was Angela's cousin. Lived 
with her. Had been brought up with her. 
Was her father's ward. Had property. 
</p>
<p>
"Emmeline is in the chaise, my dear 
Edwin?" said I, embracing him with the 
greatest affection. 
</p>
<p>
"My good fellow!" said he, "Do you 
suppose I should be going to Gretna Green 
without her!" 
</p>
<p>
I ran out with Edwin, I opened the chaise 
door, I took Emmeline in my arms, I folded 
her to my heart. She was wrapped in soft 
white fur, like the snowy landscape; but 
was warm, and young, and lovely. I put their 
leaders to with my own hands, I gave the 
boys a five-pound note a-piece, I cheered 
them as they drove away, I drove the other 
way myself as hard as I could pelt. 
</p>
<p>
I never went to Liverpool, I never went to 
America, I went straight back to London, 
and I married Angela. I have never until 
this time, even to her, disclosed the secret of 
my character, and the mistrust and the 
mistaken journey into which it led me. When 
she, and they, and our eight children and 
their seven--I mean Edwin's and Emmeline's, 
whose eldest girl is old enough now to wear 
white fur herself, and to look very like 
her mother in it--come to read these pages, 
as of course they will, I shall hardly fail to 
be found out at last. Never mind! I can 
bear it. I began at the Holly-Tree, by idle 
accident, to associate the Christmas time of 
year with human interest, and with some 
inquiry into, and some care for, the lives of 
those by whom I find myself surrounded. I 
hope that I am none the worse for it, and 
that no one near me or afar off is the worse 
for it. And I say, May the green Holly-Tree 
flourish, striking its roots deep into our 
English ground, and having its germinating 
qualities carried by the birds of Heaven all 
over the world! 
</p>
<section>
END OF THE CHRISTMAS NUMBER FOR 1855 
</section>
</chapter>
</book>
