<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>The Wreck Of The Golden Mary</title>
<subtitle>(Household Words Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1856</date>
<option name="chapter.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="chapter.number_style" value="NONE"/>
</info>

<prefix>
<info title="THE WRECK OF THE GOLDEN MARY."/>
<centre>BEING THE CAPTAIN'S ACCOUNT OF THE LOSS OF THE SHIP, AND THE MATE'S ACCOUNT OF THE GREAT DELIVERANCE OF HER PEOPLE IN AN OPEN BOAT AT SEA.</centre>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1856.</centre>
</prefix>

<chapter>
<title>THE WRECK <br/>[The Captain's Account]</title>
<p>
I <sc>WAS</sc> apprenticed to the Sea when I was 
twelve years old, and I have encountered a 
great deal of rough weather, both literal and 
metaphorical. It has always been my opinion 
since I first possessed such a thing as an 
opinion, that the man who knows only one 
subject is next tiresome to the man who 
knows no subject. Therefore, in the course 
of my life I have taught myself whatever I 
could, and although I am not an educated 
man, I am able, I am thankful to say, to have 
an intelligent interest in most things. 
</p>
<p>
A person might suppose, from reading the 
above, that I am in the habit of holding forth 
about number one. That is not the case. 
Just as if I was to come into a room among 
strangers, and must either be introduced or 
introduce myself, so I have taken the liberty 
of passing these few remarks, simply and 
plainly that it may be known who and what 
I am. I will add no more of the sort than 
that my name is William George Ravender, 
that I was born at Penrith half a year after 
my own father was drowned, and that I am 
on the second day of this present blessed 
Christmas week of one thousand eight 
hundred and fifty-six, fifty-six years of age. 
</p>
<p>
When the rumour first went flying up and 
down that there was gold in California--
which, as most people know, was before it 
was discovered in the British colony of 
Australia--I was in the West Indies, trading 
among the Islands. Being in command and 
likewise part-owner of a smart schooner, I 
had my work cut out for me, and I was doing 
it. Consequently, gold in California was no 
business of mine. 
</p>
<p>
But, by the time when I came home to 
England again, the thing was as clear as 
your hand held up before you at noon-day. 
There was Californian gold in the museums 
and in the goldsmiths’ shops, and the very 
first time I went upon ’Change, I met a friend 
of mine (a seafaring man like myself), with a 
Californian nugget hanging to his watch-
chain. I handled it. It was as like a peeled 
walnut with bits unevenly broken off here 
and there, and then electrotyped all over, as 
ever I saw anything in my life. 
</p>
<p>
I am a single man (she was too good for 
this world and for me, and she died six weeks 
before our marriage-day), so when I am 
ashore, I live in my house at Poplar. My 
house at Poplar is taken care of and kept 
ship-shape by, an old lady who was my 
mother's maid before I was born. She is as 
handsome and as upright as any old lady in 
the world. She is as fond of me as if she had 
ever had an only son, and I was he. Well do 
I know wherever I sail that she never lays 
down her head at night without having said, 
“Merciful Lord! bless and preserve William 
George Ravender, and send him safe home, 
through Christ our Saviour!” I have thought 
of it in many a dangerous moment, when it 
has done me no harm, I am sure. 
</p>
<p>
In my house at Poplar, along with this old 
lady, I lived quiet for best part of a year: 
having had a long spell of it among the 
Islands, and having (which was very uncommon 
in me) taken the fever rather badly. At 
last, being strong and hearty, and having 
read every book I could lay hold of, right 
out, I was walking down Leadenhall Street 
in the City of London, thinking of turning-to 
again, when I met what I call Smithick and 
Watersby of Liverpool. I chanced to lift up 
my eyes from looking in at a ship's chronometer 
in a window, and I saw him bearing 
down upon me, head on. 
</p>
<p>
It is, personally, neither Smithick, nor 
Watersby, that I here mention, nor was I 
ever acquainted with any man of either of 
those names, nor do I think that there has 
been any one of either of those names in that 
Liverpool House for years back. But, it is 
in reality the House itself that I refer to; 
and a wiser merchant or a truer gentleman 
never stepped. 
</p>
<p>
“My dear Captain Ravender,” says he. 
“Of all the men on earth, I wanted to see 
you most. I was on my way to you.” 
</p>
<p>
“Well!” says I. “That looks as if you 
were to see me, don't it?” With that, I put 
my arm in his, and we walked on towards 
the Royal Exchange, and, when we got there, 
walked up and down at the back of it where 
the Clock-Tower is. We walked an hour and 
more, for he had much to say to me. He had 
a scheme for chartering a new ship of their 
own to take out cargo to the diggers and 
emigrants in California, and to buy and bring 
back gold. Into the particulars of that 
scheme I will not enter, and I have no right to 
enter. All I say of it, is, that it was a very 
original one, a very fine one, a very sound 
one, and a very lucrative one, beyond doubt. 
</p>
<p>
He imparted it to me as freely as if l had 
been a part of himself. After doing so, he 
made me the handsomest sharing offer that 
ever was made to me, boy or man--or I 
believe to any other captain in the Merchant 
Navy--and he took this round turn to finish 
with: 
</p>
<p>
“Ravender, you are well aware that the 
lawlessness of that coast and country at 
present, is as special as the circumstances in 
which it is placed. Crews of vessels outward-
bound, desert as soon as they make the land; 
crews of vessels homeward-bound, ship at 
enormous wages, with the express intention 
of murdering the captain and seizing the 
gold freight; no man can trust another, and 
the devil seems let loose. Now,” says he, 
“you know my opinion of you, and you know 
I am only expressing it, and with no 
singularity, when I tell you that you are almost 
the only man on whose integrity, discretion, 
and energy--” &amp;c., &amp;c. For, I don't want to 
repeat what he said, though I was and am 
sensible of it. 
</p>
<p>
Notwithstanding my being, as I have 
mentioned, quite ready for a voyage, still I had 
some doubts of this voyage. Of course I 
knew, without being told, that there were 
peculiar difficulties and dangers in it, a long 
way over and above those which attend all 
voyages. It must not be supposed that I was 
afraid to face them; but, in my opinion a 
man has no manly motive or sustainment in 
his own breast for facing dangers, unless he 
has well considered what they are, and is 
able quietly to say to himself, “None of these 
perils can now take me by surprise; I shall 
know what to do for the best in any of them; 
all the rest lies in the higher and greater 
hands to which I humbly commit myself.” 
On this principle I have so attentively 
considered (regarding it as my duty) all the 
hazards I have ever been able to think of, in 
the ordinary way of storm, shipwreck, and 
fire at sea, that I hope I should be prepared 
to do, in any of those cases, whatever could 
be done, to save the lives entrusted to my 
charge. 
</p>
<p>
As I was thoughtful, my good friend 
proposed that he should leave me to walk there 
as long as I liked, and that I should dine with 
him by-and-by at his club in Pall Mall. I 
accepted the invitation, and I walked up and 
down there, quarter-deck fashion, a matter of 
a couple of hours; now and then looking up 
at the weathercock as I might have looked 
up aloft; and now and then taking a look into 
Cornhill, as I might have taken a look over 
the side. 
</p>
<p>
All dinner-time, and all after-dinner-time, 
we talked it over again. I gave him my 
views of his plan, and he very much approved 
of the same. I told him I had nearly 
decided, but not quite. “Well, well,” says he, 
“come down to Liverpool to-morrow with 
me, and see the Golden Mary.” I liked 
the name (her name was Mary, and she 
was golden, if golden stands for good), so 
I began to feel that it was almost done when 
I said I would go to Liverpool. On the next 
morning but one we were on board the 
Golden Mary. I might have known, from 
his asking me to come down and see her, 
what she was. I declare her to have been 
the completest and most exquisite Beauty 
that ever I set my eyes upon. 
</p>
<p>
We had inspected every timber in her, and 
had come back to the gangway to go ashore 
from the dock-basin, when I put out my hand 
to my friend. “Touch upon it,” says I, “and 
touch heartily. I take command of this ship, 
and I am hers and yours, if I can get John 
Steadiman for my chief mate.” 
</p>
<p>
John Steadiman had sailed with me four 
voyages. The first voyage, John was third 
mate out to China, and came home second. 
The other three voyages, he was my first 
officer. At this time of chartering the 
Golden Mary, he was aged thirty-two. A 
brisk, bright, blue-eyed fellow, a very neat 
figure and rather under the middle size, 
never out of the way and never in it, a face 
that pleased everybody and that all children 
took to, a habit of going about singing as 
cheerily as a blackbird, and a perfect sailor. 
</p>
<p>
We were in one of those Liverpool hackney-
coaches in less than a minute, and we cruised 
about in her upwards of three hours, looking 
for John. John had come home from Van 
Diemen’s Land barely a month before, and I 
had heard of him as taking a frisk in Liverpool. 
We asked after him, among many 
other places, at the two boarding-houses he 
was fondest of, and we found he had had a 
week's spell at each of them; but, he had 
gone here and gone there, and had set off 
“to lay out on the main-to'-gallant-yard of the 
highest Welsh mountain” (so he had told the 
people of the house), and where he might be 
then, or when he might come back nobody 
could tell us. But it was surprising, to be 
sure, to see how every face brightened the 
moment there was mention made of the name 
of Mr. Steadiman. 
</p>
<p>
We were taken aback at meeting with no 
better luck, and we had wore ship and put 
her head for my friends, when, as we were 
jogging through the streets, I clap my eyes 
on John himself coming out of a toyshop! 
He was carrying a little boy, and conducting 
two uncommon pretty women to their coach, 
and he told me afterwards that he had never 
in his life seen one of the three before, but 
that he was so taken with them on looking 
in at the toy-shop while they were buying 
the child a cranky Noah’s Ark, very much 
down by the head, that he had gone in and 
asked the ladies’ permission to treat him 
to a tolerably correct Cutter there was in 
the window, in order that such a handsome 
boy might not grow up with a lubberly idea 
of naval architecture. 
</p>
<p>
We stood off and on until the ladies’ 
coachman began to give way, and then we 
hailed John. On his coming aboard of us, 
I told him, very gravely, what I had said to 
my friend. It struck him, as he said himself, 
amidships. He was quite shaken by it. 
“Captain Ravender,” were John Steadiman’s 
words, “such an opinion from you is true 
commendation, and I’ll sail round the world 
with you for twenty years if you hoist the 
signal, and stand by you for ever!” And 
now indeed I felt that it was done, and that 
the Golden Mary was afloat. 
</p>
<p>
Grass never grew yet under the feet of 
Smithick and Watersby. The riggers were 
out of that ship in a fortnight’s time, and 
we had begun taking in cargo. John was 
always aboard, seeing everything stowed with 
his own eyes; and whenever I went aboard 
myself, early or late, whether he was below 
in the hold, or on deck at the hatchway, or 
overhauling his cabin, nailing up pictures in 
it of the Blush Roses of England, the Blue 
Belles of Scotland, and the female 
Shamrock of Ireland: of a certainty I heard John 
singing like a blackbird. 
</p>
<p>
We had room for twenty passengers. Our 
sailing advertisement was no sooner out, than 
we might have taken these, twenty times over. 
In entering our men, I and John (both 
together) picked them, and we entered none 
but good hands--as good as were to be 
found in that port. And so, in a good 
ship of the best build, well owned, well 
arranged, well officered, well manned, well 
found in all respects, we parted with our 
pilot at a quarter past four o’clock in the 
afternoon of the seventh of March, one 
thousand eight hundred and fifty-one, and stood 
with a fair wind out to sea. 
</p>
<p>
It may be easily believed that up to that 
time I had had no leisure to be intimate 
with my passengers. The most of them were 
then in their berths sea-sick; however, in 
going among them, telling them what was 
good for them, persuading them not to be 
there, but to come up on deck and feel the 
breeze, and in rousing them with a joke, or a 
comfortable word, I made acquaintance with 
them, perhaps, in a more friendly and 
confidential way from the first, than I might have 
done at the cabin table. 
</p>
<p>
Of my passengers, I need only particularise, 
just at present, a bright-eyed, blooming young 
wife who was going out to join her husband 
in California, taking with her their only child, 
a little girl of three years old, whom he had 
never seen; a sedate young woman in black, 
some five years older (about thirty, as I 
should say), who was going out to join a 
brother; and an old gentleman, a good deal 
like a hawk if his eyes had been better and 
not so red, who was always talking, morning, 
noon, and night, about the gold discovery. 
But, whether he was making the voyage, 
thinking his old arms could dig for gold, or 
whether his speculation was to buy it, or, 
to barter for it, or to cheat for it, or to 
snatch it anyhow from other people, was 
his secret. He kept his secret. 
</p>
<p>
These three and the child were the 
soonest well. The child was a most engaging 
child, to be sure, and very fond of me: 
though I am bound to admit that John 
Steadiman and I were borne on her pretty 
little books in reverse order, and that he 
was captain there, and I was mate. It was 
beautiful to watch her with John, and it 
was beautiful to watch John with her. Few 
would have thought it possible, to see John 
playing at bo-peep round the mast, that he 
was the man who had caught up an iron 
bar and struck a Malay and a Maltese 
dead, as they were gliding with their knives 
down the cabin stair aboard the barque Old 
England, when the captain lay ill in his 
cot, off Saugar Point. But he was; and 
give him his back against a bulwark, he 
would have done the same by half a dozen 
of them. The name of the young mother was 
Mrs. Atherfield, the name of the young lady in 
black was Miss Coleshaw, and the name of 
the old gentleman was Mr. Rarx. 
</p>
<p>
As the child had a quantity of shining 
fair hair, clustering in curls all about her 
face, and as her name was Lucy, Steadiman 
gave her the name of the Golden Lucy. 
So, we had the Golden Lucy and the Golden 
Mary; and John kept up the idea to that 
extent as he and the child went playing 
about the decks, that I believe she used to 
think the ship was alive somehow--a sister 
or companion, going to the same place as 
herself. She liked to be by the wheel, and 
in fine weather, I have often stood by the man 
whose trick it was at the wheel, only to 
hear her, sitting near my feet, talking to 
the ship. Never had a child such a doll 
before, I suppose; but she made a doll of the 
Golden Mary, and used to dress her up by 
tying ribbons and little bits of finery to the 
belaying-pins; and nobody ever moved them, 
unless it was to save them from being blown 
away. 
</p>
<p>
Of course I took charge of the two young 
women, and I called them “my dear,” and 
they never minded, knowing that whatever I 
said was said in a fatherly and protecting 
spirit. I gave them their places on each side 
of me at dinner, Mrs. Atherfield on my right 
and Miss Coleshaw on my left; and I directed 
the unmarried lady to serve out the breakfast, 
and the married lady to serve out the 
tea. Likewise I said to my black steward in 
their presence, “Tom Snow, these two ladies 
are equally the mistresses of this house, and 
do you obey their orders equally;” at which 
Tom laughed, and they all laughed. 
</p>
<p>
Old Mr. Rarx was not a pleasant man to 
look at, nor yet to talk to, or to be with, for no 
one could help seeing that he was a sordid 
and selfish character, and that he had warped 
further and further out of the straight with 
time. Not but what he was on his best 
behaviour with us, as everybody was; for, we 
had no bickering among us, for’ard or aft. 
I only mean to say, he was not the man 
one would have chosen for a messmate. If 
choice there had been, one might even have 
gone a few points out of one’s course, to say, 
“No! Not him!” But, there was one curious 
inconsistency in Mr. Rarx. That was, that 
he took an astonishing interest in the child. 
He looked, and, I may add, he was, one 
of the last of men to care at all for a child, 
or to care much for any human creature. 
Still, he went so far as to be habitually 
uneasy, if the child was long on deck, out of 
his sight. He was always afraid of her falling 
overboard, or falling down a hatchway, or of 
a block or what not coming down upon her 
from the rigging in the working of the ship, 
or of her getting some hurt or other. He 
used to look at her and touch her, as if she 
was something precious to him. He was 
always solicitous about her not injuring her 
health, and constantly entreated her mother 
to be careful of it. This was so much the 
more curious, because the child did not like 
him, but used to shrink away from him, and 
would not even put out her hand to 
him without coaxing from others. I believe 
that every soul on board frequently noticed 
this, and that not one of us understood it. 
However, it was such a plain fact, that John 
Steadiman said more than once when old 
Mr. Rarx was not within earshot, that if 
the Golden Mary felt a tenderness for the 
dear old gentleman she carried in her lap, 
she must be bitterly jealous of the Golden 
Lucy. 
</p>
<p>
Before I go any further with this narrative, 
I will state that our ship was a barque of 
three hundred tons, carrying a crew of 
eighteen men, a second mate in addition to 
John, a carpenter, an armourer or smith, and 
two apprentices (one a Scotch boy, poor little 
fellow). We had three boats; the Long-boat, 
capable of carrying twenty-five men; the 
Cutter, capable of carrying fifteen; and the 
Surf-boat, capable of carrying ten. I put 
down the capacity of these boats according 
to the numbers they were really meant to 
hold. 
</p>
<p>
We had tastes of bad weather and headwinds, 
of course; but, on the whole we had 
as fine a run as any reasonable man could 
expect, for sixty days. I then began to enter 
two remarks in the ship’s Log and in my 
Journal; first, that there was an unusual 
and amazing quantity of ice; second, that 
the nights were most wonderfully dark, in 
spite of the ice. 
</p>
<p>
For five days and a half, it seemed quite 
useless and hopeless to alter the ship’s course 
so as to stand out of the way of this ice. I 
made what southing I could; but, all that 
time, we were beset by it. Mrs. Atherfield 
after standing by me on deck once, looking 
for some time in an awed manner at the 
great bergs that surrounded us, said in a 
whisper, “O! Captain Ravender, it looks as 
if the whole solid earth had changed into ice, 
and broken up!” I said to her, laughing, 
“I don't wonder that it does, to your 
inexperienced eyes, my dear.” But I had never 
seen a twentieth part of the quantity, and, in 
reality, I was pretty much of her opinion. 
</p>
<p>
However, at two p.m. on the afternoon of 
the sixth day, that is to say, when we were 
sixty-six days out, John Steadiman who had 
gone aloft, sang out from the top, that the 
sea was clear ahead. Before four p.m. a 
strong breeze springing up right astern, we 
were in open water at sunset. The breeze 
then freshening into half a gale of wind, and 
the Golden Mary being a very fast sailer, we 
went before the wind merrily, all night. 
</p>
<p>
I had thought it impossible that it could 
be darker than it had been, until the sun, moon, 
and stars should fall out of the Heavens, and 
Time should be destroyed; but, it had been next 
to light, in comparison with what it was now. 
The darkness was so profound, that looking 
into it was painful and oppressive--like looking, 
without a ray of light, into a dense black 
bandage put as close before the eyes as it 
could be, without touching them. I doubled 
the look-out, and John and I stood in the 
bow side-by-side, never leaving it all night. 
Yet I should no more have known that he 
was near me when he was silent, without 
putting out my arm and touching him, than 
I should if he had turned in and been fast 
asleep below. We were not so much looking 
out, all of us, as listening to the utmost, both 
with our eyes and ears. 
</p>
<p>
Next day, I found that the mercury in the 
barometer, which had risen steadily since we 
cleared the ice, remained steady. I had had 
very good observations, with now and then 
the interruption of a day or so, since our 
departure. I got the sun at noon, and found 
that we were in Lat. 58° S., Long. 60° W., off 
New South Shetland; in the neighbourhood 
of Cape Horn. We were sixty-seven days 
out, that day. The ship’s reckoning was 
accurately worked and made up. The ship 
did her duty admirably, all on board were 
well, and all hands were as smart, efficient, 
and contented, as it was possible to be. 
</p>
<p>
When the night came on again as dark as 
before, it was the eighth night I had been on 
deck. Nor had I taken more than a very 
little sleep in the day-time, my station being 
always near the helm, and often at it, while 
we were among the ice. Few but those who 
have tried it can imagine the difficulty and 
pain of only keeping the eyes open--physically 
open--under such circumstances, in 
such darkness. They get struck by the darkness, 
and blinded by the darkness. They 
make patterns in it, and they flash in it, 
as if they had gone out of your head to 
look at you. On the turn of midnight, John 
Steadiman, who was alert and fresh (for I 
had always made him turn in by day), said to 
me, “Captain Ravender, I entreat of you to 
go below. I am sure you can hardly stand, 
and your voice is getting weak, sir. Go 
below, and take a little rest. I’ll call you if 
a block chafes.” I said to John in answer, 
“Well, well, John! Let us wait till the 
turn of one o’clock, before we talk about 
that.” I had just had one of the ship’s 
lanterns held up, that I might see how the 
night went by my watch, and it was then 
twenty minutes after twelve. 
</p>
<p>
At five minutes before one, John sang out 
to the boy to bring the lantern again, and, 
when I told him once more what the time 
was, entreated and prayed of me to go below. 
“Captain Ravender,” says he, “all’s well; 
we can’t afford to have you laid up for a 
single hour; and I respectfully and earnestly 
beg of you to go below.” The end of it was, 
that I agreed to do so, on the understanding 
that if I failed to come up of my own accord 
within three hours, I was to be punctually 
called. Having settled that, I left John in 
charge. But, I called him to me once 
afterwards, to ask him a question. I had been to 
look at the barometer, and had seen the 
mercury still perfectly steady, and had come 
up the companion again, to take a last look 
about me--if I can use such a word in 
reference to such darkness--when I thought that 
the waves, as the Golden Mary parted them 
and shook them off, had a hollow sound in 
them; something that I fancied was a rather 
unusual reverberation. I was standing by 
the quarter-deck rail on the starboard side, 
when I called John aft to me, and bade him 
listen. He did so with the greatest attention. 
Turning to me he then said, “Rely 
upon it, Captain Ravender, you have been 
without rest too long, and the novelty is only 
in the state of your sense of hearing.” I 
thought so too by that time, and I think so 
now, though I can never know for absolute 
certain in this world, whether it was or not. 
</p>
<p>
When I left John Steadiman in charge, the 
ship was still going at a great rate through 
the water. The wind still blew right astern. 
Though she was making great way, she was 
under shortened sail, and had no more than 
she could easily carry. All was snug, and 
nothing complained. There was a pretty sea 
running, but not a very high sea neither, 
nor at all a confused one. 
</p>
<p>
I turned in, as we seamen say, all standing. 
The meaning of that, is, I did not pull my 
clothes off--no, not even so much as my coat: 
though I did my shoes, for my feet were 
badly swelled with the deck. There was a 
little swing-lamp alight in my cabin. I 
thought, as I looked at it before shutting my 
eyes, that I was so tired of darkness, and 
troubled by darkness, that I could have gone 
to sleep best in the midst of a million of 
flaming gas-lights. That was the last thought 
I had before I went off, except the prevailing 
thought that I should not be able to get to 
sleep at all. 
</p>
<p>
I dreamed that I was back at Penrith 
again, and was trying to get round the 
church, which had altered its shape very 
much since I last saw it, and was cloven all 
down the middle of the steeple in a most 
singular manner. Why I wanted to get 
round the church, I don't know; but, I was 
as anxious to do it as if my life depended on 
it. Indeed, I believe it did, in the dream. For all 
that, I could not get round the church. I 
was still trying, when I came against it with 
a violent shock, and was flung out of my cot 
against the ship’s side. Shrieks and a terrific 
outcry struck me far harder than the bruising 
timbers, and amidst sounds of grinding and 
crashing, and a heavy rushing and breaking 
of water--sounds I understood too well--I 
made my way on deck. It was not an easy 
thing to do, for the ship heeled over frightfully, 
and was beating in a furious manner. 
</p>
<p>
I could not see the men as I went forward, 
but I could hear that they were hauling in 
sail, in disorder. I had my trumpet in my 
hand, and, after directing and encouraging 
them in this till it was done, I hailed 
first John Steadiman, and then my second 
mate, Mr. William Rames. Both answered 
clearly and steadily. Now, I had practised 
them and all my crew, as I have ever made 
it a custom to practise all who sail with me, 
to take certain stations, and wait my orders, 
in case of any unexpected crisis. When my 
voice was heard hailing, and their voices 
were heard answering, I was aware, through 
all the noises of the ship and sea, and all the 
crying of the passengers below, that there 
was a pause. “Are you ready, Rames?”--
“Aye, aye, sir!”--“Then light up, for God’s 
sake!” In a moment he and another were 
burning blue-lights, and the ship and all on 
board seemed to be enclosed in a mist of light, 
under a great black dome. 
</p>
<p>
The light shone up so high that I could see 
the huge Iceberg upon which we had struck, 
cloven at the top and down the middle, 
exactly like Penrith Church in my dream. At 
the same moment I could see the watch last 
relieved, crowding up and down on deck; I could 
see Mrs. Atherfield and Miss Coleshaw thrown 
about on the top of the companion as they 
struggled to bring the child up from below; 
I could see that the masts were going with 
the shock and the beating of the ship; I 
could see the frightful breach stove in on the 
starboard side, half the length of the vessel, 
and the sheathing and timbers spirting up; 
I could see that the Cutter was disabled, in a 
wreck of broken fragments; and I could see 
every eye turned upon me. It is my belief 
that if there had been ten thousand eyes 
there, I should have seen them all, with their 
different looks. And all this in a moment. 
But you must consider what a moment. 
</p>
<p>
I saw the men, as they looked at me, fall 
towards their appointed stations, like good 
men and true. If she had not righted, they 
could have done very little there or anywhere 
but die--not that it is little for a man to 
die at his post--I mean they could have done 
nothing to save the passengers and themselves. 
Happily, however, the violence of the shock 
with which we had so determinedly borne down 
direct on that fatal Iceberg, as if it had been 
our destination instead of our destruction, 
had so smashed and pounded the ship that 
she got off in this same instant, and righted. 
I did not want the carpenter to tell me she 
was filling and going down; I could see 
and hear that. I gave Rames the word to 
lower the Long-boat and the Surf-boat, and I 
myself told off the men for each duty. Not 
one hung back, or came before the other. I 
now whispered to John Steadiman, “John, 
I stand at the gangway here, to see every 
soul on board safe over the side. You shall 
have the next post of honor, and shall be 
the last but one to leave the ship. Bring 
up the passengers, and range them behind 
me; and put what provision and water you 
can get at, in the boats. Cast your eye 
for’ard, John, and you’ll see you have not a 
moment to lose.” 
</p>
<p>
My noble fellows got the boats over the 
side, as orderly as I ever saw boats lowered 
with any sea running, and, when they were 
launched, two or three of the nearest men in 
them as they held on, rising and falling with 
the swell, called out, looking up at me, 
“Captain Ravender, if anything goes wrong with 
us and you are saved, remember we stood 
by you!”--“We’ll all stand by one another 
ashore, yet, please God, my lads!” says I. 
“Hold on bravely, and be tender with the 
women.” 
</p>
<p>
The women were an example to us. They 
trembled very much, but they were quiet 
and perfectly collected. “Kiss me, Captain 
Ravender,” says Mrs. Atherfield, “and God 
in Heaven bless you, you good man!” “My 
dear,” says I, “those words are better for me 
than a life-boat.” I held her child in my 
arms till she was in the boat, and then kissed 
the child and handed her safe down. I now 
said to the people in her, “You have got 
your freight, my lads, all but me, and I am 
not coming yet awhile. Pull away from the 
ship, and keep off!” 
</p>
<p>
That was the Long-boat. Old Mr. Rarx 
was one of her complement, and he was the 
only passenger who had greatly misbehaved 
since the ship struck. Others had been a 
little wild, which was not to be wondered at, 
and not very blameable; but, he had made a 
lamentation and uproar which it was 
dangerous for the people to hear, as there is 
always contagion in weakness and selfishness. 
His incessant cry had been that he must 
not be separated from the child, that he 
couldn’t see the child, and that he and the 
child must go together. He had even tried 
to wrest the child out of my arms, that he 
might keep her in his. “Mr. Rarx,” said I 
to him when it came to that, “I have a loaded 
pistol in my pocket; and if you don't stand 
out of the gangway, and keep perfectly quiet, I 
shall shoot you through the heart, if you have 
got one.” Says he, “You won’t do murder, 
Captain Ravender?” “No, sir,” says I, “I 
won’t murder forty-four people to humour 
you, but I’ll shoot you to save them.” After 
that, he was quiet, and stood shivering a little 
way off, until I named him to go over the 
side. 
</p>
<p>
The Long-boat being cast off, the Surf-boat 
was soon filled. There only remained aboard 
the Golden Mary, John Mullion the man 
who had kept on burning the blue-lights (and 
who had lighted every new one at every old 
one before it went out, as quietly as if he had 
been at an illumination); John Steadiman; 
and myself. I hurried those two into the 
Surf-boat, called to them to keep off, and 
waited with a grateful and relieved heart for 
the Long-boat to come and take me in, if she 
could. I looked at my watch, and it showed 
me, by the blue-light, ten minutes past two. 
They lost no time. As soon as she was near 
enough, I swung myself in to her, and called 
to the men, “With a will, lads! She’s reeling!” 
We were not an inch too far out of 
the inner vortex of her going down, when, by 
the blue-light which John Mullion still burnt 
in the bow of the Surf-boat, we saw her 
lurch, and plunge to the bottom head-
foremost. The child cried, weeping wildly, 
“O the dear Golden Mary! O look at her! 
Save her! Save the poor Golden Mary!” 
And then the light burnt out, and the black 
dome seemed to come down upon us. 
</p>
<p>
I suppose if we had all stood a-top of a 
mountain, and seen the whole remainder of 
the world sink away from under us, we could 
hardly have felt more shocked and solitary 
than we did when we knew we were alone 
on the wide ocean, and that the beautiful 
ship in which most of us had been securely 
asleep within half an hour was gone for ever. 
There was an awful silence in our boat, and 
such a kind of palsy on the rowers and the 
man at the rudder, that I felt they were 
scarcely keeping her before the sea. I spoke 
out then, and said, “Let every one here thank 
the Lord for our preservation!” All the 
voices answered (even the child’s), “We thank 
the Lord!” I then said the Lord’s Prayer, 
and all hands said it after me with a solemn 
murmuring. Then I gave the word “Cheerily, 
O men, Cherrily!” and I felt that they were 
handling the boat again as a boat ought to be 
handled. 
</p>
<p>
The Surf-boat now burnt another blue-
light to show us where they were, and we 
made for her, and laid ourselves as nearly 
alongside of her as we dared. I had always 
kept my boats with a coil or two of good 
stout stuff in each of them, so both boats 
had a rope at hand. We made a shift, with 
much labor and trouble, to get near 
enough to one another to divide the blue-
lights (they were no use after that night, for 
the sea-water soon got at them), and to get a 
tow-rope out between us. All night long we 
kept together, sometimes obliged to cast off 
the rope, and sometimes getting it out again, 
and all of us wearying for the morning--which 
appeared so long in coming that old Mr. Rarx 
screamed out, in spite of his fears of me, 
“The world is drawing to an end, and the 
sun will never rise any more!” 
</p>
<p>
When the day broke, I found that we were 
all huddled together in a miserable manner. 
We were deep in the water; being, as I found 
on mustering, thirty-one in number, or at 
least six too many. In the Surf-boat they 
were fourteen in number, being at least four 
too many. The first thing I did, was to get 
myself passed to the rudder--which I took from 
that time--and to get Mrs. Atherfield, her 
child, and Miss Coleshaw, passed on to sit 
next me. As to old Mr. Rarx, I put him in 
the bow, as far from us as I could. And I put 
some of the best men near us, in order that if 
I should drop, there might be a skilful hand 
ready to take the helm. 
</p>
<p>
The sea moderating as the sun came 
up, though the sky was cloudy and wild, we 
spoke the other boat, to know what stores 
they had, and to overhaul what we had. I 
had a compass in my pocket, a small 
telescope, a double-barrelled pistol, a knife, and a 
fire-box and matches. Most of my men had 
knives, and some had a little tobacco: some, a 
pipe as well. We had a mug among us, and 
an iron-spoon. As to provisions, there were 
in my boat two bags of biscuit, one piece of 
raw beef, one piece of raw pork, a bag of 
coffee, roasted but not ground (thrown in, I 
imagine, by mistake, for something else), two 
small casks of water, and about half-a-gallon 
of rum in a keg. The Surf-boat, having 
rather more rum than we, and fewer to drink 
it, gave us, as I estimated, another quart into 
our keg. In return, we gave them three 
double-handfuls of coffee, tied up in a piece of 
a handkerchief; they reported that they had 
aboard besides, a bag of biscuit, a piece of beef, 
a small cask of water, a small box of lemons, 
and a Dutch cheese. It took a long time 
to make these exchanges, and they were not 
made without risk to both parties; the sea 
running quite high enough to make our 
approaching near to one another very hazardous. 
In the bundle with the coffee, I 
conveyed to John Steadiman (who had a ship’s 
compass with him), a paper written in 
pencil, and torn from my pocket-book, 
containing the course I meant to steer, in the 
hope of making land, or being picked up by 
some vessel--I say in the hope, though I had 
little hope of either deliverance. I then 
sang out to him, so as all might hear, that if 
we two boats could live or die together, we 
would; but, that if we should be parted by 
the weather, and join company no more, they 
should have our prayers and blessings, and 
we asked for theirs. We then gave them 
three cheers, which they returned, and I saw 
the men’s heads droop in both boats as they 
fell to their oars again. 
</p>
<p>
These arrangements had occupied the general 
attention advantageously for all, though 
(as I expressed in the last sentence) they 
ended in a sorrowful feeling. I now said a 
few words to my fellow-voyagers on the 
subject of the small stock of food on which our 
lives depended if they were preserved from 
the great deep, and on the rigid necessity of 
our eking it out in the most frugal manner. 
One and all replied that whatever allowance 
I thought best to lay down should be strictly 
kept to. We made a pair of scales out of a 
thin scrap of iron-plating and some twine, 
and I got together for weights such of the 
heaviest buttons among us as I calculated 
made up some fraction over two ounces. This 
was the allowance of solid food served out 
once a-day to each, from that time to the end; 
with the addition of a coffee-berry, or 
sometimes half a one, when the weather was very 
fair, for breakfast. We had nothing else 
whatever, but half a pint of water each per 
day, and sometimes, when we were coldest 
and weakest, a teaspoonful of rum each, 
served out as a dram. I know how learnedly 
it can be shown that rum is poison, but I 
also know that in this case, as in all similar 
cases I have ever read of--which are 
numerous--no words can express the comfort and 
support derived from it. Nor have I the 
least doubt that it saved the lives of far 
more than half our number. Having 
mentioned half a pint of water as our daily 
allowance, I ought to observe that sometimes 
we had less, and sometimes we had more; for, 
much rain fell, and we caught it in a canvas 
stretched for the purpose. 
</p>
<p>
Thus, at that tempestuous time of the 
year, and in that tempestuous part of the 
world, we shipwrecked people rose and fell 
with the waves. It is not my intention 
to relate (if I can avoid it), such circumstances 
appertaining to our doleful condition 
as have been better told in many other narratives 
of the kind than I can be expected to tell 
them. I will only note, in so many passing 
words, that day after day and night after 
night, we received the sea upon our backs to 
prevent it from swamping the boat; that 
one party was always kept baling, and that 
every hat and cap among us soon got worn 
out, though patched up fifty times, as the 
only vessels we had for that service; that 
another party lay down in the bottom of the 
boat, while a third rowed; and that we were 
soon all in boils and blisters and rags. 
</p>
<p>
The other boat was a source of such 
anxious interest to all of us that I used to 
wonder whether, if we were saved, the time 
could ever come when the survivors in this 
boat of ours could be at all indifferent to the 
fortunes of the survivors in that. We got out 
a tow-rope whenever the weather permitted, 
but that did not often happen, and how we 
two parties kept within the same horizon, as 
we did, He, who mercifully permitted it to 
be so for our consolation, only knows. I 
never shall forget the looks with which, when 
the morning light came, we used to gaze 
about us over the stormy waters, for the other 
boat. We once parted company for seventy-
two hours, and we believed them to have 
gone down, as they did us. The joy on both 
sides when we came within view of one 
another again, had something in a manner 
Divine in it; each was so forgetful of 
individual suffering, in tears of delight 
and sympathy for the people in the other 
boat. 
</p>
<p>
I have been wanting to get round to the 
individual or personal part of my subject, as 
I call it, and the foregoing incident puts me 
in the right way. The patience and good 
disposition aboard of us, was wonderful. I 
was not surprised by it in the women; for, all 
men born of women know what great 
qualities they will show when men will fail; 
but, I own I was a little surprised by it in some 
of the men. Among one-and-thirty people 
assembled at the best of times, there will 
usually, I should say, be two or three 
uncertain tempers. I knew that I had more 
than one rough temper with me among my 
own people, for I had chosen those for the 
Long-boat that I might have them under my 
eye. But, they softened under their misery, 
and were as considerate of the ladies, and as 
compassionate of the child, as the best among 
us, or among men--they could not have been 
more so. I heard scarcely any complaining. 
The party lying down would moan a good 
deal in their sleep, and I would often notice 
a man--not always the same man, it is to be 
understood, but nearly all of them at one 
time or other--sitting moaning at his oar, or 
in his place, as he looked mistily over the 
sea. When it happened to be long before I 
could catch his eye, he would go on moaning 
all the time in the dismallest manner; but, 
when our looks met, he would brighten and 
leave off. I almost always got the impression 
that he did not know what sound he had 
been making, but that he thought he had 
been humming a tune. 
</p>
<p>
Our sufferings from cold and wet were far 
greater than our sufferings from hunger. 
We managed to keep the child warm; but, I 
doubt if any one else among us ever was 
warm for five minutes together; and the 
shivering, and the chattering of teeth, were 
sad to hear. The child cried a little at first 
for her lost playfellow, The Golden Mary; 
but hardly ever whimpered afterwards; and 
when the state of the weather made it 
possible, she used now and then to be held up in 
the arms of some of us, to look over the sea 
for John Steadiman’s boat. I see the golden 
hair and the innocent face now, between me 
and the driving clouds, like an Angel going 
to fly away. 
</p>
<p>
It had happened on the second day, towards 
night, that Mrs. Atherfield, in getting Little 
Lucy to sleep, sang her a song. She had a 
soft, melodious voice, and, when she had 
finished it, our people up and begged for 
another. She sang them another, and 
after it had fallen dark ended with the 
Evening Hymn. From that time, whenever 
anything could be heard above the sea and 
wind, and while she had any voice left, nothing 
would serve the people but that she should 
sing at sunset. She always did, and always 
ended with the Evening Hymn. We mostly 
took up the last line, and shed tears when it 
was done, but not miserably. We had 
a prayer night and morning, also, when the 
weather allowed of it. 
</p>
<p>
Twelve nights and eleven days we had been 
driving in the boat, when old Mr. Rarx began 
to be delirious, and to cry out to me to throw 
the gold overboard or it would sink us, and 
we should all be lost. For days past the child 
had been declining, and that was the great 
cause of his wildness. He had been over and 
over again shrieking out to me to give her 
all the remaining meat, to give her all the 
remaining rum, to save her at any cost, or we 
should all be ruined. At this time, she lay in 
her mother’s arms at my feet. One of her 
little hands was almost always creeping 
about her mother's neck or chin. I had 
watched the wasting of the little hand, and I 
knew it was nearly over. 
</p>
<p>
The old man’s cries were so discordant 
with the mother’s love and submission, that 
I called out to him in an angry voice, unless 
he held his peace on the instant, I would 
order him to be knocked on the head and 
thrown overboard. He was mute then, until 
the child died, very peacefully, an hour 
afterwards: which was known to all in the boat 
by the mother’s breaking out into lamentations 
for the first time since the wreck--for, she 
had great fortitude and constancy, though 
she was a little gentle woman. Old Mr. 
Rarx then became quite ungovernable, tearing 
what rags he had on him, raging in 
imprecations, and calling to me that if I had 
thrown the gold overboard (always the gold 
with him!) I might have saved the child, 
“And now,” says he, in a terrible voice, 
“we shall founder, and all go to the 
Devil, for our sins will sink us, when we have 
no innocent child to bear us up!” We so 
discovered with amazement, that this old 
wretch had only cared for the life of the 
pretty little creature dear to all of us, because 
of the influence he superstitiously hoped she 
might have in preserving him! Altogether 
it was too much for the smith or armourer, 
who was sitting next the old man, to bear. 
He took him by the throat and rolled him 
under the thwarts, where he lay still enough 
for hours afterwards. 
</p>
<p>
All that thirteenth night, Miss Coleshaw, 
lying across my knees as I kept the helm, 
comforted and supported the poor mother. 
Her child, covered with a pea-jacket of mine, 
lay in her lap. It troubled me all night to 
think that there was no Prayer-Book among 
us, and that I could remember but very few 
of the exact words of the burial service. 
When I stood up at broad day, all knew 
what was going to be done, and I noticed 
that my poor fellows made the motion of 
uncovering their heads, though their heads 
had been stark bare to the sky and sea for 
many a weary hour. There was a long heavy 
swell on, but otherwise it was a fair morning, 
and there were broad fields of sunlight on the 
waves in the east. I said no more than this. 
“I am the Resurrection and the Life, saith 
the Lord. He raised the daughter of Jairus 
the ruler, and said she was not dead but 
slept. He raised the widow’s son. He arose 
himself, and was seen of many. He loved 
little children, saying Suffer them to come 
unto me and rebuke them not, for of such is 
the kingdom of Heaven. In His name, my 
friends, and committed to His merciful 
goodness!” With those words I laid my rough 
face softly on the placid little forehead, and 
buried the Golden Lucy in the grave of the 
Golden Mary. 
</p>
<p>
Having had it on my mind to relate the end 
of this dear little child, I have omitted 
something from its exact place, which I will 
supply here. It will come quite as well here 
as anywhere else. 
</p>
<p>
Foreseeing that if the boat lived through 
the stormy weather, the time must come, and 
soon come, when we should have absolutely 
no morsel to eat, I had one momentous 
point often in my thoughts. Although I had, 
years before that, fully satisfied myself that 
the instances in which human beings in the 
last distress have fed upon each other, are 
exceedingly few, and have very seldom indeed 
(if ever) occurred when the people in distress, 
however dreadful their extremity, have been 
accustomed to moderate forbearance and 
restraint--I say, though I had, long before, 
quite satisfied my mind on this topic, I felt 
doubtful whether there might not have been 
in former cases some harm and danger from 
keeping it out of sight and pretending not to 
think of it. I felt doubtful whether some 
minds, growing weak with fasting and 
exposure, and having such a terrific idea to dwell 
upon in secret, might not magnify it until it 
got to have an awful attraction about it. 
This was not a new thought of mine, for it 
had grown out of my reading. However, it 
came over me stronger than it had ever 
done before--as it had reason for doing--
in the boat, and on the fourth day I 
decided that I would bring out into the 
light that unformed fear which must have 
been more or less darkly in every brain 
among us. Therefore, as a means of beguiling 
the time and inspiring hope, I gave them the 
best summary in my power of Bligh’s voyage 
of more than three thousand miles, in an 
open boat, after the Mutiny of the Bounty, 
and of the wonderful preservation of that 
boat’s crew. They listened throughout with 
great interest, and I concluded by telling 
them, that, in my opinion, the happiest 
circumstance in the whole narrative was, 
that Bligh, who was no delicate man 
either, had solemnly placed it on 
record therein that he was sure and certain 
that under no conceivable circumstances 
whatever, would that emaciated party who 
had gone through all the pains of famine, have 
preyed on one another. I cannot describe 
the visible relief which this spread through 
the boat, and how the tears stood in every 
eye. From that time I was as well convinced 
as Bligh himself that there was no danger, 
and that this phantom, at any rate, did not 
haunt us. 
</p>
<p>
Now, it was a part of Bligh’s experience 
that when the people in his boat were most 
cast down, nothing did them so much good as 
hearing a story told by one of their number. 
When I mentioned that, I saw that it struck 
the general attention as much as it did my 
own, for I had not thought of it until I came 
to it in my summary. This was on the day 
after Mrs. Atherfield first sang to us. I 
proposed that whenever the weather would 
permit, we should have a story two hours 
after dinner (I always issued the allowance I 
have mentioned, at one o’clock and called it 
by that name), as well as our song at sunset. 
The proposal was received with a cheerful 
satisfaction that warmed my heart within 
me; and I do not say too much when I say 
that those two periods in the four-and-twenty 
hours were expected with positive pleasure, 
and were really enjoyed, by all hands. 
Spectres as we soon were in our bodily 
wasting, our imaginations did not perish like 
the gross flesh upon our bones. Music and 
Adventure, two of the great gifts of 
Providence to mankind, could charm us long after 
that was lost. 
</p>
<p>
The wind was almost always against us after 
the second day; and for many days together 
we could not nearly hold our own. We had 
all varieties of bad weather. We had rain, 
hail, snow, wind, mist, thunder and lightning. 
Still the boats lived through the heavy seas, 
and still we perishing people rose and fell 
with the great waves. 
</p>
<p>
Sixteen nights and fifteen days, twenty 
nights and nineteen days, twenty-four nights 
and twenty-three days. So the time went on. 
Disheartening as I knew that our progress, 
or want of progress, must be, I never deceived 
them as to my calculations of it. In the first 
place, I felt that we were all too near 
eternity for deceit; in the second place, I knew 
that if I failed, or died, the man who followed 
me must have a knowledge of the true state 
of things to begin upon. When I told them 
at noon, what I reckoned we had made or 
lost, they generally received what I said, in 
a tranquil and resigned manner, and always 
gratefully towards me. It was not unusual 
at any time of the day for some one to burst 
out weeping loudly without any new cause, 
and, when the burst was over, to calm down 
a little better than before. I had seen 
exactly the same thing in a house of mourning. 
</p>
<p>
During the whole of this time, old Mr. 
Rarx had had his fits of calling out to me to 
throw the gold (always the gold!) overboard, 
and of heaping violent reproaches upon me 
for not having saved the child; but, now, 
the food being all gone, and I having nothing 
left to serve out but a bit of coffee-berry 
now and then, he began to be too weak to 
do this, and consequently fell silent. Mrs. 
Atherneld and Miss Coleshaw generally 
lay, each with an arm across one of my 
knees, and her head upon it. They never 
complained at all. Up to the time of her 
child’s death, Mrs. Atherfield had bound 
up her own beautiful hair every day; and I 
took particular notice that this was always 
before she sang her song at night, when 
every one looked at her. But, she never did 
it after the loss of her darling; and it would 
have been now all tangled with dirt and 
wet, but that Miss Coleshaw was careful of 
it long after she was herself, and would 
sometimes smooth it down with her weak 
thin hands. 
</p>
<p>
We were past mustering a story now; but, 
one day, at about this period, I reverted to 
the superstition of old Mr. Rarx, concerning 
the Golden Lucy, and told them that nothing 
vanished from the eye of God, though much 
might pass away from the eyes of men. 
“We were all of us,” says I, “children once; 
and our baby feet have strolled in green 
woods ashore; and our baby hands have 
gathered flowers in gardens, where the birds 
were singing. The children that we were, 
are not lost to the great knowledge of our 
Creator. Those innocent creatures will 
appear with us before Him, and plead for us. 
What we were in the best time of our 
generous youth will arise and go with us too. 
The purest part of our lives will not desert 
us at the pass to which all of us here 
present are gliding. What we were then, 
will be as much in existence before Him, 
as what we are now.” They were no less 
comforted by this consideration, than I was 
myself; and Miss Coleshaw, drawing my ear 
nearer to her lips, said, “Captain Ravender, 
I was on my way to marry a disgraced and 
broken man, whom I dearly loved when he 
was honorable and good. Your words seem 
to have come out of my own poor heart.” 
She pressed my hand upon it, smiling. 
</p>
<p>
Twenty-seven nights and twenty-six days. 
We were in no want of rain-water, but we 
had nothing else. Aud yet, even now, I 
never turned my eyes upon a waking face 
but it tried to brighten before mine. O! 
what a thing it is, in a time of danger, 
and in the presence of death, the shining 
of a face upon a face! I have heard 
it broached that orders should be given in 
great new ships by electric telegraph. I 
admire machinery as much as any man, and 
am as thankful to it as any man can be for 
what it does for us. But, it will never be a 
substitute for the face of a man, with his soul 
in it, encouraging another man to be brave 
and true. Never try it for that. It will 
break down like a straw. 
</p>
<p>
I now began to remark certain changes in 
myself which I did not like. They caused 
me much disquiet. I often saw the Golden 
Lucy in the air above the boat. I often saw 
her I have spoken of before, sitting beside 
me. I saw the Golden Mary go down as she 
really had gone down, twenty times in a day. 
And yet the sea was mostly, to my thinking, 
not sea neither, but moving country and 
extraordinary mountainous regions, the like 
of which have never been beheld. I felt it time 
to leave my last words regarding John Steadiman, 
in case any lips should last out to repeat 
them to any living ears. I said that John 
had told me (as he had on deck) that he had 
sung out “Breakers ahead!” the instant 
they were audible, and had tried to wear 
ship, but she struck before it could be done. 
(His cry, I dare say, had made my dream.) 
I said that the circumstances were altogether 
without warning and out of any course that 
could have been guarded against; that 
the same loss would have happened if I 
had been in charge; and that John was 
not to blame, but from first to last had 
done his duty nobly, like the man he 
was. I tried to write it down in my pocket-
book, but could make no words, though I 
knew what the words were that I wanted to 
make. When it had come to that, her 
hands--though she was dead so long--laid 
me down gently in the bottom of the boat, 
and she and the Golden Lucy swung me to 
sleep. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE WRECK <br/>[John Steadiman's Account]</title>
<p>
<i>All that follows, was written by John Steadiman, Chief Mate:</i>
</p>
<p>
O<sc>N</sc> the twenty-sixth day after the foundering 
of the Golden Mary at sea, I, John Steadiman, 
was sitting in my place in the stern-
sheets of the Surf-boat, with just sense 
enough left in me to steer--that is to say, 
with my eyes strained, wide-awake, over the 
bows of the boat, and my brains fast asleep and 
dreaming--when I was roused upon a sudden 
by our second mate, Mr. William Rames. 
</p>
<p>
“Let me take a spell in your place,” says 
he. “And look you out for the Long-boat, 
astern. The last time she rose on the crest 
of a wave, I thought I made out a signal 
flying aboard her.” 
</p>
<p>
We shifted our places, clumsily and slowly 
enough, for we were both of us weak and 
dazed with wet, cold, and hunger. I waited 
some time, watching the heavy rollers astern, 
before the Long-boat rose a-top of one of 
them at the same time with us. At last, she 
was heaved up for a moment well in view, 
and there, sure enough, was the signal flying 
aboard of her--a strip of rag of some sort, 
rigged to an oar, and hoisted in her bows. 
</p>
<p>
“What does it mean?” says Rames to me 
in a quavering, trembling sort of voice. “Do 
they signal a sail in sight?” 
</p>
<p>
“Hush, for God's sake!” says I, clapping 
my hand over his mouth. “Don't let the 
people hear you. They’ll all go mad together 
if we mislead them about that signal. Wait 
a bit, till I have another look at it.” 
</p>
<p>
I held on by him, for he had set me all of 
a tremble with his notion of a sail in sight, 
and watched for the Long-boat again. Up 
she rose on the top of another roller. I made 
out the signal clearly, that second time, and 
saw that it was rigged half-mast high. 
</p>
<p>
“Rames,” says I, “it's a signal of distress. 
Pass the word forward to keep her before 
the sea, and no more. We must get the 
Long-boat within hailing distance of us, as 
soon as possible.” 
</p>
<p>
I dropped down into my old place at the 
tiller without another word--for the thought 
went through me like a knife that something 
had happened to Captain Ravender. I should 
consider myself unworthy to write another 
line of this statement, if I had not made up 
my mind to speak the truth, the whole truth, 
and nothing but the truth--and I must, 
therefore, confess plainly that now, for the 
first time, my heart sank within me. This 
weakness on my part was produced in some 
degree, as I take it, by the exhausting effects of 
previous anxiety and grief. 
</p>
<p>
Our provisions--if I may give that name 
to what we had left--were reduced to the 
rind of one lemon and about a couple of 
handsfull of coffee-berries. Besides these 
great distresses, caused by the death, the 
danger, and the suffering among my crew 
and passengers, I had had a little distress of 
my own to shake me still more, in the death 
of the child whom I had got to be very fond 
of on the voyage out--so fond that I was 
secretly a little jealous of her being taken in 
the Long-boat instead of mine when the 
ship foundered. It used to be a great 
comfort to me, and I think to those with me 
also, after we had seen the last of the Golden 
Mary, to see the Golden Lucy, held up by the 
men in the Long-boat, when the weather 
allowed it, as the best and brightest sight they 
had to show. She looked, at the distance we 
saw her from, almost like a little white bird in 
the air. To miss her for the first time, when 
the weather lulled a little again, and we all 
looked out for our white bird and looked 
in vain, was a sore disappointment. To 
see the men’s heads bowed down and the 
captain’s hand pointing into the sea when we 
hailed the Long-boat, a few days after, gave 
me as heavy a shock and as sharp a pang of 
heartache to bear as ever I remember suffering 
in all my life. I only mention these 
things to show that if I did give way a little 
at first, under the dread that our captain 
was lost to us, it was not without having 
been a good deal shaken beforehand by more 
trials of one sort or another than often fall 
to one man’s share. 
</p>
<p>
I had got over the choking in my throat with 
the help of a drop of water, and had steadied 
my mind again so as to be prepared against 
the worst, when I heard the hail (Lord help 
the poor fellows, how weak it sounded!)--
</p>
<p>
“Surf-boat, ahoy!” 
</p>
<p>
I looked up, and there were our 
companions in misfortune tossing abreast of us; 
not so near that we could make out the 
features of any of them, but near enough, 
with some exertion for people in our 
condition, to make their voices heard in the 
intervals when the wind was weakest. 
</p>
<p>
I answered the hail, and waited a bit, and 
heard nothing, and then sung out the 
captain’s name. The voice that replied did not 
sound like his; the words that reached us were: 
</p>
<p>
“Chief-mate wanted on board!” 
</p>
<p>
Every man of my crew knew what that 
meant as well as I did. As second officer in 
command, there could be but one reason for 
wanting me on board the Long-boat. A 
groan went all round us, and my men looked 
darkly in each other’s faces, and whispered 
under their breaths: 
</p>
<p>
“The captain is dead!” 
</p>
<p>
I commanded them to be silent, and not to 
make too sure of bad news, at such a pass as 
things had now come to with us. Then, 
hailing the Long-boat, I signified that I was 
ready to go on board when the weather 
would let me--stopped a bit to draw a good 
long breath--and then called out as loud as I 
could the dreadful question--
</p>
<p>
“Is the captain dead?” 
</p>
<p>
The black figures of three or four men in 
the after-part of the Long-boat all stooped 
down together as my voice reached them. 
They were lost to view for about a minute; 
then appeared again--one man among them 
was held up on his feet by the rest, and 
he hailed back the blessed words (a very 
faint hope went a very long way with people 
in our desperate situation): 
</p>
<p>
“Not yet!” 
</p>
<p>
The relief felt by me, and by all with me, 
when we knew that our captain, though 
unfitted for duty, was not lost to us, it is not 
in words--at least, not in such words as a 
man like me can command--to express. I 
did my best to cheer the men by telling them 
what a good sign it was that we were not as 
badly off yet as we had feared; and then 
communicated what instructions I had to 
give, to William Rames, who was to be left in 
command in my place when I took charge of 
the Long-boat. After that, there was nothing 
to be done, but to wait for the chance of the 
wind dropping at sunset, and the sea going 
down afterwards, so as to enable our weak 
crews to lay the two boats alongside of each 
other, without undue risk--or, to put it 
plainer, without saddling ourselves with the 
necessity for any extraordinary exertion of 
strength or skill. Both the one and the 
other had now been starved out of us for 
days and days together. 
</p>
<p>
At sunset the wind suddenly dropped, but 
the sea, which had been running high for so 
long a time past, took hours after that before 
it showed any signs of getting to rest. The 
moon was shining, the sky was wonderfully 
clear, and it could not have been, according 
to my calculations, far off midnight, when the 
long, slow, regular swell of the calming ocean 
fairly set in, and I took the responsibility of 
lessening the distance between the Long-boat 
and ourselves. 
</p>
<p>
It was, I dare say, a delusion of mine; but 
I thought I had never seen the moon shine 
so white and ghastly anywhere, either at sea 
or on land, as she shone that night while we 
were approaching our companions in misery. 
When there was not much more than a boat’s 
length between us, and the white light 
streamed cold and clear over all our faces, 
both crews rested on their oars with one 
great shudder, and stared over the gunwale 
of either boat, panic-stricken at the first sight 
of each other. 
</p>
<p>
“Any lives lost among you?” I asked, in 
the midst of that frightful silence. 
</p>
<p>
The men in the Long-boat, huddled together 
like sheep at the sound of my voice. 
</p>
<p>
“None yet, but the child, thanks be to 
God!” answered one among them. 
</p>
<p>
And at the sound of his voice, all my men 
shrank together like the men in the Long-
boat. I was afraid to let the horror produced by 
our first meeting at close quarters after the 
dreadful changes that wet, cold, and famine 
had produced, last one moment longer than 
could be helped; so, without giving time for 
anymore questions and answers, I commanded 
the men to lay the two boats close alongside 
of each other. When I rose up and 
committed the tiller to the hands of Rames, all my 
poor fellows raised their white faces imploringly 
to mine. “Don't leave us, sir,” they 
said, “don't leave us.” “I leave you,” says I, 
“under the command and the guidance of 
Mr. William Rames, as good a sailor as I am, 
and as trusty and kind a man as ever stepped. 
Do your duty by him, as you have done 
it by me; and, remember, to the last, that 
while there is life there is hope. God bless 
and help you all!” With those words, I 
collected what strength I had left, caught at 
two arms that were held out to me, and so 
got from the stern-sheets of one boat into the 
stern-sheets of the other. 
</p>
<p>
“Mind where you step, sir,” whispered 
one of the men who had helped me into the 
Long-boat. I looked down as he spoke. 
Three figures were huddled up below me, 
with the moonshine falling on them in ragged 
streaks through the gaps between the men 
standing or sitting above them. The first 
face I made out was the face of Miss 
Coleshaw, her eyes were wide open, and fixed 
on me. She seemed still to keep her 
senses, and, by the alternate parting and 
closing of her lips, to be trying to speak, but 
I could not hear that she uttered a single 
word. On her shoulder rested the head of 
Mrs. Atherfield. The mother of our poor 
little Golden Lucy must, I think, have been 
dreaming of the child she had lost; for there 
was a faint smile just ruffling the white 
stillness of her face, when I first saw it turned 
upward, with peaceful closed eyes towards the 
heavens. From her, I looked down a little, 
and there, with his head on her lap, and with 
one of her hands resting tenderly on his 
cheek--there lay the Captain, to whose help 
and guidance, up to this miserable time, we had 
never looked in vain,--there, worn out at last 
in our service, and for our sakes, lay the best 
and bravest man of all our company. I stole 
my hand in gently through his clothes and 
laid it on his heart, and felt a little feeble 
warmth over it, though my cold, dulled, 
touch could not detect even the faintest beating. 
The two men in the stern-sheets with 
me, noticing what I was doing--knowing 
I loved him like a brother--and seeing, I 
suppose, more distress in my face than I 
myself was conscious of its showing, lost 
command over themselves altogether, and 
burst into a piteous moaning, sobbing 
lamentation over him. One of the two drew aside 
a jacket from his feet, and showed me that 
they were bare, except where a wet, ragged 
strip of stocking still clung to one of them. 
When the ship struck the Iceberg, he had 
run on deck, leaving his shoes in his cabin. 
All through the voyage in the boat his 
feet had been unprotected; and not 
a soul had discovered it until he dropped! 
As long as he could keep his eyes open, the 
very look of them had cheered the men, and 
comforted and upheld the women. Not one 
living creature in the boat, with any sense 
about him, but had felt the good influence of 
that brave man in one way or another. Not 
one but had heard him, over and over again, 
give the credit to others which was due only 
to himself; praising this man for patience, 
and thanking that man for help, when the 
patience and the help had really and truly, 
as to the best part of both, come only from 
him. All this, and much more, I heard 
pouring confusedly from the men’s lips while 
they crouched down, sobbing and crying 
over their commander, and wrapping the 
jacket as warmly and tenderly as they could 
over his cold feet. It went to my heart to 
check them; but I knew that if this lamenting 
spirit spread any further, all chance of 
keeping alight any last sparks of hope and 
resolution among the boat’s company would 
be lost for ever. Accordingly I sent them to 
their places, spoke a few encouraging words 
to the men forward, promising to serve out, 
when the morning came, as much as I dared 
of any eatable thing left in the lockers; 
called to Rames, in my old boat, to keep 
as near us as he safely could; drew the 
garments and coverings of the two poor 
suffering women more closely about them; 
and, with a secret prayer to be directed 
for the best in bearing the awful 
responsibility now laid on my shoulders, took my 
Captain’s vacant place at the helm of the 
Long-boat. 
</p>
<p>
This, as well as I can tell it, is the full and 
true account of how I came to be placed in 
charge of the lost passengers and crew of The 
Golden Mary, on the morning of the twenty-
seventh day after the ship struck the Iceberg, 
and foundered at sea. 
</p>
<p>
Before I go on to relate what happened 
after the two boats were under my command, 
I will stop a little here, for the purpose of adding 
some pages of writing to the present 
narrative, without which it would not be, in my 
humble estimation, complete. I allude to 
some little record of the means by which--
before famine and suffering dulled our 
ears and silenced our tongues--we shortened 
the weary hours, and helped each other to 
forget, for a while, the dangers that 
encompassed us. The stories to which Captain 
Ravender has referred, as having been 
related by the people in his boat, were matched 
by other stories, related by the people in 
my boat; and, in both cases, as I well know, 
the good effect of our following, in this 
matter, the example of Bligh and his men, 
when they were adrift like us, was of unspeakable 
importance in keeping up our spirits, 
and, by consequence, in giving us the courage 
which was necessary, under Providence, to 
the preservation of our lives. I shall therefore 
ask permission, before proceeding to the 
account of our Deliverance, to reproduce in this 
place three or four of the most noteworthy of 
the stories which circulated among us. Some, 
I give from my remembrance; some, which I 
did not hear, from the remembrance of others. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BEGUILEMENT IN THE BOATS <br/>[The Armourer's Story]</title>
<p>
I <sc>COME FROM</sc> A<sc>SHBROOKE</sc>. (It was 
the Armourer who spun this yarn.) Dear 
me! how many years back is that? Twenty 
years ago it must be now--long before I ever 
thought of going to sea--before I let 
rambling notions get into my head when I 
used to walk up the street singing, and 
thinking of the time when I should come to 
have a forge of my own. 
</p>
<p>
It was a pretty sight to look down 
Ashbrooke, especially on a fine summer’s day, 
when the sun was out. Why, I’ve been told 
painters would come from miles off, purposely 
to put it down on paper, and you’d see them 
at turnings of the road, and under trees 
working away like bees. And no wonder; 
for I have seen pictures enough in my day, 
but none to go near that. I’ve often wished 
I could handle a brush like some of those 
people--just enough, you know, to make a 
little picture of it for myself, to bring about 
with me, and hang up over my hammock. 
For that matter, I am looking at it this 
moment, standing, as it might be, at the 
corner of the road, looking down the slope. 
There was the old church, just here on the 
right, with a slanting roof running to the 
ground, almost. You might walk round it 
for a month and not see a bare stone, the 
moss grew so thick all over it. It was very 
pleasant of Sundays, standing by and seeing 
the village folk trooping out of the porch, 
and hearing the organ-music playing away 
inside! Then, going down the hill, a little 
further on, you met queer, old-fashioned 
houses, with great shingle roofs. Beyond 
that, again, was a puzzling bit of building, 
like the half of a church-window, standing up 
quite stiff by itself. They used to say there 
had once been an abbey or nunnery in these 
parts, full of clergymen and clergywomen, in 
the old papist times, of course; and there 
were little bits of it sticking up all over 
the place. Then more old houses (How 
the moss did grow, to be sure!), until you 
passed by the Joyful Heart Inn, where 
every traveller pulled up to refresh himself 
and his nag. Many is the pleasant hour 
I’ve spent in the Joyful Heart, sitting in 
the cool porch with the ivy hanging down 
overhead, or by the great fireplace in the 
sanded kitchen.
</p>
<p>
There was a sort of open place in front of 
the Joyful Heart, with a market-cross in the 
middle, and a spring where the young 
women used to come for water, and stand 
talking there, telling each other the news. 
The painters used to put them down too--
spring and all; and I don’t wonder at their 
fancying them. For, when I was sitting that 
way in the porch, looking out at them, the 
red petticoats, and the queer jars, and the 
old cross, and the sun going down behind, 
made a kind of picture very pretty to 
look at. I've seen the same of it many a 
time in some of those places about the 
Spanish main, when the foreign women stood 
round about and carried their jars in the 
same fashion. Only there was no Joyful 
Heart. I always missed the Joyful Heart 
in such places. Neither was there the Great 
Forge just over the way, facing the Joyful 
Heart. I must put in a word here about 
the Forge, though I have been a long time 
coming round to the point. 
</p>
<p>
I never saw such a forge as that--never! 
It must have been another bit of the old 
Abbey--the great gate, most likely, for it 
was nothing but a huge, wide, archway. 
Very handsomely worked, though, and 
covered with moss like the rest. There was 
a little stone hutch at the top, that looked 
like a belfry. The bell was gone long ago, of 
course, but the rings were there, and the 
stauncheons, all soundly made--good work 
as I could have turned out myself. Some 
one had run up a bit of building at the back, 
which kept out the wind and made all snug, 
and there you had as handsome a forge as I 
ever came across. 
</p>
<p>
It was kept by a young man of the name 
of Whichelo--Will Whichelo. But he had 
another name besides that, and I think a 
better one. If you were to go asking 
through the village for one Will Whichelo, 
why, you would come back about as wise 
as you went; unless, indeed, you chanced 
upon the minister or the schoolmaster. No; 
but because he was always seen hard at his 
work, swinging his hammer with good-will, 
and stepping back at every stroke to get a 
better sweep--because he laid his whole soul to 
the business--the Ashbrooke folk christened 
him Ding Dong Will. He was always singing 
and at his work. Many a nice young woman 
of the village would have been glad if Ding 
Dong Will had looked her way. But he never 
took heed of any of them, or was more than 
civil and gentle with them. 
</p>
<p>
“Look ye,” he would say, leaning on his 
great hammer, “are they the creatures for 
handling cold iron, or lifting the sledge? No, 
no!” and would take up his favourite stave 
of Hammer and anvil! hammer and anvil! 
lads, yoho! 
</p>
<p>
I was but a youngster at that time, but had 
a great hankering after the iron business. I 
would be nothing else, I told my father, who 
wanted to send me up to London to learn 
accounts. I was always dropping down there, 
and would stay half the day, leaning against 
the arch and watching the forging. Coming 
along of a night, I used to get quite cheerful 
when I saw the blaze of the furnace, and the 
chinking of the iron was the finest music for 
me I ever heard--finer than the organ tunes 
even. Sometimes a dusty rider would come 
galloping in, and pull up sharp at the Forge; 
he had cast a shoe on the road, and Ding 
Dong Will would come out and take the 
horse’s measure. Then the village folk would 
get standing round, in twos and threes, all of 
them eyeing over the horse and the rider, 
too. Then he would get upon his nag once 
more, and the little crowd would open, and 
he ride away harder than he came, Ding 
Dong Will, with his hammer over his shoulder, 
looking after him till he got to the turn of 
the hill. 
</p>
<p>
At last, my father came round and gave up 
making me a clerk--it would never have 
done--and Ding Dong Will, who had a liking 
for me, agreed to take me at the Forge. I 
soon got to use the big sledge fairly enough--
nothing, of course, to Ding Dong Will; 
and so we worked away from morning till 
night, like two Jolly Millers. There was fine 
music at the Forge, when the two of us were 
at it. 
</p>
<p>
Ding Dong Will never went to the Joyful 
Heart; he said he had no time to be idle; 
but I went pretty often--that is, when the 
day was done and work over--just to have a 
talk in the cool porch, and hear what 
company was in the house. For, Miss Arthur--
Mary Arthur--she that used to sit in the 
parlour and manage the house, was never 
very stand-off to me. But she had a reason 
of her own for that, as you will see. She 
was niece to old Joe Fenton, the landlord, 
who brought her down from London to keep 
things going. In short, she was as good as 
mistress there. Folks said she kept her 
head a little high; but, to say truth, I never 
found her so. She had had her schooling 
up in London, and had learned manners with 
the best of them, so it was but nature she 
should be a stroke above the girls of the 
place. That was why they didn’t like her. 
About her looks? Ah! she was a beauty! 
Such hair--it went nigh down to her feet--
and her eyes--why they shot fire like a pair 
of stars--and she had a way of shifting them 
back and forward, and taking your measure 
at every look, that made you feel quite 
uneasy. All the young fellows were by 
the ears about her, but she never heeded or 
encouraged them; unless it might be that 
she had a leaning to one--and that was to 
Ding Dong Will opposite. No one thought 
of such a thing, she kept it so close; but she 
might as well have had a leaning to a lump 
of cold iron. 
</p>
<p>
The way I came to suspect it was this. 
The old Forge, as I said, was just fronting the 
Joyful Heart; and, every morning, as sure 
as I came down to work, I used to see her 
sitting in the bow-window, behind the white 
curtain, working with her needle. There she 
would be all the morning, for at that time 
there was nothing doing down-stairs, and, 
every now and again, she would be taking a 
sly look over at the Forge where Ding Dong 
Will was swinging his great sledge, and 
trolling his Hammer and anvil! lads, yoho! 
He was well worth looking out at, was Ding 
Dong Will. I used to tell him, “Mary Arthur 
is making eyes at you yonder--have a care, 
Will.” And he would laugh loud, and say, 
“She may find better sport elsewhere. No 
sweethearts for me, lad. Hand the file. Sing 
Hammer and anvil, yoho!” 
</p>
<p>
I never saw so insensible a fellow, never. 
But her liking slipped out in more ways than 
that. Whenever I went in, she was always 
taking notice of me, and asking about myself. 
How was I getting on at the Forge? Did I 
like the business? Did we do much? What 
kind was he, the other--he with the curious 
name? Then she would laugh, and show her 
white teeth. 
</p>
<p>
At last, one Saturday evening I was sitting 
in the porch, looking at the children playing 
in the road, when I heard a step at the 
back, and there was Mary Arthur standing 
behind me. “Resting after the week?” she said. 
</p>
<p>
“Yes, and a hard week we’ve had of it.” 
</p>
<p>
“Nothing doing at the Forge now, I 
suppose,” says she. (He had gone down to the 
green with the young fellows to throw the 
bar.) 
</p>
<p>
“No,” says I; “we’ve let the fire out, and 
will rest till Monday.” 
</p>
<p>
She stayed silent for a minute, and then--
“Why does he--Whichelo I mean--keep 
shut up that way at home?” She was 
beating her hands impatiently together. 
“What does it all mean? What do you make 
of it?” 
</p>
<p>
I stared, you may be sure, she spoke so 
sharply. 
</p>
<p>
“Does he never go out and see the world--
go to dances or merry-makings?” 
</p>
<p>
“No,” said I; “never.” 
</p>
<p>
“Well,” said she, “isn't it odd; how do you 
account for it?” 
</p>
<p>
“Well, it is odd,” I said. 
</p>
<p>
“And he so young?” 
</p>
<p>
All this while she was shifting her black 
eyes in a restless kind of way. 
</p>
<p>
“You should try,” says she, “and get him 
to mix more with the others, for your own 
sake as well as his.” 
</p>
<p>
I was going to tell her I was at him morning, 
noon, and night, when the bell rang, and 
she tripped off. 
</p>
<p>
Ding Dong Will came into the Forge that 
night, fairly tired and done up. “Beat them 
as usual!” he said, as he flung himself down 
on the bench. 
</p>
<p>
“I knew you would,” I said. 
</p>
<p>
“But it was thirsty work: some drink, for 
Heaven’s sake!” 
</p>
<p>
“There’s not a drop of malt in the house,” 
I said. 
</p>
<p>
“Well, go over and fetch some.” 
</p>
<p>
Said I, “Go yourself. I tell you what, 
there’s a nice girl there always talking of 
you; and, if you’ve anything of a man about 
you, you’ll go over and speak her softly, and 
show her you’re not what she takes you for. 
Now, there’s my mind for you, Ding Dong 
Will.” 
</p>
<p>
“Stuff,” says he, laughing; “let her mind 
her own business, and leave me to my anvil. 
I'll not go.” 
</p>
<p>
“Ah! you’re afraid,” said I--“that’s it!” 
</p>
<p>
“Afraid,” says he, starting up; “you 
know I'm not--you know I’m not. Here, 
I’ll go,” and made straight for the door. 
“Stop,” he said, turning round, “what did 
she say about taking me for a different sort 
of man?” 
</p>
<p>
“No matter now,” said I. “When you come 
back.” 
</p>
<p>
It should have been a five minutes’ job, 
that fetching the malt. But, would you 
believe it? he was close upon an hour about it. 
I knew well she had not been losing her 
time. When he came in, I began at once at 
him: “Ah, ah!” said I, “didn't I tell you? 
I knew it!” 
</p>
<p>
“Nonsense,” said he, with a foolish kind 
of laugh, “it was none of my fault. She 
kept me there with her talk, and I couldn’t 
get away.” 
</p>
<p>
“O, poor Ding Dong Will,” I said, “You 
had better have stayed away, after all!” 
</p>
<p>
“Folly!” says he, laughing more foolishly 
still; “you’ll see if she gets me there again. 
Enough about her. There!” 
</p>
<p>
I saw he was uneasy in his mind, and so 
gave him no more trouble. But I needn’t 
have been so delicate with him at all, for 
next day it was quite the other way. He 
never gave me peace or rest, sounding me 
and picking out of me what she had said of 
him. The man was clean gone from that 
hour. It’s always the way with those kind 
of men: when they are touched, they run off 
like a bit of melted metal. 
</p>
<p>
He got worse every day from that out. 
He was in and out of the Joyful Heart half 
his time, always on some excuse or other, 
and going lazily to his work, stopping every 
now and again to have a look at the white 
curtain over the way. It was a poor thing to 
see him--it was indeed; I was ashamed of 
him. At last he came to doing nothing at 
all, or next to nothing; and the great hammer 
was laid by in a corner. 
</p>
<p>
Well, this went on, it might be for a month, 
and folks in the village began to talk and wink, 
and say, what would come next, now that 
Ding Dong Will was caught at last. I tried 
to keep things going as well as I could, but 
it was of very little use. The business fell 
off; and I never will forget the sinking feel 
I got when the riders began to go straight 
on through the village--past the old Forge--
and pull up at a new place, lately opened, 
beyond the church! After all they only did 
what was natural, and went where they 
would be best attended to. By-and-by I saw 
a change coming on Ding Dong Will--a 
very odd change. With all his foolishness, he 
had been in great spirits--always laughing--
without much meaning to be sure; but, still 
as I say, in great spirits. But now, I saw 
that he was turning quite another way, 
getting quite a down-hearted, moping kind of 
manner, I couldn’t well make out. He would 
come in of an evening--very rough and sulky--
and sit down before the fire looking into 
the coals, and never open his mouth for 
hours at a time. Then he would get up and 
walk up and down, stamping and muttering--
nothing very holy, you may be sure. I 
soon guessed--indeed, I heard as much in 
the village--that she was drawing off a bit--
or else trying her play-acting upon him, 
for she was full of those kind of tricks. 
She was a very deep one, that Mary Arthur, 
and it was a pity she ever came into the 
place. She had a kind of up-and-down way 
of treating him--one time being all smiles 
and pleasantness, and next day like a lump 
of ice,--pretending not to see him when he 
came in. She made him know his place--
rolling her black eyes back and forward in 
every direction but his; then he would come 
home raging and swearing. I often wondered 
what she could be at, or what was at the 
bottom of it all; and, I believe, I would 
never have come at the truth if I didn't 
happen one day to run up against a handsome-
looking gentleman in a fisherman’s hat, just 
at the door of the Joyful Heart. They told 
me, inside, it was young Mr. Temple, of 
Temple Court,--some ten miles off,--come 
down to stop there for the fishing. 
</p>
<p>
There it was! That was the secret of all! 
He had been there nigh on a fortnight--
had come, mind you, for two or three 
days’ fishing; but the sport was so good 
he really must stay a bit longer. Quite natural--
and, you may say, quite proper! I’m thinking 
there was better sport going on in the 
parlour than ever he found in the river. 
Her head was nigh turned with it all, and 
I really believe she thought she was going 
to be Mistress of Temple Court before long--
though how a young girl that had come 
down to London, and had seen a bit of life, 
should be so short-seeing, is more than I 
can fancy. She took the notion into her 
head--that was certain--and every soul in 
the place could see what she was at, except 
the poor blind creature at the Forge; but 
even he had his eyes opened at last, for 
people now began to talk and whisper, and 
hope all was right up at the Joyful 
Heart. I heard that the minister had gone 
once to speak with her; but came out very 
red and angry. No doubt she had bidden 
him mind his own concerns, and not meddle 
with her. As to old Joe Fenton’s looking 
after his niece, he might as well have been 
cut out of a block of wood. 
</p>
<p>
One morning, just after breakfast, when 
he--Ding Dong Will--was sitting at the fire 
as usual, and not speaking a word, he turns 
round quite sharp upon me and says: 
</p>
<p>
“What is that young Jack doing all this 
time? What do you say?” 
</p>
<p>
“I’m sure I can’t tell,” I said, “unless it be 
fishing.” 
</p>
<p>
“Fishing!” said he, stamping down the 
coals with his great shoe, “like enough! 
I’ve never heard much of the fish in these 
waters.” 
</p>
<p>
“Still he does go out with a rod,” I said; 
“there’s nothing else here to amuse him, I 
suppose. But he goes on Monday.” 
</p>
<p>
“Look me in the face,” says he, catching 
me by the wrist, “you don’t believe that he’s 
come only for that?” 
</p>
<p>
“I can’t tell,” said I, “unless it is that he likes 
Mary Arthur’s company. She’s a nice girl!” 
</p>
<p>
“Ah!” said he, “I’ve been thinking so 
some time back--the false, hollow jade! 
This was at the bottom of all her tricks! But 
I tell you what,” said he, snatching his 
hammer, “let him look out, and not come in 
my way--I give him warning----” 
</p>
<p>
With this he got a bit of iron upon the 
anvil and beat away at it like a wild man. 
Then he flung it down into a corner and, 
taking his hat, walked out with great 
strides. I ran after him and took him by 
the arm, for I was in a desperate fright 
lest he should do something wicked. But 
he put me back quietly. 
</p>
<p>
“See,” said he, “I give you a caution, 
don’t meddle with me. Mind----” 
</p>
<p>
I didn’t try and stop him then, for he looked 
savage. But I followed a little behind. He 
made for the Joyful Heart; and, just as he 
came under the porch, with his head down, 
and never heeding where he was going to, he 
ran full up against somebody, who, without 
much more ado, gave him back his own, and 
flung him right against the wall. 
</p>
<p>
“Now then, young Hercules!” said a gay 
kind of voice--I knew it for Mr. Temple’s,--
“now then, look before you, will you! Keep 
the passage clear.” 
</p>
<p>
I thought the other was going to run at 
him straight, but he stopped himself quickly. 
</p>
<p>
“Who are you speaking to in that way?” 
said he, with a low kind of growl. “Is it 
your horse, or your dog, or your groom? 
Which? Are those manners?” 
</p>
<p>
“Now, Bruin,” says the young man, “no 
words. Let me pass,--I’m in a hurry.” 
</p>
<p>
“Who was it taught you,” says Ding Dong 
Will, with the same kind of growl, and not 
moving an inch,--“who taught you to call 
folk Bruins and Herculeses--eh? I declare,” 
says he, colouring up quite red, and trembling 
all over, “I’ve a mind to give you a lesson 
myself--I will, by----” 
</p>
<p>
I think he was going to spring at him this 
time, but I heard steps on the sanded floor, 
and there was Mary Arthur standing before 
us. A fine creature she looked, too. She 
was in a tearing rage--and her eyes had 
more of the devilish look in them than I had 
ever seen before. 
</p>
<p>
“For shame,” she said, to Will--“for 
shame! What do you come here for, with 
your low brawling ways. Who asks you to 
come? Who wants you? Take him away--
home--anywhere out of this!” 
</p>
<p>
It was a piteous sight to look at poor 
Ding Dong Will, staring stupidly at her, and 
breathing hard, as if there was a weight on 
his chest. 
</p>
<p>
“Mr. Temple,” says she, turning to him 
quite changed, and with a gentle smile on 
her face, “can you forgive me for all this? 
That such a thing should have happened to 
you in our house! But it shall never occur 
again! Never--never!” 
</p>
<p>
I could see he took her very easy, for he 
was looking out at something, and she had 
to say it twice over before he heard her. 
</p>
<p>
“Sweet Mary,” said he, “don’t give yourself 
a moment’s uneasiness about me. Let 
things go as they like, so that you don’t put 
yourself out.” Here he gave a kind of yawn, 
and went over to the window. 
</p>
<p>
She looked after him, biting her lip hard. 
</p>
<p>
“Why don’t you take him away, as I told 
you?” she says at last. “What does he 
want here?” 
</p>
<p>
I pitied him so much, to see him standing 
there so beaten down, that I could not help 
putting in my word. 
</p>
<p>
“Well, I must say, Miss Mary, poor Ding 
Dong Will didn’t deserve this,--from you, of 
all people.” 
</p>
<p>
“Hallo!” says Mr. Temple, coming back; 
“is this famous Ding Dong Will from over 
the way?” 
</p>
<p>
“No other, sir,” says I. 
</p>
<p>
“Here, Ding Dong Will,” says he, putting 
out his hand, “we musn’t fall out. If I had 
known it was you, you should have had the 
passage all to yourself. You’re a fine fellow, 
Will, and I’ve often admired the way you 
swung the great hammer.” 
</p>
<p>
She was biting her lips still harder than 
before, but said nothing. 
</p>
<p>
“Stop,” said he, “I have a great idea. So 
this is Ding Dong Will! Whisper a minute, 
Mary.” 
</p>
<p>
He did whisper something to her, and you 
never saw what a change it made in her. 
She turned all scarlet, and gave him such a 
wicked devilish look. 
</p>
<p>
“This is some joke,” said she, at last. 
</p>
<p>
“Not a bit of it,” says he, laughing; “not 
a bit of it. Ah! You see I know what 
goes on in the village!” 
</p>
<p>
“I couldn’t believe that you mean such a 
thing!” says she, getting white again. 
</p>
<p>
“Stuff!” said he, very impatiently. “I tell 
you, I am in earnest. Listen, Ding Dong 
Will. I must be off to London to-morrow,--
the ladies there are dying to see me, so go 
I must. Now, I know there has been 
something on between you two,--don’t tell me, 
I know all about it. So now, friend Ding 
Dong, show yourself a man of spirit, and 
settle it sharp. And I promise you, I’ll come 
down myself to give the bride away, and 
start you both comfortably.” 
</p>
<p>
It was well for him he was looking the 
other way, and didn’t see the infernal look 
she gave him out of those eyes of hers. I 
think if there had been a knife convenient, 
she would have plunged it into him at that 
minute. But she covered it all with a kind 
of forced laugh, and said she wasn’t quite 
ready to be disposed of so quickly, and then 
made some excuse to run up-stairs. Mr. 
Temple then yawned again, and went over 
to the window, and wondered would it be a 
fine night, as he had to dine out. Neither 
of us spoke to him, for he was an unfeeling 
fellow with all his generous offers. So we 
left him there, and I brought back Ding 
Dong Will to the Forge again. 
</p>
<p>
About four o’clock that same day (it was 
almost dark at that hour), when I was coming 
home from buying something in the village, 
I thought I saw him crossing over to the 
Joyful Heart; and as I passed the porch, I 
swear I saw the two of them (Mary Arthur 
and he) talking in the passage--there was 
no mistake about it--and she talking very 
eagerly. Presently, she drew him into the 
parlour, and shut the door. What could 
bring him there now, after the morning’s 
business? Well, I thought, he is a poor-
spirited creature, after all--a true spaniel! 
He didn’t come in, I suppose for an hour 
after that, and then in a wild sort of humour, 
as if he had been drinking. But what do you 
think of his denying that he had been near 
the Joyful Heart at all, or that he had seen 
her? Denied it flat! And then, when I 
pressed him on it, and asked if I wasn’t to 
trust my own eyes, he began to show his 
teeth, and get savage. I was only a youngster 
then, and so had to put up with his humours; 
but I determined to leave him on the first 
convenient excuse. Dear! how that man 
was changed in a short time! 
</p>
<p>
On this night he took a fancy that we 
should go to bed early. He was tired, he 
said, and wanted rest after the day’s trouble, 
and his heart was heavy. So I gave in to him 
at once, and we were soon snug in our little 
cots on each side of the hearth: we used to 
sleep of nights in a queer kind of place just 
off the forge, all vaulted over, with arches 
crossing one another and meeting, in a kind 
of carved bunch in the middle. This might 
have been the clergymen's pantry, or wine 
vaults, may be, in the old times. Whatever 
use they had for it, it was a very snug place. 
I recollect there were all sorts of queer faces 
with horns and hoods, all carved out in the 
bunch; and I often lay awake at nights 
looking at them, and studying them, and 
thinking why they were grinning and 
winking at me in that way. I remember one 
creature that always aimed straight at you 
with his tail pointed, holding it like a gun. 
</p>
<p>
It might have been about nine o’clock, or 
perhaps half-past eight, when we turned in. 
I know I heard the old church clock chiming 
pleasantly as we lay down. After watching 
the fire flashing up and down, and taking a 
look at the funny faces in the bunch 
overhead, I soon went sound asleep. I woke 
again, before the fire was out, and looking 
towards Will’s cot, saw that it was empty. 
A vague feeling of uneasiness mingled with 
my surprise at that discovery, and made me 
jump out of bed in a moment. I reflected for 
a little--felt more uneasy than ever--huddled 
on my clothes in a great hurry--and, without 
giving myself a moment’s time for any second 
thoughts, went out to see what had become 
of Ding Dong Will. 
</p>
<p>
He was not in the neighbourhood of the 
Forge, so I followed a steep footpath in the 
wood behind which led straight to the water’s 
edge. I walked on a little, observing that 
the moon was out and the stars shining, 
and the sky of a fine frosty blue, until I came 
to an old tree that I knew well. I had hardly 
cast a first careless look at it, before I 
started back all in a fright, for I saw at my 
feet, stretched out among the leaves, a figure 
with a fisherman’s hat beside it. I knew 
it to be young Mr. Temple, lying there 
quite dead, with his face all over blood. I 
thought I should have sunk down upon the 
earth with grief and horror, and ran farther 
along the little pathway as fast as I could 
to a place where the trees opened a little, 
full in the moonlight. There, I saw Ding 
Dong Will standing quite still and motionless, 
with his hammer on his shoulder, and 
his face covered up in his hand. 
</p>
<p>
He stayed a long time that way, without 
ever stirring, and then began to come up, 
very slowly, weeping, his eyes upon the 
ground. I felt as if I were fixed to that one 
spot, and waited till he met me full face 
to face. What a guilty start he gave!--I 
thought he would have dropped. 
</p>
<p>
“O, Will, Will! what have you been 
doing?” Some terrible thing!” 
</p>
<p>
“I--I--I, nothing!” he said, staggering 
about, and hiding his face. 
</p>
<p>
“What have you done with him--Mr. 
Temple?” I said, still holding him. He 
was trembling all over like a palsied man, 
and fell back against a tree with a deep 
groan. I saw how it was then--it was as 
good as written in his face. So I left him 
there--against the tree--and all the rest of 
that horrible night I wandered up and down 
along the roads and lanes: anything sooner 
than be under the same roof with him. At 
last morning came; and, as soon as the sun 
rose I stole back, and, looking through the 
window, found that he was gone. I never like 
to think of that night, though it is so far back. 
</p>
<p>
By noon the next day the whole town was 
in a fever: people talking and whispering at 
corners. He had been missed; but they were 
on his track, for it was well known that he 
was away among the hills hiding. They 
dragged the river all day; and, on that night, 
the body of young Mr. Temple was found; 
his head beaten in with a hammer. 
</p>
<p>
What end Will Whichelo came to, it would 
not be hard to guess. But Mary Arthur--she 
who drove him on to it, as everybody knew--
she was let away, and went up to London, 
where she lived to do mischief enough. The 
old Forge was shut up, and fell into greater 
ruin. For many a long day no one ventured 
near that part of the river walk after dark. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BEGUILEMENT IN THE BOATS <br/>[Poor Dick's Story]</title>
<p>
I<sc>T WAS THE FIFTH EVENING TOWARDS 
TWILIGHT</sc>, when poor Dick began to sing--in 
my boat, the Surf-Boat. At first nobody took 
any notice of him, and indeed he seemed 
to be singing more to himself than to any one 
else. I had never heard the tune before, 
neither have I heard it since, but it was 
beautiful. I don’t know how it might sound 
now, but then, in the twilight, darkness 
coming down on us fast, and, for aught we 
knew, death in the darkness, its simple words 
were full of meaning. The song was of a 
mother and child talking together of Heaven. 
I saw more than one gaunt face lifted up, and 
there was a great sob when it was done, as if 
everybody had held their breath to listen. 
Says Dick then, “That was my cousin Amy’s 
song, Mr. Steadiman.” 
</p>
<p>
“Then it will be a favourite of yours, 
Dick;” I replied, hazarding a guess at the 
state of the case. 
</p>
<p>
“Yes. I don't know why I sing it. 
Perhaps she put it in my mind. Do you believe 
in those things, Mr. Steadiman?” 
</p>
<p>
“In what things, Dick?” I wanted to draw 
him on to talk of himself, as he had no other 
story to tell. 
</p>
<p>
“She’s dead, Captain; and it seemed a little 
while since as if I heard her voice, far away, 
as it might be in England, singing it again; 
and when she stopped, I took it up. It must 
be fancy, you know, it could not really be.” 
Before long the night fell, and when we could 
not see each other’s faces--except by the faint 
starlight--it seemed as if poor Dick’s heart 
opened, and as if he must tell us who and 
what he was. 
</p>
<p>
Perhaps I ought to say how poor Dick came 
to be with us at all. About a week before 
we sailed, there came to Captain Ravender 
one morning at his inn, a man whom he had 
known intimately; when they two were young 
fellows. Said he, “Captain, there’s my 
nephew--poor Dick Tarrant--I want to ship 
him off to Australia, to California, or 
anywhere out of the way. He does nothing but 
get into mischief here, and bring disgrace on 
the family. Where are you bound for, next 
voyage?” Captain Ravender replied, 
California. “California is a long way off,” said 
Captain Ravender’s friend, “it will do as 
well as any place; he can dig for gold. The 
fact is, Dick has run through one fortune, and 
now a maiden-aunt, who considers the credit 
of the family, offers him three hundred pounds 
to leave England. He consents to go, and the 
best plan will be to put him under your 
charge, pay his passage and outfit, and leave 
the rest of the money in your hands to be 
given over to him when he lands at the 
diggings.” 
</p>
<p>
Captain Ravender agreed to the proposal, 
and poor Dick, who had been left standing 
outside the door, was called in and introduced. 
I came in just at that point, and saw him. He 
was the wreck of what had been a fine-looking 
young man, ten years ago, dragged down now 
by reckless dissipation to reckless poverty. His 
clothing was very shabby, his countenance 
wild and haggard, his shock of brown hair, 
rusty with neglect,--not a promising subject 
to look at. His uncle told him the arrangements 
he had made with Captain Ravender, in 
which he apparently acquiesced without much 
caring,--“North or south, east or west,” said 
he, “it was all the same to him. If he had gone 
out to India, when he had a chance a dozen 
years before, he should have been a man or a 
mouse then.” That was the only remark he 
offered. And the thing was settled. 
</p>
<p>
But when the time came to sail, poor Dick 
was not forthcoming. We sent up to his uncle’s 
house to know what was to be done, and, by-
and-by, down he came with his nephew, who 
had almost given us the slip. Until we got 
into blue water Dick was prisoner rather than 
passenger. He did not take to his banishment 
kindly, or see, as his relatives did, that 
there was a chance before him of redeeming 
a wasted life and repairing a ruined constitution. 
He was a very good-humoured, easy-
tempered fellow, and a great favourite aboard; 
and, till the time of the wreck, cheerful, 
except in the evening when he got to leaning 
over the ship’s-side, and singing all kinds of 
sentimental love-songs. I had told the men to 
keep an eye on him, and they did. I was 
afraid he might, in one of his black moods, 
try to make away with himself. 
</p>
<p>
He was the younger of two brothers, 
sons of a yeoman or gentleman-farmer in 
Cheshire; both whose parents died when they 
were quite little things, leaving them, 
however, for their station, amply provided for. 
There was two hundred pounds a-year for their 
bringing-up, till they were eighteen, when 
the sum was to be doubled, and at one-
and-twenty they were to get five thousand 
pounds a-piece to start them in the world. 
Old Miss Julian Tarrant took Tom, the elder, 
and my friend took poor Dick. Dick was a 
wild lad, idle at his book, hankering after 
play, but as kind-hearted and handsome a 
fellow as you could wish to see. Dick was 
generally better liked than Tom, who was 
steady as old Time. Both brothers were sent 
to the grammar-school of the town, near 
which they lived, and one of Dick’s discursive 
anecdotes related to the second master there, 
whom, he asserted, he should have had 
pleasure in soundly thrashing at that moment, 
in part payment of the severe punishment he 
had formerly inflicted on his idle pupil. When 
Dick was sixteen that tide in his affairs came, 
which, had he followed it out to India, 
would probably have led on to fortune. 
But Dick had an invincible tie to England. 
Precocious in everything, he was deeply in 
love with his cousin Amy, who was three 
years older than himself, and very beautiful; 
and Amy was very fond of him as of a 
younger brother. 
</p>
<p>
Said poor Dick, with a quiver in his 
voice, as he was telling his story, “She 
was the only creature in the whole world 
that ever really cared whether I lived 
or died. I worshipped the very ground she 
walked on! Tom was a clever, shrewd 
fellow--made for getting on in the world, 
and never minding anybody but himself. 
Uncle Tarrant was as hard and rigid as a 
machine, and his wife was worse--there was 
nobody nice but Amy; she was an angel! 
When I got into scrapes, and spent more 
money than I ought, she set me right with 
my uncle, and later--when it was too late 
for any good, and the rest of them treated 
me like a dog--she never gave me either a 
cold look or a hard word. Bless her!” 
</p>
<p>
For the sake of being near his cousin, Dick 
professed a wish to be a farmer like his 
cousin and father, which was quite agreeable 
to the family; and for three years more he 
stayed in his Uncle Tarrant’s house, very 
much beloved by all--though in his bitterness 
he said not--for his gaiety and light-
heart were like a charm about him. If there 
was a fault, he had friends too many, for 
most of them were of a kind not likely to 
profit a young man. 
</p>
<p>
Coming home one evening, about 
twilight, from a hunt which he had attended, 
the poor lad unexpectedly met the crisis of 
his fate. He told us this with an exactness 
of detail that made the scene he described 
like a bit of Dutch painting. I wish I could 
repeat it to you in his own words, but that 
is impossible; still I will be as exact as 
possible. 
</p>
<p>
In Mr. Tarrant’s house there was a little 
parlour especially appropriated to Amy’s use. 
It had a low window with a cushioned seat, 
from which one long step took you into the 
garden. In this parlour Amy had her piano, 
her book-case, her work-basket, her mother’s 
picture on the wall, and several of poor 
Dick’s sketches neatly framed. Dick liked 
this room better than any other in the house. 
When the difference betwixt Amy’s age and 
his seemed greater than it did now, it was 
here he used to come to be helped with, his 
lessons; and later, when his red-hot youth 
was secretly wreathing all manner of tender 
fancies about her, that he used to sit at her 
feet reading to her out of some poetry-book, 
or singing while she worked, or, perhaps, 
sang, too. These pleasant early intimacies 
had never been discontinued, for, while Dick’s 
heart was wasting its first passion on his 
cousin, she was all the while thinking of 
somebody else. He was a boy to her in point 
of age still, and this particular day ended 
his blissful delusions. 
</p>
<p>
Having put his pony in the stable, he made 
his way at once to Amy’s parlour, opening 
the door softly, for he liked to surprise her. 
Neither she nor the person with her heard 
him enter; they were too much occupied 
with themselves and each other to hear 
anything. Amy was standing in the window, 
and beside her, with his arm round her waist, 
was the straight-haired, pale-featured curate 
of the parish. It was a clear yellow twilight, 
and all about Amy’s head the lustre shone 
like a glory; her hands were down-dropt, 
and the busy fingers were plucking a rose to 
pieces, petal by petal, and scattering them on 
the carpet at her feet. She was as blushing 
herself as the poor rose, and seemed to listen 
willingly to the pleadings of her lover. Dick 
noticed the slight quivering of her lips and 
the humid glitter of her eyes when the low-
spoken, tremulous words, meant only for one 
ear, met his, and he said he felt as if all the 
blood in his body were driven violently up to 
his brain by their sound. 
</p>
<p>
The bird in its cage began trilling a loud 
song as it pecked at a spray of green which 
the evening wind blew against the wires 
through the open window, and under cover 
of its noise poor Dick stole out, leaving the 
young lovers alone in the blush of their 
acknowledged love. He went back to the 
stable, got his pony out, mounted it, and 
galloped away like mad to rejoin the 
companions he had left an hour before for Amy’s 
sake. It was not till after midnight that he 
came home, and then he was reeling drunk. 
His uncle Tarrant and Amy had sat up for 
him, and, being quarrelsome in his cups, he 
insulted the first, and would not speak to his 
cousin. Poor Dick thought to drown his 
sorrow, and this was the beginning of his 
downward course. 
</p>
<p>
The individual whom Amy had chosen to 
endow with her love had nothing about him 
particular to approve except his profession. 
All his attributes, moral, mental, and personal, 
were negative rather than positive. Poor 
Dick described him only as Straight-haired, 
as if that epithet embodied all his qualities. 
He thought that Amy did not really love 
him, but was attracted by some imaginary 
sanctity and perfection with which her 
imagination invested him. It was very likely: 
from what we see every day we may be sure 
that many women have loved, not the man 
himself they have married, but an ideal which 
he personates very indifferently indeed to all 
eyes but theirs. 
</p>
<p>
Dick could not, for many days, restrain the 
expression of his feelings. Coming one day 
suddenly on Amy in the garden where she 
was walking in maiden meditation, he stopped 
her and made her listen to his story, which 
he poured out with much exaggeration of 
epithet and manner. Amy was startled and 
distressed: she endeavoured in vain to stop 
his confession by appealing to his common 
sense of what was right. 
</p>
<p>
“Dick, you know I am engaged to Henry 
Lister--you ought not to have spoken--let 
me go!” said she, for he had grasped her 
hands tightly in his. 
</p>
<p>
“I ought not to have spoken, and I love 
you! O! cousin, you don’t know what love 
is if you say so. Amy, it will out! Amy, if 
I had come before the straight-haired parson, 
would you have listened to me then?” 
</p>
<p>
A vivid blush flew into the girl’s face, but 
she would not say a word of encouragement; 
on that blush, however, poor Dick, whether 
rightly or wrongly, contrived to found a 
renewed hope. Amy kept his avowal to herself, 
knowing well that its discovery would entail 
a total separation from her cousin; and she 
had become so accustomed to his usefulness 
and gaiety in a house where everybody else 
was chilly and methodical, that she could not 
readily part with him. I incline to think 
myself that she did like Dick better than the 
straight-haired curate for many reasons, and 
Dick himself was persuaded of it. Her 
indecision had, as may be supposed, a very 
pernicious effect on his mind and conduct. One 
day he was in the seventh heaven of hope 
and contentment, and the next he was the 
most miserable dog alive: then he would go 
and forget his griefs in a convivial bout with 
his comrades, till at length his Uncle Tarrant 
turned him out of doors. Amy had tried her 
influence with him in vain. 
</p>
<p>
“You are the cause of it, Amy, and nobody 
but you,” said Dick, passionately; “if you 
would give that straight-haired fellow warning, 
you should never have to complain of me 
again.” 
</p>
<p>
But Amy, though she fretted a great deal, 
held to her engagement, and Dick went on 
from bad to worse. 
</p>
<p>
It must have been very deplorable to 
behold the reckless way in which he dissipated 
his money as soon as he got it into his hands, 
ruining at once his prospects, his character, 
and his health. With a temperament that 
naturally inclined him to self-indulgence, the 
road to ruin was equally rapid and pleasant. 
When Amy married Henry Lester--which 
she did after an engagement of six months--
Dick kept no bounds, and he irretrievably 
offended his family by intruding himself, 
uninvited, amongst the guests at the wedding. 
There was a painful scene in Amy’s parlour, 
where he went secretly, as he himself 
acknowledged, in the wild hope of inducing her to 
break off the engagement at the eleventh 
hour. She was dressed ready for church, and 
her mother was with her. That made no 
difference. Poor Dick went down on his knees, 
and cried, and kissed his cousin’s hands, and 
besought her to listen to him. And Amy 
fainted. She fainted a second time at the 
altar when Dick forced himself into her 
presence and forbade the marriage. He was 
so frantic, so out of himself, that he had to 
be removed by compulsory measures before 
the service could go on. Of course, after a 
scene like this, his uncle’s family kept no 
terms with him; he was forbidden ever to 
suffer his shadow to darken their door 
again--and so the poor, wild, crazed fellow 
went headlong to destruction. I doubt very 
much myself whether Amy was worth such 
a sacrifice; but he thought so. Life, he said, 
was unendurable without her, and he did 
not care how soon he ended it. 
</p>
<p>
But this was not all. Amy died of 
consumption within a year of her marriage, and 
Dick asserted that she had been killed by bad 
usage. He went down to his uncle’s house where 
she lay, and asked to see her. The request 
was refused, and he forced his way by the 
window into the room at night, as was 
afterwards discovered by the disarrangement of 
the furniture, and stayed there crying over 
his dead love until dawn. At her funeral he 
joined the mourners, and showed more grief 
than any of them; but as the husband was 
turning away, he walked up to him and shook 
his clenched fist in his face, crying: 
</p>
<p>
“You killed her, you straight-haired dog!” 
</p>
<p>
It was supposed that if he had not been 
restrained by the bystanders, he might have 
done him a mischief. His family gave it out 
that he was mad. Perhaps he was. 
</p>
<p>
Dice, drinking, and horse-racing now soon 
made an end of poor Dick’s five thousand 
pounds. He lost every shred of self-respect, 
and herded with the lowest of the low. There 
is no telling how a man’s troubles may turn 
him--love-disappointments especially; poor 
Dick’s turned him into a thorough scamp. 
He was a disgrace to the family, and a misery 
to himself, but there was this good left in 
him amidst his degrading excesses--the 
capability of regretting. He never enjoyed his 
vices or ceased to feel the horrible debasement 
of them. He was seen at races, prize-
fights, and fairs, in rags and tatters; he was 
known to have wanted bread, he was 
suspected of theft and poaching, and his brother 
Tom rescued him once out of the streets, 
where he was singing songs disguised as a 
lame soldier. Tom allowed him a guinea a 
week, but before he had been in receipt of it 
a month he made the annuity over to an 
acquaintance for ten pounds, to take him to 
Doncaster, and this friend always went with 
him to receive the money, lest he should lose 
it, so that Dick suffered extremities while he 
was supposed to be at least fed and clothed 
by his family. Ten years of reckless 
debauchery and poignant misery reduced him 
to the state in which his uncle Tarrant 
brought him to me; his aunt Julia who had 
brought Tom up offered to give him money 
if he would go out of the country and never 
come back again. How he went out of it, I 
have told already. 
</p>
<p>
When he ceased speaking, I said to 
encourage him: 
</p>
<p>
“You’ll do well yet, Dick, if you keep 
steady, and we make land or are picked up.” 
</p>
<p>
“What can it be,” said Dick, without 
particularly answering, “that brings all these 
old things over my mind? There’s a 
child’s hymn I and Tom used to say at my 
mother’s knee when we were little ones keeps 
running through my thoughts. It’s the stars, 
maybe; there was a little window by my bed 
that I used to watch them at--a window in 
my room at home in Cheshire--and if I was 
ever afraid, as boys will be after reading a 
good ghost story, I would keep on saying it 
till I fell asleep.” 
</p>
<p>
“That was a good mother of yours, Dick; 
could you say that hymn now, do you think? 
Some of us might like to hear it.” 
</p>
<p>
“It’s as clear in my mind at this minute 
as if my mother was here listening to me,” 
said Dick, and he repeated: 
</p>
<poem>
<poem1>“Hear my prayer, O! Heavenly Father,</poem1>
<poem2>Ere I lay me down to sleep;</poem2>
<poem1>Bid thy Angels, pure and holy,</poem1>
<poem2>Round my bed their vigil keep.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>“My sins are heavy, but Thy mercy</poem1>
<poem2>Far outweighs them every one;</poem2>
<poem1>Down before Thy Cross I cast them,</poem1>
<poem2>Trusting in Thy help alone.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>“Keep me through this night of peril</poem1>
<poem2>Underneath its boundless shade;</poem2>
<poem1>Take me to Thy rest, I pray Thee,</poem1>
<poem2>When my pilgrimage is made.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>“None shall measure out Thy patience</poem1>
<poem2>By the span of human thought;</poem2>
<poem1>None shall bound the tender mercies</poem1>
<poem2>Which Thy Holy Son has bought.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>“Pardon all my past transgressions,</poem1>
<poem2>Give me strength for days to come;</poem2>
<poem1>Guide and guard me with Thy blessing</poem1>
<poem2>Till Thy Angels bid me home.”</poem2>
</poem>
<p>
After awhile Dick drew his coat up over 
his head and lay down to sleep. 
</p>
<p>
“Well, poor Dick!” thought I, “it is surely 
a blessed thing for you that--
</p>
<poem>
<poem1>“None shall measure out God’s patience,</poem1>
<poem2>By the span of human thought;</poem2>
<poem1>None shall bound the tender mercies</poem1>
<poem2>Which His Holy Son has bought.”</poem2>
</poem>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BEGUILEMENT IN THE BOATS <br/>[The Supercargo's Story]</title>
<p>
A <sc>QUIET MIDDLE-AGED GENTLEMAN PASSENGER</sc>, 
in the Long-boat, who was going to 
establish a Store out there, and had been our 
supercargo besides, told what follows. 
</p>
<p>
She lay off Naarden--the good ship 
Brocken Spectre, I mean--far out in the 
roads; and I often thought, as I looked at 
her through the haze, what an ancient, ill-
favoured hulk it was. I suppose I came 
down some three or four times that day, 
being in a lounging unsatisfied state of mind; 
and took delight in watching the high, old-
fashioned poop, as it rocked all day long in 
that one spot. I likened it to a French roof 
of the olden time, it was garnished with so 
many little windows: and over all was the 
great lantern, which might have served 
conveniently for the vane or cupola seen upon 
such structures. For all that, it was not 
unpicturesque, and would have filled a corner 
in a Vandervelde picture harmoniously 
enough. She was to sail at three o’clock next 
morning, and I was to be the solitary cabin 
passenger. 
</p>
<p>
As evening came on, it grew prematurely 
dark and cloudy; while the waves acquired 
that dull indigo tint so significant of ugly 
weather. Raw gusts came sweeping in 
towards the shore, searching me through and 
through. I must own to a sinking of the 
heart as I took note of these symptoms, for a 
leaning towards ocean in any of its moods 
had never been one of my failings; and it 
augured but poorly for the state of the 
elements next morning. “It will have spent 
itself during the night,” I muttered, 
doubtfully; and turned back to the inn to eat 
dinner with what comfort I might. 
</p>
<p>
That place of entertainment stood by itself 
upon a bleak sandy hill. From its window I 
could see, afar off, three lights rising and 
falling together, just where the high poop 
and lantern had been performing the same 
ocean-dance in the daytime. I was sitting 
by the fire, listening ruefully to the wind, 
when news was brought to me that the 
Captain, Van Steen, had come ashore, and 
was waiting below to see me. 
</p>
<p>
I found him walking up and down 
outside--a short, thick-set man--as it were, 
built upon the lines of his own vessel. 
</p>
<p>
“Well captain, you wished to see me,” I 
said. 
</p>
<p>
“Look to this, my master,” he said, 
bluntly. “There’s a gale brewing yonder, 
and wild weather coming. So just see to 
this. If we’re not round the Helder Head 
by to-morrow night, we may have to beat 
round the Bay for days and days. So look to it, 
master, and come aboard while there is time.” 
</p>
<p>
“I’m ready at any moment,” I said; “but 
how do you expect to get round now? The 
sea is high enough as it is.” 
</p>
<p>
“No matter; the wind may be with us in 
the morning. We must clear the Head before 
to-morrow night. Why look you,” he added, 
sinking his voice, mysteriously, “I wouldn’t 
be off Helder to-morrow night--no, not for a 
sack of guilders!” 
</p>
<p>
“What do you mean?” 
</p>
<p>
“Why, don’t you know? It’s Christmas 
night--Jan Fagel’s night--Captain Jan’s!” 
</p>
<p>
“Well?” 
</p>
<p>
“He comes to Helder to-morrow night; he 
is seen in the Bay. But we are losing time, 
master,” said he, seizing my arm; “get your 
things ready--these lads will carry them to 
the boat.” 
</p>
<p>
Three figures here advanced out of the 
shadow, and entered with me. I hastily paid 
the bill, and set forward with the captain for 
the shore, where the boat was waiting. My 
mails were got on board with all expedition, 
and we were soon far out upon the waters, 
making steadily for the three lights. It was 
not blowing very hard as yet; neither had 
the waves assumed the shape of what are 
known as white horses; but there was a 
heavy underground swell, and a peculiar 
swooping motion quite as disagreeable. 
Suddenly, I made out the great lantern just over 
head, shining dimly, as it were through a fog. 
We had glided under the shadow of a dark 
mass, wherein there were many more dim 
lights at long intervals--and all, together 
seemed performing a wild dance to the 
music of dismal creaking of timbers, and 
rattling of chains. As we came under, a 
voice hailed us out of the darkness--as it 
seemed from the region of the lantern; and 
presently invisible hands cast us ropes, 
whereby, with infinite pains and labour, I 
was got on deck. I was then guided 
down steep ways into the cabin, the best 
place for me under the circumstances. As 
soon as the wind changed, the captain said, 
we would put out to sea. 
</p>
<p>
By the light of a dull oil-lamp overhead, 
that never for a moment ceased swinging, I 
tried to make out what my new abode was 
like. It was of an ancient massive fashion, 
with a dark oak panelling all round, rubbed 
smooth in many places by wear of time and 
friction. All round were queer little nobs 
and projections, mounted in brass and silver, 
just like the butt-ends of pistols; while here 
and there were snug recesses that reminded 
me of canons' stalls in a cathedral. The 
swinging lamp gave but a faint yellow light, 
that scarcely reached beyond the centre of 
the room; so that the oak-work all round 
cast little grotesque shadows, which had a 
very gloomy and depressing effect. There 
was a sort of oaken shelf at one end--
handsomely wrought, no doubt, but a failure as 
to sleeping capabilities. Into this I introduced 
myself without delay, and soon fell off 
into a profound slumber, for I was weary 
enough. 
</p>
<p>
When I awoke again, I found there was 
a figure standing over me, who said he was 
Mr. Bode the mate, who wished to know, 
could he serve me in any way? Had we 
started yet? I asked. Yes, we had started--
above an hour now--but she was not making 
much way. Would I get up--this was Christmas 
day. So it was; I had forgotten that. 
What a place to hold that inspiring festival 
in! Mr. Bode, who was inclined to be 
communicative, then added that it was blowing 
great guns: whereof I had abundant 
confirmation from my own physical sufferings, 
then just commencing. No, I would not--
could not get up; and so, for the rest of that 
day, dragged on a miserable existence, many 
times wishing that the waters would rise 
and cover me. Late in the evening I fell 
into a kind of uneasy doze, which was balm 
of Gilead to the tempest-tost landsman. 
</p>
<p>
When I awoke again, it was night once 
more; at least, there was the dull oil-lamp, 
swinging lazily as before. There was the 
same painful music--the same eternal creaking 
and straining, as of ship’s timbers in 
agony. What o’clock was it? Where were 
we now? Better make an effort, and go 
up, and see how we were getting on--it was 
so lonely down here. Come in! 
</p>
<p>
Here the door was opened, and Mr. Bode 
the mate presented himself. It was a bad 
night, Mr. Bode said--a very bad night.--He 
had come to tell me we were off the Head at 
last. He thought I might care to know. 
</p>
<p>
“I am glad to hear it,” I said faintly; “it 
will be something smoother in the open sea” 
</p>
<p>
He shook his head. “No open sea for us 
to-night; no, nor to-morrow night most 
likely.” 
</p>
<p>
“What is all this mystery?” said I, now 
recollecting the captain’s strange allusions at 
the inn door. “What do you mean?” 
</p>
<p>
“It is Jan Fagel’s night,” said he solemnly. 
“He comes into the bay to-night. An hour 
more of the wind, and we should have been 
clear. But we did what we could--a man 
can do no more than his best.” 
</p>
<p>
“But who is Jan Fagel?” 
</p>
<p>
”You never heard?” 
</p>
<p>
“Never. Tell me about him.” 
</p>
<p>
“Well,” said he, “I shan’t be wanted on 
deck for some time yet, so I may as well be 
here.” And Mr. Bode settled himself in one 
of the canons’ stalls, thus retiring into the 
shadow, and began the history of Jan Fagel 
and his vessel. 
</p>
<p>
“You have never heard of the famous brig 
Maelström, once on a time well known in 
these roads? No,--for you have not been 
much about here, I dare say; and it is only 
old sea-folk like myself that would care to 
talk to you of such things. But I can tell 
you this--there’s not a sailor along the coast 
that hasn’t the story, though it’s now--let 
me see--a good hundred years since she 
made her last cruise. Why, I recollect when 
I was a boy, the old hull lying on the sands, 
and breaking up with every tide--for she came 
to that end after all--the famous Maelström, 
Captain Jan Fagel, commander. I have been 
told there never was such a boat for foul 
weather, but that was when he was on board 
of her. He was a terrible man, was Captain 
Fagel, and would turn wild when a gale got 
up; and as the wind blew harder, so he grew 
wilder, until at last it seemed as if he had 
gone mad altogether. Why, there was one 
night my father used to tell of, when there 
was a great thunderstorm, and the sea was 
washing over the lighthouses--the most 
awful night he ever was out in--it was said 
that when the flashes came, Captain Jan had 
been seen dancing and skipping upon his 
deck. Many of his sailors told afterwards how 
they heard his mad shrieks above the roaring 
of the wind! Some said he had sold himself 
to the Evil One, which I think myself more 
than likely, for he cared neither for God nor 
man. 
</p>
<p>
“Well sir, Captain Fagel took first to the 
smuggling trade; and soon he and his famous 
brig became known all along the coast, from 
Hoek up to Helder--ay, and beyond that. 
But he was seen oftenest at the Head--as if 
he had a sort of liking for the place--and 
always came and went in a storm. So, that 
when the Zuyder was like a boiling 
cauldron, and the water running over the 
lighthouse galleries, old sailors would look up in 
the wind’s eye, and say ‘Captain Fagel’s 
running a cargo to-night.’ At last it came 
to this, that whenever he was seen off 
Helder, he was thought to bring a storm 
with him. And then they would shake 
their heads, and say Captain Fagel was 
abroad that night. Soon he grew tired of 
this work--it was too quiet for him--so he 
turned Rover, and ran up the black flag. 
He still kept up his old fashion of bearing 
down in a gale; and many a poor disabled 
craft that was struggling hard to keep 
herself afloat, would see the black hull of 
the Maelström coming down upon her in the 
storm, and so would perish miserably upon 
the rocks. He was no true sailor, sir, that 
captain, but a low pirate; and he came to 
a pirate’s end. And this was the way he 
fell upon his last cruise, just off Helder Head 
yonder. 
</p>
<p>
“There was a certain councillor of the town 
who had many times crossed him in his 
schemes, and had once been near taking him. 
Fagel hated him like poison, and swore he 
would have his revenge of him, one day. But 
the councillor did not fear him--not a bit of 
him, but even offered a reward to whoever 
would take or destroy Captain Fagel and his 
vessel. When the captain came to hear of 
this he fell to raving and foaming at the 
mouth, and then swore a great oath upon his 
own soul that he would be revenged of the 
councillor. And this was the way he went 
about it: 
</p>
<p>
“The councillor had a fair, young wife, 
Madame Elde, whom he had brought out 
of France some years before, and whom 
he loved exceedingly--foolishly, some said, 
for a man of his years. They and their 
little girl, lived together at a place called 
Loo, and no family could be happier. Jan 
Fagel knew the place well, and laid his devilish 
plans accordingly. So, as usual, on one 
of his wild, stormy nights, the brig was seen 
standing in to shore--for no good purpose, as 
everybody guessed. How he and his mad 
crew got to land was never accounted for--
but this is certain--they broke into the house 
at Loo, and dragged Madame Elde and her 
child from their beds, and forced them down 
to their boats. The councillor was away in 
the city; but Captain Jan knew well enough 
how he loved his wife, and chose this way of 
torturing him. An old fisherman, who lived 
hard by the shore, said, that he woke up 
suddenly in the night, and heard their screams; 
but they were too many for him, or he would 
have gone out. He was an old man, and it 
was only natural. They then pulled away 
for the ship, he standing up, and screaming 
at the waves like a fiend incarnate, as he was. 
How the poor passengers ever got alive on 
board was a miracle--for the waves came 
dashing over the bows of the boat, where 
they were lying, at every stroke. 
</p>
<p>
“Now it fell out, that at this time, there was 
a British frigate cruising about these parts--
for Captain Fagel had a short time before 
this, fired into an English vessel. The frigate 
was, therefore, keeping a sharp look-out for 
the brig, and had been looking into all the 
creeks and harbours along the coasts, when 
she was caught in this very storm--of 
Captain Fagel’s raising. Just as she was 
struggling round the Head, she came upon the 
Maelström, taking on board her boat’s crew. 
</p>
<p>
“‘Let go all clear!’ they heard him cry, 
even above the storm--and then they saw the 
dark hull swing round, and set off along shore, 
where it was hard for the frigate to follow. 
As for Jan Fagel, if ever Satan entered into 
a man in this life, he must have possessed him 
that night! They could hear him from the 
other vessel, as he shrieked with delight, and 
swore, and bounded along his deck, when 
other men could scarcely keep their feet. 
Why, sir, one time, he was seen on the edge 
of the taffrail--his eyes looking in the dark 
like two burning coals! No doubt he would 
have got away from them, after all--for there 
was no better mariner in those seas--when 
just as he was coming round a point, they 
heard a crash, and down came his topmast 
upon his deck. The sailors rushed to clear 
away the wreck. 
</p>
<p>
“‘Bring up the woman,’ he roared through 
his trumpet. ‘Bring up the woman and 
child, you sea imps!’ Though his ship was 
in danger, he thought of the councillor. Some 
of them rushed down into the hold, and 
came up in a moment with Madame Elde 
and the little girl. She was quite scared and 
sank down upon the deck, as if she were 
insensible. 
</p>
<p>
“‘A handsome creature, sir,’ they said, even 
some of those savages felt for her. They 
heard her saying over and over again to 
herself: 
</p>
<p>
“‘O, such a Christmas night! Such a 
Christmas night!’ 
</p>
<p>
“He overheard her. 
</p>
<p>
“‘Ah, ah! witch! you shall have a merry 
Christmas. Never fear. So should your 
husband--curse him--if we had him here.’ 
</p>
<p>
“She started up with a scream when she 
heard him speaking. And then they saw 
her standing, with her long black hair blown 
back by the wind, and her arms out, as if 
she were praying. 'Where shall Thy 
judgments find this man?’ 
</p>
<p>
“‘Here, witch! Look for me here on a 
stormy night--any night; next Christmas, if 
you like. Hi, lads! get a sail here, and send 
them over the side.’ 
</p>
<p>
“Even those ruffians hung back, for it was 
too awful a night for them to add murder to 
their other sins. So, with many oaths, 
Captain Fagel went forward himself to seize the 
lady. 
</p>
<p>
“‘He shall meet me before the Judgment 
seat,’ said she, still praying. 
</p>
<p>
“‘Cant away, sorceress! come back here of 
a stormy night, and I’ll meet you: I’m not 
afraid;’ and he laughed long and loud. 
</p>
<p>
“Then he flung the wet sail round them, and 
with his own hands cast them into the sea. 
The storm came on fiercer than ever, and 
they thought that the ship’s timbers were 
going to part. But Jan Fagel strode 
about his deck, and gave his orders and 
she bore up well before the wind. It seemed 
that no harm could come to that ship when 
he was on board of her. As for the frigate, 
she had long since got away into the open 
sea. But the lady’s words were not to be in 
vain, for just as he was going one of his mad 
bounds along the poop, his foot caught in a 
coil of rope, and he went over with an 
unearthly scream into the black, swollen sea. 
All the crew ran to look out after him, 
but, strange to tell, without so much as 
thinking of casting him a rope. It seemed 
as if they had lost their sense for a time, and 
could only stand there looking into the waves 
that had swept him off. Just then, the wind 
went down a little, and they heard a voice 
high in the mainmast-top, as if some one 
were calling; and these words came to them 
very clear and distinct: ‘Yo, yo! Jan Fagel, 
yo!’ Then all the crew at the vessel’s side, 
as if they had caught some of his own devilish 
spirit, could not keep themselves from giving 
out, in a great wild chorus, ‘Yo, yo! Jan 
Fagel, yo!’ Once more the voice came from 
the mainmast-top, calling, ‘Yo, yo! Jan 
Fagel, yo!’ and again the crew answered, 
louder than before, as if they were 
possessed. He was seen no more after that. 
</p>
<p>
“The memory of that night never left that 
wicked crew; and many of them, when dying 
quietly in their beds long after, started up with 
that cry, as though they were answering a call, 
and so passed away to their last account. 
</p>
<p>
“Every year, as sure as Christmas night 
comes round, Jan Fagel comes into the bay 
to keep his word with Madame Elde. And, 
any ship that is off the Head then, must wait 
and beat about until midnight; when he goes 
away. 
</p>
<p>
“But they are wanting me on deck,” said 
Mr. Bode, looking at his watch. “I have 
stayed too long as it is.” 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Bode hastily departed, leaving me 
to ponder over his wild legend. Ruminating 
upon it, and listening to the rushing of the 
water, close to my ear, I fell off again in a 
sleep, and began to dream; and, of course, 
dreamed of Captain Jan Fagel. 
</p>
<p>
It was a wild and troubled sleep, that I had; 
and I am sure, if any one had been standing 
near, they would have seen me starting and 
turning uneasily, as if in grievous trouble. 
First, I thought I was ashore again, in a 
sheltered haven, safely delivered from 
all this wretched tossing. And I recollect 
how inexpressibly delightful the feeling 
of repose was, after all these weary 
labours. By-and-by, I remarked low-roofed 
old-fashioned houses all about, seemingly 
of wood, with little galleries running round 
the windows. And I saw stately burghers 
walking, in dresses centuries old, and ladies 
with great round frills about their necks, and 
looking very stiff and majestic, sat and talked 
to the burghers. They were coming in and out 
of the queer houses, and some passed quite close 
to me, saluting me, as they did so, very 
graciously. One thing seemed very strange to me. 
They had all a curious dried look about their 
faces, and a sort of stony cast in their eyes, 
which I could not make out. Still they came 
and went, and I looked on and wondered. 
Suddenly I saw the little Dutch houses and the 
figures all quivering and getting indistinct, 
and gradually the picture faded away until it 
grew slowly into the shape of the cabin where 
I was now lying. There it was, all before me, 
with the canons' stalls and the dull swinging 
lamp, and I myself leaning on one hand in 
the carved crib, and thinking what a weary 
voyage this was! How monotonous the 
rushing sound of the water! Then my 
dream went on, and it seemed to me that I 
took note of a canon’s stall in the centre, 
something larger and better-fashioned than 
the others--the dean’s, most likely, I 
concluded wisely, when he comes to service. 
And then on that hint, as it were, I seemed 
to travel away over the waters to ancient 
aisles, and tracery and soft ravishing music, 
and snowy figures seen afar off duskily amid 
clouds of incense. In time, too, all that 
faded away, and I was back again in the oak 
cabin, with the sickly yellow light suffusing 
everything, and a dark misty figure sitting 
right opposite. He caused me no surprise or 
astonishment, and I received him there as a 
matter of course, as people do in dreams. I 
had seen figures like him somewhere. In 
Rembrandt's pictures, was it? Most likely; 
for there was the large broad hat, and the 
stiff white collar and tassels, and the dark 
jerkin; only there was a rusty, mouldering 
look about his garments that seemed very 
strange to me. He had an ancient sword, 
too, on which he leaned his arm; and so sat 
there motionless, looking on the ground. 
He sat that way I don't know how long: I, 
as it seemed to me, studying him intently: 
when suddenly the rushing sound ceased, and 
there came a faint cry across the waters, 
as from afar off. It was the old cry: 
“Yo, yo! Jan Fagel, yo!” Then I saw 
the figure raise its head suddenly, and the 
yellow light fell upon his face--such a 
mournful, despairing face!--with the same 
stony gaze I had seen in the others. Again 
the fearful cry came--nearer, as it seemed; 
and I saw the figure rise up slowly and walk 
across the cabin to the door. As he passed 
me he turned his dead, lack-lustre eyes full 
upon me, and looked at me for an instant. 
Never shall I forget that moment. It was 
as if a horrid weight was pressing on me. 
I felt such agony that I awoke with a start, 
and found myself sitting up and trembling 
all over. But at that instant; whether the 
dreamy influence had not wholly passed away, 
or whatever was the reason I don't know; 
I can swear that, above the rushing sound 
of the waves and the whistling of the wind, 
I heard that ghostly chorus “Yo, yo! Jan 
Fagel, yo!” quite clear and distinct. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BEGUILEMENT IN THE BOATS <br/>[The Old Sailor's Story]</title>
<p>
A<sc>N OLD</sc> S<sc>EAMAN IN THE</sc> S<sc>URF-BOAT</sc> 
sang this ballad, as his story, to a curious 
sort of tuneful no-tune, which none of the 
rest could remember afterwards. 
</p>
<poem>
<poem1>I <sc>HAVE</sc> seen a fiercer tempest,</poem1>
<poem2>Known a louder whirlwind blow.</poem2>
<poem1>I was wreck’d off red Algiers,</poem1>
<poem2>Six-and-thirty years ago.</poem2>
<poem1>Young I was,--and yet old seamen</poem1>
<poem2>Were not strong or calm as I;</poem2>
<poem1>While life held such treasures for me,</poem1>
<poem2>I felt sure I could not die.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Life I struggled for--and saved it;</poem1>
<poem2>Life alone--and nothing more;</poem2>
<poem1>Bruised, half dead, alone and helpless,</poem1>
<poem2>I was cast upon the shore.</poem2>
<poem1>I fear’d the pitiless rocks of Ocean;</poem1>
<poem2>So the great sea rose--and then</poem2>
<poem1>Cast me from her friendly bosom,</poem1>
<poem2>On the pitiless hearts of men.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Gaunt and dreary ran the mountains</poem1>
<poem2>With black gorges up the land;</poem2>
<poem1>Up to where the lonely Desert</poem1>
<poem2>Spreads her burning dreary sand:</poem2>
<poem1>In the gorges of the mountains,</poem1>
<poem2>On the plain beside the sea,</poem2>
<poem1>Dwelt my stern and cruel masters,</poem1>
<poem2>The black Moors of Barbary.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Ten long years I toil’d among them,</poem1>
<poem2>Hopeless--as I used to say;</poem2>
<poem1>Now I know Hope burnt within me</poem1>
<poem2>Fiercer, stronger, day by day:</poem2>
<poem1>Those dim years of toil and sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Like one long dark dream appear;</poem2>
<poem1>One long day of weary waiting;</poem1>
<poem2>Then each day was like a year.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>How I curst the land--my prison;</poem1>
<poem2>How I curst the serpent sea,--</poem2>
<poem1>And the Demon Fate, that shower’d</poem1>
<poem2>All her curses upon me:</poem2>
<poem1>I was mad, I think--God pardon</poem1>
<poem2>Words so terrible and wild--</poem2>
<poem1>This voyage would have been my last one,</poem1>
<poem2>For I left a wife and child.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Never did one tender vision</poem1>
<poem2>Fade away before my sight,</poem2>
<poem1>Never once through all my slavery,</poem1>
<poem2>Burning day or dreary night;</poem2>
<poem1>In my soul it lived, and kept me,</poem1>
<poem2>Now I feel, from black despair,</poem2>
<poem1>And my heart was not quite broken,</poem1>
<poem2>While they lived and blest me there.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>When at night my task was over,</poem1>
<poem2>I would hasten to the shore;</poem2>
<poem1>(All was strange and foreign inland,</poem1>
<poem2>Nothing I had known before).</poem2>
<poem1>Strange look’d the bleak mountain passes,</poem1>
<poem2>Strange the red glare and black shade,</poem2>
<poem1>And the Oleanders, waving</poem1>
<poem2>To the sound the fountains made.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then I gazed at the great Ocean,</poem1>
<poem2>Till she grew a friend again;</poem2>
<poem1>And because she knew old England,</poem1>
<poem2>I forgave her all my pain:</poem2>
<poem1>So the blue still sky above me,</poem1>
<poem2>With its white clouds’ fleecy fold,</poem2>
<poem1>And the glimmering stars (though brighter),</poem1>
<poem2>Look’d like home and days of old.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And a calm would fall upon me;</poem1>
<poem2>Worn perhaps with work and pain,</poem2>
<poem1>The wild hungry longing left me,</poem1>
<poem2>And I was myself again:</poem2>
<poem1>Looking at the silver waters,</poem1>
<poem2>Looking up at the far sky,</poem2>
<poem1>Dreams of home and all I left there</poem1>
<poem2>Floated sorrowfully by.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>A fair face, but pale with sorrow,</poem1>
<poem2>With blue eyes, brimful of tears,</poem2>
<poem1>And the little red mouth, quivering</poem1>
<poem2>With a smile, to hide its fears;</poem2>
<poem1>Holding out her baby towards me,</poem1>
<poem2>From the sky she look’d on me;</poem2>
<poem1>So it was that I last saw her,</poem1>
<poem2>As the ship put out to sea.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Sometimes (and a pang would seize me</poem1>
<poem2>That the years were floating on)</poem2>
<poem1>I would strive to paint her, alter’d,</poem1>
<poem2>And the little baby gone:</poem2>
<poem1>She no longer young and girlish,</poem1>
<poem2>The child, standing by her knee,</poem2>
<poem1>And her face, more pale and sadden’d</poem1>
<poem2>With the weariness for me.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then I saw, as night grew darker,</poem1>
<poem2>How she taught my child to pray,</poem2>
<poem1>Holding its small hands together,</poem1>
<poem2>For its father, far away;</poem2>
<poem1>And I felt her sorrow, weighing</poem1>
<poem2>Heavier on me than mine own;</poem2>
<poem1>Pitying her blighted spring-time,</poem1>
<poem2>And her joy so early flown.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Till upon my hands (now harden’d</poem1>
<poem2>With the rough harsh toil of years,)</poem2>
<poem1>Bitter drops of anguish, falling,</poem1>
<poem2>Woke me from my dream, to tears;</poem2>
<poem1>Woke me as a slave, an outcast,</poem1>
<poem2>Leagues from home, across the deep;</poem2>
<poem1>So--though you may call it childish--</poem1>
<poem2>So I sobb’d myself to sleep.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Well, the years sped on--my sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Calmer, and yet stronger grown,</poem2>
<poem1>Was my shield against all suffering,</poem1>
<poem2>Poorer, meaner, than her own.</poem2>
<poem1>So my cruel master’s harshness</poem1>
<poem2>Fell upon me all in vain,</poem2>
<poem1>Yet the tale of what we suffer’d</poem1>
<poem2>Echo’d back from main to main.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>You have heard in a far country</poem1>
<poem2>Of a self-devoted band,</poem2>
<poem1>Vow’d to rescue Christian captives</poem1>
<poem2>Pining in a foreign land.</poem2>
<poem1>And these gentle-hearted strangers</poem1>
<poem2>Year by year go forth from Rome,</poem2>
<poem1>In their hands the hard-earn’d ransom</poem1>
<poem2>To restore some exiles home.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>I was freed: they broke the tidings</poem1>
<poem2>Gently to me; but indeed</poem2>
<poem1>Hour by hour sped on, I knew not</poem1>
<poem2>What the words meant--I was freed!</poem2>
<poem1>Better so, perhaps, while sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>(More akin to earthly things)</poem2>
<poem1>Only strains the sad heart’s fibres--</poem1>
<poem2>Joy, bright stranger, breaks the strings.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Yet at last it rush’d upon me,</poem1>
<poem2>And my heart beat full and fast;</poem2>
<poem1>What were now my years of waiting,</poem1>
<poem2>What was all the dreary past?</poem2>
<poem1>Nothing, to the impatient throbbing</poem1>
<poem2>I must bear across the sea:</poem2>
<poem1>Nothing to the eternal hours</poem1>
<poem2>Still between my home and me!</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>How the voyage pass’d, I know not;</poem1>
<poem2>Strange it was once more to stand,</poem2>
<poem1>With my countrymen around me,</poem1>
<poem2>And to clasp an English hand.</poem2>
<poem1>But, through all, my heart was dreaming</poem1>
<poem2>Of the first words I should hear,</poem2>
<poem1>In the gentle voice that echo’d,</poem1>
<poem2>Fresh as ever, on my ear.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Should I see her start of wonder,</poem1>
<poem2>And the sudden truth arise,</poem2>
<poem1>Flushing all her face and lightening</poem1>
<poem2>The dimm’d splendour of her eyes?</poem2>
<poem1>O! to watch the fear and doubting</poem1>
<poem2>Stir the silent depths of pain,</poem2>
<poem1>And the rush of joy--then melting</poem1>
<poem2>Into perfect peace again.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And the child!--but why remember</poem1>
<poem2>Foolish fancies that I thought?</poem2>
<poem1>Every tree and every hedgerow</poem1>
<poem2>From the well-known past I brought:</poem2>
<poem1>I would picture my dear cottage,</poem1>
<poem2>See the crackling wood-fire burn,</poem2>
<poem1>And the two beside it, seated</poem1>
<poem2>Watching, waiting, my return.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>So, at last we reach’d the harbour.</poem1>
<poem2>I remember nothing more</poem2>
<poem1>Till I stood, my sick heart throbbing</poem1>
<poem2>With my hand upon the door.</poem2>
<poem1>There I paused--I heard her speaking;</poem1>
<poem2>Low, soft, murmuring words she said;</poem2>
<poem1>Then I first knew the dumb terror</poem1>
<poem2>I had had, lest she were dead.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>It was evening in late autumn,</poem1>
<poem2>And the gusty wind blew chill;</poem2>
<poem1>Autumn leaves were falling round me,</poem1>
<poem2>And the red sun lit the hill.</poem2>
<poem1>Six and twenty years are vanish’d</poem1>
<poem2>Since then--I am old and grey--</poem2>
<poem1>But I never told to mortal</poem1>
<poem2>What I saw, until this day.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>She was seated by the fire,</poem1>
<poem2>In her arms she held a child,</poem2>
<poem1>Whispering baby-words caressing,</poem1>
<poem2>And then, looking up, she smiled.</poem2>
<poem1>Smiled on him who stood beside her--</poem1>
<poem2>O! the bitter truth was told!</poem2>
<poem1>In her look of trusting fondness,</poem1>
<poem2>I had seen the look of old.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>But she rose and turn’d towards me</poem1>
<poem2>(Cold and dumb I waited there),</poem2>
<poem1>With a shriek of fear and terror,</poem1>
<poem2>And a white face of despair.</poem2>
<poem1>He had been an ancient comrade--</poem1>
<poem2>Not a single word we said,</poem2>
<poem1>While we gazed upon each other,</poem1>
<poem2>He the living: I the dead!</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>I drew nearer, nearer to her,</poem1>
<poem2>And I took her trembling hand,</poem2>
<poem1>Looking on her white face, looking</poem1>
<poem2>That her heart might understand</poem2>
<poem1>All the love and all the pity</poem1>
<poem2>That my lips refused to say!</poem2>
<poem1>I thank God no thought save sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Rose in our crush’d hearts that day.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Bitter tears that desolate moment,</poem1>
<poem2>Bitter, bitter tears we wept</poem2>
<poem1>We three broken hearts together,</poem1>
<poem2>While the baby smiled and slept.</poem2>
<poem1>Tears alone--no words were spoken,</poem1>
<poem2>Till he--till her husband said</poem2>
<poem1>That my boy (I had forgotten</poem1>
<poem2>The poor child), that he was dead.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then at last I rose, and, turning,</poem1>
<poem2>Wrung his hand, but made no sign;</poem2>
<poem1>And I stoop’d and kiss’d her forehead</poem1>
<poem2>Once more, as if she were mine.</poem2>
<poem1>Nothing of farewell I utter’d,</poem1>
<poem2>Save in broken words to pray</poem2>
<poem1>That God in His great love would bless her--</poem1>
<poem2>Then in silence pass’d away.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Over the great restless ocean</poem1>
<poem2>For twenty and six years I roam;</poem2>
<poem1>All my comrades, old and weary,</poem1>
<poem2>Have gone back to die at home.</poem2>
<poem1>Home! yes, I shall reach a haven,</poem1>
<poem2>I, too, shall reach home and rest;</poem2>
<poem1>I shall find her waiting for me</poem1>
<poem2>With our baby on her breast.</poem2>
</poem>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE BEGUILEMENT IN THE BOATS <br/>[The Scotch Boy's Story]</title>
<p>
W<sc>HILE THE FOREGOING STORY WAS BEING 
TOLD</sc>, I had kept my eye fixed upon little Willy 
Lindsey, a young Scotch boy (one of the two 
apprentices), who had been recommended to 
Captain Ravender’s care by a friend in 
Glasgow; and very sad it was to see the 
expression of his face. All the early part of 
the voyage he had been a favourite in the 
ship. The ballads he sang, and the curious 
old stories he told, made him a popular 
visitor in the cabin, no less than among 
the people. Though only entered as apprentice 
seaman, Captain Ravender had kept him 
as much about him as he could; and I am 
bold to say, the lad’s affection for Captain 
Ravender was as sincere as if he had been 
one of his own blood. Even before the wreck, 
a change had taken place in his manner. He 
grew silent and thoughtful. Mrs. Atherfield 
and Miss Coleshaw, who had been very 
kind to him, observed the alteration, and 
bantered him on the melancholy nature of 
the songs he sang to them, and the sad air 
with which he went about the duties of the 
vessel. I asked him if anything had occurred 
to make him dull; but he put me off with a 
laugh, and at last told me that he was thinking 
about his home; for, said he, a certain 
anniversary was coming soon; “and maybe 
I’ll tell you,” he added, “why the expectation 
of it makes me so sorrowful.” 
</p>
<p>
He was a nice, delicate, almost feminine-
looking boy, of sixteen or seventeen; the son 
of a small farmer in Ayrshire, as Captain 
Ravender’s Glasgow friend had told him, and, 
as usual with his countrymen, a capital hand 
at letters and accounts. He had brought 
with him a few books, chiefly of the wild and 
supernatural kind; and it seemed as if he 
had given way to his imagination more than 
was quite healthy, perhaps, for the other 
faculties of his mind. But we all set down 
his delight and belief in ghost stories and 
such like, to the superstition of his country, 
where the folks seem to make up for being 
the most matter-of-fact people in Europe in 
the affairs of this world, by being the wildest 
and most visionary inquirers into the affairs 
of the next. Willy had been useful to all 
departments on board. The steward had 
employed him at his ledger, Captain Ravender 
at his reckonings, and as to the passengers, 
they had made quite a friend and 
companion of the youth. 
</p>
<p>
So I watched his looks, as I’ve said before, 
and I now beckoned Willy to come to my 
side, that I might keep him as warm as I 
could. At first he either did not perceive 
my signal, or was too apathetic or too deep 
sunk in his own thoughts to act upon it. 
But the carpenter, who sat next him, seeing 
my motion, helped him across the boat, and 
I put my arm round his shoulders. 
</p>
<p>
“Bear up, Willy,” I said, “you're young 
and strong, and, with the help of Heaven, 
we shall all live to see our friends again.” 
</p>
<p>
The boy’s eye brightened with hope for a 
moment; then he shook his head and 
said: 
</p>
<p>
“You’re very kind to say so, sir; but it 
canna be--at least for me.” 
</p>
<p>
The night was now closing fast in, but 
there was still light enough to see his face. 
It was quite calm, and wore a sort of smile. 
Everybody listened to hear what the poor 
laddie said; and I whispered to him: 
</p>
<p>
“You promised to tell me why you were 
depressed by the coming of an anniversary, 
Willy. When is it?” 
</p>
<p>
“It’s to-night,” he said, with a solemn 
voice. “And O! how different this is from 
what it used to be! It’s the birth-day o’ my 
sister Jean.” 
</p>
<p>
“Come, tell us all about it,” I said. 
“Maybe, speaking it out openly will ease 
your mind. Here, rest on my shoulder. 
Now say on.” 
</p>
<p>
We all tried to catch his words, and he 
began: 
</p>
<p>
“It’s two years ago, this very day, since 
we had such a merry night of it in my 
father’s house at home. He was a farmer in 
a sma’ way up among the hills above the 
Doon; and had the lands on a good tack, 
and was thought a richer man than any of 
his neighbours. There was only Jean and 
me o’ the family; and I’m thinking nobody 
was ever so happy or well cared for as I was 
a’ the time I was young. For my mither 
would let me want for nothing, and took me 
on her knee and tauld me long histories o’ 
the Bruce and Wallace; and strange 
adventures with the warlocks; and sang me a’ 
Burns’ songs, forbye reading me the grand 
auld stories out o’ the Bible, about the death 
o’ Goliath and the meeting o’ King Saul and 
the Witch of Endor. Jean was a kind o’ 
mither to me, too; for she was five years 
older, and spoilt me as much as she could. 
She was so bonny, it was a pleasure to look 
at her; and she helpit in the dairy, and 
often milkt the cows hersel’; and in the 
winter nights sat by the side o’ the bleezy 
fire, and turned the reel or span, keepin’ 
time wi’ some lang ballad about cruel 
Ranken coming in and killing Lady 
Margaret; or the ship that sailed away to 
Norway wi’ Sir Patrick Spence, and sank 
wi’ all the crew. The schoolmaster came up, 
when he was able, to gi’e me lessons; and as 
the road was long, and the nights were 
sometimes dark, it soon grew into the 
common custom for him to come up ow’r 
the hills on Friday, when the school was 
skailt, and stay till the Monday morning. 
He was a young man that had been intended 
for a minister, but the college expenses had 
been too much, and he had settled down as 
the parish teacher at Shalloch; and we 
always called him Dominie Blair. All the 
week through, we looked for the Dominie’s 
coming. Jean and I used to go and meet 
him at the bend o’ the hill, where he came off 
from the high-road, and he began his lessons 
to me in botany the moment we turned 
towards home. I noticed that he aye required 
the specimens that grew at the side o’ the 
burns that ran down valleys a good way off; 
but I was very vain of my running, and used 
to rush down the gully and gather the flower 
or weed, and overtake the two before they 
had walked on a mile. So you see, sir, it was 
na long before it was known all over the 
country side that Dominie Blair was going to 
marry my sister Jean. Everybody thought 
it a capital match, for Jean had beauty and 
siller, and Mr. Blair was the cleverest man 
in the county, and had the promise of the 
mastership of a school in the East country, 
with ninety pounds a-year. Our house grew 
happier now than ever; and when Jean’s 
birthday came round, there was a gathering 
from far and near to do honour to the 
bonniest and kindest lass in all the parish. 
The minister himsel’ came up on his pony, 
and drank prosperity to the young folks at 
the door; and inside at night there was a 
supper for all the neighbours, and John 
Chalmers played on the fiddle, and a’ the 
rest of us sang songs, and danced and skirled 
like mad; and at last, when Jean’s health 
was drank, with many wishes for her happiness, 
up she gets and lays her arms round my 
auld mither’s neck, and bursts out into a 
great passion o’ tears; and when she 
recovered herself, she said she would never 
be so happy anywhere else, and that weel or 
ill, dead or alive--in the body or in the 
spirit--she would aye come back on that 
night, and look in on the hame where 
she had spent sae sunshiny a life. Some o’ 
them laughed at the wild affection she 
showed; and some took it seriously, and 
thought she had tied herself down by ow’r 
solemn a bargain; but in a wee while the 
mirth and frolicking gaed on as before, and 
all the company confessed it was the happiest 
evening they had ever spent in their lives. 
Do you ken Loch Luart, sir?--a wee bit water 
that stretches across between the Lureloch 
and the Breelen? Ah! the grand shadows that 
pass along it when you stand on the north 
side and look over to the hill. There’s a 
great blackness settled upon the face, as if 
the sun had died away from the heavens 
altogether, till when he comes round the 
corner o’ the mountain, a glorious procession 
o’ sunbeams and colours taks its course 
across the whole length o’ the water, and all 
the hill sides give out a kind o’ glow, and at 
last the loch seems all on fire, and you can 
scarcely look at it for the brightness. A 
small skiff was kept at the side, for it saved 
the shepherds miles o’ steep climbing to get 
from flock to flock, as it cut off two or three 
miles o’ the distance between our house and 
Shalloch. One Friday, soon after the merry 
meeting at Jean’s birthday, she set off as 
usual to meet Mr. Blair. How far she went, 
or where she met him, nobody could tell, for 
nothing was ever seen or heard o’ them from 
that day to this; only the skiff on Loch 
Luart was found keel up, and the prints o’ 
feet that answered to their size were seen on 
the wet bank. Nothing wad persuade my 
mother for many a day that she wasna coming 
back. When she heard a step at the door, 
she used to flush up with a great redness in 
her cheek, and run to let her in. Then when 
she saw it was a stranger, she left the door 
open and came back into the kitchen without 
sayin’ a word. My father spoke very little, 
but sometimes he seemed to forget that Jean 
was taken away, and called for her to come 
to him in a cheery voice, as he used to do; 
and then, wi’ a sudden shake o’ his head, he 
remembered that she was gone, and passed 
away to his work as if his heart was broken. 
And other things came on to disturb him 
now, for some bank, or railway, or 
something o’ the kind, where he had bought some 
shares, failed with a great crash, and he was 
called on to make up the loss; and he grew 
careless about everything that happened, and 
the horses and carts were seized for debt, and 
a’ the cows except two were taken away, and 
the place began to go to wrack and ruin; 
and at last Jean’s birthday cam’ round again. 
But we never spoke about it the whole day 
long, though none of the three thought of 
anything else. My father pretended to be 
busy in the field; my mother span--never 
letting the thread out o’ her hand; and as for 
me, I wandered about the hills from early 
morning, and only came back when the dark 
night began. All through the lengthening 
hours we sat and never spoke; but sometimes 
my father put a fresh supply of peats 
upon the fire, and stirred it up into a blaze, 
as if it pleased him to see the great sparkles 
flying up the chimney. At last my mother, 
all of a sudden, ceased her spinning, and 
said, ‘Hark! do you no’ hear somebody 
outside?’ And we listened without getting up 
from our seats. We heard a sound as if 
somebody was slipping by on tip-toe on the way 
to the Byre; and then we heard a low, wailing 
sound, as if the person was trying to 
restrain some great sorrow; and immediately 
we heard the same footstep, as if it were lost 
in snow, coming up to the house. My mither 
stood up wi’ her hand stretched out, and 
looked at the window. Outside the pane--
where the rose-tree has grown sae thick it 
half hides the lower half--we heard a rustling, 
as if somebody was putting aside the 
leaves, and then, when a sudden flicker o’ the 
flame threw its light upon the casement, we 
saw the faint image o’ a bonny pale face--
very sad to look on--wi’ lang tresses o’ yellow 
hair hanging straight down the cheeks, as if 
it was dripping wet, and heard low, plaintive 
sobs; but nothing that we could understand. 
My mither ran forward, as if to embrace 
the visitor, and cried, ‘Jean! Jean! O, 
let me speak to you, my bairn!’ But the 
flame suddenly died away in the grate, and 
we saw nothing mair. But we all knew now 
that Jean had been drowned in Loch Luart, 
and that she minded the promise she had 
made to come and see the auld house upon 
her birthday.” 
</p>
<p>
Here the boy paused in his narrative for a 
moment, and I felt his breath coming and 
going very quick, as if his strength was 
getting rapidly exhausted. 
</p>
<p>
“Rest a while, Willy,” I said, “and try, if 
you can, to sleep.” 
</p>
<p>
But nothing could restrain him from 
finishing his tale. 
</p>
<p>
“Na, na! I canna rest upon your arm, 
sir. I ha’e wark to do, and it maun be done 
this night--wae’s me! I didna think, last 
year at this time, that ever I wad be here.” 
He looked round with a shudder at the 
coiling waves that rose high at the side of 
the boat, and shut out the faint glimmer that 
still lingered on the horizon line. “So Jean 
was drowned, ye see,” he continued; “and 
couldna put foot inside--for a’ they can do is 
to look in and see what’s doing at the auld 
fireside through the window. But even this 
was a comfort to my mither; and as I saw 
how glad it made her to have this assurance 
that she wasna forgotten, I made her the 
same promise that Jean had done on her 
birthday: ill or weel, happy or miserable, in 
the body or in the spirit--I wad find my 
way to the farm-house, and gi’e her some 
sign that I loved her as I had always done. 
And now I ken what they’re doing as if I 
was at hame. They’re sitting sad and lonely 
in the silent kitchen. My father puts fresh 
peats upon the grate, and watches their 
flame as it leaps and crackles up the 
fireplace; and my mither--Ah!”--here he 
stretched forward as if to see some object 
before him more distinctly--“ah! she’s 
spinning, spinning as if to keep herself from 
thinking--and tears are running down her 
face; and I see the cheery fire, and the 
heather bed in the corner, and the round 
table in the middle, and the picture o’ 
Abraham and Isaac on the wall, and my 
fishing-rod hung up aboon the mantelpiece, 
and my herding-staff, and my old blue bonnet. 
But how cold it is, sir,” he went on, turning 
to me; “I felt a touch on my shoulder just 
now that made me creep as if the hand were 
ice; and I looked up and saw the same face 
we had noticed last year; and I feel the 
clammy fingers yet, and they go downward--
downward, chilling me a’ the way till my 
blood seems frozen, and I canna speak. O, 
for anither look at the fire and the warm 
cosy room, and my father’s white head, and 
my puir auld mither’s een!” 
</p>
<p>
So saying, he tried to rise, and seemed 
to be busy putting aside something that 
interfered with his view. “The rose-tree!” he 
said; “it’s thicker than ever, and I canna see 
clear!” At last he appeared to get near the 
object he sought; and, after altering his 
position, as if to gain a perfect sight, he said: “I 
see them a’ again. O, mither! turn your face 
this way, for ye see I’ve kept my word; and 
we’re both here. Jean’s beside me, and very 
cold--and we darena come in.” He watched 
for about a minute, still gazing intently, and 
then, with a joyous scream, he exclaimed: 
“She sees me,--she sees me! Did na ye 
hear her cry? O mither, mither! tak’ me 
to your arms, for I’m chilled wi’ the salt 
water, and naething will make me warm 
again.” 
</p>
<p>
I tightened my hold of poor Willy as he 
spoke, for he gradually lost his power, and 
at last lay speechless with his head on my 
shoulder. I concealed from the rest the sad 
event that occurred in a few minutes, and kept 
the body hidden till the darkest part of the 
night, closely wrapped in my cloak. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE DELIVERANCE</title>
<p>
W<sc>HEN</sc> the sun rose on the twenty-seventh 
day of our calamity, the first question that I 
secretly asked myself was, How many more 
mornings will the stoutest of us live to see? 
I had kept count, ever since we took to the 
boats, of the days of the week; and I knew 
that we had now arrived at another Thursday. 
Judging by my own sensations (and I 
believe I had as much strength left as the 
best man among us), I came to the conclusion 
that, unless the mercy of Providence interposed 
to effect our deliverance, not one of 
our company could hope to see another morning 
after the morning of Sunday. 
</p>
<p>
Two discoveries that I made--after 
redeeming my promise overnight, to serve out 
with the morning whatever eatable thing I 
could find--helped to confirm me in my 
gloomy view of our future prospects. In the 
first place, when the few coffee-berries left, 
together with a small allowance of water, 
had been shared all round, I found on 
examining the lockers that not one grain 
of provision remained, fore or aft, in any 
part of the boat, and that our stock of 
fresh water was reduced to not much more 
than would fill a wine-bottle. In the 
second place, after the berries had been 
shared, and the water equally divided, I 
noticed that the sustenance thus administered 
produced no effect whatever, even of the 
most momentary kind, in raising the spirits 
of the passengers (excepting in one case) or in 
rallying the strength of the crew. The 
exception was Mr. Rarx. This tough and 
greedy old sinner seemed to wake up from 
the trance he had lain in so long, when the 
smell of the berries and water was under his 
nose. He swallowed his share with a gulp 
that many a younger and better man in the 
boat might have envied; and went maundering 
on to himself afterwards, as if he had got 
a new lease of life. He fancied now that he 
was digging a gold mine, all by himself, and 
going down bodily straight through the earth 
at the rate of thirty or forty miles an hour. 
“Leave me alone,” says he, “leave me alone. 
The lower I go, the richer I get. Down I 
go!--down, down, down, down, till I burst 
out at the other end of the world in a shower 
of gold!” So he went on, kicking feebly with 
his heels from time to time against the 
bottom of the boat. 
</p>
<p>
But, as for all the rest, it was a pitiful and 
dreadful sight to see of how little use their 
last shadow of a meal was to them. I myself 
attended, before anybody else was served, 
to the two poor women. Miss Coleshaw 
shook her head faintly, and pointed to her 
throat, when I offered her the few berries 
that fell to her share. I made a shift to 
crush them up fine and mix them with a 
little water, and got her to swallow that 
miserable drop of drink with the greatest 
difficulty. When it was down there came no 
change for the better over her face. Nor did 
she recover, for so much as a moment, the 
capacity to speak, even in a whisper. I next 
tried Mrs. Atherfield. It was hard to wake 
her out of the half-swooning, half-sleeping 
condition in which she lay,--and harder still 
to get her to open her lips when I put the 
tincup to them. When I had at last prevailed 
on her to swallow her allowance, she shut 
her eyes again, and fell back into her old 
position. I saw her lips moving; and, putting 
my ear close to them, caught some of the 
words she was murmuring to herself. She 
was still dreaming of The Golden Lucy. She 
and the child were walking somewhere by 
the banks of a lake, at the time when the 
buttercups are out. The Golden Lucy was 
gathering the buttercups, and making herself 
a watch-chain out of them, in imitation 
of the chain that her mother wore. They 
were carrying a little basket with them, and 
were going to dine together in a great 
hollow tree growing on the banks of the 
lake. To get this pretty picture painted 
on one’s mind as I got it, while listening 
to the poor mother’s broken words, and 
then to look up at the haggard faces of 
the men in the boat, and at the wild ocean 
rolling all round us, was such a change 
from fancy to reality as it has fallen, I 
hope, to few men’s lots to experience. 
</p>
<p>
My next thought, when I had done my 
best for the women, was for the Captain. 
I was free to risk losing my own share of 
water, if I pleased, so I tried, before tasting 
it myself, to get a little between his lips; 
but his teeth were fast clenched, and I had 
neither strength nor skill to open them. 
The faint warmth still remained, thank 
God, over his heart--but, in all other 
respects he lay beneath us like a dead man. 
In covering him up again as comfortably as 
I could, I found a bit of paper crunched in 
one of his hands, and took it out. There 
was some writing on it, but not a word 
was readable. I supposed, poor fellow, that 
he had been trying to write some last 
instructions for me, just before he dropped 
at his post. If they had been ever so easy 
to read, they would have been of no use 
now. To follow instructions we must have 
had some power to shape the boat’s course 
in a given direction--and this, which we 
had been gradually losing for some days 
past, we had now lost altogether. 
</p>
<p>
I had hoped that the serving out of the 
refreshment would have put a little modicum 
of strength into the arms of the men at the 
oars; but, as I have hinted, this hope turned 
out to be perfectly fruitless. Our last 
mockery of a meal, which had done nothing 
for the passengers, did nothing either for the 
crew--except to aggravate the pangs of 
hunger in the men who were still strong 
enough to feel them. While the weather 
held moderate, it was not of much 
consequence if one or two of the rowers kept 
dropping, in turn, into a kind of faint sleep over 
their oars. But if it came on to blow again 
(and we could expect nothing else in those 
seas and at that time of the year), how was 
I to steer, when the blades of the oars were 
out of the water ten times as often as they 
were in? The lives which we had undergone 
such suffering to preserve would have 
been lost in an instant by the swamping of 
the boat, if the wind had risen on the morning 
of Thursday, and had caught us trying to 
row any longer. 
</p>
<p>
Feeling this, I resolved, while the weather 
held moderately fine, to hoist the best 
substitute for a sail that we could produce, and 
to drive before the wind, on the chance (the 
last we had to hope for) of a ship picking us 
up. We had only continued to use the oars 
up to this time, in order to keep the course 
which the Captain had pointed out as 
likeliest to bring us near the land. Sailing 
had been out of the question from the first, 
the masts and suits of sails belonging to each 
boat having been out of them at the time of 
the wreck, and having gone down with the 
ship. This was an accident which there was 
no need to deplore, for we were too crowded 
from the first to admit of handling the boats 
properly, under their regular press of sail, 
in anything like rough weather. 
</p>
<p>
Having made up my mind on what it was 
necessary to do, I addressed the men, and 
told them that any notion of holding longer 
on our course with the oars was manifestly 
out of the question, and dangerous to all on 
board, as their own common sense might tell 
them, in the state to which the stoutest arms 
among us were now reduced. They looked 
round on each other as I said that, each man 
seeming to think his neighbour weaker than 
himself. I went on, and told them that we 
must take advantage of our present glimpse 
of moderate weather, and hoist the best sail 
we could set up, and drive before the wind, 
in the hope that it might please God to direct 
us in the way of some ship before it was too 
late. “Our only chance, my men,” I said, in 
conclusion, “is the chance of being picked 
up; and in these desolate seas one point of 
the compass is just as likely a point for our 
necessities as another. Half of you keep 
the boat before the sea, the other half bring 
out your knives, and do as I tell you.” The 
prospect of being relieved from the oars 
struck the wandering attention of the men 
directly; and they said, “Ay, ay, sir!” with 
something like a faint reflection of their 
former readiness, when the good ship was 
under their feet, and the mess-cans were 
filled with plenty of wholesome food. 
</p>
<p>
Thanks to Captain Ravender’s forethought 
in providing both boats with a coil of rope, 
we had our lashings, and the means of 
making what rigging was wanted, ready 
to hand. One of the oars was made fast 
to the thwart, and well stayed fore and 
aft, for a mast. A large pilot coat that I 
wore was spread; enough of sail for us. The 
only difficulty that puzzled me was 
occasioned by the necessity of making a yard. 
The men tried to tear up one of the thwarts, 
but were not strong enough. My own knife 
had been broken in the attempt to split a bit 
of plank for them; and I was almost at my 
wit’s end, when I luckily thought of searching 
the Captain’s pockets for his knife. I 
found it--a fine large knife of Sheffield 
manufacture, with plenty of blades, and a small 
saw among them. With this we made a shift 
to saw off about a third of another oar; and 
then the difficulty was conquered; and 
we got my pilot-coat hoisted on our jury-
mast, and rigged it as nigh as we could to the 
fashion of a lug-sail. 
</p>
<p>
I had looked anxiously towards the Surf-
boat, while we were rigging our mast, and 
observed, with a feeling of great relief, 
that the men in her--as soon as they 
discovered what we were about--were wise 
enough to follow our example. They got on 
faster than we did; being less put to it for 
room to turn round in. We set our sails as 
nearly as possible about the same time; and 
it was well for both boats that we finished 
our work when we did. At noon the wind began 
to rise again to a stiff breeze, which soon 
knocked up a heavy, tumbling sea. We drove 
before it in a direction North and by East, 
keeping wonderfully dry, considering all 
things. The mast stood well; and the sail, 
small as it was, did good service in steadying 
the boat and lifting her easily over the seas. 
I felt the cold after the loss of my coat, but not 
so badly as I had feared; for the two men who 
were with me in the stern sheets, sat as close 
as they could on either side of me, and helped 
with the warmth of their own bodies to keep 
the warmth in mine. Forward, I told off 
half-a-dozen of the most trustworthy of the 
men who could still muster strength enough 
to keep their eyes open, to set a watch, turn 
and turn about, on our frail rigging. The 
wind was steadily increasing, and if any 
accident happened to our mast, the chances were 
that the boat would broach-to, and that 
every one of us would go to the bottom. 
</p>
<p>
So we drove on--all through that day--
sometimes catching sight of the Surf-boat 
a little ahead of us--sometimes losing her 
altogether in the scud. How little and 
frail, how very different to the kind of 
boat that I had expected to see, she 
looked to my eyes now that I was out 
of her, and saw what she showed like on 
the waters for the first time! But to 
return to the Long-boat. The watch on the 
rigging was relieved every two hours, and at 
the same regular periods all the brightest 
eyes left amongst us looked out for the 
smallest vestige of a sail in view, and looked in 
vain. Among the passengers, nothing 
happened in the way of a change--except that 
Miss Coleshaw seemed to grow fainter, and 
that Mrs. Atherfield got restless, as if she 
were waking out of her long dream about the 
Golden Lucy. 
</p>
<p>
It got on towards sunset. The wind 
was rising to half a gale. The clouds 
which had been heavy all over the firmament 
since noon, were lifting to the westward, and 
leaving there, over the horizon line of the 
ocean, a long strip of clear pale greenish sky, 
overhung by a cloud-bank, whose ragged 
edges were tipped with burning crimson by 
the sun. I did not like the look of the night, 
and, keeping where I was, in the forward 
part of the boat, I helped the men to ease 
the strain off our mast, by lowering the yard 
a little and taking a pull on the sheet, so as 
to present to the wind a smaller surface even 
of our small sail. Noting the wild look of 
the weather, and the precautions we were 
taking against the chance of a gale rising in 
the night--and being, furthermore, as I believe, 
staggered in their minds by the death that had 
taken place among them--three of the passengers 
struggled up in the bottom of the boat, 
clasped their arms round me as if they were 
drowning men already, and hoarsely 
clamoured for a last drink of water, before the 
storm rose and sent us all to the bottom. 
</p>
<p>
“Water you shall have,” I said, “when I 
think the time has come to serve it out. The 
time has not come yet.” 
</p>
<p>
“Water, pray!” they all three groaned 
together. Two more passengers who were 
asleep, woke up, and joined the cry. 
</p>
<p>
“Silence!” I said. “There are not two 
spoonsful of fresh water left for each man in 
the boat. I shall wait three hours more for 
the chance of rain before I serve that out. 
Silence, and drop back to your places!” 
</p>
<p>
They let go of me, but clamoured weakly 
for water still; and, this time, the voices of 
some of the crew joined them. At this 
moment, to my great alarm (for I thought 
they were going mad and turning violent 
against me), I was seized round the neck 
by one of the men, who had been standing 
up, holding on by the mast, and looking 
out steadily to the westward. 
</p>
<p>
I raised my right hand to free myself; but 
before I touched him, the sight of the man’s 
face close to mine made me drop my arm 
again. There was a speechless, breathless, 
frantic joy in it, that made all the blood in 
my veins stand still in a moment. 
</p>
<p>
“Out with it!” I said. “Man alive, out 
with it, for God’s sake!” 
</p>
<p>
His breath beat on my cheek in hot, quick, 
heavy gasps; but he could not utter a word. 
For a moment he let go of the mast (tightening 
his hold on me with the other arm) and 
pointed out westward--then slid heavily down 
on to the thwart behind us. 
</p>
<p>
I looked westward, and saw that one of 
the two trustworthy men whom I had left 
at the helm was on his feet looking out 
westward, too. As the boat rose, I fixed my eyes 
on the strip of clear greenish sky in the west, 
and on the bright line of the sea just under 
it. The boat dipped again before I could see 
anything. I squeezed my eyelids together to 
get the water out of them, and when we rose 
again looked straight into the middle of the 
bright sea-line. My heart bounded as if it 
would choke me--my tongue felt like a 
cinder in my mouth--my knees gave way 
under me--I dropped down on to the thwart, 
and sobbed out, with a great effort, as if I 
had been dumb for weeks before, and had 
only that instant found my speech: 
</p>
<p>
“A sail! a sail!” 
</p>
<p>
The words were instantly echoed by the 
man in the stern sheets. 
</p>
<p>
“Sail, ho!” he screeches out, turning 
round on us, and swinging his arms about 
his head like a madman. 
</p>
<p>
This made three of our company who had 
seen the ship already, and that one fact was 
sufficient to remove all dread lest our eyes 
might have been deceiving us. The great 
fear now was, not that we were deluded, but 
that we might come to some serious harm 
through the excess of joy among the people; 
that is to say, among such of the people as 
still had the sense to feel and the strength to 
express what they felt. I must record in my 
own justification, after confessing that I lost 
command over myself altogether on the 
discovery of the sail, that I was the first who 
set the example of self-control. I was in a 
manner forced to this by the crew frantically 
entreating me to lay-to until we could make 
out what course the ship was steering--a 
proceeding which, with the sea then running, 
with the heavy lading of the boat, and with 
such feeble substitutes for mast and sail as 
we possessed, must have been attended with 
total destruction to us all. I tried to remind 
the men of this, but they were in such a 
transport--hugging each other round the 
neck, and crying and laughing all in a breath--
that they were not fit to listen to reason. 
Accordingly, I myself went to the helm 
again, and chose the steadiest of my two men 
in the after part of the boat, as a guard over 
the sheet, with instructions to use force, if 
necessary, towards any one who stretched out 
so much as a finger to it. The wind was 
rising every minute, and we had nothing for 
it but to scud, and be thankful to God’s 
mercy that we had sea-room to do it in. 
</p>
<p>
“It will be dark in an hour’s time, sir,” 
says the man left along with me when I took 
the helm again. “We have no light to show. 
The ship will pass us in the night. Lay to, 
sir! For the love of Heaven, give us all a 
chance, and lay to!” says he, and goes 
down on his knees before me, wringing his 
hands. 
</p>
<p>
“Lay to!” says I. “Lay to, under a coat! 
Lay to, in a boat like this, with the wind 
getting up to a gale! A seaman like you 
talk in that way! Who have I got along 
here with me? Sailors who know their craft, 
or a pack of long-shore lubbers, who ought 
to be turned adrift in a ferry-boat on a 
pond?” My heart was heavy enough, God 
knows, but I spoke out as loud as I could, in 
that light way, to try and shame the men 
back to their proper senses. I succeeded at 
least in restoring silence; and that was 
something in such a condition as ours. 
</p>
<p>
My next anxiety was to know if the men 
in the Surf-Boat had sighted the sail to the 
westward. She was still driving a-head of 
us, and the first time I saw her rise on the 
waves, I made out a signal on board--a strip 
of cloth fastened to a boat-hook. I ordered 
the man by my side to return it with his 
jacket tied on to the end of an oar; being 
anxious to see whether his agitation had 
calmed down and left him fit for his duty 
again. He followed my directions steadily 
and when he had got his jacket on again, 
asked me to pardon him for losing his self-
command in a quiet, altered voice. 
</p>
<p>
I shook hands with him, and gave him 
the helm, in proof that my confidence was 
restored; then stood up and turned my face to 
the westward once again. I looked long into 
the belt of clear sky, which was narrowing 
already as the cloud-bank above sank over it. 
I looked with all my heart and soul and 
strength. It was only when my eyes could 
stand the strain on them no longer, that I 
gave in, and sat down again by the tiller. If I 
had not been supported by a firm trust in 
the mercy of Providence, which had 
preserved us thus far, I am afraid I should have 
abandoned myself at that trying time to 
downright hopeless, speechless despair. 
</p>
<p>
It would not express much to any but 
seafaring readers if I mentioned the number of 
leagues off that I considered the ship to be. 
I shall give a better idea of the terrible 
distance there was between us, when I say that 
no landsman’s eye could have made her out 
at all, and that none of us sailors could have 
seen her but for the bright opening in 
the sky, which made even a speck on 
the waters visible to a mariner’s 
experienced sight all that weary way off. When 
I have said this, I have said enough to 
render it plain to every man’s 
understanding that it was a sheer impossibility 
to make out what course the ship was 
steering, seeing that we had no chance of 
keeping her in view at that closing time of 
day for more than another half-hour, at most. 
There she was, astern to leeward of us; and 
here were we, driving for our lives before the 
wind, with any means of kindling a light that 
we might have possessed on leaving our ship 
wetted through long ago--with no guns to 
fire as signals of distress in the darkness--
and with no choice, if the wind shifted, but 
still to scud in any direction in which it might 
please to drive us. Supposing, even at the 
best, that the ship was steering on our course, 
and would overhaul us in the night, what 
chance had we of making our position known 
to her in the darkness? Truly, look at it 
anyhow we might from our poor mortal point 
of view, our prospect of deliverance seemed 
to be of the most utterly hopeless kind that 
it is possible to conceive. 
</p>
<p>
The men felt this bitterly, as the cloud-
bank dropped to the verge of the waters, and 
the sun set redly behind it. The moaning 
and lamenting among them was miserable to 
hear, when the last speck and phantom of 
the ship had vanished from view. Some few 
still swore they saw her when there was 
hardly a flicker of light left in the west, and 
only gave up looking out, and dropped 
down in the boat, at my express orders. I 
charged them all solemnly to set an example 
of courage to the passengers, and to trust the 
rest to the infinite wisdom and mercy of the 
Creator of us all. Some murmured, some 
fell to repeating scraps out of the Bible and 
Prayer-Book, some wandered again in their 
minds. This went on till the darkness 
gathered--then a great hush of silence fell 
drearily over passengers and crew; and the 
waves and the wind hissed and howled about 
us, as if we were tossing in the midst of them, 
a boat-load of corpses already! 
</p>
<p>
Twice in the forepart of the night the 
clouds overhead parted for a little, and let 
the blessed moonlight down upon us. On 
the first of those occasions, I myself served 
out the last drops of fresh water we had left. 
The two women--poor suffering creatures!--
were past drinking. Miss Coleshaw shivered 
a little when I moistened her lips with the 
water; and Mrs. Atherfield, when I did the 
same for her, drew her breath with a faint, 
fluttering sigh, which was just enough to 
show that she was not dead yet. The Captain 
still lay as he had lain ever since I got on 
board the boat. The others, both passengers 
and crew, managed for the most part to 
swallow their share of the water--the men 
being just sufficiently roused by it to get up on 
their knees, while the moonlight lasted, and 
look about wildly over the ocean for a chance 
of seeing the ship again. When the clouds 
gathered once more; they crouched back in 
their places with a long groan of despair. 
Hearing that, and dreading the effect of the 
pitchy darkness (to say nothing of the fierce 
wind and sea) on their sinking spirits, I 
resolved to combat their despondency, if it 
were still possible to contend against it, by 
giving them something to do. First telling 
them that no man could say at what time of 
the night the ship (in case she was steering 
our course) might forge ahead of us, or how 
near she might be when she passed, I 
recommended that all who had the strength should 
join their voices at regular intervals, and 
shout their loudest when the boat rose 
highest on the waves, on the chance of that 
cry of distress being borne by the wind within 
hearing of the watch on board the ship. It is 
unnecessary to say that I knew well how near 
it was to an absolute impossibility that this 
last feeble exertion on our parts could lead 
to any result. I only proposed it because I 
was driven to the end of my resources to keep 
up the faintest flicker of spirit among the 
men. They received my proposal with more 
warmth and readiness than I had ventured 
in their hopeless state, to expect from them. 
Up to the turn of midnight they resolutely 
raised their voices with me, at intervals 
of from five to ten minutes, whenever the 
boat was tossed highest on the waves. The 
wind seemed to whirl our weak cries savagely 
out of our mouths almost before we could 
utter them. I, sitting astern in the boat, 
only heard them, as it seemed, for something 
like an instant of time. But even that was 
enough to make me creep all over--the 
cry was so forlorn and fearful. Of all 
the dreadful sounds I had heard since 
the first striking of the ship, that shrill 
wail of despair--rising on the wave-tops, one 
moment; whirled away, the next, into the black 
night--was the most frightful that entered 
my ears. There are times, even now, when it 
seems to be ringing in them still. 
</p>
<p>
Whether our first gleam of moonshine fell 
upon old Mr. Rarx, while he was sleeping, 
and helped to upset his weak brains 
altogether, is more than I can say. But, for 
some reason or other, before the clouds 
parted and let the light down on us for the 
second time, and while we were driving along 
awfully through the blackest of the night, he 
stirred in his place, and began rambling 
and raving again more vehemently than ever. 
To hear him now--that is to say, as well as I 
could hear him for the wind--he was still 
down in his gold-mine; but was laden so 
heavy with his precious metal that he could 
not get out, and was in mortal peril of being 
drowned by the water rising in the bottom of 
the shaft. So far, his maundering attracted 
my attention disagreeably, and did no more. 
But when he began--if I may say so--to 
take the name of the dear little dead child in 
vain, and to mix her up with himself and 
his miserly greed of gain, I got angry, and 
called to the men forward to give him a 
shake and make him hold his tongue. 
Whether any of them obeyed or not, I don’t 
know--Mr. Rarx went on raving louder than 
ever. The shrill wind was now hardly more 
shrill than he. He swore he saw the white 
frock of our poor little lost pet fluttering in 
the daylight, at the top of the mine, and 
he screamed out to her in a great fright 
that the gold was heavy, and the water 
rising fast, and that she must come down 
quick as lightning if she meant to be in time 
to help him. I called again angrily to the 
men to silence him; and just as I did so, the 
clouds began to part for the second time, and 
the white tip of the moon grew visible. 
</p>
<p>
“There she is!” screeches Mr. Rarx; and 
I saw him by the faint light, scramble on his 
knees in the bottom of the boat, and wave a 
ragged old handkerchief up at the moon. 
</p>
<p>
“Pull him down!” I called out. “Down 
with him; and tie his arms and legs!” 
</p>
<p>
Of the men who could still move about, 
not one paid any attention to me. They were 
all upon their knees again, looking out in the 
strengthening moonlight for a sight of the ship. 
</p>
<p>
“Quick, Golden Lucy!” screams Mr. Rarx, 
and creeps under the thwarts right forward 
into the bows of the boat. “Quick! my 
darling, my beauty, quick! The gold is 
heavy, and the water rises fast! Come down 
and save me, Golden Lucy! Let all the rest 
of the world drown, and save me! Me! me! 
me! me!” 
</p>
<p>
He shouted these last words out at the 
top of his cracked, croaking voice, and 
got on his feet, as I conjectured (for the 
coat we had spread for a sail now hid 
him from me) in the bows of the boat. Not 
one of the crew so much as looked round 
at him, so eagerly were their eyes seeking 
for the ship. The man sitting by me 
was sunk in a deep sleep. If I had left 
the helm for a moment in that wind and 
sea, it would have been the death of 
every soul of us. I shouted desperately to 
the raving wretch to sit down. A screech 
that seemed to cut the very wind in two 
answered me. A huge wave tossed the boat’s 
head up wildly at the same moment. I 
looked aside to leeward as the wash of the 
great roller swept by us, gleaming of a lurid, 
bluish white in the moonbeams; I looked 
and saw, in one second of time, the face of 
Mr. Rarx rush past on the wave, with the 
foam seething in his hair and the moon 
shining in his eyes. Before I could draw my 
breath he was a hundred yards astern of us, 
and the night and the sea had swallowed him 
up and had hid his secret, which he had kept 
all the voyage, from our mortal curiosity, for 
ever. 
</p>
<p>
“He’s gone! he’s drowned!” I shouted to 
the men forward. 
</p>
<p>
None of them took any notice; none of 
them left off looking out over the ocean for 
a sight of the ship. Nothing that I could 
say on the subject of our situation at that 
fearful time can, in my opinion, give such an 
idea of the extremity and the frightfulness of 
it, as the relation of this one fact. I leave it 
to speak by itself the sad and shocking truth, 
and pass on gladly to the telling of what 
happened next, at a later hour of the night. 
</p>
<p>
After the clouds had shut out the moon 
again, the wind dropped a little and shifted 
a point or two, so as to shape our course 
nearer to the eastward. How the hours 
passed after that, till the dawn came, is more 
than I can tell. The nearer the time of 
daylight approached the more completely 
everything seemed to drop out of my mind, except 
the one thought of where the ship we had 
seen in the evening might be, when we looked 
for her with the morning light. 
</p>
<p>
It came at last--that grey, quiet light 
which was to end all our uncertainty; which 
was to show us if we were saved, or to warn 
us if we were to prepare for death. With 
the first streak in the east, every one of the 
boat’s company, except the sleeping and the 
senseless, roused up and looked out in breathless 
silence upon the sea. Slowly and slowly 
the daylight strengthened, and the darkness 
rolled off farther and farther before it over 
the face of the waters. The first pale flush 
of the sun flew trembling along the paths of 
light broken through the grey wastes of the 
eastern clouds. We could look clearly--we 
could see far; and there, ahead of us--O! 
merciful, bountiful providence of God!--there 
was the ship! 
</p>
<p>
I have honestly owned the truth, and 
confessed to the human infirmity under suffering 
of myself, my passengers, and my crew. I 
have earned, therefore, as I would fain hope, 
the right to record it to the credit of all, that 
the men, the moment they set eyes on the 
ship, poured out their whole hearts in 
humble thanksgiving to the Divine Mercy which 
had saved them from the very jaws of death. 
They did not wait for me to bid them do this; 
they did it of their own accord, in their own 
language, fervently, earnestly, with one will 
and one heart. 
</p>
<p>
We had hardly made the ship out--a fine 
brigantine, hoisting English colours--before 
we observed that her crew suddenly hove her 
up in the wind. At first we were at a loss 
to understand this; but as we drew nearer, 
we discovered that she was getting the Surf-
boat (which had kept ahead of us all through 
the night) alongside of her, under the lee 
bow. My men tried to cheer when they saw 
their companions in safety, but their weak 
cries died away in tears and sobbing. 
</p>
<p>
In another half hour we, too, were alongside 
of the brigantine. 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
From this point, I recollect nothing very 
distinctly. I remember faintly many loud 
voices and eager faces;--I remember fresh 
strong willing fellows, with a colour in their 
cheeks, and a smartness in their movements 
that seemed quite preternatural to me at that 
time, hanging over us in the rigging of the 
brigantine, and dropping down from her sides 
into our boat;--I remember trying with my 
feeble hands to help them in the difficult and 
perilous task of getting the two poor women 
and the Captain on board;--I remember one 
dark hairy giant of a man swearing that it 
was enough to break his heart, and catching 
me in his arms like a child--and from that 
moment I remember nothing more with the 
slightest certainty for over a week of time. 
</p>
<p>
When I came to my own senses again, 
in my cot on board the brigantine my first 
inquiries were naturally for my fellow-
sufferers. Two--a passenger in the Long-boat, 
and one of the crew of the Surf-boat--
had sunk in spite of all the care that could 
be taken of them. The rest were likely, with 
time and attention, to recover. Of those 
who have been particularly mentioned in 
this narrative, Mrs. Atherfield had shown 
signs of rallying the soonest; Miss Coleshaw, 
who had held out longer against exhaustion, 
was now the slower to recover. Captain 
Ravender, though slowly mending, was still 
not able to speak or to move in his cot 
without help. The sacrifices for us all which 
this good man had so nobly undergone, not 
only in the boat, but before that, when he 
had deprived himself of his natural rest on 
the dark nights that preceded the wreck of 
the Golden Mary, had sadly undermined his 
natural strength of constitution. He, the 
heartiest of all, when we sailed from England, 
was now, through his unwearying devotion 
to his duty and to us, the last to recover, the 
longest to linger between life and death. 
</p>
<p>
My next questions (when they helped me on 
deck to get my first blessed breath of fresh 
air) related to the vessel that had saved us. 
She was bound to the Columbia river--a long 
way to the northward of the port for which we 
had sailed in the Golden Mary. Most 
providentially for us, shortly after we had lost sight 
of the brigantine in the shades of the evening, 
she had been caught in a squall, and had 
sprung her foretopmast badly. This accident 
had obliged them to lay-to for some hours, 
while they did their best to secure the spar, 
and had warned them, when they continued 
on their course, to keep the ship under easy 
sail through the night. But for this 
circumstance we must, in all human probability, 
have been too far astern when the morning 
dawned, to have had the slightest chance 
of being discovered. 
</p>
<p>
Excepting always some of the stoutest of 
our men, the next of the Long-boat’s company 
who was helped on deck was Mrs. Atherfield. 
Poor soul! when she and I first looked at 
each other, I could see that her heart went 
back to the early days of our voyage, when 
the Golden Lucy and I used to have our 
game of hide-and-seek round the mast. She 
squeezed my hand as hard as she could with 
her wasted trembling fingers, and looked up 
piteously in my face, as if she would like to 
speak to little Lucy’s playfellow, but dared 
not trust herself--then turned away quickly 
and laid her head against the bulwark, and 
looked out upon the desolate sea that was 
nothing to her now but her darling’s grave. 
I was better pleased when I saw her later in 
the day, sitting by Captain Ravender’s cot; 
for she seemed to take comfort in nursing 
him. Miss Coleshaw soon afterwards got 
strong enough to relieve her at this duty; 
and, between them, they did the Captain such 
a world of good, both in body and spirit, that 
he also got strong enough before long to come 
on deck, and to thank me, in his old generous 
self-forgetful way, for having done my duty--
the duty which I had learnt how to do by his 
example. 
</p>
<p>
Hearing what our destination had been 
when we sailed from England, the captain of 
the brigantine (who had treated us with the 
most unremitting attention and kindness, 
and had been warmly seconded in his efforts 
for our good by all the people under his 
command) volunteered to go sufficiently out 
of his course to enable us to speak the first 
Californian coasting-vessel sailing in the 
direction of San Francisco. We were lucky in 
meeting with one of these sooner than we 
expected. Three days after parting from the 
kind captain of the brigantine, we, the 
surviving passengers and crew of the Golden 
Mary, touched the firm ground once more, on 
the shores of California. 
</p>
<p>
We were hardly collected here before we 
were obliged to separate again. Captain 
Ravender, though he was hardly yet in good 
travelling trim, accompanied Mrs. Atherfield 
inland, to see her safe under her husband’s 
protection. Miss Coleshaw went with them, 
to stay with Mrs. Atherfield for a little while 
before she attempted to proceed with any 
matters of her own which had brought her 
to this part of the world. The rest of us, 
who were left behind with nothing particular 
to do until the Captain’s return, followed the 
passengers to the gold diggings. Some few 
of us had enough of the life there in a very 
short time. The rest seemed bitten by old 
Mr. Rarx’s mania for gold, and insisted on 
stopping behind when Rames and I proposed 
going back to the port. We two, and five of 
our steadiest seamen, were all the officers and 
crew left to meet the Captain on his return 
from the inland country. 
</p>
<p>
He reported that he had left Mrs. Atherfield 
and Miss Coleshaw safe and comfortable 
under Mr. Atherfield’s care. They sent 
affectionate messages to all of us, and especially 
(I am proud to say) to me. After hearing 
this good news, there seemed nothing better 
to do than to ship on board the first vessel 
bound for England. There were plenty in 
port, ready to sail, and only waiting for the 
men belonging to them who had deserted to 
the gold-diggings. We were all snapped up 
eagerly, and offered any rate we chose to set 
on our services, the moment we made known 
our readiness to ship for England--all, I 
ought to have said, except Captain Ravender, 
who went along with us in the capacity of 
passenger only. 
</p>
<p>
Nothing of any moment occurred on the 
voyage back. The Captain and I got ashore 
at Gravesend safe and hearty, and went up 
to London as fast as the train could carry us, 
to report the calamity that had occurred to 
the owners of the Golden Mary. When that 
duty had been performed, Captain Ravender 
went back to his own house at Poplar, 
and I travelled to the West of England 
to report myself, to my old father and 
mother. 
</p>
<p>
Here I might well end all these pages of 
writing; but I cannot refrain from adding a 
few more sentences, to tell the reader what 
I am sure he will be glad to hear. In the 
summer-time of this present year eighteen 
hundred and fifty-six, I happened to be at 
New York, and having spare time on my 
hands, and spare cash in my pocket, I walked 
into one of the biggest and grandest of their 
Ordinaries there, to have my dinner. I had 
hardly sat down at table, before who should 
I see opposite but Mrs. Atherfield, as bright-
eyed and pretty as ever, with a gentleman on 
her right hand, and on her left--another 
Golden Lucy! Her hair was a shade or two 
darker than the hair of my poor little pet of 
past sad times; but in all other respects the 
living child reminded me so strongly of the 
dead, that I quite started at the first sight of 
her. I could not tell, if I was to try, how 
happy we were after dinner, or how much we 
had to say to each other. I was introduced 
to Mrs. Atherfield’s husband, and heard from 
him, among other things, that Miss Coleshaw 
was married to her old sweetheart, who 
had fallen into misfortunes and errors, and 
whom she was determined to set right by 
giving him the great chance in life of getting 
a good wife. They were settled in America, 
like Mr. and Mrs. Atherfield--these last and 
the child being on their way, when I met 
them, to visit a friend living in the northern-
most part of the States. 
</p>
<p>
With the relation of this circumstance, and 
with my personal testimony to the good 
health and spirits of Captain Ravender the 
last time I saw him, ends all that I have to 
say in connection with the subject of the 
Wreck of the Golden Mary, and the Great 
Deliverance of her People at Sea. 
</p>
<section>THE END OF THE CHRISTMAS NUMBER FOR 1856.</section>
</chapter>
</book>
