<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>The Perils Of Certain English Prisoners</title>
<subtitle>(Household Words Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1857</date>
<option name="chapter.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="chapter.number_style" value="NONE"/>
</info>

<prefix>
<info title="THE PERILS OF CERTAIN ENGLISH PRISONERS"/>
<centre>AND THEIR TREASURE IN WOMEN, CHILDREN, SILVER, AND JEWELS.</centre>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1857.</centre>
</prefix>

<chapter>
<title>THE ISLAND OF SILVER-STORE.</title>
<p>
IT was in the year of our Lord one thousand 
seven hundred and forty-four, that I, 
Gill Davis to command, His Mark, having 
then the honor to be a private in the Royal 
Marines, stood a-leaning over the bulwarks 
of the armed sloop Christopher Columbus, in 
the South American waters off the Mosquito 
shore. 
</p>
<p>
My lady remarks to me, before I go any 
further, that there is no such christian-name 
as Gill, and that her confident opinion is, 
that the name given to me in the baptism 
wherein I was made, &amp;c., was Gilbert. She 
is certain to be right, but I never heard of 
it. I was a foundling child, picked up 
somewhere or another, and I always understood 
my christian-name to be Gill. It is true that 
I was called Gills when employed at 
Snorridge Bottom betwixt Chatham and 
Maidstone, to frighten birds; but that had nothing 
to do with the Baptism wherein I was made, 
&amp;c., and wherein a number of things were 
promised for me by somebody, who let me 
alone ever afterwards as to performing any of 
them, and who, I consider, must have been 
the Beadle. Such name of Gills was entirely 
owing to my cheeks, or gills, which at that 
time of my life were of a raspy description. 
</p>
<p>
My lady stops me again, before I go any 
further, by laughing exactly in her old way 
and waving the feather of her pen at me. 
That action on her part, calls to my mind as 
I look at her hand with the rings on it--
Well! I won't! To be sure it will come in, in 
its own place. But it's always strange to me, 
noticing the quiet hand, and noticing it (as I 
have done, you know, so many times) 
a-fondling children and grandchildren asleep, 
to think that when blood and honor were 
up--there! I won't! not at present!--
Scratch it out. 
</p>
<p>
She won't scratch it out, and quite honorable; 
because we have made an understanding 
that everything is to be taken down, and 
that nothing that is once taken down shall be 
scratched out. I have the great misfortune 
not to be able to read and write, and I am 
speaking my true and faithful account of those 
Adventures, and my lady is writing it, word 
for word. 
</p>
<p>
I say, there I was, a-leaning over the 
bulwarks of the sloop Christopher Columbus in 
the South American waters off the Mosquito 
shore: a subject of his Gracious Majesty 
King George of England, and a private in 
the Royal Marines. 
</p>
<p>
In those climates, you don't want to do 
much. I was doing nothing. I was thinking 
of the shepherd (my father, I wonder?) on 
the hill-sides by Snorridge Bottom, with a 
long staff, and with a rough white coat in all 
weathers all the year round, who used to let 
me lie in a corner of his hut by night, and 
who used to let me go about with him and 
his sheep by day when I could get nothing 
else to do, and who used to give me so little 
of his victuals and so much of his staff, that 
I ran away from him--which was what he 
wanted all along, I expect--to be knocked 
about the world in preference to Snorridge 
Bottom. I had been knocked about the 
world for nine-and-twenty years in all, when 
I stood looking along those bright blue 
South American waters. Looking after the 
shepherd, I may say. Watching him in a 
half-waking dream, with my eyes half-shut, 
as he, and his flock of sheep, and his two 
dogs, seemed to move away from the ship's 
side, far away over the blue water, and go 
right down into the sky. 
</p>
<p>
"It's rising out of the water, steady," a 
voice said close to me. I had been thinking 
on so, that it like woke me with a start, 
though it was no stranger voice than the 
voice of Harry Charker, my own comrade. 
</p>
<p>
"What's rising out of the water, steady?" 
I asked my comrade. 
</p>
<p>
"What?" says he. "The Island." 
</p>
<p>
"O! The Island!" says I, turning my 
eyes towards it. "True. I forgot the Island." 
</p>
<p>
"Forgot the port you're going to? That's 
odd, an't it?" 
</p>
<p>
"It is odd," says I. 
</p>
<p>
"And odd," he said, slowly considering 
with himself, "an't even. Is it, Gill?" 
</p>
<p>
He had always a remark just like that to 
make, and seldom another. As soon as he 
had brought a thing round to what it was 
not, he was satisfied. He was one of the 
best of men, and, in a certain sort of a 
way, one with the least to say for himself. 
I qualify it, because, besides being able to 
read and write like a Quarter-master, he had 
always one most excellent idea in his mind. 
That was, Duty. Upon my soul, I don't 
believe, though I admire learning beyond 
everything, that he could have got a better 
idea out of all the books in the world, if he 
had learnt them every word, and been the 
cleverest of scholars. 
</p>
<p>
My comrade and I had been quartered 
in Jamaica, and from there we had been 
drafted off to the British settlement of 
Belize, lying away West and North of the 
Mosquito coast. At Belize there had been 
great alarm of one cruel gang of pirates 
(there were always more pirates than enough 
in those Caribbean Seas), and as they got 
the better of our English cruisers by running 
into out-of-the-way creeks and shallows, and 
taking the land when they were hotly 
pressed, the governor of Belize had received 
orders from home to keep a sharp look-out 
for them along shore. Now, there was an 
armed sloop came once a-year from Port 
Royal, Jamaica, to the Island, laden with 
all manner of necessaries, to eat and to drink, 
and to wear, and to use in various ways; and 
it was aboard of that sloop which had 
touched at Belize, that I was a-standing, leaning 
over the bulwarks. 
</p>
<p>
The Island was occupied by a very small 
English colony. It had been given the name 
of Silver-Store. The reason of its being so 
called, was, that the English colony owned 
and worked a silver mine over on the mainland, 
in Honduras, and used this island as a 
safe and convenient place to store their silver 
in, until it was annually fetched away by the 
sloop. It was brought down from the mine 
to the coast on the backs of mules, attended 
by friendly Indians and guarded by white 
men; from thence, it was conveyed over to 
Silver-Store, when the weather was fair, in 
the canoes of that country; from Silver-Store, 
it was carried to Jamaica by the armed 
sloop once a-year, as I have already 
mentioned; from Jamaica it went, of course, all 
over the world. 
</p>
<p>
How I came to be aboard the armed sloop, 
is easily told. Four-and-twenty marines under 
command of a lieutenant--that officer's name 
was Linderwood--had been told off at Belize, 
to proceed to Silver-Store, in aid of boats 
and seamen stationed there for the chace 
of the Pirates. The island was considered 
a good post of observation against the 
pirates, both by land and sea; neither the 
pirate ship nor yet her boats had been seen by 
any of us, but they had been so much heard of, 
that the reinforcement was sent. Of that 
party, I was one. It included a corporal and a 
Serjeant. Charker was corporal, and the 
serjeant's name was Drooce. He was the most 
tyrannical non-commissioned officer in His 
Majesty's service. 
</p>
<p>
The night came on, soon after I had had 
the foregoing words with Charker. All the 
wonderful bright colors went out of the sea 
and sky, in a few minutes, and all the stars 
in the Heavens seemed to shine out together, 
and to look down at themselves in the sea, over 
one another's shoulders, millions deep. Next 
morning, we cast anchor off the Island. There 
was a snug harbor within a little reef; there 
was a sandy beach; there were cocoa-nut trees 
with high straight stems, quite bare, and 
foliage at the top like plumes of magnificent 
green feathers; there were all the objects 
that are usually seen in those parts, and I 
am not going to describe them, having 
something else to tell about. 
</p>
<p>
Great rejoicings, to be sure, were made 
on our arrival. All the flags in the place 
were hoisted, all the guns in the place were 
fired, and all the people in the place came 
down to look at us. One of those Sambo 
fellows--they call those natives Sambos, when 
they are half-negro and half-Indian--had 
come off outside the reef, to pilot us in, 
and remained on board after we had let go 
our anchor. He was called Christian George 
King, and was fonder of all hands than 
anybody else was. Now, I confess, for 
myself, that on that first day, if I had been 
captain of the Christopher Columbus, instead of 
private in the Royal Marines, I should have 
kicked Christian George King--who was no 
more a Christian, than he was a King, or a 
George--over the side, without exactly knowing 
why, except that it was the right thing 
to do. 
</p>
<p>
But, I must likewise confess, that I was not 
in a particularly pleasant humor, when I stood 
under arms that morning, aboard the 
Christopher Columbus in the harbor of the 
Island of Silver-Store. I had had a hard 
life, and the life of the English on the Island 
seemed too easy and too gay, to please me. 
"Here you are," I thought to myself, "good 
scholars and good livers; able to read what 
you like, able to write what you like, able 
to eat and drink what you like, and spend 
what you like, and do what you like; and 
much you care for a poor, ignorant Private 
in the Royal Marines! Yet it's hard, too, I 
think, that you should have all the 
halfpence, and I all the kicks; you all the smooth, 
and I all the rough; you all the oil, and I 
all the vinegar." It was as envious a thing 
to think as might be, let alone its being 
nonsensical; but, I thought it. I took it so 
much amiss, that, when a very beautiful young 
English lady came aboard, I grunted to 
myself, "Ah! you have got a lover, I'll be 
bound!" As if there was any new offence 
to me in that, if she had! 
</p>
<p>
She was sister to the captain of our sloop, 
who had been in a poor way for some time, 
and who was so ill then that he was obliged to 
be carried ashore. She was the child of a 
military officer, and had come out there with 
her sister, who was married to one of the 
owners of the silver-mine, and who had three 
children with her. It was easy to see that 
she was the light and spirit of the Island. 
After I had got a good look at her, I grunted 
to myself again, in an even worse state of 
mind than before, "I'll be damned, if I 
don't hate him, whoever he is!" 
</p>
<p>
My officer, Lieutenant Linderwood, was as 
ill as the captain of the sloop, and was 
carried ashore, too. They were both young 
men of about my age, who had been delicate 
in the West India climate. I even took 
that, in bad part. I thought I was much 
fitter for the work than they were, and 
that if all of us had our deserts, I should 
be both of them rolled into one. (It may be 
imagined what sort of an officer of marines I 
should have made, without the power of 
reading a written order. And as to any 
knowledge how to command the sloop--Lord! 
I should have sunk her in a quarter of an 
hour!) 
</p>
<p>
However, such were my reflections; and 
when we men were ashore aud dismissed, I 
strolled about the place along with Charker, 
making my observations in a similar spirit. 
</p>
<p>
It was a pretty place: in all its arrangements 
partly South American and partly 
English, and very agreeable to look at on 
that account, being like a bit of home that 
had got chipped off and had floated away to 
that spot, accommodating itself to 
circumstances as it drifted along. The huts of the 
Sambos, to the number of five-and-twenty, 
perhaps, were down by the beach to the left 
of the anchorage. On the right was a sort 
of barrack, with a South American Flag 
and the Union Jack, flying from the same 
staff, where the little English colony could 
all come together, if they saw occasion. It 
was a walled square of building, with a sort 
of pleasure-ground inside, and inside that 
again, a sunken block like a powder magazine, 
with a little square trench round it, and 
steps down to the door. Charker and I 
were looking in at the gate, which was 
not guarded; and I had said to Charker, 
in reference to the bit like a powder magazine, 
"that's where they keep the silver, 
you see;" and Charker had said to me, after 
thinking it over, "And silver an't gold. Is it, 
Gill?" when the beautiful young English 
lady I had been so bilious about, looked out 
of a door, or a window--at all events looked 
out, from under a bright awning. She no 
sooner saw us two in uniform, than she came 
out so quickly that she was still putting on 
her broad Mexican hat of plaited straw when 
we saluted. 
</p>
<p>
"Would you like to come in," she said, 
"and see the place? It is rather a curious 
place." 
</p>
<p>
We thanked the young lady, and said we 
didn't wish to be troublesome; but, she said 
it could be no trouble to an English 
soldier's daughter, to show English soldiers 
how their countrymen aud countrywomen 
fared, so far away from England; and 
consequently we saluted again, and went in. 
Then, as we stood in the shade, she showed 
us (being as affable as beautiful), how the 
different families lived in their separate 
houses, and how there was a general house 
for stores, and a general reading-room, and a 
general room for music and dancing, and a 
room for Church; and how there were other 
houses on the rising-ground called the Signal 
Hill, where they lived in the hotter weather. 
</p>
<p>
"Your officer has been carried up there," 
she said, "and my brother, too, for the better 
air. At present, our few residents are 
dispersed over both spots: deducting, that is to 
say, such of our number as are always going 
to, or coming from, or staying at, the Mine." 
</p>
<p>
("<em>He</em> is among one of those parties," I 
thought, "and I wish somebody would knock 
his head off.") 
</p>
<p>
"Some of our married ladies live here," 
she said, "during at least half the year, as 
lonely as widows, with their children." 
</p>
<p>
"Many children here, ma'am?" 
</p>
<p>
"Seventeen. There are thirteen married 
ladies, and there are eight like me." 
</p>
<p>
There were not eight like her--there was 
not one like her--in the world. She meant, 
single. 
</p>
<p>
"Which, with about thirty Englishmen of 
various degrees," said the young lady, "form 
the little colony now on the Island. I don't 
count the sailors, for they don't belong to us. 
Nor the soldiers," she gave us a gracious 
smile when she spoke of the soldiers, "for 
the same reason." 
</p>
<p>
"Nor the Sambos, ma'am," said I. 
</p>
<p>
"No." 
</p>
<p>
"Under your favor, and with your leave, 
ma'am," said I, "are they trustworthy?" 
</p>
<p>
"Perfectly! We are all very kind to 
them, and they are very grateful to us." 
</p>
<p>
"Indeed, ma'am? Now--Christian George 
King?--" 
</p>
<p>
"Very much attached to us all. Would 
die for us." 
</p>
<p>
She was, as in my uneducated way I have 
observed very beautiful women almost 
always to be, so composed, that her 
composure gave great weight to what she said, 
and I believed it. 
</p>
<p>
Then, she pointed out to us the building 
like a powder magazine, and explained to 
us in what manner the silver was brought 
from the mine, and was brought over from 
the mainland, and was stored there. The 
Christopher Columbus would have a rich 
lading, she said, for there had been a great 
yield that year, a much richer yield than 
usual, and there was a chest of jewels besides 
the silver. 
</p>
<p>
When we had looked about us, and were 
getting sheepish, through fearing we were 
troublesome, she turned us over to a young 
woman, English born but West India bred, 
who served her as her maid. This young 
woman was the widow of a non-commissioned 
officer in a regiment of the line. She had 
got married and widowed at St. Vincent, with 
only a few months between the two events. 
She was a little saucy woman, with a bright 
pair of eyes, rather a neat little foot and figure, 
and rather a neat little turned-up nose. The 
sort of young woman, I considered at the 
time, who appeared to invite you to give her 
a kiss, and who would have slapped your 
face if you accepted the invitation. 
</p>
<p>
I couldn't make out her name at first; 
for, when she gave it in answer to my 
inquiry, it sounded like Beltot, which didn't 
sound right. But, when we became better 
acquainted--which was while Charker and I 
were drinking sugar-cane sangaree, which 
she made in a most excellent manner--I 
found that her Christian name was Isabella, 
which they shortened into Bell, and that the 
name of the deceased non-commissioned 
officer was Tott. Being the kind of neat 
little woman it was natural to make a toy of,--
I never saw a woman so like a toy in my 
life--she had got the plaything name of 
Belltott. In short, she had no other name on the 
island. Even Mr. Commissioner Pordage 
(and he was a grave one!) formally addressed 
her as Mrs. Belltott. But, I shall come to 
Mr. Commissioner Pordage presently. 
</p>
<p>
The name of the captain of the sloop was 
Captain Maryon, and therefore it was no 
news to hear from Mrs. Belltott, that his 
sister, the beautiful unmarried young English 
lady, was Miss Maryon. The novelty was, that 
her Christian name was Marion too. Marion 
Maryon. Many a time I have run off those 
two names in my thoughts, like a bit of verse. 
O many, and many, and many, a time! 
</p>
<p>
We saw out all the drink that was 
produced, like good men and true, and then 
took our leaves, and went down to the beach. 
The weather was beautiful; the wind steady, 
low, and gentle; the island, a picture; the sea, 
a picture; the sky, a picture. In that country 
there are two rainy seasons in the year. One 
sets in at about our English Midsummer; the 
other, about a fortnight after our English 
Michaelmas. It was the beginning of August 
at that time; the first of these rainy seasons 
was well over; and everything was in its 
most beautiful growth, and had its loveliest 
look upon it. 
</p>
<p>
"They enjoy themselves here," I says to 
Charker, turning surly again. "This is 
better than private-soldiering." 
</p>
<p>
We had come down to the beach, to be 
friendly with the boat's-crew who were 
camped and hutted there; and we were 
approaching towards their quarters over the 
sand, when Christian George King comes 
up from the landing-place at a wolf's-trot, 
crying, "Yup, So-Jeer!"--which was that 
Sambo Pilot's barbarous way of saying, Hallo, 
Soldier! I have stated myself to be a man 
of no learning, and, if I entertain prejudices, 
I hope allowance may be made. I will 
now confess to one. It may be a right one 
or it may be a wrong one; but, I never did 
like Natives, except in the form of oysters. 
</p>
<p>
So, when Christian George King, who was 
individually unpleasant to me besides, comes 
a trotting along the sand, clucking "Yap, So-Jeer!" 
I had a thundering good mind to let 
fly at him with my right. I certainly should 
have done it, but that it would have exposed 
me to reprimand. 
</p>
<p>
"Yup, So-Jeer!" says he. "Bad job." 
</p>
<p>
"What do you mean?" says I. 
</p>
<p>
"Yup, So-Jeer!" says he, "Ship Leakee." 
</p>
<p>
"Ship leaky?" says I. 
</p>
<p>
"Iss," says he, with a nod that looked as if 
it was jerked out of him by a most violent 
hiccup--which is the way with those savages. 
</p>
<p>
I cast my eyes at Charker, and we both 
heard the pumps going aboard the sloop, and 
saw the signal run up, "Come on board; 
hands wanted from the shore." In no time 
some of the sloop's liberty-men were already 
running down to the water's edge, and the 
party of seamen, under orders against the 
Pirates, were putting off to the Columbus 
in two boats. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh Christian George King sar berry 
sorry!" says that Sambo vagabond, then. 
"Christian George King cry, English fashion!" 
His English fashion of crying was to 
screw his black knuckles into his eyes, howl 
like a dog, and roll himself on his back on the 
sand. It was trying not to kick him, but I 
gave Charker the word, "Double-quick, 
Harry!" and we got down to the water's 
edge, and got on board the sloop. 
</p>
<p>
By some means or other, she had sprung such 
a leak, that no pumping would keep her free; 
and what between the two fears that she would 
go down in the harbor, and that, even if she 
did not, all the supplies she had brought 
for the little colony would be destroyed by 
the sea-water as it rose in her, there was 
great confusion. In the midst of it, Captain 
Maryon was heard hailing from the beach. 
</p>
<p>
He had been carried down in his hammock, 
and looked very bad; but, he insisted on 
being stood there on his feet; and I saw 
him, myself, come off in the boat, sitting 
upright in the stern-sheets, as if nothing was 
wrong with him. 
</p>
<p>
A quick sort of council was held, and 
Captain Maryon soon resolved that we must 
all fall to work to get the cargo out, and, 
that when that was done, the guns and heavy 
matters must be got out, and that the sloop 
must be hauled ashore, and careened, and 
the leak stopped. We were all mustered 
(the Pirate-Chace party volunteering), and 
told off into parties, with so many hours of 
spell and so many hours of relief, and we all 
went at it with a will. Christian George King 
was entered one of the party in which I 
worked, at his own request, and he went 
at it with as good a will as any of the 
rest. He went at it with so much heartiness, 
to say the truth, that he rose in my 
good opinion, almost as fast as the water 
rose in the ship. Which was fast enough, 
and faster. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Commissioner Pordage kept in a red 
and black japanned box, like a family 
lump-sugar box, some document or other 
which some Sambo chief or other had got 
drunk and spilt some ink over (as well as I 
could understand the matter), and by that 
means had given up lawful possession of the 
Island. Through having hold of this box, 
Mr. Pordage got his title of Commissioner. 
He was styled Consul, too, and spoke of 
himself as "Government." 
</p>
<p>
He was a stiff-jointed, high-nosed old 
gentleman, without an ounce of fat on him, of a 
very angry temper and a very yellow 
complexion. Mrs. Commissioner Pordage, making 
allowance for difference of sex, was much the 
same. Mr. Kitten, a small, youngish, bald, 
botanical and mineralogical gentleman, also 
connected with the mine--but everybody 
there was that, more or less--was sometimes 
called by Mr. Commissioner Pordage, his 
Vice-commissioner, and sometimes his 
Deputy-consul. Or sometimes he spoke of Mr. 
Kitten, merely as being "under Government." 
</p>
<p>
The beach was beginning to be a lively 
scene with the preparations for careening the 
sloop, and, with cargo, and spars, and rigging, 
and water-casks, dotted about it, and with 
temporary quarters for the men rising up there 
out of such sails and odds and ends as could be 
best set on one side to make them, when Mr. 
Commissioner Pordage comes down in a high 
fluster, and asks for Captain Maryon. The 
Captain, ill as he was, was slung in his 
hammock betwixt two trees, that he might 
direct; and he raised his head, and answered 
for himself. 
</p>
<p>
"Captain Maryon," cries Mr. Commissioner 
Pordage, "this is not official. This is not 
regular." 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," says the Captain, "it hath been 
arranged with the clerk and supercargo, 
that you should be communicated with, and 
requested to render any little assistance that 
may lie in your power. I am quite certain 
that hath been duly done." 
</p>
<p>
"Captain Maryon," replies Mr. Commissioner 
Pordage, "there hath been no written 
correspondence. No documents have passed, 
no memoranda have been made, no minutes 
have been made, no entries and counter-entries 
appear in the official muniments. 
This is indecent. I call upon you, sir, to desist, 
until all is regular, or Government will take 
this up." 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," says Captain Maryon, chafing a 
little, as he looked out of his hammock; 
"between the chances of Government taking this 
up, and my ship taking herself down, I much 
prefer to trust myself to the former." 
</p>
<p>
"You do, sir?" cries Mr. Commissioner 
Pordage. 
</p>
<p>
"I do, sir," says Captain Maryon, lying 
down again. 
</p>
<p>
"Then, Mr. Kitten," says the Commissioner, 
"send up instantly for my Diplomatic coat." 
</p>
<p>
He was dressed in a linen suit at that 
moment; but, Mr. Kitten started off himself 
and brought down the Diplomatic coat, which 
was a blue cloth one, gold-laced, and with a 
crown on the button. 
</p>
<p>
"Now, Mr. Kitten," says Pordage, "I 
instruct you, as Vice-commissioner, and 
Deputy-consul of this place, to demand of 
Captain Maryon, of the sloop Christopher 
Columbus, whether he drives me to the act 
of putting this coat on?" 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Pordage," says Captain Maryon, 
looking out of his hammock again, "as I can 
hear what you say, I can answer it without 
troubling the gentleman. I should be sorry 
that you should be at the pains of putting on 
too hot a coat on my account; but, otherwise, 
you may put it on hind-side before, or inside-out, 
or with your legs in the sleeves, or your 
head in the skirts, for any objection that I have 
to offer to your thoroughly pleasing yourself." 
</p>
<p>
"Very good, Captain Maryon," says Pordage, 
in a tremendous passion. "Very good, 
sir. Be the consequences on your own head! 
Mr. Kitten, as it has come to this, help me 
on with it." 
</p>
<p>
When he had given that order, he walked off 
in the coat, and all our names were taken, and 
I was afterwards told that Mr. Kitten wrote 
from his dictation more than a bushel of 
large paper on the subject, which cost more 
before it was done with, than ever could be 
calculated, and which only got done with 
after all, by being lost. 
</p>
<p>
Our work went on merrily, nevertheless, 
and the Christopher Columbus, hauled up, 
lay helpless on her side like a great fish out 
of water. While she was in that state, there 
was a feast, or a ball, or an entertainment, or 
more properly all three together, given us in 
honor of the ship, and the ship's company, 
and the other visitors. At that assembly, I 
believe, I saw all the inhabitants then upon 
the Island, without any exception. I took no 
particular notice of more than a few, but I 
found it very agreeable in that little corner 
of the world to see the children, who were of 
all ages, and mostly very pretty--as they 
mostly are. There was one handsome elderly 
lady, with very dark eyes and grey hair, 
that I inquired about. I was told that her 
name was Mrs. Venning; and her married 
daughter, a fair slight thing, was pointed 
out to me by the name of Fanny Fisher. 
Quite a child she looked, with a little copy 
of herself holding to her dress; and her 
husband, just come back from the mine, 
exceeding proud of her. They were a 
good-looking set of people on the whole, but 
I didn't like them. I was out of sorts; 
in conversation with Charker, I found fault 
with all of them. I said of Mrs. Venning, 
she was proud; of Mrs. Fisher, she was a 
delicate little baby-fool. What did I think of 
this one? Why, he was a fine gentleman. 
What did I say to that one? Why, she was 
a fine lady. What could you expect them to 
be (I asked Charker), nursed in that climate, 
with the tropical night shining for them, 
musical instruments playing to them, great 
trees bending over them, soft lamps lighting 
them, fire-flies sparkling in among them, 
bright flowers and birds brought into 
existence to please their eyes, delicious drinks to 
be had for the pouring out, delicious fruits to 
be got for the picking, and every one dancing 
and murmuring happily in the scented air, 
with the sea breaking low on the reef for 
a pleasant chorus. 
</p>
<p>
"Fine gentlemen and fine ladies, Harry?" 
I says to Charker. "Yes, I think so! Dolls! 
Dolls! Not the sort of stuff for wear, that 
comes of poor private soldiering in the Royal 
Marines!" 
</p>
<p>
However, I could not gainsay that they 
were very hospitable people, and that they 
treated us uncommonly well. Every man of 
us was at the entertainment, and Mrs. Belltott 
had more partners than she could dance 
with: though she danced all night, too. As 
to Jack (whether of the Christopher Columbus, 
or of the Pirate pursuit party, it made 
no difference), he danced with his brother 
Jack, danced with himself, danced with the 
moon, the stars, the trees, the prospect, 
anything. I didn't greatly take to the chief-officer 
of that party, with his bright eyes, 
brown face, and easy figure. I didn't much 
like his way when he first happened to come 
where we were, with Miss Maryon on his arm. 
"Oh, Captain Carton," she says, "here are 
two friends of mine!" He says, "Indeed? 
These two Marines?"--meaning Charker 
and self. "Yes," says she, "I showed these 
two friends of mine when they first came, all 
the wonders of Silver-Store." He gave us a 
laughing look, and says he, "You are in luck, 
men. I would be disrated and go before the 
mast to-morrow, to be shown the way upward 
again by such a guide. You are in luck, 
men." When we had saluted, and he and 
the young lady had waltzed away, I said, 
"You are a pretty fellow, too, to talk of luck. 
You may go to the Devil!" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Commissioner Pordage and Mrs. 
Commissioner, showed among the company on 
that occasion like the King and Queen of a 
much Greater Britain than Great Britain. 
Only two other circumstances in that jovial 
night made much separate impression on 
me. One was this. A man in our draft 
of marines, named Tom Packer, a wild 
unsteady young fellow, but the son of a 
respectable shipwright in Portsmouth Yard, 
and a good scholar who had been well 
brought up, comes to me after a spell of 
dancing, and takes me aside by the elbow, 
and says, swearing angrily: 
</p>
<p>
"Gill Davis, I hope I may not be the death 
of Serjeant Drooce one day!" 
</p>
<p>
Now, I knew Drooce always had borne 
particularly hard on this man, and I knew 
this man to be of a very hot temper: so, I 
said: 
</p>
<p>
"Tut, nonsense! don't talk so to me! If 
there's a man in the corps who scorns the 
name of an assassin, that man and Tom 
Packer are one." 
</p>
<p>
Tom wipes his head, being in a mortal 
sweat, and says he: 
</p>
<p>
"I hope so, but I can't answer for myself 
when he lords it over me, as he has just now 
done, before a woman. I tell you what, 
Gill! Mark my words! It will go hard with 
Serjeant Drooce, if ever we are in an engagement 
together, and he has to look to me to 
save him. Let him say a prayer then, if he 
knows one, for it's all over with him, and he 
is on his Death-bed. Mark my words!" 
</p>
<p>
I did mark his words, and very soon afterwards, 
too, as will shortly be taken down. 
</p>
<p>
The other circumstance that I noticed at 
that ball, was, the gaiety and attachment of 
Christian George King. The innocent spirits 
that Sambo Pilot was in, and the 
impossibility he found himself under of showing 
all the little colony, but especially the ladies 
and children, how fond he was of them, how 
devoted to them, and how faithful to them 
for life and death, for present, future, and 
everlasting, made a great impression on me. 
If ever a man, Sambo or no Sambo, was 
trustful and trusted, to what may be called 
quite an infantine and sweetly beautiful 
extent, surely, I thought that morning when I 
did at last lie down to rest, it was that Sambo 
Pilot, Christian George King. 
</p>
<p>
This may account for my dreaming of him. 
He stuck in my sleep, cornerwise, and I 
couldn't get him out. He was always flitting 
about me, dancing round me, and peeping 
in over my hammock, though I woke and 
dozed off again fifty times. At last, when I 
opened my eyes, there he really was, looking 
in at the open side of the little dark hut; 
which was made of leaves, and had Charker's 
hammock slung in it as well as mine. 
</p>
<p>
"So-Jeer!" says he, in a sort of a low 
croak. "Yup!" 
</p>
<p>
"Hallo!" says I, starting up. "What? 
You are there, are you?" 
</p>
<p>
"Iss," says he. "Christian George King 
got news." 
</p>
<p>
"What news has he got?" 
</p>
<p>
"Pirates out!" 
</p>
<p>
I was on my feet in a second. So was 
Charker. We were both aware that Captain 
Carton, in command of the boats, constantly 
watched the main land for a secret signal, 
though, of course, it was not known to such 
as us what the signal was. 
</p>
<p>
Christian George King had vanished before 
we touched the ground. But, the word was 
already passing from hut to hut to turn out 
quietly, and we knew that the nimble 
barbarian had got hold of the truth, or 
something near it. 
</p>
<p>
In a space among the trees behind the 
encampment of us visitors, naval and military, 
was a snugly-screened spot, where we kept 
the stores that were in use, and did our 
cookery. The word was passed to assemble 
here. It was very quickly given, and was 
given (so far as we were concerned) by 
Serjeant Drooce, who was as good in a 
soldier point of view, as he was bad in a 
tyrannical one. We were ordered to drop 
into this space, quietly, behind the trees, one 
by one. As we assembled here, the seamen 
assembled too. Within ten minutes, as I 
should estimate, we were all here, except the 
usual guard upon the beach. The beach (we 
could see it through the wood) looked as it 
always had done in the hottest time of the 
day. The guard were in the shadow of the 
sloop's hull, and nothing was moving but the 
sea, and that moved very faintly. Work had 
always been knocked off at that hour, until 
the sun grew less fierce, and the sea-breeze 
rose; so that its being holiday with us, made 
no difference, just then, in the look of the 
place. But, I may mention that it was a 
holiday, and the first we had had since our 
hard work began. Last night's ball had 
been given, on the leak's being repaired, and 
the careening done. The worst of the work 
was over, and to-morrow we were to begin 
to get the sloop afloat again. 
</p>
<p>
We marines were now drawn up here, 
under arms. The chace-party were drawn 
up separate. The men of the Columbus 
were drawn up separate. The officers 
stepped out into the midst of the three 
parties, and spoke so as all might hear. 
Captain Carton was the officer in command, 
and he had a spy-glass in his hand. His 
coxswain stood by him with another 
spyglass, and with a slate on which he seemed 
to have been taking down signals. 
</p>
<p>
"Now, men!" says Captain Carton; "I have 
to let you know, for your satisfaction: Firstly, 
that there are ten pirate-boats, strongly-manned 
and armed, lying hidden up a creek yonder 
on the coast, under the overhanging branches 
of the dense trees. Secondly, that they 
will certainly come out this night when the 
moon rises, on a pillaging and murdering 
expedition, of which some part of the main 
land is the object. Thirdly--don't cheer, 
men!--that we will give chace, and, if we 
can get at them, rid the world of them, 
please God!" 
</p>
<p>
Nobody spoke, that I heard, and nobody 
moved, that I saw. Yet there was a kind of 
ring, as if every man answered and approved 
with the best blood that was inside of him. 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," says Captain Maryon, "I beg to 
volunteer on this service, with my boats. My 
people volunteer, to the ship's boys." 
</p>
<p>
"In His Majesty's name and service," the 
other answers, touching his hat, "I accept 
your aid with pleasure. Lieutenant Linderwood, 
how will you divide your men?" 
</p>
<p>
I was ashamed--I give it out to be written 
down as large and plain as possible--I was 
heart and soul ashamed of my thoughts of 
those two sick officers, Captain Maryon and 
Lieutenant Linderwood, when I saw them, 
then and there. The spirit in those two 
gentlemen beat down their illness (and 
very ill I knew them to be) like Saint 
George beating down the Dragon. Pain and 
weakness, want of ease and want of rest, had 
no more place in their minds than fear itself. 
Meaning now to express for my lady to write 
down, exactly what I felt then and there, I 
felt this: "You two brave fellows that I have 
been so grudgeful of, I know that if you were 
dying you would put it off to get up and do 
your best, and then you would be so modest 
that in lying down again to die, you would 
hardly say, 'I did it!'" 
</p>
<p>
It did me good. It really did me good. 
</p>
<p>
But, to go back to where I broke off. Says 
Captain Carton to Lieutenant Linderwood, 
"Sir, how will you divide your men? There 
is not room for all; and a few men should, in 
any case, be left here." 
</p>
<p>
There was some debate about it. At 
last, it was resolved to leave eight Marines 
and four seamen on the Island, besides 
the sloop's two boys. And because it was 
considered that the friendly Sambos would 
only want to be commanded in case of 
any danger (though none at all was 
apprehended there), the officers were in favour 
of leaving the two non-commissioned 
officers, Drooce and Charker. It was a heavy 
disappointment to them, just as my being 
one of the left was a heavy disappointment to 
me--then, but not soon afterwards. We men 
drew lots for it, and I drew "Island." So 
did Tom Packer. So, of course, did four 
more of our rank and file. 
</p>
<p>
When this was settled, verbal instructions 
were given to all hands to keep the intended 
expedition secret, in order that the women 
and children might not be alarmed, or the 
expedition put in a difficulty by more 
volunteers. The assembly was to be on that 
same spot, at sunset. Every man was to keep 
up an appearance, meanwhile, of occupying 
himself in his usual way. That is to say, 
every man excepting four old trusty seamen, 
who were appointed, with an officer, to see to 
the arms and ammunition, and to muffle the 
rullocks of the boats, and to make everything as 
trim and swift and silent as it could be made. 
</p>
<p>
The Sambo Pilot had been present all the 
while, in case of his being wanted, and had said 
to the officer in command, five hundred times 
over if he had said it once, that Christian 
George King would stay with the So-Jeers, 
and take care of the booffer ladies and the 
booffer childs--booffer being that native's 
expression for beautiful. He was now asked 
a few questions concerning the putting off of 
the boats, and in particular whether there 
was any way of embarking at the back of the 
Island: which Captain Carton would have 
half liked to do, and then have dropped round 
in its shadow and slanted across to the main. 
But, "No," says Christian George King. 
"No, no, no! Told you so, ten time. No, 
no, no! All reef, all rock, all swim, all 
drown!" Striking out as he said it, like a 
swimmer gone mad, and turning over on 
his back on dry land, and spluttering himself 
to death, in a manner that made him quite 
an exhibition. 
</p>
<p>
The sun went down, after appearing to 
be a long time about it, and the assembly 
was called. Every man answered to his 
name, of course, and was at his post. It 
was not yet black dark, and the roll was 
only just gone through, when up comes Mr. 
Commissioner Pordage with his Diplomatic 
coat on. 
</p>
<p>
"Captain Carton," says he, "Sir, what is 
this?" 
</p>
<p>
"This, Mr. Commissioner," (he was very 
short with him) "is an expedition against 
the Pirates. It is a secret expedition, so 
please to keep it a secret." 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," says Commissioner Pordage, "I 
trust there is going to be no unnecessary 
cruelty committed?" 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," returns the officer, "I trust not." 
</p>
<p>
"That is not enough, sir," cries Commissioner 
Pordage, getting wroth. "Captain Carton, 
I give you notice. Government requires 
you to treat the enemy with great delicacy, 
consideration, clemency, and forbearance." 
</p>
<p>
"Sir," says Captain Carton, "I am an 
English Officer, commanding English Men, 
and I hope I am not likely to disappoint the 
Government's just expectations. But, I 
presume you know that these villains under their 
black flag have despoiled our countrymen of 
their property, burnt their homes, barbarously 
murdered them and their little children, 
and worse than murdered their wives and 
daughters?" 
</p>
<p>
"Perhaps I do, Captain Carton," answers 
Pordage, waving his hand, with dignity; 
"perhaps I do not. It is not customary, sir, for 
Government to commit itself." 
</p>
<p>
"It matters very little, Mr. Pordage, 
whether or no. Believing that I hold my 
commission by the allowance of God, and not 
that I have received it direct from the Devil, 
I shall certainly use it, with all avoidance of 
unnecessary suffering and with all merciful 
swiftness of execution, to exterminate these 
people from the face of the earth. Let me 
recommend you to go home, sir, and to keep 
out of the night-air." 
</p>
<p>
Never another syllable did that officer say 
to the Commissioner, but turned away to his 
men. The Commissioner buttoned his 
Diplomatic coat to the chin, said, "Mr. Kitten, 
attend me!" gasped, half choked himself, and 
took himself off. 
</p>
<p>
It now fell very dark, indeed. I have seldom, 
if ever, seen it darker, nor yet so dark. The 
moon was not due until one in the morning, 
and it was but a little after nine when our 
men lay down where they were mustered. 
It was pretended that they were to take a 
nap, but everybody knew that no nap was to 
be got under the circumstances. Though all 
were very quiet, there was a restlessness 
among the people; much what I have seen 
among the people on a race-course, when the 
bell has rung for the saddling for a great race 
with large stakes on it. 
</p>
<p>
At ten, they put off; only one boat putting 
off at a time; another following in five 
minutes; both then lying on their oars until 
another followed. Ahead of all, paddling his 
own outlandish little canoe without a sound, 
went the Sambo pilot, to take them safely 
outside the reef. No light was shown but 
once, and that was in the commanding 
officer's own hand. I lighted the dark lantern 
for him, and he took it from me when he 
embarked. They had blue lights and such 
like with them, but kept themselves as dark 
as Murder. 
</p>
<p>
The expedition got away with wonderful 
quietness, and Christian George King soon 
came back, dancing with joy. 
</p>
<p>
"Yup, So-Jeer," says he to myself in a very 
objectionable kind of convulsions, "Christian 
George King sar berry glad. Pirates all be 
blown a-pieces. Yup! Yup!" 
</p>
<p>
My reply to that cannibal was, "However 
glad you may be, hold your noise, and don't 
dance jigs and slap your knees about it, for I 
can't abear to see you do it." 
</p>
<p>
I was on duty then; we twelve who were 
left, being divided into four watches of three 
each, three hours' spell. I was relieved at 
twelve. A little before that time, I had 
challenged, and Miss Maryon and Mrs. 
Belltott had come in. 
</p>
<p>
"Good Davis," says Miss Maryou, "what 
is the matter? Where is my brother?" 
</p>
<p>
I told her what was the matter, and where 
her brother was. 
</p>
<p>
"O Heaven help him!" says she, clasping 
her hands and looking up--she was close in 
front of me, and she looked most lovely to be 
sure; "he is not sufficiently recovered, not 
strong enough, for such strife!" 
</p>
<p>
"If you had seen him, miss," I told her, "as 
I saw him when he volunteered, you would 
have known that his spirit is strong enough 
for any strife. It will bear his body, miss, to 
wherever duty calls him. It will always bear 
him to an honorable life, or a brave death." 
</p>
<p>
"Heaven bless you!" says she, touching 
my arm. "I know it. Heaven bless you!" 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Belltott surprised me by trembling 
and saying nothing. They were still standing 
looking towards the sea and listening, 
after the relief had come round. It 
continuing very dark, I asked to be allowed to 
take them back. Miss Maryon thanked me, 
and she put her arm in mine, and I did take 
them back. I have now got to make a 
confession that will appear singular. After I had 
left them, I laid myself down on my face on 
the beach, and cried, for the first time since I 
had frightened birds as a boy at Snorridge 
Bottom, to think what a poor, ignorant, low-placed, 
private soldier I was. 
</p>
<p>
It was only for half a minute or so. A 
man can't at all times be quite master of 
himself, and it was only for half a minute or 
so. Then I up and went to my hut, and 
turned into my hammock, and fell asleep with 
wet eyelashes, and a sore, sore heart. Just 
as I had often done when I was a child, and 
had been worse used than usual. 
</p>
<p>
I slept (as a child under those circumstances 
might) very sound, and yet very sore 
at heart all through my sleep. I was awoke 
by the words, "He is a determined man." I 
had sprung out of my hammock, and had 
seized my firelock, and was standing on the 
ground, saying the words myself. "He is a 
determined man." But, the curiosity of my 
state was, that I seemed to be repeating 
them after somebody, and to have been 
wonderfully startled by hearing them. 
</p>
<p>
As soon as I came to myself, I went out of 
the hut, and away to where the guard was. 
Charker challenged: "Who goes there?" "A 
friend." "Not Gill?" says he, as he shouldered 
his piece. "Gill," says I. "Why, what 
the deuce do you do out of your hammock?" 
says he. "Too hot for sleep," says I; "is all 
right?" "Right!" says Charker, "yes, 
yes; all's right enough here; what should 
be wrong here? It's the boats that we want 
to know of. Except for fire-flies twinkling 
about, and the lonesome splashes of great 
creatures as they drop into the water, there's 
nothing going on here to ease a man's mind 
from the boats." 
</p>
<p>
The moon was above the sea, and had 
risen, I should say, some half-an-hour. As 
Charker spoke, with his face towards the 
sea, I, looking landward, suddenly laid my 
right hand on his breast, and said, "Don't 
move. Don't turn. Don't raise your voice! 
You never saw a Maltese face here?" 
</p>
<p>
"No. What do you mean?" he asks, 
staring at me. 
</p>
<p>
"Nor yet an English face, with one eye and 
a patch across the nose?" 
</p>
<p>
"No. What ails you? What do you mean?"
</p>
<p>
I had seen both, looking at us round the 
stem of a cocoa-nut tree, where the moon 
struck them. I had seen that Sambo Pilot, 
with one hand laid on the stem of the tree, 
drawing them back into the heavy shadow. 
I had seen their naked cutlasses twinkle 
and shine, like bits of the moonshine in 
the water that had got blown ashore 
among the trees by the light wind. I had 
seen it all, in a moment. And I saw in a 
moment (as any man would), that the 
signalled move of the pirates on the main-land 
was a plot and a feint; that the leak had 
been made to disable the sloop; that the 
boats had been tempted away, to leave the 
Island unprotected; that the pirates had 
landed by some secreted way at the back; 
and that Christian George King was a 
double-dyed traitor, and a most infernal 
villain. 
</p>
<p>
I considered, still all in one and the same 
moment, that Charker was a brave man, but 
not quick with his head; and that Serjeant 
Drooce, with a much better head, was close 
by. All I said to Charker was, "I am afraid 
we are betrayed. Turn your back full to the 
moonlight on the sea, and cover the stem of 
the cocoa-nut tree which will then be right 
before you, at the height of a man's heart. 
Are you right?" 
</p>
<p>
"I am right," says Charker, turning 
instantly, and falling into the position with 
a nerve of iron; "and right a'nt left. Is 
it Gill?" 
</p>
<p>
A few seconds brought me to Serjeant 
Drooce's hut. He was fast asleep, and being 
a heavy sleeper, I had to lay my hand upon 
him to rouse him. The instant I touched 
him he came rolling out of his hammock, and 
upon me like a tiger. And a tiger he was, 
except that he knew what he was up to, in 
his utmost heat, as well as any man. 
</p>
<p>
I had to struggle with him pretty hard to 
bring him to his senses, panting all the while 
(for he gave me a breather), "Serjeant, I 
am Gill Davis! Treachery! Pirates on the 
Island!" 
</p>
<p>
The last words brought him round, and he 
took his hands off. "I have seen two of 
them within this minute," said I. And so I 
told him what I had told Harry Charker. 
</p>
<p>
His soldierly, though tyrannical, head was 
clear in an instant. He didn't waste one 
word, even of surprise. "Order the guard," 
says he, "to draw off quietly into the Fort." 
(They called the enclosure I have before 
mentioned, the Fort, though it was not much 
of that.) "Then get you to the Fort as 
quick as you can, rouse up every soul 
there, and fasten the gate. I will bring in 
all those who are up at the Signal Hill. If 
we are surrounded before we can join you, 
you must make a sally and cut us out if you 
can. The word among our men is, 'Women 
and children!'" 
</p>
<p>
He burst away, like fire going before the 
wind over dry reeds. He roused up the 
seven men who were off duty, and had them 
bursting away with him, before they knew 
they were not asleep. I reported orders to 
Charker, and ran to the Fort, as I have never 
run at any other time in all my life: no, not 
even in a dream. 
</p>
<p>
The gate was not fast, and had no good 
fastening: only a double wooden bar, a poor 
chain, and a bad lock. Those, I secured as 
well as they could be secured in a few 
seconds by one pair of hands, and so ran to 
that part of the building where Miss Maryon 
lived. I called to her loudly by her name 
until she answered. I then called loudly all 
the names I knew--Mrs. Macey (Miss 
Maryon's married sister), Mr. Macey, Mrs. 
Venning, Mr. and Mrs. Fisher, even Mr. 
and Mrs. Pordage. Then I called out, "All 
you gentlemen here, get up and defend the 
place! We are caught in a trap. Pirates 
have landed. We are attacked!" 
</p>
<p>
At the terrible word "Pirates!"--for, those 
villains had done such deeds in those seas as 
never can be told in writing, and can scarcely 
be so much as thought of--cries and screams 
rose up from every part of the place. Quickly, 
lights moved about from window to window, 
and the cries moved about with them, and 
men, women and children came flying down 
into the square. I remarked to myself, even 
then, what a number of things I seemed to 
see at once. I noticed Mrs. Macey coming 
towards me, carrying all her three children 
together. I noticed Mr. Pordage, in the 
greatest terror, in vain trying to get on his 
Diplomatic coat; and Mr. Kitten respectfully 
tying his pocket-handkerchief over Mrs. 
Pordage's nightcap. I noticed Mrs. Belltott 
run out screaming, and shrink upon the 
ground near me, and cover her face in her 
hands, and lie, all of a bundle, shivering. 
But, what I noticed with the greatest pleasure 
was, the determined eyes with which those 
men of the Mine that I had thought fine 
gentlemen, came round me with what arms 
they had: to the full as cool and resolute as I 
could be, for my life--aye, and for my soul, 
too, into the bargain! 
</p>
<p>
The chief person being Mr. Macey, I told 
him how the three men of the guard would 
be at the gate directly, if they were not 
already there, and how Serjeant Drooce and 
the other seven were gone to bring in the 
outlying part of the people of Silver-store. 
I next urged him, for the love all who were 
dear to him, to trust no Sambo, and, above 
all, if he could get any good chance at 
Christian George King, not to lose it, but to 
put him out of the world. "I will follow 
your advice to the letter, Davis," says he; 
"what next?" My answer was, "I think, 
sir, I would recommend you next, to order 
down such heavy furniture and lumber as can 
be moved, and make a barricade within the 
gate." "That's good again," says he; "will 
you see it done?" "I'll willingly help to do 
it," says I, "unless or until my superior, 
Serjeant Drooce, gives me other orders." He 
shook me by the hand, and having told 
off some of his companions to help me, 
bestirred himself to look to the arms and 
ammunition. A proper quick, brave, steady, 
ready gentleman! 
</p>
<p>
One of their three little children was deaf 
and dumb. Miss Maryon had been from the 
first with all the children, soothing them, and 
dressing them (poor little things, they had 
been brought out of their beds), and making 
them believe that it was a game of play, so 
that some of them were now even laughing. 
I had been working hard with the others 
at the barricade, and had got up a pretty 
good breastwork within the gate. Drooce 
and the seven had come back, bringing in 
the people from the Signal Hill, and had 
worked along with us: but, I had not so 
much as spoken a word to Drooce, nor had 
Drooce so much as spoken a word to me, for 
we were both too busy. The breastwork 
was now finished, and I found Miss Maryon 
at my side, with a child in her arms. Her 
dark hair was fastened round her head with 
a band. She had a quantity of it, and it 
looked even richer and more precious, put 
up hastily out of her way, than I had seen 
it look when it was carefully arranged. She 
was very pale, but extraordinarily quiet and 
still. 
</p>
<p>
"Dear good Davis," said she, "I have been 
waiting to speak one word to you." 
</p>
<p>
I turned to her directly. If I had received 
a musket-ball in the heart, and she had stood 
there, I almost believe I should have turned 
to her before I dropped. 
</p>
<p>
"This pretty little creature," said she, 
kissing the child in her arms, who was 
playing with her hair and trying to pull it 
down, "cannot hear what we say--can hear 
nothing. I trust you so much, and have 
such great confidence in you, that I want you 
to make me a promise." 
</p>
<p>
"What is it, Miss?" 
</p>
<p>
"That if we are defeated, and you are 
absolutely sure of my being taken, you will 
kill me." 
</p>
<p>
"I shall not be alive to do it, Miss. I shall 
have died in your defence before it comes to 
that. They must step across my body, to lay 
a hand on you." 
</p>
<p>
"But, if you are alive, you brave soldier." 
How she looked at me! "And if you cannot 
save me from the Pirates, living, you will 
save me, dead. Tell me so." 
</p>
<p>
Well! I told her I would do that, at the 
last, if all else failed. She took my hand--
my rough, coarse hand--and put it to her 
lips. She put it to the child's lips, and the 
child kissed it. I believe I had the strength 
of half a dozen men in me, from that moment, 
until the fight was over. 
</p>
<p>
All this time, Mr. Commissioner Pordage 
had been wanting to make a Proclamation to 
the Pirates, to lay down their arms and go 
away; and everybody had been hustling him 
about and tumbling over him, while he was 
calling for pen and ink to write it with. 
Mrs. Pordage, too, had some curious ideas 
about the British respectability of her nightcap 
(which had as many frills to it, growing 
in layers one inside another, as if it was a 
white vegetable of the artichoke sort), and 
she wouldn't take the nightcap off, and would 
be angry when it got crushed by the other 
ladies who were handing things about, and, 
in short, she gave as much trouble as her 
husband did. But, as we were now forming 
for the defence of the place, they were both 
poked out of the way with no ceremony. 
The children and ladies were got into the 
little trench which surrounded the silver-house 
(we were afraid of leaving them in any 
of the light buildings, lest they should be set 
on fire), and we made the best disposition we 
could. There was a pretty good store, in 
point of amount, of tolerable swords and 
cutlasses. Those were issued. There were, also, 
perhaps a score or so of spare muskets. 
Those were brought out. To my astonishment, 
little Mrs. Fisher that I had taken for 
a doll and a baby, was not only very active 
in that service, but volunteered to load the 
spare arms. 
</p>
<p>
"For, I understand it well," says she, 
cheerfully, without a shake in her voice. 
</p>
<p>
"I am a soldier's daughter and a sailor's 
sister, and I understand it too," says Miss 
Maryon, just in the same way. 
</p>
<p>
Steady and busy behind where I stood, 
those two beautiful and delicate young women 
fell to handling the guns, hammering the 
flints, looking to the locks, and quietly directing 
others to pass up powder and bullets 
from hand to hand, as unflinching as the best 
of tried soldiers. 
</p>
<p>
Serjeant Drooce had brought in word that 
the pirates were very strong in numbers--
over a hundred, was his estimate--and that 
they were not, even then, all landed; for, he 
had seen them in a very good position on the 
further side of the Signal Hill, evidently 
waiting for the rest of their men to come up. 
In the present pause, the first we had had 
since the alarm, he was telling this over 
again to Mr. Macey, when Mr. Macey 
suddenly cried out: 
</p>
<p>
"The signal! Nobody has thought of the 
signal!" 
</p>
<p>
We knew of no signal, so we could not 
have thought of it. "What signal may you 
mean, sir?" says Serjeant Drooce, looking 
sharp at him. 
</p>
<p>
"There is a pile of wood upon the Signal 
Hill. If it could be lighted--which never 
has been done yet--it would be a signal of 
distress to the mainland." 
</p>
<p>
Charker cries, directly: "Serjeant Drooce, 
dispatch me on that duty. Give me the two 
men who were on guard with me to-night, 
and I'll light the fire, if it can be done." 
</p>
<p>
"And if it can't, Corporal--" Mr. Macey 
strikes in. 
</p>
<p>
"Look at these ladies and children, sir!" 
says Charker. "I'd sooner light myself, than 
not try any chance to save them." 
</p>
<p>
We gave him a Hurrah!--it burst from us, 
come of it what might--and he got his two 
men, and was let out at the gate, and crept 
away. I had no sooner come back to my 
place from being one of the party to handle 
the gate, than Miss Maryon said in a low 
voice behind me: 
</p>
<p>
"Davis, will you look at this powder. This 
is not right?" 
</p>
<p>
I turned my head. Christian George King 
again, and treachery again! Sea-water had 
been conveyed into the magazine, and every 
grain of powder was spoiled! 
</p>
<p>
"Stay a moment," said Serjeant Drooce, 
when I had told him, without causing a 
movement in a muscle of his face: "look to your 
pouch, my lad. You Tom Packer, look to 
your pouch, confound you! Look to your 
pouches, all you Marines." 
</p>
<p>
The same artful savage had got at them, 
somehow or another, and the cartridges were 
all unserviceable. "Hum!" says the 
Serjeant, "Look to your loading, men. You are 
right so far?" 
</p>
<p>
Yes; we were right so far. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, my lads, and gentlemen all," says the 
Serjeant, "this will be a hand-to-hand affair, 
and so much the better." 
</p>
<p>
He treated himself to a pinch of snuff, 
and stood up, square-shouldered and broad-chested, 
in the light of the moon--which 
was now very bright--as cool as if he was 
waiting for a play to begin. He stood quiet, 
and we all stood quiet, for a matter of 
something like half-an-hour. I took notice from 
such whispered talk as there was, how little 
we that the silver did not belong to, thought 
about it, and how much the people that it 
did belong to, thought about it. At the end 
of the half-hour, it was reported from the 
gate that Charker and the two were falling 
back on us, pursued by about a dozen. 
</p>
<p>
"Sally! Gate-party, under Gill Davis," 
says the Sergeant, "and bring 'em in! Like 
men, now!" 
</p>
<p>
We we're not long about it, and we brought 
them in. "Don't take me," says Charker, 
holding me round the neck, and stumbling 
down at my feet when the gate was fast, 
"don't take me near the ladies or the 
children, Gill. They had better not see 
Death, till it can't be helped. They'll see 
it soon enough." 
</p>
<p>
"Harry!" I answered, holding up his head. 
"Comrade!" 
</p>
<p>
He was cut to pieces. The signal had 
been secured by the first pirate party that 
lauded; his hair was all singed off, and his 
face was blackened with the running pitch 
from a torch. 
</p>
<p>
He made no complaint of pain, or of 
anything. "Good bye, old chap," was all he 
said, with a smile. "I've got my death. And 
Death a'nt life. Is it, Gill?" 
</p>
<p>
Having helped to lay his poor body on one 
side, I went back to my post. Serjeant 
Drooce looked at me, with his eyebrows a 
little lifted. I nodded. "Close up here, men, 
and gentlemen all!" said the Serjeant. 
"A place too many, in the line." 
</p>
<p>
The Pirates were so close upon us at this 
time, that the foremost of them were already 
before the gate. More and more came up 
with a great noise, and shouting loudly. 
When we believed from the sound that they 
were all there, we gave three English cheers. 
The poor little children joined, and were so 
fully convinced of our being at play, that 
they enjoyed the noise, and were heard 
clapping their hands in the silence that followed. 
</p>
<p>
Our disposition was this, beginning with 
the rear. Mrs. Venning, holding her daughter's 
child in her arms, sat on the steps of the 
little square trench surrounding the silver-house, 
encouraging and directing those women 
and children as she might have done in the 
happiest and easiest time of her life. Then, 
there was an armed line, under Mr. Macey, 
across the width of the enclosure, facing that 
way and having their backs towards the gate, 
in order that they might watch the walls 
and prevent our being taken by surprise. 
Then, there was a space of eight or ten feet 
deep, in which the spare arms were, and in 
which Miss Maryon and Mrs. Fisher, their 
hands and dresses blackened with the spoilt 
gunpowder, worked on their knees, tying 
such things as knives, old bayonets, and 
spear-heads, to the muzzles of the useless 
muskets. Then, there was a second armed 
line, under Serjeant Drooce, also across the 
width of the enclosure, but facing to the 
gate. Then, came the breastwork we had 
made, with a zig-zag way through it for me 
and my little party to hold good in retreating, 
as long as we could, when we were 
driven from the gate. We all knew that 
it was impossible to hold the place long, 
and that our only hope was in the timely 
discovery of the plot by the boats, and in 
their coming back. 
</p>
<p>
I and my men were now thrown forward 
to the gate. From a spy-hole, I could see the 
whole crowd of Pirates. There were Malays 
among them, Dutch, Maltese, Greeks, Sambos, 
Negroes, and Convict Englishmen from the 
West India Islands; among the last, him 
with the one eye and the patch across the 
nose. There were some Portuguese, too, and 
a few Spaniards. The captain was a 
Portuguese; a little man with very large ear-rings 
under a very broad hat, and a great bright 
shawl twisted about his shoulders. They 
were all strongly armed, but like a boarding 
party, with pikes, swords, cutlasses, and axes. 
I noticed a good many pistols, but not a gun 
of any kind among them. This gave me to 
understand that they had considered that a 
continued roll of musketry might perhaps 
have been heard on the mainland; also, that 
for the reason that fire would be seen from 
the mainland they would not set the Fort 
in flames and roast us alive; which was one 
of their favorite ways of carrying on. I 
looked about for Christian George King, 
and if I had seen him I am much mistaken 
if he would not have received my one round 
of ball-cartridge in his head. But, no 
Christian George King was visible. 
</p>
<p>
A sort of a wild Portuguese demon, who 
seemed either fierce-mad or fierce-drunk--
but, they all seemed one or the other--came 
forward with the black flag, and gave it a 
wave or two. After that, the Portuguese 
captain called out in shrill English. "I say you! 
English fools! Open the gate! Surrender!" 
</p>
<p>
As we kept close and quiet, he said 
something to his men which I didn't understand, 
and when he had said it, the one-eyed 
English rascal with the patch (who had stepped 
out when he began), said it again in English. 
It was only this. "Boys of the black flag, 
this is to be quickly done. Take all the 
prisoners you can. If they don't yield, kill 
the children to make them. Forward!" 
Then, they all came on at the gate, and, in 
another half minute were smashing and 
splitting it in. 
</p>
<p>
We struck at them through the gaps and 
shivers, and we dropped many of them, too; 
but, their very weight would have carried 
such a gate, if they had been unarmed. 
I soon found Serjeant Drooce at my side, 
forming us six remaining marines in line--
Tom Packer next to me--and ordering 
us to fall back three paces, and, as they 
broke in, to give them our one little volley 
at short distance. "Then," says he, "receive 
them behind your breastwork on the bayonet, 
and at least let every man of you pin one of 
the cursed cockchafers through the body." 
</p>
<p>
We checked them by our fire, slight as it 
was, and we checked them at the 
breastwork. However, they broke over it like 
swarms of devils--they were, really and 
truly, more devils than men--and then it 
was hand to hand, indeed. 
</p>
<p>
We clubbed our muskets and laid about 
us; even then, those two ladies--always 
behind me--were steady and ready with the 
arms. I had a lot of Maltese and Malays 
upon me, and, but for a broadsword that 
Miss Maryon's own hand put in mine, should 
have got my end from them. But, was that 
all? No. I saw a heap of banded dark hair 
and a white dress come thrice between me 
and them, under my own raised right arm, 
which each time might have destroyed the 
wearer of the white dress; and each time one 
of the lot went down, struck dead. 
</p>
<p>
Drooce was armed with a broad-sword, 
too, and did such things with it, that there 
was a cry, in half-a dozen languages, of 
"Kill that serjeant!" as I knew, by the cry 
being raised in English, and taken up in 
other tongues. I had received a severe cut 
across the left arm a few moments before, 
and should have known nothing of it, except 
supposing that somebody had struck me a 
smart blow, if I had not felt weak, and seen 
myself covered with spouting blood, and, at 
the same instant of time, seen Miss Maryon 
tearing her dress, and binding it with Mrs. 
Fisher's help round the wound. They called 
to Tom Packer, who was scouring by, to stop 
and guard me for one minute, while I was 
bound, or I should bleed to death in trying 
to defend myself. Tom stopped directly, with 
a good sabre in his hand. 
</p>
<p>
In that same moment all--things seem to 
happen in that same moment, at such a time--
half-a-dozen had rushed howling at Serjeant 
Drooce. The Serjeant, stepping back against 
the wall, stopped one howl for ever with 
such a terrible blow, and waited for the rest 
to come on, with such a wonderfully unmoved 
face, that they stopped and looked at him. 
</p>
<p>
"See him now!" cried Tom Packer. 
"Now, when I could cut him out! Gill! 
Did I tell you to mark my words?" 
</p>
<p>
I implored Tom Packer in the Lord's 
name, as well as I could in my faintness, to 
go to the Serjeant's aid. 
</p>
<p>
"I hate and detest him," says Tom, moodily 
wavering. "Still, he is a brave man." Then 
he calls out, "Serjeant Drooce, Serjeant 
Drooce! Tell me you have driven me too 
hard, and are sorry for it." 
</p>
<p>
The Serjeant, without turning his eyes 
from his assailants, which would have been 
instant death to him, answers: 
</p>
<p>
"No. I won't." 
</p>
<p>
"Serjeant Drooce!" cries Tom, in a kind 
of an agony. "I have passed my word that I 
would never save you from Death, if I could, 
but would leave you to die. Tell me you 
have driven me too hard and are sorry for it, 
and that shall go for nothing." 
</p>
<p>
One of the group laid the Serjeant's bald 
bare head open. The Serjeant laid him 
dead. 
</p>
<p>
"I tell you," says the Serjeant, breathing 
a little short, and waiting for the next 
attack. "No. I won't. If you are not man 
enough to strike for a fellow-soldier because 
he wants help, and because of nothing else, 
I'll go into the other world and look for a 
better man." 
</p>
<p>
Tom swept upon them, and cut him out. 
Tom and he fought their way through another 
knot of them, and sent them flying, and came 
over to where I was beginning again to feel, 
with inexpressible joy, that I had got a 
sword in my hand. 
</p>
<p>
They had hardly come to us, when I heard, 
above all the other noises, a tremendous cry 
of women's voices. I also saw Miss Maryon, 
with quite a new face, suddenly clap her two 
hands over Mrs. Fisher's eyes. I looked 
towards the silver-house, and saw Mrs. 
Venning--standing upright on the top of the steps 
of the trench, with her grey hair and her 
dark eyes--hide her daughter's child behind 
her, among the folds of her dress, strike a 
pirate with her other hand, and fall, shot by 
his pistol. 
</p>
<p>
The cry arose again, and there was a 
terrible and confusing rush of the women 
into the midst of the struggle. In another 
moment, something came tumbling down 
upon me that I thought was the wall. It 
was a heap of Sambos who had come over 
the wall; and of four men who clung to my 
legs like serpents, one who clung to my right 
leg was Christian George King. 
</p>
<p>
"Yup, So-Jeer!" says he, "Christian 
George King sar berry glad So-Jeer a 
prisoner. Christian George King been waiting 
for So-Jeer sech long time. Yup, yup!" 
</p>
<p>
What could I do, with five-and-twenty of 
them on me, but be tied hand and foot? So, 
I was tied hand and foot. It was all over 
now--boats not come back--all lost! When 
I was fast bound and was put up against 
the wall, the one-eyed English convict came 
up with the Portuguese Captain, to have a 
look at me. 
</p>
<p>
"See!" says he, "Here's the determined 
man! If you had slept sounder, last night, 
you'd have slept your soundest last night, my 
determined man." 
</p>
<p>
The Portuguese Captain laughed in a cool 
way, and, with the flat of his cutlass, hit me 
crosswise, as if I was the bough of a tree 
that he played with: first on the face, and 
then across the chest and the wounded arm. 
I looked him steady in the face without 
tumbling while he looked at me, I am happy 
to say; but, when they went away, I fell, 
and lay there. 
</p>
<p>
The sun was up, when I was roused and 
told to come down to the beach and be 
embarked. I was full of aches and pains, and 
could not at first remember; but, I remembered 
quite soon enough. The killed were 
lying about all over the place, and the 
Pirates were burying their dead, and taking 
away their wounded on hastily-made litters, 
to the back of the Island. As for us prisoners, 
some of their boats had come round to the 
usual harbour, to carry us off. We looked 
a wretched few, I thought, when I got down 
there; still, it was another sign that we had 
fought well, and made the enemy suffer. 
</p>
<p>
The Portuguese Captain had all the women 
already embarked in the boat he himself 
commanded, which was just putting off when I 
got down. Miss Maryon sat on one side of 
him, and gave me a moment's look, as full 
of quiet courage, and pity, and confidence, as 
if it had been an hour long. On the other 
side of him was poor little Mrs. Fisher, 
weeping for her child and her mother. I 
was shoved into the same boat with Drooce 
and Packer, and the remainder of our party 
of marines: of whom we had lost two privates, 
besides Charker, my poor, brave comrade. We 
all made a melancholy passage, under the hot 
sun, over to the mainland. There, we landed 
in a solitary place, and were mustered on the 
sea sand. Mr. and Mrs. Macey and their 
children were amongst us, Mr. and Mrs. 
Pordage, Mr. Kitten, Mr. Fisher, and Mrs. 
Belltott. We mustered only fourteen men, 
fifteen women, and seven children. Those 
were all that remained of the English who 
had lain down to sleep last night, unsuspecting 
and happy, on the Island of Silver-Store. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE PRISON IN THE WOODS.</title>
<p>
THERE we all stood, huddled up on the 
beach under the burning sun, with the 
pirates closing us in on every side--as forlorn 
a company of helpless men, women, and 
children as ever was gathered together out 
of any nation in the world. I kept my 
thoughts to myself; but I did not in my 
heart believe that any one of our lives was 
worth five minutes' purchase. 
</p>
<p>
The man on whose will our safety or 
our destruction depended was the Pirate 
Captain. All our eyes, by a kind of instinct, 
fixed themselves on him--excepting in the 
case of the poor children, who, too frightened 
to cry, stood hiding their faces against their 
mothers' gowns. The ruler who held all 
the ruffians about us in subjection, was, 
judging by appearances, the very last man I 
should have picked out as likely to fill a 
place of power among any body of men, good 
or bad, under heaven. By nation, he was a 
Portuguese; and, by name, he was generally 
spoken of among his men as The Don. He 
was a little, active, weazen, monkey-faced man, 
dressed in the brightest colours and the 
finest-made clothes I ever saw. His three-cornered 
hat was smartly cocked on one side. 
His coat-skirts were stiffened and stuck out, 
like the skirts of the dandies in the Mall in 
London. When the dance was given at the 
Island, I saw no such lace on any lady's dress 
there as I saw on his cravat and ruffles. 
Round his neck he wore a thick gold chain, 
with a diamond cross hanging from it. His 
lean, wiry, brown fingers were covered with 
rings. Over his shoulders, and falling down 
in front to below his waist, he wore a sort of 
sling of broad scarlet cloth, embroidered with 
beads and little feathers, and holding, at the 
lower part, four loaded pistols, two on a side, 
lying ready to either hand. His face was 
mere skin and bone, and one of his wrinkled 
cheeks had a blue scar running all across it, 
which drew up that part of his face, and 
showed his white shining teeth on that side 
of his mouth. An uglier, meaner, weaker, 
man-monkey to look at, I never saw; and 
yet there was not one of his crew, from his 
mate to his cabin-boy, who did not obey him 
as if he had been the greatest monarch in 
the world. As for the Sambos, including 
especially that evil-minded scoundrel, 
Christian George King, they never went near 
him without seeming to want to roll before 
him on the ground, for the sake of winning 
the honour of having one of his little dancing-master's 
feet set on their black bullock 
bodies. 
</p>
<p>
There this fellow stood, while we were 
looking at him, with his hands in his pockets, 
smoking a cigar. His mate (the one-eyed 
Englishman), stood by him; a big, hulking fellow 
he was, who might have eaten the Captain 
up, pistols and all, and looked about for 
more afterwards. The Don himself seemed, 
to an ignorant man like me, to have a gift of 
speaking in any tongue he liked. I can 
testify that his English rattled out of his 
crooked lips as fast as if it was natural to 
them; making allowance, of course, for his 
foreign way of clipping his words. 
</p>
<p>
"Now, Captain," says the big mate, running 
his eye over us as if we were a herd of cattle, 
"here they are. What's to be done with 
them?" 
</p>
<p>
"Are they all off the Island?" says the 
Pirate Captain. 
</p>
<p>
"All of them that are alive," says the 
mate. 
</p>
<p>
"Good, and very good," says the captain. 
"Now, Giant-Georgy, some paper, a pen, 
and a horn of ink." 
</p>
<p>
Those things were brought immediately. 
</p>
<p>
"Something to write on," says the Pirate 
Captain. "What? Ha! why not a broad 
nigger back?" 
</p>
<p>
He pointed with the end of his cigar to 
one of the Sambos. The man was pulled 
forward, and set down on his knees with his 
shoulders rounded. The Pirate Captain laid 
the paper on them, and took a dip of ink--then 
suddenly turned up his snub-nose with a look 
of disgust, and, removing the paper again, took 
from his pocket a fine cambric handkerchief 
edged with lace, smelt at the scent on it, and 
afterwards laid it delicately over the Sambo's 
shoulders. 
</p>
<p>
"A table of black man's back, with the 
sun on it, close under my nose--ah, Giant-Georgy, 
pah! pah!" says the Pirate Captain, 
putting the paper on the handkerchief, with 
another grimace expressive of great disgust. 
</p>
<p>
He began to write immediately, waiting 
from time to time to consider a little with 
himself; and once stopping, apparently, to 
count our numbers as we stood before him. 
To think of that villain knowing how to 
write, and of my not being able to make so 
much as a decent pothook, if it had been to 
save my life! 
</p>
<p>
When he had done, he signed to one of his 
men to take the scented handkerchief off the 
Sambo's back, and told the sailor he might 
keep it for his trouble. Then, holding the 
written paper open in his hand, he came 
forward a step or two closer to us, and said, 
with a grin, and a mock bow, which made 
my fingers itch with wanting to be at him: 
</p>
<p>
"I have the honour of addressing myself 
to the ladies. According to my reckoning 
they are fifteen ladies in all. Does any one of 
them belong to the chief officer of the sloop?" 
</p>
<p>
There was a momentary silence. 
</p>
<p>
"You don't answer me," says the Pirate 
Captain. "Now, I mean to be answered. Look 
here, women." He drew one of his four pistols 
out of his gay scarlet sling, and walked up 
to Tom Packer, who happened to be standing 
nearest to him of the men prisoners. "This 
is a pistol, and it is loaded. I put the barrel 
to the head of this man with my right hand, 
and I take out my watch with my left. I 
wait five minutes for an answer. If I don't 
get it in five minutes, I blow this man's brains 
out. I wait five minutes again, and if I 
don't get an answer, I blow the next man's 
brains out. And so I go on, if you are obstinate, 
and your nerves are strong, till not one 
of your soldiers or your sailors is left. On 
my word of honour, as a gentleman-buccanier, 
I promise you that. Ask my men if 
I ever broke my word." 
</p>
<p>
He rested the barrel of the pistol against 
Tom Packer's head, and looked at his watch, 
as perfectly composed, in his cat-like cruelty, 
as if he was waiting for the boiling of an 
egg. 
</p>
<p>
"If you think it best not to answer him, 
ladies," says Tom, "never mind me. It's 
my trade to risk my life; and I shall lose it 
in a good cause." 
</p>
<p>
"A brave man," said the Pirate Captain, 
lightly. "Well, ladies, are you going to sacrifice 
the brave man?" 
</p>
<p>
"We are going to save him," said Miss 
Maryon," as he has striven to save us. I 
belong to the captain of the sloop. I am his 
sister." She stopped, and whispered anxiously 
to Mrs. Macey, who was standing with her. 
"Don't acknowledge yourself, as I have done--
you have children." 
</p>
<p>
"Good!" said the Pirate Captain. "The 
answer is given, and the brains may stop in 
the brave man's head." He put his watch and 
pistol back, and took two or three quick puffs 
at his cigar to keep it alight--then handed the 
paper he had written on, and his penfull of 
ink, to Miss Maryon. 
</p>
<p>
"Read that over," he said, "and sign it 
for yourself, and the women and children 
with you." 
</p>
<p>
Saying those words, he turned round 
briskly on his heel, and began talking, in a 
whisper, to Giant Georgy, the big English 
mate. What he was talking about, of course, 
I could not hear; but I noticed that he 
motioned several times straight into the 
interior of the country. 
</p>
<p>
"Davis," said Miss Maryon, "look at 
this." 
</p>
<p>
She crossed before her sister, as she spoke, 
and held the paper which the Pirate Captain 
had given to her, under my eyes--my bound 
arms not allowing me to take it myself. 
Never to my dying day shall I forget the 
shame I felt, when I was obliged to 
acknowledge to Miss Maryon that I could not 
read a word of it! 
</p>
<p>
"There are better men than me, ma'am," 
I said, with a sinking heart, "who can read 
it, and advise you for the best." 
</p>
<p>
"None better," she answered, quietly. 
"None, whose advice I would so willingly 
take. I have seen enough, to feel sure of 
that. Listen, Davis, while I read." 
</p>
<p>
Her pale face turned paler still, as she fixed 
her eyes on the paper. Lowering her voice 
to a whisper, so that the women and children 
near might not hear, she read me these 
lines: 
</p>
<letter>
<p>
"To the Captains of English men-of-war, and to 
the commanders of vessels of other nations, cruising in 
the Caribbean Seas. 
</p>
<p>
"The precious metal and the jewels laid up in the 
English Island of Silver-Store, are in the possession of 
the Buccaniers, at sea. 
</p>
<p>
"The women and children of the Island of Silver-Store, 
to the number of Twenty-Two, are in the 
possession of the Buccaniers, on land. 
</p>
<p>
"They will be taken up the country, with fourteen 
men prisoners (whose lives the Buccaniers have 
private reasons of their own for preserving), to a place of 
confinement, which is unapproachable by strangers. 
They will be kept there until a certain day, previously 
agreed on between the Buccaniers at sea, and the 
Buccaniers on land. 
</p>
<p>
"If, by that time, no news from the party at sea, 
reaches the party on land, it will be taken for granted 
that the expedition which conveys away the silver and 
jewels has been met, engaged, and conquered by 
superior force; that the Treasure has been taken from its 
present owners; and that the Buccaniers guarding it, 
have been made prisoners, to be dealt with according 
to the law. 
</p>
<p>
"The absence of the expected news at the appointed 
time, being interpreted in this way, it will be the next 
object of the Buccaniers on land to take reprisals for 
the loss and the injury inflicted on their companions at 
sea. The lives of the women and children of the 
Island of Silver-Store are absolutely at their mercy; 
and those lives will pay the forfeit, if the Treasure is 
taken away, and if the men in possession of it come 
to harm. 
</p>
<p>
"This paper will be nailed to the lid of the largest 
chest taken from the Island. Any officer whom the 
chances of war may bring within reading distance of it, 
is warned to pause and consider, before his conduct 
signs the death-warrant of the women and children of 
an English colony. 
</p>
<right>
"Signed, under the Black Flag, 
</right>
<right>
"PEDRO MENDEZ, 
</right>
<p>
"Commander of the Buccaniers, and Chief of the 
Guard over the English Prisoners." 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
"The statement above written, in so far as it 
regards the situation we are now placed in, may be 
depended on as the truth. 
</p>
<p>
"Signed, on behalf of the imprisoned women and 
children of the Island of Silver-Store." 
</p>
</letter>
<p>
"Beneath this last line," said Miss Maryon, 
pointing to it, "is a blank space, in which I 
am expected to sign my name." 
</p>
<p>
"And in five minutes' time," added the 
Pirate Captain, who had stolen close up to us, 
"or the same consequences will follow which 
I had the pleasure of explaining to you a few 
minutes ago." 
</p>
<p>
He again drew out his watch and pistol; 
but, this time, it was my head that he touched 
with the barrel. 
</p>
<p>
"When Tom Packer spoke for himself, 
miss, a little while ago," I said, "please to 
consider that he spoke for me." 
</p>
<p>
"Another brave man!" said the Pirate 
Captain, with his ape's grin. "Am I to fire 
my pistol this time, or am I to put it back 
again as I did before?" 
</p>
<p>
Miss Maryon did not seem to hear him. 
Her kind eyes rested for a moment on my 
face, and then looked up to the bright Heaven 
above us. 
</p>
<p>
"Whether I sign, or whether I do not sign," 
she said, "we are still in the hands of God, 
and the future which His wisdom has 
appointed will not the less surely come." 
</p>
<p>
With those words she placed the paper on 
my breast, signed it, and handed it back to 
the Pirate Captain. 
</p>
<p>
"This is our secret, Davis," she whispered. 
"Let us keep the dreadful knowledge of it 
to ourselves as long as we can." 
</p>
<p>
I have another singular confession to 
make--I hardly expect anybody to believe 
me when I mention the circumstance--but 
it is not the less the plain truth that, even 
in the midst of that frightful situation, I felt, 
for a few moments, a sensation of happiness 
while Miss Maryon's hand was holding the 
paper on my breast, and while her lips were 
telling me that there was a secret between us 
which we were to keep together. 
</p>
<p>
The Pirate Captain carried the signed paper 
at once to his mate. 
</p>
<p>
"Go back to the Island," he says, "and 
nail that with your own hands on the lid of the 
largest chest. There is no occasion to hurry 
the business of shipping the Treasure, 
because there is nobody on the Island to make 
signals that may draw attention to it from 
the sea. I have provided for that; and I 
have provided for the chance of your being 
outmanoeuvred afterwards, by English, or 
other cruisers. Here are your sailing 
orders" (he took them from his pocket while 
he spoke), "your directions for the disposal 
of the Treasure, and your appointment of the 
day and the place for communicating again 
with me and my prisoners. I have done my 
part--go you, now, and do yours." 
</p>
<p>
Hearing the clearness with which he gave 
his orders; knowing what the devilish 
scheme was that he had invented for preventing 
the recovery of the Treasure, even if our 
ships happened to meet and capture the 
pirates at sea; remembering what the look 
and the speech of him had been, when he put 
his pistol to my head and Tom Packer's; I 
began to understand how it was that this 
little, weak, weazen, wicked spider had got 
the first place and kept it among the villains 
about him. 
</p>
<p>
The mate moved off, with his orders, 
towards the sea. Before he got there, the 
Pirate Captain beckoned another of the crew 
to come to him; and spoke a few words in 
his own, or in some other foreign language. 
I guessed what they meant, when I saw 
thirty of the pirates told off together, and set 
in a circle all round us. The rest were 
marched away after the mate. In the same 
manner the Sambos were divided next. Ten, 
including Christian George King, were left 
with us; and the others were sent down to the 
canoes. When this had been done, the Pirate 
Captain looked at his watch; pointed to some 
trees, about a mile off, which fringed the land 
as it rose from the beach; said to an American 
among the pirates round us, who seemed to 
hold the place of second mate, "In two hours 
from this time;" and then walked away 
briskly, with one of his men after him, to 
some baggage piled up below us on the 
beach. 
</p>
<p>
We were marched off at once to the shady 
place under the trees, and allowed to sit 
down there, in the cool, with our guard in a 
ring round us. Feeling certain from what I 
saw, and from what I knew to be 
contained in the written paper signed by Miss 
Maryon, that we were on the point of 
undertaking a long journey up the country, I 
anxiously examined my fellow prisoners to 
see how fit they looked for encountering 
bodily hardship and fatigue: to say nothing 
of mental suspense and terror, over and above. 
</p>
<p>
With all possible respect for an official 
gentleman, I must admit that Mr. 
Commissioner Pordage struck me as being, 
beyond any comparison, the most helpless 
individual in our unfortunate company. 
What with the fright he had suffered, the 
danger he had gone through, and the 
bewilderment of finding himself torn clean away 
from his safe Government moorings, his poor 
unfortunate brains seemed to be as completely 
discomposed as his Diplomatic coat. He was 
perfectly harmless and quiet, but also 
perfectly light-headed--as anybody could 
discover who looked at his dazed eyes or 
listened to his maundering talk. I tried him 
with a word or two about our miserable 
situation; thinking that, if any subject would 
get a trifle of sense out of him, it must surely 
be that. 
</p>
<p>
"You will observe," said Mr. Pordage, 
looking at the torn cuffs of his Diplomatic 
coat instead of at me, "that I cannot take 
cognisance of our situation. No memorandum 
of it has been drawn up; no report in 
connexion with it has been presented to me. 
I cannot possibly recognise it until the necessary 
minutes and memorandums and reports 
have reached me through the proper channels. 
When our miserable situation presents 
itself to me, on paper, I shall bring it under 
the notice of Government; and Government, 
after a proper interval, will bring it back 
again under my notice; and then I shall 
have something to say about it. Not a 
minute before,--no, my man, not a minute 
before!" 
</p>
<p>
Speaking of Mr. Pordage's wanderings of 
mind, reminds me that it is necessary to say 
a word next, about the much more serious 
case of Serjeant Drooce. The cut on his 
head, acted on by the heat of the climate, 
had driven him, to all appearance, stark mad. 
Besides the danger to himself, if he broke out 
before the Pirates, there was the danger to 
the women and children, of trusting him 
among them--a misfortune which, in 
our captive condition, it was impossible to 
avoid. Most providentially, however (as I 
found on inquiry) Tom Packer, who had 
saved his life, had a power of controlling 
him, which none of the rest of us possessed. 
Some shattered recollection of the manner in 
which he had been preserved from death, 
seemed to be still left in a corner of his 
memory. Whenever he showed symptoms 
of breaking out, Tom looked at him, and 
repeated with his hand and arm the action 
of cutting out right and left which had been 
the means of his saving the sergeant. On 
seeing that, Drooce always huddled himself 
up close to Tom, and fell silent. We,--that 
is, Packer and I--arranged it together that 
he was always to keep near Drooce, whatever 
happened, and however far we might 
be marched before we reached the place of 
our imprisonment. 
</p>
<p>
The rest of us men--meaning Mr. Macey, 
Mr. Fisher, two of my comrades of the Marines, 
and five of the sloop's crew--were, making 
allowance for a little smarting in our 
wounds, in tolerable health, and not half 
so much broken in spirit by troubles, past, 
present, and to come, as some persons might 
be apt to imagine. As for the seamen, 
especially, no stranger who looked at 
their jolly brown faces would ever have 
imagined that they were prisoners, and in 
peril of their lives. They sat together, chewing 
their quids, and looking out good-humouredly 
at the sea, like a gang of liberty-men 
resting themselves on shore. "Take it 
easy, soldier," says one of the six, seeing me 
looking at him. "And, if you can't do that, 
take it as easy as you can." I thought, at 
the time, that many a wiser man might have 
given me less sensible advice than this, 
though it was only offered by a boatswain's 
mate. 
</p>
<p>
A movement among the Pirates attracted 
my notice to the beach below us, and I saw 
their Captain approaching our halting-place, 
having changed his fine clothes for 
garments that were fit to travel in. 
</p>
<p>
His coming back to us had the effect of 
producing unmistakable signs of preparation 
for a long journey. Shortly after he 
appeared, three Indians came up, leading three 
loaded mules; and these were followed, in a 
few minutes, by two of the Sambos, carrying 
between them a copper full of smoking meat 
and broth. After having been shared among 
the Pirates, this mess was set down before 
us, with some wooden bowls floating about 
in it, to dip out the food with. Seeing that we 
hesitated before touching it, the Pirate Captain 
recommended us not to be too mealy-mouthed, 
as that was meat from our own stores on the 
Island, and the last we were likely to taste 
for a long time to come. The sailors, without 
any more ado about it, professed their 
readiness to follow this advice, muttering 
among themselves that good meat was 
a good thing, though the devil himself had 
cooked it. The Pirate Captain then, 
observing that we were all ready to accept 
the food, ordered the bonds that confined 
the hands of us men to be loosened and 
cast off, so that we might help ourselves. 
After we had served the women and 
children, we fell to. It was a good meal--
though I can't say that I myself had much 
appetite for it. Jack, to use his own phrase, 
stowed away a double allowance. The jolly 
faces of the seamen lengthened a good deal, 
however, when they found there was nothing 
to drink afterwards but plain water. One of 
them, a fat man, named Short, went so far 
as to say that, in the turn things seemed 
to have taken, he should like to make his 
will before we started, as the stoppage of his 
grog and the stoppage of his life were two 
events that would occur uncommonly close 
together. 
</p>
<p>
When we had done, we were all ordered 
to stand up. The Pirates approached me and 
the other men, to bind our arms again; but, 
the Captain stopped them. 
</p>
<p>
"No," says he. "I want them to get on 
at a good pace; and they will do that best 
with their arms free. Now, prisoners," he 
continued, addressing us, "I don't mean to 
have any lagging on the road. I have fed 
you up with good meat, and you have no 
excuse for not stepping out briskly--women, 
children, and all. You men are without 
weapons and without food, and you know 
nothing of the country you are going to 
travel through. If you are mad enough, in 
this helpless condition, to attempt escaping 
on the march, you will be shot, as sure as you 
all stand there,--and if the bullet misses, you 
will starve to death in forests that have no 
path and no end." 
</p>
<p>
Having addressed us in those words, he 
turned again to his men. I wondered then, as 
I had wondered once or twice already, what 
those private reasons might be, which he had 
mentioned in his written paper, for sparing 
the lives of us male prisoners. I hoped he 
would refer to them now--but I was 
disappointed. 
</p>
<p>
"While the country allows it," he went 
on, addressing his crew, "march in a square, 
and keep the prisoners inside. Whether it 
is man, woman, or child, shoot any one of 
them who tries to escape, on peril of being 
shot yourselves if you miss. Put the Indians 
and mules in front, and the Sambos next to 
them. Draw up the prisoners all together. 
Tell off seven men to march before them, 
and seven more for each side; and leave the 
other nine for the rear-guard. A fourth 
mule for me, when I get tired, and another 
Indian to carry my guitar." 
</p>
<p>
His guitar! To think of the murderous 
thief having a turn for strumming tunes, and 
wanting to cultivate it on such an expedition 
as ours! I could hardly believe my eyes when 
I saw the guitar brought forward in a neat 
green case, with the piratical skull and cross-bones 
and the Pirate Captain's initials painted 
on it in white. 
</p>
<p>
"I can stand a good deal," whispers Tom 
Packer to me, looking hard at the guitar; 
"but con-found me, Davis, if it's not a trifle 
too much to be taken prisoner by such a 
fellow as that!" 
</p>
<p>
The Pirate Captain lights another cigar. 
</p>
<p>
"March!" says he, with a screech like a 
cat, and a flourish with his sword, of the sort 
that a stage-player would give at the head of 
a mock army. 
</p>
<p>
We all moved off, leaving the clump of 
trees to the right, going, we knew not whither, 
to unknown sufferings and an unknown fate. 
The land that lay before us was wild and 
open, without fences or habitations. Here 
and there, cattle wandered about over it, and 
a few stray Indians. Beyond, in the 
distance, as far as we could see, rose a prospect 
of mountains and forests. Above us, was the 
pitiless sun, in a sky that was too brightly 
blue to look at. Behind us, was the calm 
murmuring ocean, with the dear island home 
which the women and children had lost, 
rising in the distance like a little green 
garden on the bosom of the sea. After half-an-hour's 
walking, we began to descend into 
the plain, and the last glimpse of the Island 
of Silver-Store disappeared from our view. 
</p>
<p>
The order of march which we prisoners 
now maintained among ourselves, being the 
order which, with certain occasional variations, 
we observed for the next three days, I 
may as well give some description of it in 
this place, before I get occupied with other 
things, and forget it. 
</p>
<p>
I myself, and the sailor I have mentioned 
under the name of Short, led the march. 
After us came Miss Maryon, and Mr. and 
Mrs. Macey. They were followed by two of 
my comrades of the Marines with Mrs. 
Pordage, Mrs. Belltott, and two of the strongest of 
the ladies to look after them. Mr. Fisher, the 
ship's boy, and the three remaining men of the 
sloop's crew, with the rest of the women and 
children came next; Tom Packer, taking 
care of Serjeant Drooce, brought up the 
rear. So long as we got on quickly enough, 
the pirates showed no disposition to 
interfere with our order of march; but, if 
there were any signs of lagging--and God 
knows it was hard enough work for a 
man to walk under that burning sun!--
the villains threatened the weakest of our 
company with the points of their swords. 
The younger among the children gave out, 
as might have been expected, poor things, 
very early on the march. Short and I set 
the example of taking two of them up, pick-a-back, 
which was followed directly by the 
rest of the men. Two of Mrs. Macey's three 
children fell to our share; the eldest, travelling 
behind us on his father's back. Short hoisted 
the next in age, a girl, on his broad shoulders. 
I see him now as if it was yesterday, 
with the perspiration pouring down his fat 
face and bushy whiskers, rolling along as if 
he was on the deck of a ship, and making a 
sling of his neck-handkerchief, with his clever 
sailor's fingers, to support the little girl on 
his back. "I expect you'll marry me, my 
darling, when you grow up," says he, in his 
oily, joking voice. And the poor child, in 
her innocence, laid her weary head down on 
his shoulder, and gravely and faithfully 
promised that she would. 
</p>
<p>
A lighter weight fell to my share. I had 
the youngest of the children, the pretty 
little boy, already mentioned, who had been 
deaf and dumb from his birth. His mother's 
voice trembled sadly, as she thanked 
me for taking him up, and tenderly put 
his little dress right while she walked 
behind me. "He is very little and light 
of his age," says the poor lady, trying 
hard to speak steady. "He won't give you 
much trouble, Davis--he has always been a 
very patient child from the first." The boy's 
little frail arms clasped themselves round my 
neck while she was speaking; and something 
or other seemed to stop in my throat the 
cheerful answer that I wanted to make. I 
walked on with what must have looked, I 
am afraid, like a gruff silence; the poor child 
humming softly on my back, in his unchanging, 
dumb way, till he hummed himself to 
sleep. Often and often, since that time, in 
dreams, I have felt those small arms round my 
neck again, and have heard that dumb 
murmuring song in my ear, dying away fainter 
and fainter, till nothing was left but the light 
breath rising and falling regularly on my 
cheek, telling me that my little fellow-prisoner 
had forgotten his troubles in sleep. 
</p>
<p>
We marched, as well as I could guess, 
somewhere about seven miles that day--a 
short spell enough, judging by distance, but 
a terrible long one judging by heat. Our 
halting place was by the banks of a stream, 
across which, at a little distance, some wild 
pigs were swimming as we came up. Beyond 
us, was the same view of forests and 
mountains that I have already mentioned; and all 
round us, was a perfect wilderness of flowers. 
The shrubs, the bushes, the ground, all blazed 
again with magnificent colours, under the 
evening sun. When we were ordered to 
halt, wherever we set a child down, there 
that child had laps and laps full of flowers 
growing within reach of its hand. We sat 
on flowers, eat on flowers, slept at night on 
flowers--any chance handful of which would 
have been well worth a golden guinea among 
the gentlefolks in England. It was a sight 
not easily described, to see niggers, savages, 
and Pirates, hideous, filthy, and ferocious in 
the last degree to look at, squatting about 
grimly upon a natural carpet of beauty, of 
the sort that is painted in pictures with 
pretty fairies dancing on it. 
</p>
<p>
The mules were unloaded, and left to roll 
among the flowers to their hearts' content. A 
neat tent was set up for the Pirate Captain, at 
the door of which, after eating a good meal, 
he laid himself down in a languishing attitude, 
with a nosegay in the bosom of his waistcoat, 
and his guitar on his knees, and jingled away 
at the strings, singing foreign songs, with a 
shrill voice and with his nose conceitedly 
turned up in the air. I was obliged to 
caution Short and the sailors--or they would, to 
a dead certainty, have put all our lives in 
peril by openly laughing at him. 
</p>
<p>
We had but a poor supper that night. 
The Pirates now kept the provisions they 
had brought from the Island, for their own 
use; and we had to share the miserable 
starvation diet of the country, with the 
Indians and the Sambos. This consisted of 
black beans fried, and of things they call 
Tortillas, meaning, in plain English, flat cakes 
made of crushed Indian corn, and baked on a 
clay griddle. Not only was this food insipid, 
but the dirty manner in which the Indians 
prepared it, was disgusting. However, complaint 
was useless; for we could see for ourselves that 
no other provision had been brought for the 
prisoners. I heard some grumbling among our 
men, and some little fretfulness among the 
children, which their mothers soon quieted. 
I myself was indifferent enough to the 
quality of the food; for I had noticed a 
circumstance, just before it was brought to us, 
which occupied my mind with more serious 
considerations. One of the mules was 
unloaded near us, and I observed among the 
baggage a large bundle of new axes, doubtless 
taken from some ship. After puzzling 
my brains for some time to know what they 
could be wanted for, I came to the conclusion 
that they were to be employed in cutting 
our way through, when we came to the 
forests. To think of the kind of travelling 
which these preparations promised--if the 
view I took of them was the right one--and 
then to look at the women and children, 
exhausted by the first day's march, was 
sufficient to make any man uneasy. It 
weighed heavily enough on my mind, I know, 
when I woke up among the flowers, from 
time to time, that night. 
</p>
<p>
Our sleeping arrangements, though we 
had not a single civilised comfort, were, 
thanks to the flowers, simple and easy 
enough. For the first time in their lives, the 
women and children laid down together, with 
the sky for a roof, and the kind earth for a 
bed. We men shook ourselves down, as well 
as we could, all round them; and the Pirates, 
relieving guard regularly, ranged themselves 
outside of all. In that tropical climate, and 
at that hot time, the night was only 
pleasantly cool. The bubbling of the stream, 
and, now and then, the course of the breeze 
through the flowers, was all we heard. 
During the hours of darkness, it occurred to 
me--and I have no doubt the same idea 
struck my comrades--that a body of 
determined men, making a dash for it, might now 
have stood a fair chance of escaping. We 
were still near enough to the sea-shore to 
be certain of not losing our way; and the 
plain was almost as smooth, for a good long 
run, as a natural race-course. However, 
the mere act of dwelling on such a notion, 
was waste of time and thought, situated 
as we were with regard to the women 
and children. They were, so to speak, the 
hostages who insured our submission to 
captivity, or to any other hardship that might 
be inflicted on us; a result which I have no 
doubt the Pirate Captain had foreseen, when 
he made us all prisoners together on taking 
possession of the Island. 
</p>
<p>
We were roused up at four in the morning, 
to travel on before the heat set in; our 
march under yesterday's broiling sun having 
been only undertaken for the purpose of 
getting us away from the sea-shore, and from 
possible help in that quarter, without loss of 
time. We forded the stream, wading through 
it waist-deep: except the children, who crossed 
on our shoulders. An hour before noon, we 
halted under two immense wild cotton-trees, 
about half a mile from a little brook, which 
probably ran into the stream we had passed 
in the morning. Late in the afternoon we 
were on foot again, and encamped for the 
night at three deserted huts, built of mud 
and poles. There were the remains of an 
enclosure here, intended, as I thought, for 
cattle; and there was an old well, from which 
our supply of water was got. The greater 
part of the women were very tired and sorrowful 
that night; but Miss Maryon did wonders 
in cheering them up. 
</p>
<p>
On the third morning, we began to skirt 
the edge of a mountain, carrying our store 
of water with us from the well. We men 
prisoners had our full share of the burden. 
What with that, what with the way being 
all up-hill, and what with the necessity of 
helping on the weaker members of our 
company, that day's march was the hardest I 
remember to have ever got through. 
Towards evening, after resting again in the 
middle of the day, we stopped for the night 
on the verge of the forest. A dim, lowering, 
awful sight it was, to look up at the 
mighty wall of trees, stretching in front, and 
on either side of us without a limit and 
without a break. Through the night, though 
there was no wind blowing over our encampment, 
we heard deep, moaning, rushing 
sounds rolling about, at intervals, in the 
great inner wilderness of leaves; and, now 
and then, those among us who slept, were 
startled up by distant crashes in the depths 
of the forest--the death-knells of falling 
trees. We kept fires alight, in case of wild 
animals stealing out on us in the darkness; 
and the flaring red light, and the thick, 
winding smoke, alternately showed and hid 
the forest-prospect in a strangely treacherous 
and ghostly way. The children shuddered 
with fear; even the Pirate Captain forgot, 
for the first time, to jingle his eternal guitar. 
</p>
<p>
When we were mustered in the morning 
for the march, I fully expected to see the 
axes unpacked. To my surprise they were 
not disturbed. The Indians drew their long 
chopping-knives (called machetes in the 
language of that country); made for a place 
among the trees where I could see no signs 
of a path; and begun cutting at the bushes 
and shrubs, and at the wild vines and 
creepers, twirling down together in all sorts 
of fantastic forms, from the lofty branches. 
After clearing a few dozen yards inwards 
they came out to us again, whooping and 
showing their wicked teeth, as they laid 
hold of the mules' halters to lead them on. 
The Pirate Captain, before we moved after, 
took out a pocket compass, set it, pondered 
over it for some time, shrugged his shoulders, 
and screeched out "March," as usual. We 
entered the forest, leaving behind us the last 
chance of escape, and the last hope of ever 
getting back to the regions of humanity and 
civilisation. By this time, we had walked 
inland, as nearly as I could estimate, about 
thirty miles. 
</p>
<p>
The order of our march was now, of necessity, 
somewhat changed. We all followed 
each other in a long line, shut in, however, 
as before, in front and in rear, by the Indians, 
the Sambos, and the pirates. Though none 
of us could see a vestige of any path, it was 
clear that our guides knew where they were 
going; for, we were never stopped by any 
obstacles, except the shrubs and wild-vines 
which they could cut through with their 
chopping-knives. Sometimes, we marched 
under great branches which met like arches 
high over our heads. Sometimes, the boughs 
were so low that we had to stoop to pass 
under them. Sometimes, we wound in and 
out among mighty trunks of trees, with their 
gnarled roots twisting up far above the 
ground, and with creepers in full flower 
twining down in hundreds from their lofty 
branches. The size of the leaves and the 
countless multitude of the trees shut 
out the sun, and made a solemn dimness 
which it was awful and without hope to 
walk through. Hours would pass without 
our hearing a sound but the dreary rustle 
of our own feet over the leafy ground. 
At other times, whole troops of parrots, with 
feathers of all the colours of the rainbow, 
chattered and shrieked at us; and processions 
of monkeys, fifty or sixty at a time, 
followed our progress in the boughs 
overhead: passing through the thick leaves 
with a sound like the rush of a steady wind. 
Every now and then, the children were startled 
by lizard-like creatures, three feet long, 
running up the trunks of the trees as we 
passed by them; more than once, swarms 
of locusts tormented us, startled out of 
their hiding-places by the monkeys in the 
boughs. For five days we marched 
incessantly through this dismal forest-region, 
only catching a clear glimpse of the sky 
above us, on three occasions in all that time. 
The distance we walked each day seemed to 
be regulated by the positions of springs and 
streams in the forest, which the Indians 
knew of. Sometimes those springs and 
streams lay near together; and our day's 
work was short. Sometimes they were 
far apart; and the march was long and 
weary. On all occasions, two of the Indians, 
followed by two of the Sambos, disappeared 
as soon as we encamped for the night; and 
returned, in a longer or shorter time, bringing 
water with them. Towards the latter 
part of the journey, weariness had so 
completely mastered the weakest among our 
company, that they ceased to take notice of 
anything. They walked without looking to 
the right or to the left, and they eat their 
wretched food and lay down to sleep with 
a silent despair that was shocking. Mr. 
Pordage left off maundering now, and 
Serjeant Drooce was so quiet and biddable, that 
Tom Packer had an easy time of it with him 
at last. Those among us who still talked, 
began to get a habit of dropping our voices 
to a whisper. Short's jokes languished and 
dwindled; Miss Maryon's voice, still kind 
and tender as ever, began to lose its clearness; 
and the poor children, when they got 
weary and cried, shed tears silently, like old 
people. It seemed as if the darkness and 
the hush of the endless forest had cast its 
shadow on our spirits, and had stolen drearily 
into our inmost hearts. 
</p>
<p>
On the sixth day, we saw the blessed 
sunshine on the ground before us, once more. 
Prisoners as we were, there was a feeling of 
freedom on stepping into the light again, and 
on looking up, without interruption, into the 
clear blue Heaven, from which no human 
creature can keep any other human 
creature, when the time comes for rising to 
it. A turn in the path brought us out 
suddenly at an Indian village--a wretched 
place, made up of two rows of huts built 
with poles, the crevices between them stopped 
with mud, and the roofs thatched in 
the coarsest manner with palm-leaves. The 
savages squatted about, jumped to their feet 
in terror as we came in view; but, seeing the 
Indians at the head of our party, took heart, 
and began chattering and screeching, just like 
the parrots we had left in the forest. Our 
guides answered in their gibberish; some lean, 
half-wild dogs yelped and howled incessantly; 
and the Pirates discharged their muskets and 
loaded them again, to make sure that their 
powder had not got damp on the march. 
No want of muskets among them now! 
The noise and the light and the confusion, 
after the silence, darkness, and discipline that 
we had been used to for the last five days, so 
bewildered us all, that it was quite a relief 
to sit down on the ground and let the 
guard about us shut out our view on every 
side. 
</p>
<p>
"Davis! Are we at the end of the march?" 
says Miss Maryon, touching my arm. 
</p>
<p>
The other women looked anxiously at me, 
as she put the question. I got on my feet, 
and saw the Pirate Captain communicating 
with the Indians of the village. His hands 
were making signs in the fussy foreign way, 
all the time he was speaking. Sometimes, 
they pointed away to where the forest began 
again beyond us; and sometimes they went 
up both together to his mouth, as if he was 
wishful of getting a fresh supply of the 
necessaries of life. 
</p>
<p>
My eyes next turned towards the mules. 
Nobody was employed in unpacking the 
baggage; nobody went near that bundle of axes 
which had weighed on my mind so much 
already, and the mystery of which still 
tormented me in secret. I came to the conclusion 
that we were not yet at the end of 
our journey; I communicated my opinion to 
Miss Maryon. She got up herself, with my 
help, and looked about her, and made the 
remark, very justly, that all the huts in the 
village would not suffice to hold us. At the 
same time, I pointed out to her that the mule 
which the Pirate Captain had ridden had 
been relieved of his saddle, and was being led 
away, at that moment, to a patch of grass 
behind one of the huts. 
</p>
<p>
"That looks as if we were not going much 
farther on," says I. 
</p>
<p>
"Thank Heaven if it be so, for the sake of 
the poor children!" says Miss Maryon. 
"Davis, suppose something happened which 
gave us a chance of escaping? Do you think 
we could ever find our way back to the sea?" 
</p>
<p>
"Not a hope of getting back, miss. If the 
Pirates were to let us go this very instant, 
those pathless forests would keep us in prison 
for ever." 
</p>
<p>
"Too true! Too true!" she said, and said 
no more. 
</p>
<p>
In another half-hour we were roused up, 
and marched away from the village (as I had 
thought we should be) into the forest again. 
This time, though there was by no means so 
much cutting through the underwood needed as 
in our previous experience, we were accompanied 
by at least a dozen Indians, who seemed 
to me to be following us out of sheer idleness 
and curiosity. We had walked, as well as I 
could calculate, more than an hour, and I was 
trudging along with the little deaf-and-dumb 
boy on my back, as usual, thinking, not very 
hopefully, of our future prospects, when I 
was startled by a moan in my ear from the 
child. One of his arms was trembling round 
my neck, and the other pointed away towards 
my right hand. I looked in that direction--
and there, as if it had started up out of the 
ground to dispute our passage through the 
forest, was a hideous monster carved in stone, 
twice my height at least. The thing loomed out 
of a ghostly white, against the dark curtain of 
trees all round it. Spots of rank moss stuck 
about over its great glaring stone-face; its 
stumpy hands were tucked up into its breast; 
its legs and feet were four times the size of 
any human limbs; its body and the flat space 
of spare stone which rose above its head, 
were all covered with mysterious devices--
little grinning men's faces, heads of crocodiles 
and apes, twisting knots and twirling knobs, 
strangely shaped leaves, winding lattice-work; 
legs, arms, fingers, toes, skulls, bones, and 
such like. The monstrous statue leaned over 
on one side, and was only kept from falling 
to the ground by the roots of a great tree 
which had wound themselves all round the 
lower half of it. Altogether, it was as 
horrible and ghastly an object to come upon 
suddenly, in the unknown depths of a great 
forest, as the mind (or, at all events, my 
mind) can conceive. When I say that the 
first meeting with the statue struck me 
speechless, nobody can wonder that the 
children actually screamed with terror at the 
sight of it. 
</p>
<p>
"It's only a great big doll, my darling," 
says Short, at his wit's end how to quiet the 
little girl on his back. "We'll get a nice 
soft bit of wood soon, and show these nasty 
savages how to make a better one." 
</p>
<p>
While he was speaking, Miss Maryon was 
close behind me, soothing the deaf-and-dumb 
boy by signs which I could not understand. 
</p>
<p>
"I have heard of these things, Davis," she 
says. "They are idols, made by a lost race 
of people, who lived, no one can say how many 
hundred or how many thousand years ago. 
That hideous thing was carved and 
worshipped while the great tree that now 
supports it was yet a seed in the ground. We 
must get the children used to these stone 
monsters. I believe we are coming to many 
more of them. I believe we are close to the 
remains of one of those mysterious ruined 
cities which have long been supposed to exist 
in this part of the world." 
</p>
<p>
Before I could answer, the word of 
command from the rear drove us on again. In 
passing the idol, some of the Pirates fired 
their muskets at it. The echoes from the 
reports rang back on us with a sharp rattling 
sound. We pushed on a few paces, when the 
Indians a-head suddenly stopped, nourished 
their chopping-knives, and all screamed out 
together "El Palacio!" The Englishmen 
among the Pirates took up the cry, and, 
running forward through the trees on either 
side of us, roared out, "The Palace!" Other 
voices joined theirs in other tongues; and, 
for a minute or two, there was a general 
confusion of everybody,--the first that had 
occurred since we were marched away, 
prisoners, from the sea-shore. 
</p>
<p>
I tightened my hold of the child on my 
back; took Miss Maryon closer to me, to save 
her from being roughly jostled by the men 
about us; and marched up as near to the 
front as the press and the trees would let me. 
Looking over the heads of the Indians, and 
between the trunks, I beheld a sight which I 
shall never forget: no, not to my dying day. 
</p>
<p>
A wilderness of ruins spread out before me, 
overrun by a forest of trees. In every direction, 
look where I would, a frightful confusion 
of idols, pillars, blocks of stone, heavy walls, 
and flights of steps, met my eye; some, whole 
and upright; others, broken and scattered on 
the ground; and all, whatever their condition, 
overgrown and clasped about by roots, 
branches, and curling vines, that writhed 
round them like so many great snakes. 
Every here and there, strange buildings stood 
up, with walls on the tops of which three 
men might have marched abreast--buildings 
with their roofs burst off or tumbled in, and 
with the trees springing up from inside, and 
waving their restless shadows mournfully 
over the ruins. High in the midst of this 
desolation, towered a broad platform of 
rocky earth, scarped away on three sides, 
so as to make it unapproachable except 
by scaling ladders. On the fourth side, 
the flat of the platform was reached by 
a flight of stone steps, of such mighty size 
and strength that they might have been made 
for the use of a race of giants. They led to a 
huge building girded all round with a row of 
thick pillars, long enough and broad enough 
to cover the whole flat space of ground; 
solid enough, as to the walls, to stand for 
ever; but broken in, at most places, as to the 
roof; and overshadowed by the trees that 
sprang up from inside, like the smaller houses 
already mentioned, below it. This was the 
dismal ruin which was called the Palace; and 
this was the Prison in the Woods which was 
to be the place of our captivity. 
</p>
<p>
The screeching voice of the Pirate Captain 
restored order in our ranks, and sent the 
Indians forward with their chopping-knives to 
the steps of the Palace. We were directed to 
follow them across the ruins, and in and out 
among the trees. Out of every ugly crevice 
crack in the great stairs, there sprouted up 
flowers, long grasses, and beautiful large-leaved 
plants and bushes. When we had 
toiled to the top of the flight, we could look 
back from the height over the dark waving 
top of the forest behind us. More than a 
glimpse of the magnificent sight, however, 
was not allowed: we were ordered still to 
follow the Indians. They had already 
disappeared in the inside of the Palace; and we 
went in after them. 
</p>
<p>
We found ourselves, first, under a square 
portico, supported upon immense flat slabs of stone, 
which were carved all over, at top and 
bottom, with death's-heads set in the midst of 
circles of sculptured flowers. I guessed the 
length of the portico to be, at the very least, 
three hundred feet. In the inside wall of it, 
appeared four high gaping doorways; three 
of them were entirely choked up by fallen 
stones: so jammed together, and so girt about 
by roots and climbing plants, that no force 
short of a blast of gunpowder, could possibly 
have dislodged them. The fourth entrance 
had, at some former time, been kept just 
clear enough to allow of the passing of one 
man at once through the gap that had been 
made in the fallen stones. Through this, 
the only passage left into the Palace, or out 
of it, we followed the Indians into a great hall, 
nearly one half of which was still covered 
by the remains of the roof. In the unsheltered 
half: surrounded by broken stones 
and with a carved human head, five times 
the size of life, leaning against it: rose the 
straight, naked trunk of a beautiful tree, 
that shot up high above the ruins, and 
dropped its enormous branches from the 
very top of it, bending down towards us, in 
curves like plumes of immense green feathers. 
In this hall, which was big enough to hold 
double our number, we were ordered to make 
a halt, while the Pirate Captain, accompanied 
by three of his crew, followed the Indians 
through a doorway, leading off to the left 
hand, as we stood with our backs to the 
portico. In front of us, towards the right, 
was another doorway, through which we 
could see some of the Indians, cutting away 
with their knives, right and left, at the 
overspreading underwood. Even the noise 
of the hacking, and the hum and murmur 
of the people outside, who were unloading 
the mules, seemed to be sounds too faint 
and trifling to break the awful stillness of 
the ruins. To my ears, at least, the 
unearthly silence was deepened rather than 
broken by the few feeble sounds which 
tried to disturb it. The wailings of the 
poor children were stifled within them. The 
whispers of the women, and the heavy 
breathing of the overlaboured men, sank 
and sank gradually till they were heard no 
more. Looking back now, at the whole 
course of our troubles, I think I can safely 
say that nothing--not even the first discovery 
of the treachery on the Island--tried 
our courage and endurance like that interval 
of speechless waiting in the Palace, with the 
hush of the ruined city, and the dimness 
of the endless forest, all about us. 
</p>
<p>
When we next saw the Pirate Captain, he 
appeared at the doorway to the right, just 
as the Pirates began to crowd in from the 
portico, with the baggage they had taken 
from the mules. 
</p>
<p>
"There is the way for the Buccaniers," 
squeaks the Pirate Captain, addressing the 
American mate, and pointing to the doorway 
on the left. "Three big rooms, that will hold 
you all, and that have more of the roof left on 
them than any of the others. The prisoners," 
he continues, turning to us, and pointing to the 
doorway behind him, "will file in, that way, 
and will find two rooms for them, with the 
ceilings on the floor, and the trees in their 
places. I myself, because my soul is big, 
shall live alone in this grand hall. My 
bed shall be there in the sheltered corner; 
and I shall eat, and drink, and smoke, and 
sing, and enjoy myself, with one eye always 
on my prisoners, and the other eye always on 
my guard outside." 
</p>
<p>
Having delivered this piece of eloquence, 
he pointed with his sword to the prisoners' 
doorway. We all passed through it quickly, 
glad to be out of the sight and hearing of 
him. 
</p>
<p>
The two rooms set apart for us,communicated 
with each other. The inner one of the two 
had a second doorway, leading, as I supposed, 
further into the building, but so choked up 
by rubbish, as to be impassable, except by 
climbing, and that must have been skilful 
climbing too. Seeing that this accident cut 
off all easy means of approach to the room 
from the Pirates' side, we determined, 
supposing nobody meddled with us, to establish 
the women and children here; and to take 
the room nearest to the Pirate Captain and 
his guard for ourselves. 
</p>
<p>
The first thing to be done was to clear away 
the rubbish in the women's room. The ceiling 
was, indeed, as the Pirate Captain had told us, 
all on the floor; and the growth of trees, shrubs, 
weeds, and flowers, springing up everywhere 
among the fragments of stone, was so 
prodigious in this part of the Palace, that, but 
for the walls with their barbarous sculptures 
all round, we should certainly have believed 
ourselves to be encamped in the forest, without 
a building near us. All the lighter parts of 
the rubbish in the women's room we 
disposed of, cleverly, by piling it in the doorway 
on the Pirates' side, so as to make any 
approach from that direction all but impossible, 
even by climbing. The heavy blocks 
of stone--and it took two men to lift some 
of them that were not the heaviest--we 
piled up in the middle of the floor. Having 
by this means cleared away plenty of 
space round the walls, we gathered up all 
the litter of young branches, bushes, and 
leaves which the Indians had chopped away; 
added to them as much as was required of the 
underwood still standing; and laid the whole 
smooth and even, to make beds. I noticed, 
while we were at this work, that the ship's 
boy--whose name was Robert--was particularly 
helpful and considerate with the children, 
when it became necessary to quiet them 
and to get them to lie down. He was a 
rough boy to look at, and not very sharp; but, 
he managed better, and was more naturally 
tender-hearted with the little ones than any 
of the rest of us. This may seem a small 
thing to mention; but Robert's attentive 
ways with the children, attached them to 
him; and that attachment, as will be 
hereafter shown, turned out to be of great benefit 
to us, at a very dangerous and very important 
time. 
</p>
<p>
Our next piece of work was to clear our 
own room. It was close at the side of the 
Palace; and a break in the outward wall 
looked down over the sheer precipice on 
which the building stood. We stopped this 
up, breast high, in case of accidents, with the 
rubbish on the floor; we then made our beds, 
just as we had made the women's beds 
already. 
</p>
<p>
A little later, we heard the Pirate Captain 
in the hall, which he kept to himself for 
his big soul and his little body, giving orders 
to the American mate about the guard. 
On mustering the Pirates, it turned out 
that two of them, who had been wounded 
in the fight on the Island, were unfit for 
duty. Twenty-eight, therefore, remained. 
These, the Pirate Captain divided into 
companies of seven, who were to mount guard, 
in turn, for a spell of six hours each company; 
the relief coming round, as a matter of course, 
four times in the twenty-four hours. Of the 
guard of seven, two were stationed under the 
portico; one was placed as a look-out, on the 
top landing of the great flight of steps; and 
two were appointed to patrol the ground 
below, in front of the Palace. This left only 
two men to watch the three remaining sides 
of the building. So far as any risks of attack 
were concerned, the precipices at the back and 
sides of the Palace were a sufficient defence 
for it, if a good watch was kept on the weak 
side. But what the Pirate Captain dreaded 
was the chance of our escaping; and he would 
not trust the precipices to keep us, knowing 
we had sailors in our company, and suspecting 
that they might hit on some substitute 
for ropes, and lower themselves and their 
fellow-prisoners down from the back or the 
sides of the Palace, in the dark. Accordingly, 
the Pirate Captain settled it that two men out 
of each company should do double duty, after 
nightfall: the choice of them to be decided 
by casting dice. This gave four men to patrol 
round the sides and the back of the building: 
a sufficient number to keep a bright look-out. 
The Pirates murmured a little at the prospect 
of double duty; but, there was no remedy for 
it. The Indians, having a superstitious 
horror of remaining in the ruined city after 
dark, had bargained to be allowed to go back 
to their village, every afternoon. And, as 
for the Sambos, the Pirate Captain knew them 
better than the English had known them at 
Silver-Store, and would have nothing to do 
with them in any matter of importance. 
</p>
<p>
The setting of the watch was completed 
without much delay. If any of us had felt 
the slightest hope of escaping, up to this time, 
the position of our prison and the number of 
sentinels appointed to guard it, would have 
been more than enough to extinguish that 
hope for ever. 
</p>
<p>
An hour before sunset, the Indians--whose 
only business at the Palace was to supply us 
with food from the village, and to prepare 
the food for eating--made their last batch 
of Tortillas, and then left the ruins in a body, 
at the usual trot of those savages when 
they are travelling in a hurry. 
</p>
<p>
When the sun had set, the darkness came 
down upon us, I might almost say, with a 
rush. Bats whizzed about, and the low 
warning hum of Mosquitos sounded close to 
our ears. Flying beetles, with lights in their 
heads, each light as bright as the light of 
a dozen glowworms, sparkled through the 
darkness, in a wonderful manner, all night 
long. When one of them settled on the 
walls, he lighted up the hideous sculptures; 
for a yard all round him, at the very 
least. Outside, in the forest, the dreadful 
stillness seemed to be drawing its breath, 
from time to time, when the night-wind 
swept lightly through the million-million 
leaves. Sometimes, the surge of monkeys 
travelling through the boughs, burst out with 
a sound like waves on a sandy shore; 
sometimes, the noise of falling branches and trunks 
rang out suddenly with a crash, as if the great 
ruins about us were splitting into pieces; 
sometimes, when the silence was at its deepest--
when even the tread of the watch outside 
had ceased--the quick rustle of a lizard or a 
snake, sounded treacherously close at our ears. 
It was long before the children in the women's 
room were all quieted and hushed to sleep--
longer still before we, their elders, could 
compose our spirits for the night. After all 
sounds died away among us, and when I 
thought that I was the only one still awake, 
I heard Miss Maryon's voice saying, softly, 
"God help and deliver us!" A man in our 
room, moving on his bed of leaves, repeated 
the words after her; and the ship's boy, 
Robert, half-asleep, half-awake, whispered to 
himself sleepily, "Amen!" After that, the 
silence returned upon us, and was broken no 
more. So the night passed--the first night 
in our Prison in the Woods. 
</p>
<p>
With the morning, came the discovery of a 
new project of the Pirate Captain's, for which 
none of us had been prepared. 
</p>
<p>
Soon after sunrise, the Pirate Captain 
looked into our room, and ordered all the 
men in it out into the large hall, where he 
lived with his big soul and his little body. 
After eyeing us narrowly, he directed three 
of the sailors, myself, and two of my 
comrades, to step apart from the rest. When 
we had obeyed, the bundle of axes which had 
troubled my mind so much, was brought into 
the hall; and four men of the guard, then 
on duty, armed with muskets and pistols, 
were marched in afterwards. Six of the 
axes were chosen and put into our hands, the 
Pirate Captain pointing warningly, as we 
took them, to the men with fire-arms in the 
front of us. He and his mate, both armed to 
the teeth, then led the way out to the steps; 
we followed; the other four Pirates came after 
us. We were formed, down the steps, in single 
file; the Pirate Captain at the head; I myself 
next to him; a Pirate next to me; and so on to 
the end, in such order as to keep a man with a 
loaded musket between each one or two of us 
prisoners. I looked behind me as we started, 
and saw two of the Sambos--that Christian 
George King was one of them--following us. 
We marched round the back of the Palace, and 
over the ruins beyond it, till we came to a 
track through the forest, the first I had seen. 
After a quarter of an hour's walking, I saw 
the sunlight, bright beyond the trees in front 
of us. In another minute or two, we stood 
under the clear sky, and beheld at our feet a 
broad river, running with a swift silent 
current, and overshadowed by the forest, rising 
as thick as ever on the bank that was opposite 
to us. 
</p>
<p>
On the bank where we stood, the trees 
were young; some great tempest of past 
years having made havoc in this part of the 
forest, and torn away the old growth to 
make room for the new. The young trees 
grew up, mostly, straight and slender,--
that is to say, slender for South America, 
the slightest of them being, certainly, as 
thick as my leg. After peeping and peering 
about at the timber, with the look of 
a man who owned it all, the Pirate Captain 
sat himself down cross-legged on the grass, 
and did us the honor to address us. 
</p>
<p>
"Aha! you English, what do you think 
I have kept you alive for?" says he. 
"Because I am fond of you? Bah! 
Because I don't like to kill you? Bah! What 
for, then? Because I want the use of your 
arms to work for me. See those trees!" 
He waved his hand backwards and 
forwards, over the whole prospect. "Cut 
them all down--lop off the branches--
smooth them into poles--shape them into 
beams--chop them into planks. Camarado!" 
he went on, turning to the mate, "I mean to 
roof in the Palace again, and to lay new 
floors over the rubbish of stones. I will 
make the big house good and dry to live in, 
in the rainy weather--I will barricade the 
steps of it for defence against an army,--I 
will make it my strong castle of retreat for 
me and my men, and our treasure, and our 
prisoners, and all that we have, when the 
English cruisers of the devil get too many 
for us along the coast. To work, you six! 
Look at those four men of mine,--their 
muskets are loaded. Look at these two 
Sambos who will stop here to fetch help if 
they want it. Remember the women and 
children you have left at the Palace--and 
at your peril and at their peril, turn those 
axes in your hands from their proper 
work! You understand? You English fools?" 
</p>
<p>
With those words he jumped to his feet, 
and ordered the niggers to remain and place 
themselves at the orders of our guard. 
Having given these last directions, and having 
taken his mate's opinion as to whether 
three of the Buccaniers would not be enough 
to watch the Palace in the day, when the 
six stoutest men of the prisoners were away 
from it, the Pirate Captain offered his little 
weazen arm to the American, and strutted 
back to his castle, on better terms with 
himself than ever. 
</p>
<p>
As soon as he and the mate were gone, 
Christian George King tumbled himself down 
on the grass, and kicked up his ugly heels 
in convulsions of delight. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, golly, golly, golly!" says he. "You 
dam English do work, and Christian George 
King look on. Yup, Sojeer! whack at them 
tree!" 
</p>
<p>
I paid no attention to the brute, being 
better occupied in noticing my next comrade, 
Short. I had remarked that all the while 
the Pirate Captain was speaking, he was 
looking hard at the river, as if the sight of 
a large sheet of water did his sailorly eyes 
good. When we began to use the axes, 
greatly to my astonishment, he buckled to 
at his work like a man who had his whole 
heart in it: chuckling to himself at every 
chop, and wagging his head as if he was in 
the forecastle again telling his best yarns. 
</p>
<p>
"You seem to be in spirits, Short?" I says, 
setting to on a tree close by him. 
</p>
<p>
"The river's put a notion in my head," 
says he. "Chop away, Gill, as hard as you 
can, or they may hear us talking." 
</p>
<p>
"What notion has the river put in your 
head?" I asked that man, following his 
directions. 
</p>
<p>
"You don't know where that river runs 
to, I suppose?" says Short. "No more don't 
I. But, did it say anything particular to you, 
Gill, when you first set eyes on it? It said 
to me, as plain as words could speak, 'I'm 
the road out of this. Come and try me!'--
Steady! Don't stop to look at the water. 
Chop away, man, chop away." 
</p>
<p>
"The road out of this?" says I. "A road 
without any coaches, Short. I don't see so 
much as the ruins of one old canoe lying 
about anywhere." 
</p>
<p>
Short chuckles again, and buries his axe 
in his tree. 
</p>
<p>
"What are we cutting down these here 
trees for?" says he. 
</p>
<p>
"Roofs and floors for the Pirate Captain's 
castle," says I. 
</p>
<p>
"Rafts for ourselves!" says he, with another 
tremendous chop at the tree, which brought 
it to the ground--the first that had fallen. 
</p>
<p>
His words struck through me as if I had 
been shot. For the first time since our 
imprisonment I now saw, clear as daylight, a 
chance of escape. Only a chance, to be sure; 
but, still a chance. 
</p>
<p>
Although the guard stood several paces 
away from us, and could by no possibility 
hear a word that we said, through the noise 
of the axes, Short was too cautious to talk 
any more. 
</p>
<p>
"Wait till night," he said, lopping the 
branches off the tree. "Pass the word on in 
a whisper to the nearest of our men to work 
with a will; and say, with a wink of your 
eye, there's a good reason for it." 
</p>
<p>
After we had been allowed to knock off for 
that day, the Pirates had no cause to 
complain of the work we had done; and they 
reported us to the Pirate Captain as obedient 
and industrious, so far. When we lay down 
at night, I took the next place on the leaves 
to Short. We waited till the rest were 
asleep, and till we heard the Pirate Captain 
snoring in the great hall, before we began to 
talk again about the river and the rafts. 
This is the amount of what Short whispered 
in my ear on that occasion: 
</p>
<p>
He told me he had calculated that it would 
take two large rafts to bear all our company, 
and that timber enough to make such two rafts 
might be cut down by six men in ten days, or, 
at most, in a fortnight. As for the means of 
fastening the rafts--the lashings, he called 
them--the stout vines and creepers supplied 
them abundantly; and the timbers of both 
rafts might be connected together, in this 
way, firmly enough for river navigation, in 
about five hours. That was the very shortest 
time the job would take, done by the willing 
hands of men who knew that they were 
working for their lives, said Short. 
</p>
<p>
These were the means of escape. How to 
turn them to account was the next question. 
Short could not answer it; and though I 
tried all that night, neither could I. 
</p>
<p>
The difficulty was one which, I think, 
might have puzzled wiser heads than ours. 
How were six-and-thirty living souls (being 
the number of us prisoners, including the 
children) to be got out of the Palace safely, 
in the face of the guard that watched it? 
And, even if that was accomplished, when 
could we count on gaining five hours all to 
ourselves for the business of making the 
rafts? The compassing of either of these 
two designs, absolutely necessary as they 
both were to our escape, seemed to be 
nothing more or less than a rank 
impossibility. Towards morning, I got a wild 
notion into my head about letting ourselves 
down from the back of the Palace, in the 
dark, and taking our chance of being able to 
seize the sentinels at that part of the building, 
unawares, and gag them before they could 
give the alarm to the Pirates in front. But, 
Short, when I mentioned my plan to him, 
would not hear of it. He said that men by 
themselves--provided they had not got a 
madman, like Drooce, and a maundering old 
gentleman, like Mr. Pordage, among them--
might, perhaps, run some such desperate risk 
as I proposed; but, that letting women and 
children, to say nothing of Drooce and Pordage, 
down a precipice in the dark, with make-shift 
ropes which might give way at a moment's 
notice, was out of the question. It was 
impossible, on further reflection, not to see 
that Short's view of the matter was the right 
one. I acknowledged as much, and then I put 
it to Short whether our wisest course would 
not be to let one or two of the sharpest of our 
fellow-prisoners into our secret, and see what 
they said. Short asked me which two I had 
in my mind when I made that proposal? 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Macey," says I, "because he is 
naturally quick, and has improved his gifts by 
learning, and Miss Maryon--" 
</p>
<p>
"How can a woman help us?" says Short, 
breaking in on me. 
</p>
<p>
"A woman with a clear head and a high 
courage and a patient resolution--all of 
which Miss Maryon has got, above all the 
world--may do more to help us, in our 
present strait, than any man of our company," 
says I. 
</p>
<p>
"Well," says Short, "I daresay you're 
right. Speak to anybody you please, Gill; 
but, whatever you do, man, stick to it at the 
trees. Let's get the timber down--that's the 
first thing to be done, anyhow." 
</p>
<p>
Before we were mustered for work, I took 
an opportunity of privately mentioning to 
Miss Maryon and Mr. Macey what had 
passed between Short and me. They were 
both thunderstruck at the notion of the rafts. 
Miss Maryon, as I had expected, made 
lighter of the terrible difficulties in the way 
of carrying out our scheme than Mr. Macey 
did. 
</p>
<p>
"We are left here to watch and think, 
all day," she whispered--and I could almost 
hear the quick beating of her heart. 
"While you are making the best of your 
time among the trees, we will make the 
best of ours in the Palace. I can say 
no more, now--I can hardly speak at all 
for thinking of what you have told me. 
Bless you, bless you, for making me hope 
once more! Go now--we must not risk 
the consequences of being seen talking 
together. When you come back at night, look 
at me. If I close my eyes, it is a sign that 
nothing has been thought of yet. If I keep 
them open, take the first safe opportunity of 
speaking secretly to me or to Mr. Macey." 
</p>
<p>
She turned away; and I went back to my 
comrades. Half an hour afterwards, we 
were off for our second day's work among the 
trees. 
</p>
<p>
When we came back, I looked at Miss 
Maryon. She closed her eyes. So, nothing had 
been thought of, yet. 
</p>
<p>
Six more days we worked at cutting down 
the trees, always meriting the same good 
character for industry from our Pirate-guard. 
Six more evenings I looked at Miss Maryon; 
and six times her closed eyes gave me the 
same disheartening answer. On the ninth 
day of our work, Short whispered to me, that 
if we plied our axes for three days longer, he 
considered we should have more than timber 
enough down, to make the rafts. He had 
thought of nothing, I had thought of nothing, 
Miss Maryon and Mr. Macey had thought 
of nothing. I was beginning to get low 
in spirits; but, Short was just as cool and 
easy as ever. "Chop away, Davis," was 
all he said. "The river won't run dry yet 
awhile. Chop away!" 
</p>
<p>
We knocked off, earlier than usual that 
day, the Pirates having a feast in prospect, off 
a wild hog. It was still broad daylight (out 
of the forest) when we came back, and when 
I looked once more in Miss Maryon's face. 
</p>
<p>
I saw a flush in her cheeks; and her eyes 
met mine brightly. My heart beat quicker at 
the glance of them; for I saw that the time had 
come, and that the difficulty was conquered. 
</p>
<p>
We waited till the light was fading, and the 
Pirates were in the midst of their feast. 
Then, she beckoned me into the inner room, 
and I sat down by her in the dimmest corner 
of it. 
</p>
<p>
"You have thought of something, at last, 
Miss?" 
</p>
<p>
"I have. But the merit of the thought 
is not all mine. Chance--no! Providence--
suggested the design; and the instrument 
with which its merciful Wisdom has worked, 
is--a child." 
</p>
<p>
She stopped, and looked all round her 
anxiously, before she went on. 
</p>
<p>
"This afternoon," she says, "I was sitting 
against the trunk of that tree, thinking of 
what has been the subject of my thoughts 
ever since you spoke to me. My sister's 
little girl was whiling away the tedious time, 
by asking Mr. Kitten to tell her the names of 
the different plants which are still left growing 
about the room. You know he is a 
learned man in such matters?" 
</p>
<p>
I knew that; and have, I believe, formerly 
given that out, for my Lady to take in writing. 
</p>
<p>
"I was too much occupied," she went 
on, "to pay attention to them, till they 
came close to the tree against which I was 
sitting. Under it and about it, there grew 
a plant with very elegantly-shaped leaves, 
and with a kind of berry on it. The child 
showed it to Mr. Kitten; and saying, 'Those 
berries look good to eat,' stretched out her 
hand towards them. Mr. Kitten stopped 
her. 'You must never touch that,' he 
said. 'Why not?' the child asked. 
'Because if you eat much of it, it would poison 
you.' 'And if I only eat a little?' said the 
child, laughing. 'If you only eat a little,' 
said Mr. Kitten, 'it would throw you into a 
deep sleep--a sleep that none of us could 
wake you from, when it was time for breakfast--
a sleep that would make your mama 
think you were dead.' Those words were 
hardly spoken, when the thought that I have 
now to tell you of, flashed across my mind. 
But, before I say anything more, answer me 
one question. Am I right in supposing that 
our attempt at escape must be made in the 
night?" 
</p>
<p>
"At night, certainly," says I, "because 
we can be most sure, then, that the Pirates off 
guard are all in this building, and not likely 
to leave it." 
</p>
<p>
"I understand. Now, Davis, hear what 
I have observed of the habits of the men 
who keep us imprisoned in this place. 
The first change of guard at night, is at 
nine o'clock. At that time, seven men 
come in from watching, and nine men (the 
extra night-guard) go out to replace them; 
each party being on duty, as you know, for 
six hours. I have observed, at the nine 
o'clock change of guard, that the seven men 
who come off duty, and the nine who go on, 
have a supply of baked cakes of Indian 
corn, reserved expressly for their use. They 
divide the food between them; the Pirate 
Captain (who is always astir at the change of 
guard) generally taking a cake for himself, 
when the rest of the men take theirs. This 
makes altogether, seventeen men who partake 
of food especially reserved for them, at nine 
o'clock. So far you understand me?" 
</p>
<p>
"Clearly, Miss." 
</p>
<p>
"The next thing I have noticed, is the 
manner in which that food is prepared. 
About two hours before sunset, the Pirate 
Captain walks out to smoke, after he has 
eaten the meal which he calls his dinner. 
In his absence from the hall, the Indians 
light their fire on the unsheltered side of 
it, and prepare the last batch of food 
before they leave us for the night. They 
knead up two separate masses of dough. 
The largest is the first which is separated 
into cakes and baked. That is taken for the 
use of us prisoners and of the men who are 
off duty all the night. The second and 
smaller piece of dough is then prepared for 
the nine o'clock change of guard. On that 
food--come nearer, Davis, I must say it in 
a whisper--on that food all our chances of 
escape now turn. If we can drug it 
unobserved, the Pirates who go off duty, the 
Pirates who go on duty, and the Captain, who 
is more to be feared than all the rest, will be 
as absolutely insensible to our leaving the 
Palace, as if they were every one of them 
dead men." 
</p>
<p>
I was unable to speak--I was unable even 
to fetch my breath at those words. 
</p>
<p>
"I have taken Mr. Kitten, as a matter of 
necessity, into our confidence," she said. "I 
have learnt from him a simple way of obtaining 
the juice of that plant which he forbade 
the child to eat. I have also made myself 
acquainted with the quantity which it is 
necessary to use for our purpose; and I have 
resolved that no hands but mine shall be 
charged with the work of kneading it into 
the dough." 
</p>
<p>
"Not you, Miss,--not you. Let one of us--
let me--run that risk."
</p>
<p>
"You have work enough and risk enough 
already," said Miss Maryon. "It is time that 
the women, for whom you have suffered and 
ventured so much, should take their share. 
Besides, the risk is not great, where the 
Indians only are concerned. They are idle 
and curious. I have seen, with my own 
eyes, that they are as easily tempted away 
from their occupation by any chance sight or 
chance noise as if they were children; and I 
have already arranged with Mr. Macey that 
he is to excite their curiosity by suddenly 
pulling down one of the loose stones in that 
doorway, when the right time comes. The 
Indians are certain to run in here to find 
out what is the matter. Mr. Macey will 
tell them that be has seen a snake,--they 
will hunt for the creature (as I have seen 
them hunt, over and over again, in this 
ruined place)--and while they are so 
engaged, the opportunity that I want, the 
two minutes to myself, which are all that 
I require, will be mine. Dread the Pirate 
Captain, Davis, for the slightest caprice 
of his may ruin all our hopes,--but never 
dread the Indians, and never doubt me." 
</p>
<p>
Nobody, who had looked in her face at 
that moment--or at any moment that ever I 
knew of--could have doubted her. 
</p>
<p>
"There is one thing more," she went on. 
"When is the attempt to be made?" 
</p>
<p>
"In three days' time," I answered; "there 
will be timber enough down to make the 
rafts." 
</p>
<p>
"In three days' time, then, let us decide 
the question of our freedom or our death." 
She spoke those words with a firmness that 
amazed me. "Rest now," she said. "Rest 
and hope." 
</p>
<p>
The third day was the hottest we had yet 
experienced; we were kept longer at work 
than usual; and when we had done, we left 
on the bank enough, and more than enough, 
of timber and poles, to make both the rafts. 
</p>
<p>
The Indians had gone when we got back 
to the Palace, and the Pirate Captain was 
still smoking on the flight of steps. As we 
crossed the hall, I looked on one side and 
saw the Tortillas set up in a pile, waiting 
for the men who came in and went out at 
nine o'clock. 
</p>
<p>
At the door which opened between our 
room and the women's room, Miss Maryon 
was waiting for us. 
</p>
<p>
"Is it done?" I asked in a whisper. 
</p>
<p>
"It is done," she answered. 
</p>
<p>
It was, then, by Mr. Macey's watch (which 
he had kept hidden about him throughout 
our imprisonment), seven o'clock. We had 
two hours to wait: hours of suspense, but 
hours of rest also for the overworked men 
who had been cutting the wood. Before I lay 
down, I looked into the inner room. The 
women were all sitting together; and I saw 
by the looks they cast on me that Miss Maryon 
had told them of what was coming with the 
night. The children were much as usual, playing 
quiet games among themselves. In the 
men's room, I noticed that Mr. Macey had 
posted himself along with Tom Packer, 
close to Serjeant Drooce, and that Mr. Fisher 
seemed to be taking great pains to make 
himself agreeable to Mr. Pordage. I was 
glad to see that the two gentlemen of the 
company, who were quick-witted and 
experienced in most things, were already taking 
in hand the two unreasonable men. 
</p>
<p>
The evening brought no coolness with it. 
The heat was so oppressive that we all 
panted under it. The stillness in the forest 
was awful. We could almost hear the falling 
of the leaves. 
</p>
<p>
Half-past seven, eight, half-past eight, a 
quarter to nine--Nine. The tramp of feet 
came up the steps on one side, and the tramp 
of feet came into the hall, on the other. 
There was a confusion of voices,--then, the 
voice of the Pirate Captain, speaking in his 
own language,--then, the voice of the 
American mute, ordering out the guard,--then 
silence. 
</p>
<p>
I crawled to the door of our room, and laid 
myself down behind it, where I could see a 
strip of the hall, being that part of it in 
which the way out was situated. Here, also, 
the Pirate Captain's tent had been set up, 
about twelve or fourteen feet from the door. 
Two torches were burning before it. By 
their light, I saw the guard on duty file out, 
each man munching his Tortilla, and each 
man grumbling over it. At the same time, 
in the part of the hall which I could not see, 
I heard the men off duty grumbling also. 
The Pirate Captain, who had entered his tent 
the minute before, came out of it, and calling 
to the American mate, at the far end of the 
hall, asked sharply in English, what that 
murmuring meant. 
</p>
<p>
"The men complain of the Tortillas," the 
mate tells him." They say, they are nastier 
than ever to-night." 
</p>
<p>
"Bring me one, and let me taste it," said 
the Captain. I had often before heard people 
talk of their hearts being in their mouths, 
but I never really knew what the sensation 
was, till I heard that order given. 
</p>
<p>
The Tortilla was brought to him. He 
nibbled a bit off it, spat the morsel out 
with disgust, and threw the rest of the cake 
away. 
</p>
<p>
"Those Indian beasts have burnt the 
Tortillas," he said, "and their dirty hides 
shall suffer for it to-morrow morning." With 
those words, he whisked round on his heel, 
and went back into his tent. 
</p>
<p>
Some of the men had crept up behind 
me, and, looking over my head, had seen 
what I saw. They passed the account of it 
in whispers to those who could not see; and 
they, in their turn, repeated it to the women. 
In five minutes everybody in the two rooms 
knew that the scheme had failed with the 
very man whose sleep it was most important 
to secure. I heard no stifled crying among 
the women or stifled cursing among the men. 
The despair of that time was too deep for 
tears, and too deep for words. 
</p>
<p>
I myself could not take my eyes off the 
tent. In a little while he came out of it 
again, pulling and panting with the heat. He 
lighted a cigar at one of the torches, and laid 
himself down on his cloak just inside the 
doorway leading into the portico, so that all 
the air from outside might blow over him. 
Little as he was, he was big enough to lie 
right across the narrow way out. 
</p>
<p>
He smoked and he smoked, slowly and more 
slowly, for, what seemed to me to be, hours, but 
for what, by the watch, was little more than 
ten minutes after all. Then, the cigar dropped 
out of his mouth--his hand sought for it, and 
sank lazily by his side his head turned over 
a little towards the door--and he fell off: not 
into the drugged sleep that there was safety 
in, but into his light, natural sleep, which a 
touch on his body might have disturbed. 
</p>
<p>
"Now's the time to gag him," says Short, 
creeping up close to me, and taking off his 
jacket and shoes. 
</p>
<p>
"Steady," says I. "Don't let's try that till 
we can try nothing else. There are men asleep 
near us who have not eaten the drugged cakes--
the Pirate Captain is light and active--
and if the gag slips on his mouth, we are all 
done for. I'll go to his head, Short, with my 
jacket ready in my hands. When I'm there, 
do you lead the way with your mates, and step 
gently into the portico, over his body. Every 
minute of your time is precious on account of 
making the rafts. Leave the rest of the 
men to get the women and children over; 
and leave me to gag him if he stirs while 
we are getting out." 
</p>
<p>
"Shake hands on it, Davis," says Short, 
getting to his feet. "A team of horses 
wouldn't have dragged me out first, if you 
hadn't said that about the rafts." 
</p>
<p>
"Wait a bit," says I, "till I speak to Mr. 
Kitten." 
</p>
<p>
I crawled back into the room, taking care 
to keep out of the way of the stones in the 
middle of it, and asked Mr. Kitten how long 
it would be before the drugged cakes acted 
on the men outside who had eaten them? 
He said we ought to wait another quarter 
of an hour, to make quite sure. At the 
same time, Mr. Macey whispered in my 
ear to let him pass over the Pirate Captain's 
body, alone with the dangerous man of 
our company--Serjeant Drooce. "I know 
how to deal with mad people," says he. 
"I have persuaded the Sergeant that if he is 
quiet, and if he steps carefully, I can help 
him to escape from Tom Packer, whom he 
is beginning look on as his keeper. He has 
been as stealthy and quiet as a cat ever since--
and I will answer for him till we get to 
the river side." 
</p>
<p>
What a relief it was to hear that! I was 
turning round to get back to Short, when a 
hand touched me lightly. 
</p>
<p>
"I have heard you talking," whispered 
Miss Maryon; "and I will prepare all in my 
room for the risk we must now run. Robert, 
the ship's boy, whom the children are so fond 
of, shall help us to persuade them, once more, 
that we are going to play a game. If you 
can get one of the torches from the tent, and 
pass it in here, it may prevent some of us 
from stumbling. Don't be afraid of the 
women and children, Davis. They shall not 
endanger the brave men who are saving 
them." 
</p>
<p>
I left her at once to get the torch. The 
Pirate Captain was still fast asleep as I stole 
on tiptoe, into the hall, and took it from the 
tent. When I returned, and gave it to Miss 
Maryon, her sister's little deaf and dumb boy 
saw me, and, slipping between us, caught 
tight hold of one of my hands. Having been 
used to riding on my shoulders for so many 
days, he had taken a fancy to me; and, 
when I tried to put him away, he only clung 
the tighter, and began to murmur in his 
helpless dumb way. Slight as the noise was 
which the poor little fellow could make, we 
all dreaded it. His mother wrung her hands 
in despair when she heard him; and Mr. 
Fisher whispered to me for Heaven's sake to 
quiet the child, and humour him at any cost. 
I immediately took him up in my arms, and 
went back to Short. 
</p>
<p>
"Sling him on my back," says I, "as you 
slung the little girl on your own the first day 
of the march. I want both my hands, and 
the child won't be quiet away from me." 
</p>
<p>
Short did as I asked him in two minutes. 
As soon as he had finished, Mr. Macey passed 
the word on to me, that the quarter of an 
hour was up; that it was time to try the 
experiment with Drooce; and that it was necessary 
for us all to humour him by feigning 
sleep. We obeyed. Looking out of the 
corner of my eye, I saw Mr. Macey take the 
mad Serjeant's arm, point round to us all, 
and then lead him out. Holding tight by Mr. 
Macey, Drooce stepped as lightly as a woman, 
with as bright and wicked a look of cunning 
as ever I saw in any human eyes. They 
crossed the hall--Mr. Macey pointed to the 
Pirate Captain, and whispered, "Hush!"--
the Serjeant imitated the action and repeated 
the word--then the two stepped over his 
body (Drooce cautiously raising his feet the 
highest), and disappeared through the portico. 
We waited to hear if there was any noise or 
confusion. Not a sound. 
</p>
<p>
I got up, and Short handed me his jacket 
for the gag. The child, having been startled 
from his sleep by the light of the torch, when 
I brought it in, had fallen off again, already, 
on my shoulder. "Now for it," says I, and 
stole out into the hall. 
</p>
<p>
I stopped at the tent, went in, and took 
the first knife I could find there. With the 
weapon between my teeth, with the little 
innocent asleep on my shoulder, with the 
jacket held ready in both hands, I kneeled 
down on one knee at the Pirate Captain's 
head, and fixed my eyes steadily on his ugly 
sleeping face. 
</p>
<p>
The sailors came out first, with their shoes 
in their hands. No sound of footsteps from 
any one of them. No movement in the ugly 
face as they passed over it. 
</p>
<p>
The women and children were ready next. 
Robert, the ship's boy, lifted the children 
over: most of them holding their little hands 
over their mouths to keep from laughing--
so well had Robert persuaded them that we 
were only playing a game. The women 
passed next, all as light as air; after them, 
in obedience to a sign from me, my 
comrades of the Marines, holding their shoes 
in their hands, as the sailors had done before 
them. So far, not a word had been spoken, 
not a mistake had been made--so far, not a 
change of any sort had passed over the 
Pirate Captain's face. 
</p>
<p>
There were left now in the hall, besides 
myself and the child on my back, only Mr. 
Fisher and Mr. Pordage. Mr. Pordage! 
Up to that moment, in the risk and excitement 
of the time, I had not once thought of 
him. 
</p>
<p>
I was forced to think of him now, though; 
and with anything but a friendly feeling. 
</p>
<p>
At the sight of the Pirate Captain, asleep 
across the way out, the unfortunate, 
mischievous old simpleton tossed up his head, 
and folded his arms, and was on the point of 
breaking out loud into a spoken document 
of some kind, when Mr. Fisher wisely and 
quickly clapped a hand over his mouth. 
</p>
<p>
"Government despatches outside," whispers 
Mr. Fisher, in an agony. "Secret service. 
Forty-nine reports from head-quarters, all 
waiting for you half a mile off. I'll show 
you the way, sir. Don't wake that man 
there, who is asleep: he must know nothing 
about it--he represents the Public." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Pordage suddenly looked very knowing 
and hugely satisfied with himself. He 
followed Mr. Fisher to within a foot of the 
Pirate Captain's body--then stopped short. 
</p>
<p>
"How many reports?" he asked, very 
anxiously. 
</p>
<p>
"Forty-nine," said Mr. Fisher. "Come 
along, sir,--and step clean over the Public, 
whatever you do." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Pordage instantly stepped over, as 
jauntily as if he was going to dance. At the 
moment of his crossing, a hanging rag of his 
cursed, useless, unfortunate, limp Diplomatic 
coat touched the Pirate Captain's forehead, 
and woke him. 
</p>
<p>
I drew back softly, with the child still 
asleep on my shoulder, into the black 
shadow of the wall behind me. At the 
instant when the Pirate Captain awoke, I had 
been looking at Mr. Pordage, and had 
consequently lost the chance of applying the gag 
to his mouth suddenly, at the right time. 
</p>
<p>
On rousing up, he turned his face inwards, 
towards the prisoners' room. If he had 
turned it outwards, he must to a dead 
certainty have seen the tail of Mr. Pordage's 
coat, disappearing in the portico. 
</p>
<p>
Though he was awake enough to move, he 
was not awake enough to have the full 
possession of his sharp senses. The drowsiness 
of his sleep still hung about him. He 
yawned, stretched himself, spat wearily, sat 
up, spat again, got on his legs, and stood up, 
within three foot of the shadow in which I 
was hiding behind him. 
</p>
<p>
I forgot the knife in my teeth,--I declare 
solemnly, in the frightful suspense of that 
moment, I forgot it--and doubled my fist as 
if I was an unarmed man, with the purpose 
of stunning him by a blow on the head if he 
came any nearer. I suppose I waited, with 
my fist clenched, nearly a minute, while he 
waited, yawning and spitting. At the end of 
that time, he made for his tent, and I heard 
him (with what thankfulness no words can 
tell!) roll himself down, with another yawn, 
on his bed inside. 
</p>
<p>
I waited--in the interest of us all--to 
make quite sure, before I left, that he was 
asleep again. In what I reckoned as about 
five minutes' time, I heard him snoring, and 
felt free to take myself and my little sleeping 
comrade out of the prison, at last. 
</p>
<p>
The drugged guards in the portico were 
sitting together, dead asleep, with their backs 
against the wall. The third man was lying 
flat, on the landing of the steps. Their arms 
and ammunition were gone: wisely taken by 
our men--to defend us, if we were meddled 
with before we escaped, and to kill food for 
us when we committed ourselves to the river. 
</p>
<p>
At the bottom of the steps I was startled 
by seeing two women standing together. They 
were Mrs. Macey and Miss Maryon: the 
first, waiting to see her child safe; the 
second (God bless her for it!) waiting to 
see me safe. 
</p>
<p>
In a quarter of an hour we were by the 
river-side, and saw the work bravely begun: 
the sailors and the marines under their 
orders, labouring at the rafts in the shallow 
water by the bank; Mr. Macey and Mr. 
Fisher rolling down fresh timber as it was 
wanted; the women cutting the vines, 
creepers, and withies for the lashings. We 
brought with us three more pair of hands to 
help; and all worked with such a will, that, 
in four hours and twenty minutes, by Mr. 
Macey's watch, the rafts, though not finished 
as they ought to have been, were still strong 
enough to float us away. 
</p>
<p>
Short, another seaman, and the ship's 
boy, got aboard the first raft, carrying 
with them poles and spare timber. Miss 
Maryon, Mrs. Fisher and her husband, 
Mrs. Macey and her husband and three 
children, Mr. and Mrs. Pordage, Mr. Kitten, 
myself, and women and children besides, to 
make up eighteen, were the passengers on 
the leading raft. The second raft, under the 
guidance of the two other sailors, held 
Serjeant Drooce (gagged, for he now threatened 
to be noisy again), Tom Packer, the 
two marines, Mrs. Belltott, and the rest of 
the women and children, We all got on board 
silently and quickly, with a fine moonlight 
over our heads, and without accidents or 
delays of any kind. 
</p>
<p>
It was a good half-hour before the time 
would come for the change of guard at the 
prison, when the lashings which tied us to the 
bank were cast off, and we floated away, a 
company of free people, on the current of 
an unknown river. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE RAFTS ON THE RIVER.</title>
<p>
WE contrived to keep afloat all that night, 
and, the stream running strong with us, to 
glide a long way down the river. But, we 
found the night to be a dangerous time for 
such navigation, on account of the eddies and 
rapids, and it was therefore settled next day 
that in future we would bring-to at sunset, 
and encamp on the shore. As we knew of 
no boats that the Pirates possessed, up at the 
Prison in the Woods, we settled always to 
encamp on the opposite side of the stream, 
so as to have the breadth of the river between 
our sleep and them. Our opinion was, that 
if they were acquainted with any near way 
by land to the mouth of this river, they 
would come up it in force, and re-take us or 
kill us, according as they could; but, that if 
that was not the case, and if the river ran by 
none of their secret stations, we might escape. 
</p>
<p>
When I say we settled this or that, I do 
not mean that we planned anything with any 
confidence as to what might happen an hour 
hence. So much had happened in one night, 
and such great changes had been violently 
and suddenly made in the fortunes of many 
among us, that we had got better used to 
uncertainty, in a little while, than I dare say 
most people do in the course of their lives. 
</p>
<p>
The difficulties we soon got into, through the 
off-settings and point-currents of the stream, 
made the likelihood of our being drowned, 
alone--to say nothing of our being retaken--
as broad and plain as the sun at noon-day to 
all of us. But, we all worked hard at 
managing the rafts, under the direction of 
the seamen (of our own skill, I think we 
never could have prevented them from 
oversetting), and we also worked hard at making 
good the defects in their first hasty construction--
which the water soon found out. While 
we humbly resigned ourselves to going down, 
if it was the will of Our Father that was in 
Heaven, we humbly made up our minds, that 
we would all do the best that was in us. 
</p>
<p>
And so we held on, gliding with the stream. 
It drove us to this bank, and it drove us to 
that bank, and it turned us, and whirled us; 
but yet it carried us on. Sometimes much 
too slowly, sometimes much too fast, but yet 
it carried us on. 
</p>
<p>
My little deaf and dumb boy slumbered 
a good deal now, and that was the case 
with all the children. They caused very 
little trouble to any one. They seemed, in 
my eyes, to get more like one another, not 
only in quiet manner, but in the face, too. 
The motion of the raft was usually so much 
the same, the scene was usually so much the 
same, the sound of the soft wash and ripple 
of the water was usually so much the same, 
that they were made drowsy, as they might 
have been by the constant playing of one 
tune. Even on the grown people, who worked 
hard and felt anxiety, the same things 
produced something of the same effect. Every 
day was so like the other, that I soon lost count 
of the days, myself, and had to ask Miss 
Maryon, for instance, whether this was the 
third or fourth? Miss Maryon had a pocketbook 
and pencil, and she kept the log; that 
is to say, she entered up a clear little journal 
of the time, and of the distances our seamen 
thought we had made, each night. 
</p>
<p>
So, as I say, we kept afloat and glided on. 
All day long, and every day, the water, and 
the woods, and sky; all day long, and every 
day, the constant watching of both sides of 
the river, and far a-head at every bold turn 
and sweep it made, for any signs of Pirate-boats, 
or Pirate-dwellings. So, as I say, we 
kept afloat and glided on. The days melting 
themselves together to that degree, that I 
could hardly believe my ears when I asked 
"How many, now, Miss?" and she answered, 
"Seven." 
</p>
<p>
To be sure, poor Mr. Pordage had, by 
about now, got his Diplomatic coat into such 
a state as never was seen. What with the 
mud of the river, what with the water of the 
river, what with the sun, and the dews, and 
the tearing boughs, and the thickets, it hung 
about him in discoloured shreds like a mop. 
The sun had touched him a bit. He had 
taken to always polishing one particular 
button, which just held on to his left wrist, 
and to always calling for stationery. I 
suppose that man called for pens, ink, and paper, 
tape, and sealing-wax, upwards of one 
thousand times in four and twenty hours. He 
had an idea that we should never get out of 
that river unless we were written out of it 
in a formal Memorandum; and the more we 
laboured at navigating the rafts, the more he 
ordered us not to touch them at our peril, and 
the more he sat and roared for stationery. 
</p>
<p>
Mrs. Pordage, similarly, persisted in wearing 
her nightcap. I doubt if any one but 
ourselves who had seen the progress of that 
article of dress, could by this time have told 
what it was meant for. It had got so limp 
and rugged that she couldn't see out of her 
eyes for it. It was so dirty, that whether it 
was vegetable matter out of a swamp, or 
weeds out of the river, or an old porter's-knot 
from England, I don't think any new 
spectator could have said. Yet, this 
unfortunate old woman had a notion that it was 
not only vastly genteel, but that it was the 
correct thing as to propriety. And she really 
did carry herself over the other ladies who 
had no night-caps, and who were forced to tie 
up their hair how they could, in a superior 
manner that was perfectly amazing. 
</p>
<p>
I don't know what she looked like, sitting 
in that blessed night-cap, on a log of wood, 
outside the hut or cabin upon our raft. She 
would have rather resembled a fortune-teller 
in one of the picture-books that used to be 
in the shop windows in my boyhood, except 
for her stateliness. But, Lord bless my heart, 
the dignity with which she sat and moped, 
with her head in that bundle of tatters, was 
like nothing else in the world! She was not 
on speaking terms with more than three of 
the ladies. Some of them had, what she 
called, "taken precedence" of her--in getting 
into, or out of, that miserable little shelter!--
and others had not called to pay their 
respects, or something of that kind. So, there 
she sat, in her own state and ceremony, while 
her husband sat on the same log of wood, 
ordering us one and all to let the raft go to 
the bottom, and to bring him stationery. 
</p>
<p>
What with this noise on the part of Mr. 
Commissioner Pordage, and what with the 
cries of Serjeant Drooce on the raft astern 
(which were sometimes more than Tom 
Packer could silence), we often made our slow 
way down the river, anything but quietly. 
Yet, that it was of great importance that no 
ears should be able to hear us from the woods 
on the banks, could not be doubted. We 
were looked for, to a certainty, and we might 
be retaken at any moment. It was an 
anxious time; it was, indeed, indeed, an anxious 
time. 
</p>
<p>
On the seventh night of our voyage on the 
rafts, we made fast, as usual, on the opposite 
side of the river to that from which we had 
started, in as dark a place as we could pick 
out. Our little encampment was soon made, 
and supper was eaten, and the children fell 
asleep. The watch was set, and everything 
made orderly for the night. Such a starlight 
night, with such blue in the sky, and such 
black in the places of heavy shade on the 
banks of the great stream! 
</p>
<p>
Those two ladies, Miss Maryon and Mrs. 
Fisher, had always kept near me since the 
night of the attack. Mr. Fisher, who was 
untiring in the work of our raft, had said to me: 
</p>
<p>
"My dear little childless wife has grown so 
attached to you, Davis, and you are such a gentle 
fellow, as well as such a determined one;" 
our party had adopted that last expression 
from the one-eyed English pirate, and I 
repeat what Mr. Fisher said, only because he 
said it; "that it takes a load off my mind 
to leave her in your charge." 
</p>
<p>
I said to him: "Your lady is in far better 
charge than mine, sir, having Miss Maryon 
to take care of her; but, you may rely upon 
it, that I will guard them both--faithful and 
true." 
</p>
<p>
Says he: "I do rely upon it, Davis, and I 
heartily wish all the silver on our old Island 
was yours." 
</p>
<p>
That seventh starlight night, as I have 
said, we made our camp, and got our supper, 
and set our watch, and the children fell 
asleep. It was solemn and beautiful in those 
wild and solitary parts, to see them, every 
night before they lay down, kneeling under 
the bright sky, saying their little prayers at 
women's laps. At that time we men all 
uncovered, and mostly kept at a distance. 
When the innocent creatures rose up, we 
murmured "Amen!" all together. For, 
though we had not heard what they said, we 
knew it must be good for us. 
</p>
<p>
At that time, too, as was only natural, 
those poor mothers in our company whose 
children had been killed, shed many tears. 
I thought the sight seemed to console them 
while it made them cry; but, whether I was 
right or wrong in that, they wept very much. 
On this seventh night, Mrs. Fisher had cried 
for her lost darling until she cried herself 
asleep. She was lying on a little couch of 
leaves and such-like (I made the best little 
couch I could, for them every night), and 
Miss Maryon had covered her, and sat by 
her, holding her hand. The stars looked 
down upon them. As for me, I guarded them. 
</p>
<p>
"Davis!" says Miss Maryon. (I am not 
going to say what a voice she had. I couldn't 
if I tried.) 
</p>
<p>
"I am here, Miss." 
</p>
<p>
"The river sounds as if it were swollen 
to-night." 
</p>
<p>
"We all think, Miss, that we are coming 
near the sea." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you believe, now, we shall escape?" 
</p>
<p>
"I do now, Miss, really believe it." I had 
always said I did; but, I had in my own 
mind been doubtful." 
</p>
<p>
"How glad you will be, my good Davis, to 
see England again!" 
</p>
<p>
I have another confession to make that 
will appear singular. When she said these 
words, something rose in my throat; and the 
stars I looked away at, seemed to break into 
sparkles that fell down my face and burnt it. 
</p>
<p>
"England is not much to me, Miss, except 
as a name." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh! So true an Englishman should 
not say that!--Are you not well to-night, 
Davis?" Very kindly, and with a quick change. 
</p>
<p>
"Quite well, Miss." 
</p>
<p>
"Are you sure? Your voice sounds 
altered in my hearing." 
</p>
<p>
"No, Miss, I am a stronger man than ever. 
But, England is nothing to me." 
</p>
<p>
Miss Maryon sat silent for so long a while, 
that I believed she had done speaking to me 
for one time. However, she had not; for 
by and by she said in a distinct, clear tone: 
</p>
<p>
"No, good friend; you must not say, that 
England is nothing to you. It is to be much to 
you, yet--everything to you. You have to 
take back to England the good name you 
have earned here, and the gratitude and 
attachment and respect you have won here; 
and you have to make some good English 
girl very happy and proud, by marrying her; 
and I shall one day see her, I hope, and make 
her happier and prouder still, by telling her 
what noble services her husband's were in 
South America, and what a noble friend he 
was to me there." 
</p>
<p>
Though she spoke these kind words in a 
cheering manner, she spoke them 
compassionately. I said nothing. It will appear to 
be another strange confession, that I paced 
to and fro, within call, all that night, a most 
unhappy man reproaching myself all the 
night long. "You are as ignorant as any 
man alive; you are as obscure as any man 
alive; you are as poor as any man alive; you 
are no better than the mud under your foot." 
That was the way in which I went on against 
myself until the morning. 
</p>
<p>
With the day, came the day's labour. 
What I should have done without the labour, 
I don't know. We were afloat again at the 
usual hour, and were again making our way 
down the river. It was broader, and clearer 
of obstructions than it had been, and it seemed 
to flow faster. This was one of Drooce's 
quiet days; Mr. Pordage, besides being 
sulky, had almost lost his voice; and we 
made good way, and with little noise. 
</p>
<p>
There was always a seaman forward on 
the raft, keeping a bright look-out. 
Suddenly, in the full heat of the day, when the 
children were slumbering, and the very trees 
and reeds appeared to be slumbering, this 
man--it was Short--holds up his hand, and 
cries with great caution: 
</p>
<p>
"Avast! Voices ahead!" 
</p>
<p>
We held on against the stream as soon as 
we could bring her up, and the other raft 
followed suit. At first, Mr. Macey, Mr. 
Fisher, and myself, could hear nothing; 
though both the seamen aboard of us agreed 
that they could hear voices and oars. After 
a little pause, however, we united in thinking 
that we could hear the sound of voices, and 
the dip of oars. But, you can hear a long way 
in those countries, and there was a bend of 
the river before us, and nothing was to be 
seen except such waters and such banks as 
we were now in the eighth day (and might, 
for the matter of our feelings, have been in the 
eightieth), of having seen with anxious eyes. 
</p>
<p>
It was soon decided to put a man ashore 
who should creep through the wood, see what 
was coming, and warn the rafts. The rafts 
in the meantime to keep the middle of the 
stream. The man to be put ashore, and not 
to swim ashore, as the first thing could be 
more quickly done than the second. The raft 
conveying him, to get back into mid-stream, 
and to hold on along with the other, as well 
as it could, until signalled by the man. In 
case of danger, the man to shift, for himself 
until it should be safe to take him aboard 
I volunteered to be the man. 
</p>
<p>
We knew that the voices and oars must come 
up slowly against the stream; and our seamen 
knew, by the set of the stream, under which 
bank they would come. I was put ashore 
accordingly. The raft got off well, and I 
broke into the wood. 
</p>
<p>
Steaming hot it was, and a tearing place to 
get through. So much the better for me, 
since it was something to contend against and 
do. I cut off the bend in the river, at a great 
saving of space, came to the water's edge 
again, and hid myself, and waited. I could 
now hear the dip of the oars very distinctly; 
the voices had ceased. 
</p>
<p>
The sound came on in a regular tune, and 
as I lay hidden, I fancied the tune so played 
to be, "Chris'en--George--King!--Chris'en--
George--King! Chris'en--George--King!" 
over and over again, always the same, with the 
pauses always at the same places. I had 
likewise time to make up my mind that if these 
were the Pirates, I could and would (barring 
my being shot), swim off to my raft, in spite 
of my wound, the moment I had given 
the alarm, and hold my old post by Miss 
Maryon. 
</p>
<p>
"Chris'en--George--King! Chris'en--
George--King! Chris'en--George--King!" 
coming up, now, very near. 
</p>
<p>
I took a look at the branches about me, 
to see where a shower of bullets would be 
most likely to do me least hurt; and I 
took a look back at the track I had made 
in forcing my way in; and now I was 
wholly prepared and fully ready for them. 
</p>
<p>
"Chris'en--George--King! Chrise'n--
George--King! Chris'en--George--King!" 
Here they were! 
</p>
<p>
Who were they? The barbarous Pirates, 
scum of all nations, headed by such men as the 
hideous little Portuguese monkey, and the one-eyed 
English convict with the gash across his 
face, that ought to have gashed his wicked 
head off? The worst men in the world 
picked out from the worst, to do the cruellest 
and most atrocious deeds that ever 
stained it? The howling, murdering, black-flag 
waving, mad, and drunken crowd of 
devils that had overcome us by numbers 
and by treachery? No. These were English 
men in English boats--good blue-jackets and 
red-coats--marines that I knew myself, and 
sailors that knew our seamen! At the helm 
of the first boat, Captain Carton, eager and 
steady. At the helm of the second boat, 
Captain Maryon, brave and bold. At the 
helm of the third boat, an old seaman, with 
determination carved into his watchful face, 
like the figure-head of a ship. Every man 
doubly and trebly armed from head to foot. 
Every man lying-to at his work, with a will 
that had all his heart and soul in it. Every 
man looking out for any trace of friend or 
enemy, and burning to be the first to do good, 
or avenge evil. Every man with his face on 
fire when he saw me, his countryman who 
had been taken prisoner, and hailed me with 
a cheer, as Captain Carton's boat ran in and 
took me on board. 
</p>
<p>
I reported, "All escaped, sir! All well, 
all safe, all here!" 
</p>
<p>
God bless me--and God bless them--what 
a cheer! It turned me weak, as I was 
passed on from hand to hand to the stern of 
the boat: every hand patting me or grasping 
me in some way or other, in the moment of 
my going by. 
</p>
<p>
"Hold up, my brave fellow," says Captain 
Carton, clapping me on the shoulder like a 
friend, and giving me a flask. "Put your 
lips to that, and they'll be red again. Now, 
boys, give way!" 
</p>
<p>
The banks flew by us, as if the mightiest 
stream that ever ran was with us; and so 
it was, I am sure, meaning the stream of 
those men's ardour and spirit. The banks 
flew by us, and we came in sight of the rafts--
the banks flew by us, and we came alongside 
of the rafts--the banks stopped; and 
there was a tumult of laughing and crying 
and kissing and shaking of hands, and catching 
up of children and setting of them down again, 
and a wild hurry of thankfulness and joy that 
melted every one and softened all hearts. 
</p>
<p>
I had taken notice, in Captain Carton's 
boat, that there was a curious and quite new 
sort of fitting on board. It was a kind of a 
little bower made of flowers, and it was set 
up behind the captain, and betwixt him and 
the rudder. Not only was this arbor, so to 
call it, neatly made of flowers, but it was 
ornamented in a singular way. Some of the 
men had taken the ribbons and buckles off 
their hats, and hung them among the flowers; 
others, had made festoons and streamers of 
their handkerchiefs, and hung them there; 
others, had intermixed such trifles as bits of 
glass and shining fragments of lockets and 
tobacco-boxes, with the flowers; so that 
altogether it was a very bright and lively object in 
the sunshine. But, why there, or what for, 
I did not understand. 
</p>
<p>
Now, as soon as the first bewilderment was 
over, Captain Carton gave the order to land 
for the present. But, this boat of his, with 
two hands left in her, immediately put off 
again when the men were out of her, and 
kept off, some yards from the shore. As she 
floated there, with the two hands gently 
backing water to keep her from going down 
the stream, this pretty little arbor attracted 
many eyes. None of the boat's crew, however, 
had anything to say about it, except that it 
was the captain's fancy. 
</p>
<p>
The captain, with the women and children 
clustering round him, and the men of all 
ranks grouped outside them, and all listening, 
stood telling how the Expedition, deceived by 
its bad intelligence, had chased the light 
Pirate boats all that fatal night, and had 
still followed in their wake next day, and 
had never suspected until many hours too 
late that the great Pirate body had drawn off 
in the darkness when the chace began, and 
shot over to the Island. He stood telling 
how the Expedition, supposing the whole 
array of armed boats to be ahead of it, got 
tempted into shallows and went aground; 
but, not without having its revenge upon the 
two decoy-boats, both of which it had come 
up with, overland, and sent to the bottom 
with all on board. He stood telling how the 
Expedition, fearing then that the case stood 
as it did, got afloat again, by great exertion, 
after the loss of four more tides, and returned 
to the Island, where they found the sloop 
scuttled and the treasure gone. He stood 
telling how my officer, Lieutenant Linderwood, 
was left upon the Island, with as 
strong a force as could be got together 
hurriedly from the mainland, and how the three 
boats we saw before us were manned and 
armed and had come away, exploring the 
coast and inlets, in search of any tidings of 
us. He stood telling all this, with his face 
to the river; and, as he stood telling it, the 
little arbor of flowers floated in the sunshine 
before all the faces there. 
</p>
<p>
Leaning on Captain Carton's shoulder, 
between him and Miss Maryon, was Mrs. 
Fisher, her head drooping on her arm. She 
asked him, without raising it, when he had 
told so much, whether he had found her 
mother? 
</p>
<p>
"Be comforted! She lies," said the 
Captain, gently, "under the cocoa-nut trees on 
the beach." 
</p>
<p>
"And my child, Captain Carton, did you 
find my child, too? Does my darling rest 
with my mother?" 
</p>
<p>
"No. Your pretty child sleeps," said the 
Captain, "under a shade of flowers." 
</p>
<p>
His voice shook; but, there was something 
in it that struck all the hearers. At that 
moment, there sprung from the arbor in his 
boat, a little creature, clapping her hand 
and stretching out her arms, and crying, 
"Dear papa! Dear mamma! I am not 
killed. I am saved. I am coming to kiss 
you. Take me to them, take me to them, 
good, kind sailors!" 
</p>
<p>
Nobody who saw that scene has ever 
forgotten it, I am sure, or ever will forget it. 
The child had kept quite still, where her brave 
grandmama had put her (first whispering in 
her ear, "Whatever happens to me, do not 
stir, my dear!"), and had remained quiet 
until the fort was deserted; she had then 
crept out of the trench, and gone into her 
mother's house; and there, alone on the 
solitary Island, in her mother's room, and 
asleep on her mother's bed, the Captain had 
found her. Nothing could induce her to be 
parted from him after he took her up in his 
arms, and he had brought her away with 
him, and the men had made the bower for 
her. To see those men now, was a sight. 
The joy of the women was beautiful; the 
joy of those women who had lost their own 
children, was quite sacred and divine; but, 
the ecstasies of Captain Carton's boat's crew, 
when their pet was restored to her parents, 
were wonderful for the tenderness they 
showed in the midst of roughness. As the 
Captain stood with the child in his arms, and 
the child's own little arms now clinging 
round his neck, now round her father's, now 
round her mother's, now round some one who 
pressed up to kiss her, the boat's crew shook 
hands with one another, waved their hats over 
their heads, laughed, sang, cried, danced--and 
all among themselves, without wanting to 
interfere with anybody--in a manner never 
to be represented. At last, I saw the coxswain 
and another, two very hard-faced men with 
grizzled heads who had been the heartiest of 
the hearty all along, close with one another, 
get each of them the other's head under his 
arm, and pummel away at it with his fist as 
hard as he could, in his excess of joy. 
</p>
<p>
When we had well rested and refreshed 
ourselves--and very glad we were to have 
some of the heartening things to eat and 
drink that had come up in the boats--we 
recommenced our voyage down the river: 
rafts, and boats, and all. I said to myself, it 
was a very different kind of voyage now, from 
what it had been; and I fell into my proper 
place and station among my fellow-soldiers. 
</p>
<p>
But, when we halted for the night, I found 
that Miss Maryon had spoken to Captain 
Carton concerning me. For, the Captain 
came straight up to me, and says he, "My 
brave fellow, you have been Miss Maryon's 
body-guard all along, and you shall remain 
so. Nobody shall supersede you in the 
distinction and pleasure of protecting that 
young lady." I thanked his honor in the 
fittest words I could find, and that night 
I was placed on my old post of watching the 
place where she slept. More than once in the 
night, I saw Captain Carton come out into the 
air, and stroll about there, to see that all was 
well. I have now this other singular confession 
to make, that I saw him with a heavy heart. 
Yes; I saw him with a heavy, heavy heart. 
</p>
<p>
In the day-time, I had the like post in 
Captain Carton's boat. I had a special 
station of my own, behind Miss Maryon, and 
no hands but hers ever touched my wound. 
(It has been healed these many long years; 
but, no other hands have ever touched it.) 
Mr. Pordage was kept tolerably quiet now, 
with pen and ink, and began to pick up his 
senses a little. Seated in the second boat, he 
made documents with Mr. Kitten, pretty well 
all day; and he generally handed in a 
Protest about something whenever we stopped. 
The Captain, however, made so very light of 
these papers that it grew into a saying 
among the men, when one of them wanted a 
match for his pipe, "Hand us over a Protest, 
Jack!" As to Mrs. Pordage, she still wore 
the nightcap, and she now had cut all the 
ladies on account of her not having been 
formally and separately rescued by Captain 
Carton before anybody else. The end of Mr. 
Pordage, to bring to an end all I know about 
him, was, that he got great compliments at 
home for his conduct on these trying 
occasions, and that he died of yellow jaundice, a 
Governor and a K.C.B. 
</p>
<p>
Serjeant Drooce had fallen from a high 
fever into a low one, Tom Packer--the only 
man who could have pulled the Serjeant 
through it--kept hospital a-board the old 
raft, and Mrs. Belltott, as brisk as ever again 
(but the spirit of that little woman, when 
things tried it, was not equal to appearances), 
was head-nurse under his directions. Before 
we got down to the Mosquito coast, the joke 
had been made by one of our men, that we 
should see her gazetted Mrs. Tom Packer, 
vice Belltott exchanged. 
</p>
<p>
When we reached the coast, we got 
native boats as substitutes for the rafts; 
and we rowed along under the land; 
and in that beautiful climate, and upon 
that beautiful water, the blooming days 
were like enchantment. Ah! They were 
running away, faster than any sea or river, 
and there was no tide to bring them back. 
We were coming very near the settlement 
where the people of Silver-Store were to be 
left, and from which we Marines were under 
orders to return to Belize. 
</p>
<p>
Captain Carton had, in the boat by him, a 
curious long-barreled Spanish gun, and he 
had said to Miss Maryon one day that it was 
the best of guns, and had turned his head to 
me, and said: 
</p>
<p>
"Gill Davis, load her fresh with a couple 
of slugs, against a chance of showing how 
good she is." 
</p>
<p>
So, I had discharged the gun over the sea, 
and had loaded her, according to orders, and 
there it had lain at the Captain's feet, 
convenient to the Captain's hand. 
</p>
<p>
The last day but one of our journey was 
an uncommonly hot day. We started very 
early; but, there was no cool air on the sea 
as the day got on, and by noon the heat was 
really hard to bear, considering that there 
were women and children to bear it. Now, 
we happened to open, just at that time, a 
very pleasant little cove or bay, where there 
was a deep shade from a great growth of 
trees. Now, the Captain, therefore, made 
the signal to the other boats to follow him in 
and lie by a while. 
</p>
<p>
The men who were off duty went ashore, 
and lay down, but were ordered, for 
caution's sake, not to stray, and to keep 
within view. The others rested on their 
oars, and dozed. Awnings had been made 
of one thing and another, in all the boats, 
and the passengers found it cooler to be 
under them in the shade, when there was 
room enough, than to be in the thick woods. 
So, the passengers were all afloat, and mostly 
sleeping. I kept my post behind Miss 
Maryon, and she was on Captain Carton's 
right in the boat, and Mrs. Fisher sat on her 
right again. The Captain had Mrs. Fisher's 
daughter on his knee. He and the two ladies 
were talking about the Pirates, and were talking 
softly: partly, because people do talk 
softly under such indolent circumstances, and 
partly because the little girl had gone off 
asleep. 
</p>
<p>
I think I have before given it out for my 
Lady to write down, that Captain Carton had 
a fine bright eye of his own. All at once, 
he darted me a side look, as much as to 
say. "Steady--don't take on--I see 
something!"--and gave the child into her mother's 
arms. That eye of his was so easy to 
understand, that I obeyed it by not so much as 
looking either to the right or to the left out 
of a corner of my own, or changing my 
attitude the least trifle. The Captain went on 
talking in the same mild and easy way; but 
began--with his arms resting across his knees, 
and his head a little hanging forward, as if 
the heat were rather too much for him--
began to play with the Spanish gun. 
</p>
<p>
"They had laid their plans, you see," says 
the Captain, taking up the Spanish gun 
across his knees, and looking, lazily, at the 
inlaying on the stock, "with a great deal of 
art; and the corrupt or blundering local 
authorities were so easily deceived;" he ran 
his left hand idly along the barrel, but I 
saw, with my breath held, that he covered 
the action of cocking the gun with his right--
"so easily deceived, that they summoned 
us out to come into the trap. But my intention 
as to future operations--" In a flash the 
Spanish gun was at his bright eye, and he fired. 
</p>
<p>
All started up; innumerable echoes 
repeated the sound of the discharge; a cloud of 
bright-colored birds flew out of the woods 
screaming; a handful of leaves were 
scattered in the place where the shot had struck; 
a crackling of branches was heard; and some 
lithe but heavy creature sprang into the air, 
and fell forward, head down, over the muddy 
bank. 
</p>
<p>
"What is it?" cries Captain Maryon from 
his boat. All silent then, but the echoes 
rolling away. 
</p>
<p>
"It is a Traitor and a Spy," said Captain 
Carton, handing me the gun to load again. 
"And I think the other name of the animal 
is Christian George King!" 
</p>
<p>
Shot through the heart. Some of the 
people ran round to the spot, and drew him 
out, with the slime and wet trickling down 
his face; but, his face itself would never stir 
any more to the end of time. 
</p>
<p>
"Leave him hanging to that tree," cried 
Captain Carton; his boat's crew giving way, 
and he leaping ashore. "But first into this 
wood, every man in his place. And boats! 
Out of gunshot!" 
</p>
<p>
It was a quick change, well meant and 
well made, though it ended in disappointment. 
No Pirates were there; no one but the Spy 
was found. It was supposed that the Pirates, 
unable to retake us, and expecting a great 
attack upon them, to be the consequence of 
our escape, had made from the ruins in the 
Forest, taken to their ship along with the 
Treasure, and left the Spy to pick up what 
intelligence he could. In the evening we 
went away, and he was left hanging to the 
tree, all alone, with the red sun making a 
kind of a dead sunset on his black face. 
</p>
<p>
Next day, we gained the settlement on the 
Mosquito coast for which we were bound. 
Having stayed there to refresh, seven days, 
and having been much commended, and highly 
spoken of, and finely entertained, we Marines 
stood under orders to march from the Town-Gate 
(it was neither much of a town nor 
much of a gate), at five in the morning. 
</p>
<p>
My officer had joined us before then. 
When we turned out at the gate, all the 
people were there; in the front of them all 
those who had been our fellow-prisoners, and 
all the seamen. 
</p>
<p>
"Davis," says Lieutenant Linderwood. 
"Stand out, my friend!" 
</p>
<p>
I stood out from the ranks, and Miss 
Maryon and Captain Carton came up to me. 
</p>
<p>
"Dear Davis," says Miss Maryon, while 
the tears fell fast down her face, "your 
grateful friends, in most unwillingly taking 
leave of you, ask the favour that, while you 
bear away with you their affectionate 
remembrance which nothing can ever impair, you 
will also take this purse of money--far more 
valuable to you, we all know, for the deep 
attachment and thankfulness with which it is 
offered, than for its own contents, though we 
hope those may prove useful to you, too, in 
after life." 
</p>
<p>
I got out, in answer, that I thankfully 
accepted the attachment and affection, but 
not the money. Captain Carton looked at me 
very attentively, and stepped back, and moved 
away. I made him my bow as he stepped 
back, to thank him for being so delicate. 
</p>
<p>
"No, miss," said I, "I think it would 
break my heart to accept of money. But, if 
you could condescend to give to a man so 
ignorant and common as myself, any little thing 
you have worn--such as a bit of ribbon--" 
</p>
<p>
She took a ring from her finger, and put it 
in my hand. And she rested her hand in 
mine, while she said these words: 
</p>
<p>
"The brave gentlemen of old--but not one 
of them was braver, or had a nobler nature 
than you--took such gifts from ladies, and 
did all their good actions for the givers' sakes. 
If you will do yours for mine, I shall think 
with pride that I continue to have some share 
in the life of a gallant and generous man." 
</p>
<p>
For the second time in my life, she kissed 
my hand. I made so bold, for the first time, 
as to kiss hers; and I tied the ring at my 
breast, and I fell back to my place. 
</p>
<p>
Then, the horse-litter went out at the gate, 
with Serjeant Drooce in it; and the horse-litter 
went out at the gate with Mrs. Belltott 
in it; and Lieutenant Linderwood gave the 
word of command, "Quick march!" and, 
cheered and cried for, we went out of the 
gate too, marching along the level plain 
towards the serene blue sky as if we were 
marching straight to Heaven. 
</p>
<p>
When I have added here that the Pirate 
scheme was blown to shivers, by the Pirate-ship 
which had the Treasure on board being so 
vigorously attacked by one of His Majesty's 
cruisers, among the West India Keys, and 
being so swiftly boarded and carried, that 
nobody suspected anything about the scheme 
until three-fourths of the Pirates were killed, 
and the other fourth were in irons, and the 
Treasure was recovered; I come to the last 
singular confession I have got to make. 
</p>
<p>
It is this. I well knew what an immense 
and hopeless distance there was between me 
and Miss Maryon; I well knew that I was no 
fitter company for her than I was for the angels; 
I well knew that she was as high above my 
reach as the sky over my head; and yet I loved 
her. What put it in my low heart to be so 
daring, or whether such a thing ever 
happened before or since, as that a man so 
uninstructed and obscure as myself got his 
unhappy thoughts lifted up to such a height, 
while knowing very well how presumptuous 
and impossible to be realised they were, I am 
unable to say; still, the suffering to me was 
just as great as if I had been a gentleman. 
I suffered agony--agony. I suffered hard, and 
I suffered long. I thought of her last words 
to me, however, and I never disgraced them. 
If it had not been for those dear words, I 
think I should have lost myself in despair 
and recklessness. 
</p>
<p>
The ring will be found lying on my heart, of 
course, and will be laid with me wherever I 
am laid. I am getting on in years now, 
though I am able and hearty. I was 
recommended for promotion, and everything was 
done to reward me that could be done; but, 
my total want of all learning stood in my 
way, and I found myself so completely out of 
the road to it, that I could not conquer any 
learning, though I tried. I was long in the 
service, and I respected it, and was respected 
in it, and the service is dear to me at this 
present hour. 
</p>
<p>
At this present hour, when I give this out 
to my Lady to be written down, all my old 
pain has softened away, and I am as happy 
as a man can be, at this present fine old 
country-house of Admiral Sir George Carton, 
Baronet. It was my Lady Carton who herself 
sought me out, over a great many miles of 
the wide world, and found me in Hospital 
wounded, and brought me here. It is my 
Lady Carton who writes down my words. 
My Lady was Miss Maryon. And now, that 
I conclude what I had to tell, I see my Lady's 
honored grey hair droop over her face, as she 
leans a little lower at her desk; and I 
fervently thank her for being so tender as I 
see she is, towards the past pain and trouble 
of her poor, old, faithful, humble soldier. 
</p>
<section>THE END OF THE CHRISTMAS NUMBER FOR 1857.</section>
</chapter>
</book>
