<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>Another Round Of Stories By The Christmas Fire</title>
<subtitle>(Household Words Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1853</date>
<option name="chapter.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="chapter.number_style" value="NONE"/>
</info>

<prefix>
<info title="ANOTHER ROUND OF STORIES BY THE CHRISTMAS FIRE."/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>HOUSEHOLD WORDS.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1853.</centre>
</prefix>

<chapter>
<title>THE SCHOOLBOY'S STORY.</title>
<p>
Being rather young at present I am 
getting on in years, but still I am rather 
young--I have no particular adventures of 
my own to fall back upon. It wouldn't much 
interest anybody here, I suppose, to know 
what a screw the Reverend is, or what a 
griffin she is, or how they do stick it into 
parents--particularly hair-cutting and medical 
attendance. One of our fellows was charged 
in his half's account twelve and six-pence for 
two pills--tolerably profitable at six and three-
pence a-piece, I should think--and he never 
took them either, but put them up the sleeve 
of his jacket. 
</p>
<p>
As to the beef, it's shameful. It's not beef. 
Regular beef isn't veins. You can chew regular 
beef. Besides which there's gravy to regular 
beef, and you never see a drop to ours. 
Another of our fellows went home ill, and heard 
the family doctor tell his father that he 
couldn't account for his complaint unless it 
was the beer. Of course it was the beer, and 
well it might be! 
</p>
<p>
However, beef and Old Cheeseman are two 
different things. So is beer. It was Old 
Cheeseman I meant to tell about; not the 
manner in which our fellows get their 
constitutions destroyed for the sake of profit. 
</p>
<p>
Why, look at the pie-crust alone. There's 
no flakiness in it. It's solid--like damp lead. 
Then our fellows get nightmares, and are 
bolstered for calling out and waking other 
fellows. Who can wonder! 
</p>
<p>
Old Cheeseman one night walked in his 
sleep, put his hat on over his night-cap, got 
hold of a fishing-rod and a cricket-bat, and 
went down into the parlor, where they 
naturally thought from his appearance he was a 
Ghost. Why, he never would have done that 
if his meals had been wholesome. When we 
all begin to walk in our sleeps, I suppose 
they'll be sorry for it. 
</p>
<p>
Old Cheeseman wasn't second Latin Master 
then; he was a fellow himself. He was first 
brought there, very small, in a post-chaise, 
by a woman who was always taking snuff and 
shaking him--and that was the most he 
remembered about it. He never went home for 
the holidays. His accounts (he never learnt 
any extras) were sent to a Bank, and the Bank 
paid them; and he had a brown suit twice a 
year, and went into boots at twelve. They 
were always too big for him, too. 
</p>
<p>
In the midsummer holidays, some of our 
fellows who lived within walking distance, 
used to come back and climb the trees outside 
the playground wall, on purpose to look at 
Old Cheeseman reading there by himself. 
He was always as mild as the tea--and that's 
pretty mild, I should hope!--so when they 
whistled to him, he looked up and nodded; 
and when they said "Holloa Old Cheeseman, 
what have you had for dinner?" he said 
"Boiled mutton;" and when they said "An't 
it solitary, Old Cheeseman?" he said "It is a 
little dull, sometimes;" and then they said 
"Well, good bye, Old Cheeseman!" and 
climbed down again. Of course it was imposing 
on Old Cheeseman to give him nothing 
but boiled mutton through a whole Vacation, 
but that was just like the system. When 
they didn't give him boiled mutton they gave 
him rice pudding, pretending it was a treat. 
And saved the butcher. 
</p>
<p>
So Old Cheeseman went on. The holidays 
brought him into other trouble besides the 
loneliness; because when the fellows began 
to come back, not wanting to, he was always 
glad to see them: which was aggravating 
when they were not at all glad to see him, 
and so he got his head knocked against walls, 
and that was the way his nose bled. But he 
was a favourite in general. Once, a subscription 
was raised for him; and, to keep up his 
spirits, he was presented before the holidays 
with two white mice, a rabbit, a pigeon, and 
a beautiful puppy. Old Cheeseman cried 
about it, especially soon afterwards, when 
they all ate one another. 
</p>
<p>
Of course Old Cheeseman used to be called 
by the names of all sorts of cheeses, Double 
Glo'sterman, Family Cheshireman, Dutchman, 
North Wiltshireman, and all that. But he 
never minded it. And I don't mean to say 
he was old in point of years, because he wasn't, 
only he was called, from the first, Old Cheeseman. 
</p>
<p>
At last, Old Cheeseman was made second 
Latin Master. He was brought in one morning 
at the beginning of a new half, and 
presented to the school in that capacity as "Mr. 
Cheeseman." Then our fellows all agreed 
that Old Cheeseman was a spy, and a deserter, 
who had gone over to the enemy's camp, 
and sold himself for gold. It was no excuse 
for him that he had sold himself for very little 
gold--two pound ten a quarter, and his washing, 
as was reported. It was decided by a 
Parliament which sat about it, that Old 
Cheeseman's mercenary motives could alone 
be taken into account, and that he had 
"coined our blood for drachmas." The 
Parliament took the expression out of the quarrel 
scene between Brutus and Cassius. 
</p>
<p>
When it was settled in this strong way that 
Old Cheeseman was a tremendous traitor, 
who had wormed himself into our fellows 
secrets on purpose to get himself into favour 
by giving up everything he knew, all courageous 
fellows were invited to come forward 
and enrol themselves in a Society for making 
a set against him. The President of the 
Society was First boy, named Bob Tarter. His 
father was in the West Indies, and he owned, 
himself, that his father was worth Millions. 
He had great power among our fellows, and 
he wrote a parody, beginning, 
</p>
<poem>
<poem1>"Who made believe to be so meek</poem1>
<poem1>That we could hardly hear him speak,</poem1>
<poem1>Yet turned out an Informing Sneak?</poem1>
<poem4>Old Cheeseman."</poem4>
</poem>
<p0>
--and on in that way through more than a 
dozen verses, which he used to go and sing, 
every morning, close by the new master's 
desk. He trained one of the low boys too, a 
rosy cheeked little Brass who didn't care what 
he did, to go up to him with his Latin Grammar 
one morning, and say it so:--<em>Nominativus 
pronominum</em>--Old Cheeseman, <em>raro 
exprimitur</em>--was never suspected, <em>nisi distinctionis</em>--
of being an informer, <em>aut emphasis  
gratia</em>--until he proved one. <em>Ut</em>--for 
instance, <em>Vos damnastis</em>--when he sold the 
boys, <em>Quasi</em>--as though, <em>dicat</em>--he should 
say, <em>Pretaerea nemo</em>--I'm a Judas! All this 
produced a great effect on Old Cheeseman. 
He had never had much hair; but what he 
had, began to get thinner and thinner every 
day. He grew paler and more worn; and 
sometimes of an evening he was seen sitting 
at his desk with a precious long snuff to his 
candle, and his hands before his face, crying. 
But no member of the Society could pity him, 
even if he felt inclined, because the President 
said it was Old Cheeseman's conscience. 
</p0>
<p>
So Old Cheeseman went on, and didn't he 
lead a miserable life! Of course the Reverend 
turned up his nose at him, and of course  
she did--because both of them always do at 
all the masters, but he suffered from the 
fellows most, and he suffered from them 
constantly. He never told about it, that the 
Society could find out; but he got no credit 
for that, because the President said it was 
Old Cheeseman's cowardice. 
</p>
<p>
He had only one friend in the world, and 
that one was almost as powerless as he was, 
for it was only Jane. Jane was a sort of 
wardrobe-woman to our fellows, and took care 
of the boxes. She come at first, I believe, as 
a kind of apprentice, some of our fellows say 
from a Charity, but I don't know, and after 
her time was out, had stopped at so much a 
year. So little a year, perhaps I ought to 
say, for it is far more likely. However, she 
had put some pounds in the Savings' Bank, 
and she was a very nice young woman. She 
was not quite pretty; but she had a very frank, 
honest, bright face, and all our fellows were 
fond of her. She was uncommonly neat and 
cheerful, and uncommonly comfortable and 
kind. And if anything was the matter with 
a fellow's mother, he always went and showed 
the letter to Jane. 
</p>
<p>
Jane was Old Cheeseman's friend. The 
more the Society went against him the more 
Jane stood by him. She used to give him a 
good-humoured look out of her still-room 
window, sometimes, that seemed to set him 
up for the day. She used to pass out of the 
orchard and the kitchen-garden (always kept 
locked, I believe you!) through the 
playground, when she might have gone the other 
way, only to give a turn of her head, as much 
as to say "Keep up your spirits!" to Old 
Cheeseman. His slip of a room was so fresh 
and orderly, that it was well known who 
looked after it while he was at his desk; and 
when our fellows, saw a smoking hot dumpling 
on his plate at dinner, they knew with 
indignation who had sent it up. 
</p>
<p>
Under these circumstances, the Society 
resolved, after a quantity of meeting and 
debating, that Jane should be requested to cut 
Old Cheeseman dead: and that if she refused, 
she must be sent to Coventry herself. So a 
deputation, headed by the President, was 
appointed to wait on Jane, and inform her of 
the vote the Society had been under the 
painful necessity of passing. She was very 
much respected for all her good qualities, and 
there was a story of her having once waylaid 
the Reverend in his own study and got a 
fellow off from severe punishment, of her own 
kind comfortable heart. So the deputation 
didn't much like the job. However, they 
went up, and the President told Jane all about 
it. Upon which Jane turned very red, burst 
into tears, informed the President and the 
deputation, in a way not at all like her usual 
way, that they were a parcel of malicious 
young savages, and turned the whole respected 
body out of the room. Consequently it was 
entered in the Society's book (kept in 
astronomical cypher for fear of detection), that all 
communication with Jane was interdicted; 
and the President addressed the members on 
this convincing instance of Old Cheeseman's 
undermining. 
</p>
<p>
But Jane was as true to Old Cheeseman as 
Old Cheeseman was false to our fellows--in 
their opinion at all events--and steadily 
continued to be his only friend. It was a great 
exasperation to the Society, because Jane was 
as much a loss to them as she was a gain to 
him; and being more inveterate against him 
than ever, they treated him worse than ever. 
</p>
<p>
At last one morning, his desk stood empty, 
his room was peeped into and found to be 
vacant, and a whisper went about among the 
pale faces of our fellows that Old Cheeseman, 
unable to bear it any longer, had got up early 
and drowned himself. 
</p>
<p>
The mysterious looks of the other masters 
after breakfast, and the evident fact that Old 
Cheeseman was not expected, confirmed the 
Society in this opinion. Some began to 
discuss whether the President was liable to 
hanging or only transportation for life, and 
the President's face showed a great anxiety 
to know which. However, he said that a 
jury of his countrymen should find him game; 
and that in his address he should put it to 
them to lay their hands upon their hearts, and 
say whether they as Britons, approved of 
Informers, and how they thought they would 
like it themselves. Some of the Society 
considered that he had better run away until he 
found a Forest where he might change clothes 
with a woodcutter, and stain his face with 
blackberries; but the majority believed that 
if he stood his ground, his father--belonging, 
as he did, to the West Indies, and being worth 
millions--could buy him off. 
</p>
<p>
All our fellows' hearts beat fast when the 
Reverend came in, and made a sort of a 
Roman, or a Field Marshal, of himself with 
the ruler; as he always did before delivering 
an address. But their fears were nothing to 
their astonishment when he came out with 
the story that Old Cheeseman, "so long our 
respected friend and fellow-pilgrim in the 
pleasant plains of knowledge," he called him--
O yes! I dare say! Much of that! was 
the orphan child of a disinherited young lady 
who had married against her father's wish, 
and whose young husband had died, and who 
had died of sorrow herself, and whose 
unfortunate baby (Old Cheeseman) had been 
brought up at the cost of a grandfather who 
would never consent to see it, baby, boy, or 
man; which grandfather was now dead, and 
serve him right--that's my putting in--and 
which grandfather's large property, there 
being no will, was now, and all of a sudden 
and for ever. Old Cheeseman's! Our so long 
respected friend and fellow-pilgrim in the 
pleasant plains of knowledge, the Reverend 
wound up a lot of bothering quotations by 
saying, would "come among us once more" 
that day fortnight, when he desired to take 
leave of us himself in a more particular manner. 
With these words, he stared severely 
round at our fellows, and went solemnly out. 
</p>
<p>
There was precious consternation among the 
members of the Society now. Lots of them 
wanted to resign, and lots more began to 
try to make out that they had never belonged 
to it. However, the President stuck up, and 
said that they must stand or fall together, 
and that if a breach was made it should be 
over his body--which was meant to encourage 
the Society: but it didn't. The President 
further said, he would consider the position 
in which they stood, and would give them his 
best opinion and advice in a few days. This 
was eagerly looked for, as he knew a good 
deal of the world on account of his father's 
being in the West Indies. 
</p>
<p>
After days and days of hard thinking, and 
drawing armies all over his slate, the President 
called our fellows together, and made the 
matter clear. He said it was plain that when 
Old Cheeseman came on the appointed day, 
his first revenge would be to impeach the 
Society, and have it flogged all round. After 
witnessing with joy the torture of his enemies, 
and gloating over the cries which agony would 
extort from them, the probability was that 
he would invite the Reverend, on pretence of 
conversation, into a private room--say the 
parlor into which parents were shown, where 
the two great globes were which were never 
used--and would there reproach him with 
the various frauds and oppressions he had endured 
at his hands. At the close of his observations, 
he would make a signal to a Prize-fighter 
concealed in the passage, who would then 
appear and pitch into the Reverend till he 
was left insensible. Old Cheeseman would 
then make Jane a present of from five to ten 
pounds, and would leave the establishment in 
fiendish triumph. 
</p>
<p>
The President explained that against the 
parlour part, or the Jane part, of these arrangements 
he had nothing to say; but, on the 
part of the Society, he counselled deadly 
resistance. With this view he recommended 
that all available desks should be filled with 
stones, and that the first word of the 
complaint should be the signal to every fellow to 
let fly at Old Cheeseman. The bold advice 
put the Society in better spirits, and was 
unanimously taken. A post about Old Cheeseman's 
size was put up in the playground, 
and all our fellows practised at it till it was 
dented all over. 
</p>
<p>
When the day came, and places were called, 
every fellow sat down in a tremble. There 
had been much discussing and disputing as 
to how Old Cheeseman would come; but it 
was the general opinion that he would appear 
in a sort of a triumphal car drawn by four 
horses, with two livery servants in front, and 
the Prize-fighter in disguise up behind. So 
all our fellows sat listening for the sound of 
wheels. But no wheels were heard, for Old 
Cheeseman walked after all, and came into 
the school without any preparation. Pretty 
much as he used to be, only dressed in black. 
</p>
<p>
"Gentlemen," said the Reverend, presenting 
him, "our so long respected friend and 
fellow-pilgrim in the pleasant plains of knowledge, 
is desirous to offer a word or two. Attention, 
gentlemen, one and all!" 
</p>
<p>
Every fellow stole his hand into his desk, 
and looked at the President The President 
was allready, and taking aim at Old Cheeseman 
with his eyes. 
</p>
<p>
What did Old Cheeseman then, but walk 
up to his old desk, look round him with a 
queer smile as if there was a tear in his eye, 
and begin in a quavering mild voice, "My 
dear companions and old friends!" 
</p>
<p>
Every fellow's hand came out of his desk, 
and the President suddenly began to cry. 
</p>
<p>
"My dear companions and old friends," 
said Old Cheeseman, "you have heard of my 
good fortune. I have passed so many years 
under this roof--my entire life so far, I may 
say--that I hope you have been glad to hear 
of it for my sake. I could never enjoy it 
without exchanging congratulations with you. 
If we have ever misunderstood one another 
at all, pray my dear boys let us forgive 
and forget. I have a great tenderness for 
you, and I am sure you return it. I want, 
in the fulness of a grateful heart, to shake 
hands with you every one. I have come 
back to do it, if you please, my dear boys." 
</p>
<p>
Since the President had begun to cry, 
several other fellows had broken out here and 
there: but now, when Old Cheeseman began 
with him as first boy, laid his left hand 
affectionately on his shoulder and gave him 
his right; and when the President said 
"Indeed I don't deserve it. Sir; upon my honour 
I don't;" there was sobbing and crying all 
over the school. Every other fellow said he 
didn't deserve it, much in the same way; but 
Old Cheeseman, not minding that a bit, went 
cheerfully round to every boy, and wound up 
with every master--finishing off the Reverend 
last. 
</p>
<p>
Then a snivelling little chap in a corner, 
who was always under some punishment or 
other, set up a shrill cry of "Success to Old 
Cheeseman! Hoorray!" The Reverend glared 
upon him, and said "Mr. Cheeseman, Sir." 
But, Old Cheeseman protesting that he liked 
his old name a great deal better than his new 
one, all our fellows took up the cry; and, for 
I don't know how many minutes, there was 
such a thundering of feet and hands, and 
such a roaring of Old Cheeseman, as never 
was heard. 
</p>
<p>
After that, there was a spread in the dining 
room of the most magnificent kind. Fowls, 
tongues, preserves, fruits, confectioneries, 
jellies, neguses, barley-sugar temples, trifles, 
crackers--eat all you can and pocket what you 
like--all at Old Cheeseman's expense. After 
that, speeches, whole holiday, double and 
treble sets of all manners of games, donkeys, 
pony-chaises and drive yourself, dinner for all 
the masters at the Seven Bells, (twenty pounds 
a-head our fellows estimated it at,) an annual 
holiday and feast fixed for that day every 
year, and another on Old Cheeseman's birthday--
Reverend bound down before the fellows 
to allow it, so that he could never back out--
all at Old Cheeseman's expense. 
</p>
<p>
And didn't our fellows go down in a body 
and cheer outside the Seven Bells? O no! 
</p>
<p>
But there's some thing else besides. Don't 
look at the next story-teller, for there's more 
yet. Next day, it was resolved that the 
Society should make it up with Jane, and then be 
dissolved. What do you think of Jane being 
gone, though! "What? Gone for ever?" said 
our fellows with long faces. "Yes, to be 
sure," was all the answer they could get. 
None of the people about the house would say 
anything more. At length, the first boy took 
upon himself to ask the Reverend whether 
our old friend Jane was really gone? The 
Reverend (he has got a daughter at home--
turn-up nose, and red) replied severely, "Yes 
sir. Miss Pitt is gone." The idea of calling 
Jane Miss Pitt! Some said she had been sent 
away in disgrace for taking money from Old 
Cheeseman; others said she had gone into 
Old Cheeseman's service at a rise of ten 
pounds a year. All that our fellows knew, 
was, she was gone. 
</p>
<p>
It was two or three months afterwards, 
when, one afternoon, an open carriage stopped 
at the cricket-field, just outside bounds, with 
a lady and gentleman in it, who looked at the 
game a long time and stood up to see it played. 
Nobody thought much about them, until the 
same little snivelling chap came in, against all 
rules, from the post where he was Scout, and 
said, "It's Jane!" Both Elevens forgot the 
game directly, and run crowding round the 
carriage. It was Jane! In such a bonnet! 
And if you'll believe me, Jane was married to 
Old Cheeseman. 
</p>
<p>
It soon became quite a regular thing when 
our fellows were hard at it in the play-ground, 
to see a carriage at the low part of the wall 
where it joins the high part, and a lady and 
gentleman standing up in it, looking over. 
The gentleman was always Old Cheeseman, 
and the lady was always Jane. 
</p>
<p>
The first time I ever saw them, I saw them 
in that way. There had been a good many 
changes among our fellows then, and it had 
turned out that Bob Tarter's father wasn't 
worth millions! He wasn't worth anything. 
Bob had gone for a soldier, and Old Cheeseman 
had purchased his discharge. But that's 
not the carriage. The carriage stopped, and 
all our fellows stopped as soon as it was seen. 
</p>
<p>
"So you have never sent me to Coventry 
after all!" said the lady laughing, as our fellows 
swarmed up the wall to shake hands with her. 
"Are you never going to do it?" 
</p>
<p>
"Never! never! never!" on all sides. 
</p>
<p>
I didn't understand what she meant then, 
but of course I do now. I was very much 
pleased with her face though, and with her 
good way, and I couldn't help looking at her--
and at him too--with all our fellows clustering 
so joyfully about them. 
</p>
<p>
They soon took notice of me as a new boy, 
so I thought I might as well swarm up the 
wall myself, and shake hands with them as the 
rest did. I was quite as glad to see them 
as the rest were, and was quite as familiar 
with them in a moment. 
</p>
<p>
"Only a fortnight now," said Old Cheeseman, 
"to the holidays. Who stops? 
Anybody?" 
</p>
<p>
A good many fingers pointed at me, and a 
good many voices cried, "He does!" For 
it was the year when you were all away, and 
rather low I was about it, I can tell you. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh!" said Old Cheeseman. "But it's 
solitary here in the holiday time. He had 
better come to us." 
</p>
<p>
So I went to their delightful house, and 
was as happy as I could possibly be. They 
understood how to conduct themselves towards 
boys, they do. When they take a boy to the 
play, for instance, they do take him. They 
don't go in after it's begun, or come out before 
it's over. They know how to bring a boy up, 
too. Look at their own! Though he is very 
little as yet, what a capital boy he is! Why, 
my next favourite to Mrs. Cheeseman, and Old 
Cheeseman, is young Cheeseman. 
</p>
<p>
So, now I have told you all I know about 
Old Cheeseman. And it's not much after all, 
I am afraid. Is it? 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE OLD LADY'S STORY.</title>
<p>
I HAVE never told you my secret, my dear 
nieces. However, this Christmas, which may 
be the last to an old woman, I will give the 
whole story; for though it is a strange story, 
and a sad one, it is true; and what sin there 
was in it I trust I may have expiated by my 
tears and my repentance. Perhaps the last 
expiation of all this is painful confession. 
</p>
<p>
We were very young at the time, Lucy and 
I, and the neighbours said we were pretty. 
So we were, I believe, though entirely different; 
for Lucy was quiet, and fair, and I was 
full of life and spirits; wild beyond any power 
of control, and reckless. I was the elder by 
two years; but more fit to be in leading strings 
myself than to guide or govern my sister. 
But she was so good, so quiet, and so wise, 
that she needed no one's guidance; for if 
advice was to be given, it was she who gave it, 
not I; and I never knew her judgment or 
perception fail. She was the darling of the 
house. My mother had died soon after Lucy 
was born. A picture in the dining-room of 
her, in spite of all the difference of dress, was 
exactly like Lucy; and, as Lucy was now 
seventeen and my mother had been only eighteen 
when it was taken, there was no discrepancy 
of years. 
</p>
<p>
One Allhallow's eve a party of us--all 
young girls, not one of us twenty years of age--
were trying our fortunes round the drawing-
room fire; throwing nuts into the bright 
blaze, to hear if mythic "He's" loved any of 
us, and in what proportion; or pouring hot 
lead into water, to find cradles and rings, 
or purses and coffins; or breaking the whites 
of eggs into tumblers half full of water, and 
then drawing up the white into pictures of the 
future--the prettiest experiment of all. I 
remember Lucy could only make a recumbent 
figure of her's, like a marble monument in 
miniature; and I, a maze of masks and sculls 
and things that looked like dancing apes or 
imps, and vapoury lines that did not require 
much imagination to fashion into ghosts or 
spirits; for they were clearly human in the 
outline, but thin and vapoury. And we all 
laughed a great deal, and teased one another, 
and were as full of fun and mischief, and 
innocence and thoughtlessness, as a nest of 
young birds. 
</p>
<p>
There was a certain room at the other end 
of our rambling old manor-house, which was 
said to be haunted, and which my father had 
therefore discontinued as a dwelling-room, so 
that we children might not be frightened by 
foolish servants; and he had made it into a 
lumber-place--a kind of ground-floor granary--
where no one had any business. Well, it 
was proposed that one of us should go into 
this room alone, lock the door, stand before a 
glass, pare and eat an apple very deliberately, 
looking fixedly in the glass all the time; and 
then, if the mind never once wandered, the 
future husband would be clearly shown in the 
glass. As I was always the foolhardy girl of 
every party, and was, moreover, very desirous 
of seeing that apocryphal individual, my 
future husband (whose non-appearance I used 
to wonder at and bewail in secret,) I was glad 
enough to make the trial, notwithstanding 
the entreaties of some of the more timid. Lucy, 
above all, clung to me, and besought me 
earnestly not to go--at last, almost with tears. 
But my pride of courage, and my curiosity, 
and a certain nameless feeling of attraction, 
were too strong for me. I laughed Lucy and 
her abettors into silence; uttered half a dozen 
bravadoes; and taking up a bed-room candle, 
passed through the long silent passages, to 
the cold, dark, deserted room--my heart beating 
with excitement, my foolish head dizzy 
with hope and faith. The church-clock chimed 
a quarter past twelve as I opened the door. 
</p>
<p>
It was an awful night. The windows shook, 
as if every instant they would burst in with 
some strong man's hand on the bars, and his 
shoulder against the frames; and the trees 
howled and shrieked, as if each branch were 
sentient and in pain. The ivy beat against 
the window, sometimes with fury, and 
sometimes with the leaves slowly scraping against 
the glass, and drawing out long shrill sounds, 
like spirits crying to each other. In the room 
itself it was worse. Rats had made it their 
refuge for many years, and they rushed 
behind the wainscot and down inside the 
walls, bringing with them showers of lime and dust, 
which rattled like chains, or sounded like 
men's feet hurrying to and fro; and every 
now and then a cry broke through the room, 
one could not tell from where or from what, 
but a cry, distinct and human; heavy blows 
seemed to be struck on the floor, which cracked 
like parting ice beneath my feet, and loud 
knockings shook the walls. Yet in this tumult 
I was not afraid, I reasoned on each new 
sound very calmly--and said, "Those are 
rats," or "those are leaves," and "birds in 
the chimney," or "owls in the ivy," as each 
new howl or scream struck my ear. And I 
was not in the least frightened or disturbed; 
it all seemed natural and familiar. I placed 
the candle on a table in the midst of the room, 
where an old broken mirror stood; and, looking 
steadily into the glass (having first wiped 
off the dust), I began to eat Eve's forbidden 
fruit, wishing intently, as I had been bidden, 
for the apparition of my future husband. 
</p>
<p>
In about ten minutes I heard a dull, vague, 
unearthly sound; felt, not heard. It was as 
if countless wings rushed by, and small low 
voices whispering too; as if a crowd, a 
multitude of life was about me; as if shadowy 
faces crushed up against me, and eyes and 
hands, and sneering lips, all mocked me. I 
was suffocated. The air was so heavy, so filled 
with life, that I could not breathe. I was 
pressed on from all sides, and could not turn 
nor move without parting thickening vapours. 
I heard my own name, I can swear to that 
today! I heard it repeated through the room; 
and then bursts of laughter followed, and the 
wings rustled and fluttered, and the whispering 
voices mocked and chattered, and the 
heavy air, so filled with life, hung heavier and 
thicker, and the Things pressed up to me 
closer, and checked the breath on my lips 
with the clammy breath from theirs. 
</p>
<p>
I was not alarmed, I was not excited; but 
I was fascinated and spell-bound; yet with 
every sense seeming to possess ten times its 
natural power. I still went on looking in the 
glass, still earnestly desiring an apparition, 
when suddenly I saw a man's face peering 
over my shoulder in the glass. Girls, I could 
draw that face to this hour! The low 
forehead, with the short curling hair, black as jet, 
growing down in a sharp point; the dark 
eyes, beneath thick eye-brows, burning with 
a peculiar light; the nose and the dilating 
nostrils; the thin lips, curling into a smile, I 
see them all plainly before me now. And--
O, the smile that it was!--the mockery and 
sneer, the derision, the sarcasm, the contempt, 
the victory that were in it! even then it struck 
into me a sense of submission. The eyes 
looked full into mine; those eyes and mine 
fastened on each other; and, as I ended my 
task, the church clock chimed the half-hour; 
and, suddenly released, as if from a spell, I 
turned round, expecting to see a living man 
standing beside me. But I met only the chill 
air coming in from the loose window, and the 
solitude of the dark night. The Life had 
gone; the wings had rushed away; the voices 
had died out, and I was alone; with the rats 
behind the wainscot, the owls hooting in the 
ivy, and the wind howling through the trees. 
</p>
<p>
Convinced that either some trick had 
been played me, or that some one was 
concealed in the room, I searched every corner 
of it. I lifted lids of boxes filled with the dust 
of ages, and with rotting paper lying like 
bleaching skin. I took down the chimney-
board, and soot and ashes flew up in clouds. I 
opened dim old closets, where all manner of 
foul insects had made their homes, and where 
daylight had not entered for generations; but 
I found nothing. Satisfied that nothing 
human was in the room, and that no one could 
have been there to-night, nor for many months, 
if not years, and still nerved to a state of 
desperate courage, I went back to the drawing-
room. But, as I left that room I felt that 
something flowed out with me; and, all 
through the long passages, I retained the 
sensation that this something was behind me. 
My steps were heavy, the consciousness of 
pursuit having paralyzed not quickened me; 
for I knew that when I left that haunted 
room I had not left it alone. As I opened 
the drawing-room door, the blazing fire and 
the strong lamp-light bursting out upon me 
with a peculiar expression of cheerfulness and 
welcome, I heard a laugh close at my elbow, 
and felt a hot blast across my neck. I started 
back, but the laugh died away, and all I saw 
were two points of light, fiery and flaming, 
that somehow fashioned themselves into eyes 
beneath their heavy brows, and looked at me 
meaningly through the darkness. 
</p>
<p>
They all wanted to know what I had seen; 
but I refused to say a word; not liking to tell 
a falsehood then, and not liking to expose 
myself to ridicule. For I felt that what I had 
seen was true, and that no sophistry and no 
argument, no reason and no ridicule, could 
shake my belief in it. My sweet Lucy came 
up to me, seeing me look so pale and wild, 
threw her arms round my neck, and leaned 
forward to kiss me. As she bent her head, I 
felt the same warm blast rush over my lips, 
and my sister, cried, "Why Lizzie, your lips 
burn like fire!" 
</p>
<p>
And so they did, and for long after. The 
Presence was with me still, never leaving me 
day or night: by my pillow, its whispering 
voice often waking me from wild dreams; by 
my side in the broad sunlight; by my side 
in the still moonlight; never absent, busy at 
my brain, busy at my heart--a form ever 
banded to me. It flitted like a cold cloud 
between my sweet sister's eyes and mine, and 
dimmed them so that I could scarcely see 
their beauty. It drowned my father's voice, 
and his words fell confused and indistinct. 
</p>
<p>
Not long after, a stranger came into our 
neighbourhood. He bought Green Howe, a 
deserted old property by the river side, where 
no one had lived for many years; not since 
the young bride, Mrs. Braithwaite, had been 
found in the river one morning, entangled 
among the dank weeds and dripping alders, 
strangled and drowned, and her husband 
dead--none knew how--lying by the chapel 
door. The place had had a bad name ever 
since, and no one would live there. However, 
it was said that a stranger, who had been long 
in the East, a Mr. Felix, had now bought it, 
and that he was coming to reside there. And, 
true enough, one day, the whole of our little 
town of Thornhill was in a state of excitement; 
for a travelling carriage and four, followed by 
another full of servants--Hindoos, or Lascars, 
or Negroes; dark-coloured, strange looking 
people--passed through, and Mr. Felix took 
possession of Green Howe. 
</p>
<p>
My father called on him after a time; and 
I, as the mistress of the house, went with him. 
Green Howe had been changed, as if by 
magic, and we both said so together, as we 
entered the iron gates that led up the broad 
walk. The ruined garden was one mass of 
plants, fresh and green, many of them quite 
new to me; and the shrubbery, which had 
been a wilderness, was restored to order. The 
house looked larger than before, now that it 
was so beautifully decorated; and the broken 
trellis-work, which used to hang dangling 
among the ivy, was matted with creeping 
roses, and jasmine, which left on me the 
impression of having been in flower, which was 
impossible. It was a fairy palace; and we 
could scarcely believe that this was the 
deserted, ill-omened Green Howe. The foreign 
servants, too, in Eastern dresses, covered with 
rings, and necklaces, and earrings, the foreign 
smells of sandal wood, and camphor, and 
musk; the curtains that hung everywhere in 
place of doors, some of velvet, and some of 
cloth of gold; the air of luxury, such as I, a 
simple country girl, had never seen before, 
made such a powerful impression on me that 
I felt as if carried away to some unknown 
region. As we entered, Mr. Felix came to meet 
us; and drawing aside a heavy curtain that 
seemed all of gold and fire--for the flame-
coloured flowers danced and quivered on the 
gold--he led us into an inner room, where 
the darkened light, the atmosphere heavy 
with perfumes, the statues, the birds like living 
jewels, the magnificence of stuffs, and the 
luxuriousness of arrangement overpowered 
me. I felt as if I had sunk into a lethargy in 
which I heard only the rich voice, and saw 
only the form of our stranger host. 
</p>
<p>
He was certainly very handsome; tall, 
dark, yet pale as marble: his very lips were 
pale; with eyes that were extremely bright, 
but which had an expression behind them 
that subdued me. His manners were graceful. 
He was very cordial to us, and made us 
stay a long time, taking us through his 
grounds to see his improvements, and pointing 
out here and there further alterations to 
be made, all with such a disregard for local 
difficulties, and for cost, that, had he been 
one of the princes of the genii he could not 
have talked more royally. He was more than 
merely attentive to me; speaking to me often 
and in a lower voice, bending down near to 
me, and looking at me with eyes that thrilled 
through every nerve and fibre. I saw that 
my father was uneasy; and when we left, I 
asked him how he liked our new neighbour. 
He said, "Not much, Lizzie," with a grave 
and almost displeased look, as if he had 
probed the weakness I was scarcely conscious 
of myself. I thought at the time that he was 
harsh. 
</p>
<p>
However, as there was nothing positively 
to object to in Mr. Felix, my father's impulse 
of distrust could not well be indulged without 
rudeness; and my dear father was too 
thoroughly a gentleman ever to be rude even to 
his enemy. We therefore saw a great deal of 
the stranger, who established himself in our 
house on the most familiar footing, and forced 
on my father and Lucy an intimacy they both 
disliked but could not avoid. For it was 
forced with such consummate skill and tact, 
that there was nothing which the most rigid 
could object to. 
</p>
<p>
I gradually became an altered being under 
his influence. In one thing only a happier--
in the loss of the Voice and the Form which 
had haunted me. Since I had known Felix 
this terror had gone. The reality had 
absorbed the shadow. But in nothing else was 
this strange man's influence over me 
beneficial. I remember that I used to hate 
myself for my excessive irritability of temper 
when I was away from him. Everything at 
home displeased me. Everything seemed so 
small and mean, and old and poor after the 
lordly glory of that house; and the very 
caresses of my family and olden school-day 
friends were irksome and hateful to me. All 
except my Lucy lost its charm; and to her I 
was faithful as ever; to her I never changed. 
But her influence seemed to war with his 
wonderfully. When with him I felt borne 
away in a torrent. His words fell upon me 
mysterious and thrilling, and he gave me 
fleeting glimpses into worlds which had never 
opened themselves to me before; glimpses 
seen and gone like the Arabian gardens. 
</p>
<p>
When I came back to my sweet sister, her 
pure eyes and the holy light that lay in them, 
her gentle voice speaking of the sacred things 
of heaven and the earnest things of life, 
seemed to me like a former existence; a state 
I had lived in years ago. But this divided 
influence nearly killed me; it seemed to part 
my very soul and wrench my being in twain; 
and this more than all the rest, made me sad 
beyond anything people believed possible in 
one so gay and reckless as I had been. 
</p>
<p>
My father's dislike to Felix increased daily; 
and Lucy, who had never been known to use 
a harsh word in her life, from the first 
refused to believe a thought of good in him, or 
to allow him one single claim to praise. She 
used to cling to me in a wild, beseeching 
way, and entreat me with prayers, such as a 
mother might have poured out before an 
erring child, to stop in time, and return to 
those who loved me. "For your soul is lost 
from among us, Lizzie," she used to say; 
"and nothing but a frame remains of the full 
life of love you once gave us!" But one word, 
one look, from Felix was enough to make me 
forget every tear and every prayer of her who, 
until now, had been my idol and my law. 
</p>
<p>
At last my dear father commanded me not 
to see Felix again. I felt as if I should have 
died. In vain I wept and prayed. In vain I 
gave full license to my thoughts, and suffered 
words to pour from my lips which ought never 
to have crept into my heart. In vain; my 
father was inexorable. 
</p>
<p>
I was in the drawing-room. Suddenly, 
noiselessly, Felix was beside me. He had 
not entered by the door which was directly 
in front of me; and the window was closed. 
I never could understand this sudden appearance; 
for I am certain that he had not been 
concealed. 
</p>
<p>
"Your father has spoken of me, Lizzie?" 
he said with a singular smile. I was silent. 
</p>
<p>
"And has forbidden you to see me again?" 
he continued. 
</p>
<p>
"Yes," I answered, impelled to speak by 
something stronger than my will. 
</p>
<p>
"And you intend to obey him?" 
</p>
<p>
"No," I said again, in the same manner, as 
if I had been talking in a dream. 
</p>
<p>
He smiled again. Who was he so like 
when he smiled? I could not remember, and 
yet I knew that he was like some one I had 
seen--a face that hovered outside my memory, 
on the horizon, and never floated near enough 
to be distinctly realized. 
</p>
<p>
"You are right, Lizzie," he then said; 
"there are ties which are stronger than a 
father's commands; ties which no man has 
the right, and no man has the power to break. 
Meet me to-morrow at noon in the Low Lane; 
we will speak further." 
</p>
<p>
He did not say this in any supplicating, nor 
in any loving manner; it was simply a 
command, unaccompanied by one tender word or 
look. He had never said he loved me--never; 
it seemed to be too well understood between 
us to need assurances. 
</p>
<p>
I answered, "yes," burying my face in my 
hands, in shame at this my first act of 
disobedience to my father; and, when I raised 
my head, he was gone. Gone as he had 
entered, without a footfall sounding ever so 
lightly. 
</p>
<p>
I met him the next day, and it was not the 
only time that I did so. Day after day I stole 
at his command from the house, to walk with 
him in the Low Lane--the lane which the 
country people said was haunted, and which 
was consequently always deserted. And there 
we used to walk or sit under the blighted elm 
tree for hours; he talking, but I not 
understanding all he said: for there was a tone of 
grandeur and of mystery in his words that 
overpowered without enlightening me, and 
that left my spirit dazzled rather than 
convinced. I had to give reasons at home for 
my long absences, and he bade me say that 
I had been with old Dame Todd, the blind 
widow of Thornhill Rise, and that I had been 
reading the Bible to her. And I obeyed, 
although, while I said it, I felt Lucy's eyes 
fixed plaintively on mine, and heard her 
murmur a prayer that I might be forgiven. 
</p>
<p>
Lucy grew ill. As the flowers and the 
summer sun came on, her spirit faded more 
rapidly away. I have known since, that it 
was grief more than malady which was killing 
her. The look of nameless suffering which 
used to be in her face, has haunted me through 
life with undying sorrow. It was suffering 
that I, who ought to have rather died for her, 
had caused. But not even her illness stayed 
me. In the intervals, I nursed her tenderly 
and lovingly as before; but for hours and 
hours I left her--all through the long days 
of summer--to walk in the Low Lane, and 
to sit in my world of poetry and fire. When 
I came back my sister was often weeping, and 
I knew that it was for me--I, who once would 
have given my life to save her from one hour 
of sorrow. Then I would fling myself on my 
knees beside her, in an agony of shame and 
repentance, and promise better things of the 
morrow, and vow strong efforts against the 
power and the spell that was on me. But the 
morrow subjected me to the same unhallowed 
fascination, the same faithlessness. 
</p>
<p>
At last Felix told me that I must come 
with him; that I must leave my home, and 
take part in his life; that I belonged to him 
and to him only, and that I could not break 
the tablet of a fate ordained; that I was his 
destiny, and he mine, and that I must fulfil 
the law which the stars had written in the 
sky. I fought against this. I spoke of my 
father's anger, and of my sister's illness. I 
prayed to him for pity, not to force this on 
me, and knelt in the shadows of the autumn 
sunset to ask from him forbearance. 
</p>
<p>
I did not yield this day, nor the next, nor 
for many days. At last he conquered. When 
I said "Yes," he kissed the scarf I wore round 
my neck. Until then he had never touched 
even my hand with his lips. I consented to 
leave my sister, who I well knew was dying; 
I consented to leave my father, whose whole 
life had been one act of love and care for his 
children; and to bring a stain on our name, 
unstained until then. I consented to leave 
those who loved me, all I loved, for a 
stranger. 
</p>
<p>
All was prepared; the hurrying clouds, lead 
coloured, and the howling wind, the fit 
companions in nature with the evil and the despair 
of my soul. Lucy was worse to-day; but 
though I felt going to my death, in leaving 
her, I could not resist. Had his voice called 
me to the scaffold, I must have gone. It was 
the last day of October, and at midnight, when 
I was to leave the house. I had kissed my 
sleeping sister, who was dreaming in her sleep, 
and cried, and grasped my hand, called aloud, 
"Lizzie, Lizzie!, Come back!" But the spell 
was on me, and I left her; and still her dreaming 
voice called out, choking with sobs, "Not 
there! not there, Lizzie! Come back to 
me!" 
</p>
<p>
I was to leave the house by the large, old, 
haunted room that I have spoken of before; 
Felix waiting for me outside. And, a little 
after twelve o'clock, I opened the door to pass 
through. This time the chill, and the damp, 
and the darkness unnerved me. The broken 
mirror was in the middle of the room, as 
before, and, in passing it, I mechanically raised 
my eyes. Then I remembered that it was 
Allhallow's eve, the anniversary of the 
apparition of last year. As I looked, the room, 
which had been so deadly still, became filled 
with the sound I had heard before. The rushing 
of large wings, and the crowd of whispering 
voices flowed like a river round me; and 
again, glaring into my eyes, was the same 
face in the glass that I had seen before, the 
sneering smile even more triumphant, the 
blighting stare of the fiery eyes, the low brow 
and the coal-black hair, and the look of mockery. 
All were there; and all I had seen before 
and since: for it was Felix who was gazing 
at me from the glass. When I turned to speak 
to him, the room was empty. Not a living 
creature was there; only a low laugh, and the 
far-off voices whispering, and the wings. And 
then a hand tapped on the window, and the 
voice of Felix cried from outside, "Come, 
Lizzie, come!" 
</p>
<p>
I staggered, rather than walked, to the 
window; and, as I was close to it--my hand 
raised to open it--there stood between me 
and it a pale figure clothed in white; her 
face more pale than the linen round it. Her 
hair hung down on her breast, and her blue 
eyes looked earnestly and mournfully into 
mine. She was silent, and yet it seemed as 
if a volume of love and of entreaty flowed 
from her lips; as if I heard words of deathless 
affection. It was Lucy; standing there 
in this bitter midnight cold--giving her life to 
save me. Felix called to me again, 
impatiently; and, as he called, the figure turned, 
and beckoned me; beckoning me gently, 
lovingly, beseechingly; and then slowly faded 
away. The chime of the half-hour sounded; 
and, I fled from the room to my sister. I 
found her lying dead on the floor; her hair 
hanging over her breast, and one hand 
stretched out as if in supplication. 
</p>
<p>
The next day Felix disappeared; he and 
his whole retinue; and Green Howe fell into 
ruins again. No one knew where he went, 
as no one knew from whence he came. And 
to this day I sometimes doubt whether or not 
he was a clever adventurer, who had heard of 
my father's wealth; and who, seeing my weak 
and imaginative character, had acted on it for 
his own purposes. All that I do know is that 
my sister's spirit saved me from ruin; and that 
she died to save me. She had seen and known 
all, and gave herself for my salvation down to 
the last and supreme effort she made to rescue 
me. She died at that hour of half-past twelve; 
and at half-past twelve, as I live before you all, 
she appeared to me and recalled me. 
</p>
<p>
And this is the reason why I never married, 
and why I pass Allhallow's eve in prayer by 
my sister's grave. I have told you to-night 
this story of mine, because I feel that I shall 
not live over another last night of October, 
but before the next white Christmas roses 
come out like winter stars on the earth, I shall 
be at peace in the grave. Not in the grave; 
let me rather hope with my blessed sister in 
Heaven! 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>OVER THE WAY'S STORY.</title>
<p>
Once upon a time, before I retired from 
mercantile pursuits and came to live over the 
way, I lived, for many years, in Ursine 
Lane. 
</p>
<p>
Ursine Lane is a very rich, narrow, dark, 
dirty, straggling lane in the great city of 
London (said by some to be itself as rich, as 
dark, and as dirty.) Ursine Lane leads 
from Cheapside into Thames Street, facing 
Sir John Pigg's wharf; but whether Ursine 
Lane be above or below Bow Church, I shall 
not tell you. Neither, whether its name be 
derived from a bear-garden, (which was in 
great vogue in its environs in Queen Bess's 
time) or from an Ursuline Nunnery which 
flourished in its vicinity, before big, bad 
King Harry sent nuns to spin, or to do 
anything else they could. Ursine Lane it was 
before the great fire of London, and Ursine 
Lane it is now. 
</p>
<p>
The houses in Ursine Lane are very old, 
very inconvenient, and very dilapidated; 
and I don't think another great fire (all the 
houses being well-insured, depend upon it) 
would do the neighbourhood any harm, in 
clearing the rubbishing old lane away. Number 
four tumbled in, and across the road on 
to number sixteen, a few years ago: and 
since then, Ursine Lane has been provided 
with a species of roofing in the shape of great 
wooden beams to shore up its opposite sides. 
The district surveyor shakes his head very 
much at Ursine Lane, and resides as far from 
it as he can. The cats of the neighbourhood 
find great delectation in the shoring 
beams, using them, in the night season, as 
rialtos and bridges, not of sighs, but of 
miauws; but foot passengers look wistfully 
and somewhat fearfully upwards at the 
wooden defences. Yet Ursine Lane remains. 
To be sure, if you were to pull it down, you 
would have to remove the old church of St. 
Nicholas Bearcroft, where the bells ring every 
Friday night in conformity with a bequest 
Master Miniver Squirrell, furrier, obiit 
sixteen hundred and eighty-four, piously to 
commemorate his escape from the paws of a 
grisly bear while travelling in the wilds of 
Muscovy. You would have to demolish the 
brave gilt lion and the brave gilt unicorn at 
the extremity of the churchwarden's pew, 
who (saving their gender) with the clerk, 
the sexton, and two or three deaf old shop-
keepers and their wives, are pretty nearly all 
the dearly beloved brethren whom the 
Reverand Tremaine Popples, M. A., can gather 
together as a congregation. Worse than all, 
if Ursine Lane were to come down--the 
pump must come down, the old established, 
constitutional, vested, endowed pump; built, 
so tradition runs, over a fountain blessed by 
the great St. Ursula herself. So Ursine Lane 
remains. 
</p>
<p>
At a certain period of the world's history, 
it may have been yesterday, it may have 
been yesterday twenty years, there dwelt in 
this dismal avenue, a Beast. Everybody 
called him a Beast. He was a Manchester 
warehouseman. Now it is not at all necessary 
for a Manchester warehouseman--or, 
indeed, for any warehouseman--to be a beast 
or a brute, or anything disagreeable. Quite 
the contrary. For instance, next door to the 
Beast's were the counting-houses and ware-
rooms of Tapperly and Grigg, also Manchester 
warehousemen, as merry, light-hearted, 
good-humoured young fellows as you would 
wish to see. Tapperly was somewhat of a 
sporting character, rode away every afternoon 
on a high-stepping brown mare, and lounged 
regularly about the entrance to "Tats" 
whether he booked any bets or not. As for 
Grigg, he was the Coryphaeus of all the 
middle class soirees, dancing academies, and 
subscription balls in London, and it was a 
moving sight to see him in his famous 
Crusader costume at a Drury Lane Bal-Masque. 
Nor was old Sir William Watch (of the firm 
of Watch, Watch and Hover, Manchester 
warehousemen) at the corner, who was fined 
so many thousand pounds for smuggling 
once upon a time, at all beastlike or brutish. 
He was a white-headed, charitable, jolly old 
gentleman, fond of old port, and old songs, 
and old clerks and porters, and his cheque-
book was as open as his heart. Lacteal, 
Flewitt, and Company, again, on the other 
side of the Beast's domicile, the great dealers 
in gauzes and ribbons, were mild, placable, 
pious men, the beloved of Clapham. But 
the Beast was a Beast, and no mistake. 
Everybody said he was: and what everybody 
says, must be true. His name was Braddlescroggs. 
</p>
<p>
Barnard Braddlescroggs. He was the 
head, the trunk, and the tail of the firm. No 
Co., no son, no nephew, no brothers: B. 
BRADDLESCROGGS glared at you from either 
door-jamb. His warerooms were extensive, 
gloomy, dark and crowded. So were his 
counting-houses, which were mostly, 
underground and candle-lit. He loved to keep his 
subordinates in these dark dens, where he 
could rush in upon them suddenly, and growl 
at them. You came wandering through these 
subterraneans upon wan men, pent up among 
parasols and cartons of gay ribbon; upon 
pale lads in spectacles registering silks and 
merinos by the light of flickering, strong-
smelling tallow candles in rusty sconces. 
There was no counting-house community; 
no desk-fellowship: the clerks were isolated--
dammed up in steep little pulpits, relegated 
behind walls of cotton goods, consigned to 
the inpace of bales of tarlatan and barege. 
The Beast was everywhere. He prowled 
about continually. He lurked in holes and 
corners. He reprimanded clerks on staircases, 
and discharged porters in dark entries. 
His deep, harsh, grating voice could ever be 
heard growling during the hours of business, 
somewhere, like a sullen earthquake. His 
stern Wellington boots continually creaked. 
His numerous keys rattled gaoler-fashion. 
His very watch, when wound up, made a 
savage gnashing noise, as though the works 
were in torment. He was a Beast. 
</p>
<p>
Tall, square, sinewy, and muscular in person; 
large and angular in features; with a 
puissant, rebellious head of grey hair that 
would have defied all the brushing, combing, 
and greasing of the Burlington Arcade; with 
black bushy eyebrows nearly meeting on his 
forehead; with a horseshoe frown between 
his eyes; with stubby whiskers, like horsehair 
spikes, rather indented in his cheekbones 
than growing on his cheeks; with a 
large, stiff shirt collar and frill defending his 
face like chevaux-de-frise; with large, coarse, 
bony hands plunged in his trousers pockets; 
with a great seal and ribbons and the savage 
ticking watch I have mentioned--such was 
Barnard Braddlescroggs. From the ears 
and nostrils of such men you see small hairs 
growing, indomitable by tweezers; signs of 
inflexibility of purpose, and stern virility. 
Their joints crack as they walk. His did. 
</p>
<p>
Very rich, as his father, old Simon 
Braddlescroggs, had been before him, B. 
Braddlescroggs was not an avaricious man. He had 
never been known to lend or advance a 
penny to the necessitous; but he paid his 
clerks and servants liberal salaries. This 
was a little unaccountable in the Beast, but 
it was said they did not hate him the less. 
He gave largely to stern charities, such as 
dragged sinners to repentance, or administered 
eleemosynary food, education and blows 
(in a progressively liberal proportion) to 
orphan children. He was a visiting justice 
to strict gaols, and was supposed not to have 
quite made up his mind as to what system 
of prison discipline was the best, unremitting 
corporal punishment, or continuous solitary 
confinement. He apprenticed boys to hard 
trades, or assisted them to emigrate to inclement 
climates. He was a member of a rigid 
persuasion, and one in high authority, and 
had half built a chapel at his own expense; 
but everybody said that few people thanked 
him, or were grateful to him for his 
generosity. He was such a Beast. He bit the 
orphan's nose off, and bullied the widow. He 
gave alms as one who pelts a dog with marrow-
bones, hurting him while he feeds him. 
Those in his employment who embezzled or 
robbed him, were it of but a penny piece, he 
mercilessly prosecuted to conviction. Everybody 
had observed it. He sued all debtors, 
opposed all insolvents, and strove to bring 
all bankrupts within the meaning of the 
penal clauses. Everybody knew it. The 
merchants and brokers, his compeers, fell 
away from him on 'Change; his 
correspondents opened his hard, fierce letters with 
palpitating hearts; his clerks cowered before 
him; his maid servants passed him (when 
they had courage to pass him at all) with 
fear and trembling. The waiters at the 
"Cock" in Threadneedle Street, where he 
took a fiery bowl of Mulligatawney soup for 
lunch, daily, didn't like him. At his club at 
the West End he had a bow-window and a 
pile of newspapers all to himself, dined by 
himself, drank by himself, growled to 
himself. 
</p>
<p>
There had been a Mrs. Braddlescroggs; a 
delicate, blue-eyed little woman out of Devonshire, 
who had been Beauty to the Beast. 
She died early. Her husband was not 
reported to have beaten her, or starved her, 
or verbally ill-treated her, but simply to 
have frightened her to death. Everybody 
said so. She could never take those mild 
blue eyes of hers off her terrible husband, 
and died, looking at him timorously. One 
son had been born to B. B. at her demise. 
He grew up a pale, fair-haired, frightened 
lad, with his mother's eyes. The Beast had 
treated him (everybody was indignant at it) 
from his earliest years with unvarying and 
consistent severity; and at fourteen he was 
removed from the school of the rigid persuasion, 
where he had received his dreary 
commercial education, to his father's rigider, 
drearier establishment in Ursine Lane. He 
had a department to himself there, and a 
tallow candle to himself. 
</p>
<p>
The clerks, some twelve in number, all dined 
and, slept in the house. They had a dismal 
dormitory over some stables in Grizzly Buildings, 
at the back of Ursine Lane; and dined 
in a dingy, uncarpeted room at the top of the 
building--on one unvarying bill of fare of 
beef, mutton, and potatoes--plenty of it, 
though, for the Beast never stinted them: 
which was remarkable in such a Beast. The 
domestic arrangements were superintended by 
a housekeeper--a tall, melancholy, middle-
aged lady, supposed to have been once in 
affluent circumstances. She had been very 
good looking, too, once, but had something 
the matter with her spine, and not 
unfrequently fell down stairs, or upstairs, in fits 
of syncope. When the Beast had no one else 
to abuse and mal-treat, he would go upstairs 
and abuse Mrs. Plimmets, and threaten her 
with dismissal and inevitable starvation. 
Business hours concluded at eight nightly, 
and from that hour to ten P. M. the clerks 
were permitted to walk where they listed--but 
exclusion and expulsion were the never failing 
result of a moment's unpunctuality in 
returning home. The porters slept out of the 
house, and the clerks looked at them almost 
as superior beings, as men of strange 
experiences and knowledge of life--men who had 
been present at orgies prolonged beyond 
midnight, men who had remained in the galleries 
of theatres till the performances were 
concluded. 
</p>
<p>
Of the dozen clerks who kept the books of 
Barnard Braddlescroggs (save that grim 
auriferous banker's pass-book of his) and 
registered his wares, I have to deal with but two. 
My business lies only with blue-eyed, pale-
faced William Braddlescroggs, and with John 
Simcox, the corresponding clerk. 
</p>
<p>
Simcox among his fellow clerks, Mr. Simcox 
among the porters, Jack Simcox among his 
intimates at the "Admiral Benbow" near 
Camberwell Gate, "you Simcox," with his 
growling chief. A grey-haired, smiling, red-
faced simpleton was Simcox; kind of heart, 
simple of mind, affectionate of disposition, 
confiding of nature, infirm of purpose, 
convivial of habits. He was fifty years in age, 
and fifteen in wisdom. He had been at the 
top of the ladder once--a rich man at least 
by paternal inheritance, with a carriage and 
horses and lands; but when he tumbled 
(which he did at five-and-twenty very quickly 
and right to the bottom), he never managed 
to rise again. The dupe of every shallow 
knave; the victim in every egregious scheme; 
an excellent arithmetician, yet quite unable 
to put two and two together in a business 
sense: he had never even had strength of 
character to be his own enemy; he had always 
found such a multiplicity of friends ready to 
do the inimical for him. If you let him alone 
he would do well enough. He would not lose 
his money till you cheated him out of it; he 
would not get drunk himself but would allow 
you to make him so, with the most charming 
willingness and equanimity. There are many 
Simcoxes in the world, and more rogues 
always ready to prey upon them; yet though 
I should like to hang the rogues, I should 
not like to see the breed of Simcox quite 
extinct. 
</p>
<p>
John Simcox had a salary of one hundred 
and twenty pounds a year. If I were writing 
fiction instead of sober (though veiled) truth, 
I should picture him to you as a victim with 
some two score of sovereigns per annum. No; 
he had a hundred and twenty of those yellow 
tokens annually, for the Beast never stinted 
in this respect either, which was again 
remarkable in such a Beast. One hundred and 
twenty golden sovereigns annually, had John 
Simcox; and they were of about as much 
use to him as one hundred and twenty penny 
pieces. When a man has a quarter's salary 
amounting to twenty-seven pounds, receivable 
next Thursday, and out of that has a score of 
three pounds due at the "Admiral Benbow," 
and has promised to (and will) lend ten pounds 
to a friend, and has borrowed five more of 
another friend himself, which he means to 
pay; and has, besides, his little rent to meet, 
and his little butcher and his little grocer and 
his little tailor, it is not very difficult to imagine 
how the man may be considerably embarrassed 
in satisfying all these demands out of the 
capital. But, when the administrator of the 
capital happens to be (as Simcox was) a man 
without the slightest command of himself or 
his money, you will have no difficulty in 
forming a conviction that the end of 
Simcox's quarter-days were worse then their 
commencement. 
</p>
<p>
Nor will you be surprised that "executions" 
in Simcox's lttle house in Carolina-terrace, 
Albany-road, Camberwell, were of frequent 
occurrence; that writs against him were 
always "out," and the brokers always "in." 
That he was as well known in the county 
court as the judge. That orders for payment 
were always coming due and never being 
paid. His creditors never arrested him, 
however. If they did so they knew he would 
lose his situation; so the poor man went on 
from week to week, and from month to 
month, borrowing here and borrowing there, 
obtaining small advances from loan societies 
held at public-houses, robbing Peter to pay 
Paul--always in a muddle, in short; but still 
smoking his nightly pipes, and drinking his 
nightly glasses, and singing his nightly songs; 
the latter with immense applause at the 
"Admiral Benbow." 
</p>
<p>
I don't think Simcox's worldly position 
was at all improved by his having married (in 
very early life, and direct from the finishing 
establishment of the Misses Gimp, at 
Hammersmith) a young lady highly accomplished 
in the useful and productive arts of tambour-
work and Poonah painting; but of all domestic 
or household duties considerably more 
ignorant than a Zooloo Kaffir. When Simcox 
had run through his money, an operation he 
performed with astonishing celerity, Mrs. Simcox, 
finding herself with three daughters of 
tender age and a ruined husband, took refuge 
in a flood of tears; subsequently met the 
crisis of misfortune with a nervous fever; 
and ultimately subsided into permanent ill 
health, curl papers, and shoes down at heel. 
</p>
<p>
When the events took place herein narrated, 
the three daughters of Mr. and Mrs. Simcox 
were all grown up. Madeline, aged twenty-
two, was a young lady of surprising altitude, 
with shoulders of great breadth and sharpness 
of outline, with very large black eyes and 
very large black ringlets, attributes of which 
she was consciously proud, but with a nose 
approaching to--what shall I say?--the snub. 
Chemists' assistants had addressed acrostics 
to her; and the young man at the circulating 
library was supposed to be madly in love 
with her. Helena, daughter number two, 
aged twenty, was also tall, had also black 
eyes, black ringlets, white resplendent shoulders, 
was the beloved of apothecaries, and 
the Laura of Petrarchs in the linen drapery-
line. These young ladies were both 
acknowledged, recognised, established as real 
beauties in the Camberwellian district. They 
dressed, somehow, in the brightest and most 
variegated colours; they had, somehow, the 
prettiest of bonnets, the tightest of gloves, 
the neatest of kid boots. Their sabbatical 
entrance to the parish church always created 
a sensation. The chemist's assistant kissed 
his hand as they passed; the young man at 
the circulating library laid down his book 
and sighed; passing young ladies envied and 
disparaged; passing young gentlemen 
admired and aspired; yet, somehow, Miss 
Madeline would be twenty-three next birthday, 
and Miss Helena twenty-one, and no 
swain had yet declared himself in explicit 
terms; no one had said "I have a hundred a 
year with a prospect of an advance: take it, 
my heart, and hand." Old Muggers, indeed, 
the tailor of Acacia Cottages, the friend, 
creditor, and boon companion of Simcox, 
had intimated, in his cups, at the "Admiral 
Benbow," his willingness to marry either of 
the young ladies; but his matrimonial proposals 
generally vanished with his inebriety; 
and he was besides known to be a dreadfully 
wicked old man, addicted to drinking, smoking, 
and snuff-taking. As a climax of villany, 
he was supposed to have two wives already, 
alive and resident in different parts of the 
provinces. 
</p>
<p>
And daughter number three--have I forgotten 
her? Not by any means. Was she a beauty? 
No. In the opinion of her sisters, Camberwell, 
and of the chemist's assistant, she was 
not a beauty. She had dark eyes; but they 
were neither brilliant nor piercing. She had 
dark hair; but wore it in no long or resplendent 
ringlets. She was an ordinary girl, "a plain 
little thing" (according to the Camberwell 
opinion); there was "nothing about her" in 
the eyes of the chemist's assistant. 
</p>
<p>
This young person, (Bessy by name), from 
the earliest periods of authentic record to the 
mature age of sixteen, had occupied, in the 
Simcox household, an analogous position to 
that of the celebrated Cinderella. She did not 
exactly sit in the chimney-corner among the 
ashes: but she lighted the fire, waited upon, 
dressed, and was otherwise the humble 
and willing drudge of her accomplished 
relatives. She did not exactly dress in rags; but 
she trotted about the house and neighbourhood 
in a shabby brown merino frock, which 
she had wofully outgrown, a lamentable old 
beaver bonnet, and a faded Paisley shawl, 
which held a sort of middle rank in appearance, 
between a duster and a pocket-
handkerchief well to do in the world. As a child, 
she was punished for the things she did not 
do, and doubly punished for those she did do. 
As a girl, she ran of errands, fetched the beer, 
lighted the fire (as I have said), read the 
sentimental novels to mamma as she lay upon 
the sofa, and accompanied her sisters on the 
piano-forte when they rehearsed those famous 
songs and duets with which they did terrific 
execution in the Camberwell circles. 
</p>
<p>
Honest Simcox, like a stupid, undiscerning, 
shiftless man as he was, did not entertain the 
domestic or Camberwell opinion concerning 
Bessy. He maintained that she had more 
sense in her little finger than her sisters put 
together (with his wife into the bargain, the 
honest fellow thought, I dare swear, though 
he did not dare to say so). He called her his 
little darling, his little Mentor, his willing, 
patient Betsy-petsy, with other foolish and weak-
minded expressions of 'endearment. What 
else could you expect of a red-nosed 
warehouseman's clerk who fuddled himself nightly 
at the "Admiral Benbow!" Profoundly 
submissive to his wife in most instances, he had 
frequently presumed, during Bessy's nonage, 
to differ from Mrs. Simcox as to the amount 
of whipping meted out to his youngest daughter 
for childish delinquencies, and had once 
even dared to interfere when his lady undertook 
to inflict that punishment for a fault the 
child had never committed, and to "stay 
justice in its mid career." So in process of time 
the alliance between the snubbed, neglected 
little girl and her father became of so close a 
nature as to be almost recognised and 
permitted by the rest of the family. Bessy was 
reckoned among the rest of the low company 
with whom the degraded Simcox chose to 
associate. She was allowed to pull off his muddy 
boots, to prepare his dinner, to fill his pipe 
and mix his grog when he muddled himself 
at home; and to lead him home, shambling, 
from the "Admiral Benbow," when he 
performed that operation abroad. Notably of 
late times she had been commissioned to fetch 
her papa home from Ursine Lane on the 
eventful quarter-day; and the meek, guiding 
help of Bessy had often saved that infirm old 
fellow from many a dark and dangerous pit-
fall. The child would wait patiently outside 
the doors of public-houses while her father 
boozed within: she would lead him away 
gently but firmly from his riotous companions, 
or, meeting them and taking them aside, would 
plead passionately, tearfully, that they would 
not make papa tipsy to-night. Some of the 
disreputable personages with whom she was 
brought into such strange contact were quite 
subdued and abashed by her earnest, artless 
looks and speech. Jack Flooks himself, 
formerly of the Stock Exchange, now principally 
of the bar of the "Bag o'Nails," the very worst, 
most dissipated and most reckless of Simcox's 
associates, forbore drinking with Bessy's 
father for one whole week, and actually 
returned, in a private and mysterious manner, 
to Bessy two half-crowns he had borrowed of 
him! So useful was this filial surveillance 
found to be by the other branches of his family 
that the quarter-day functions of our plain 
little Bessy were gradually extended, and 
became next of weekly and afterwards of diurnal 
occurrence. It was good to see this girl 
arrayed in the forlorn beaver bonnet and the 
faded Paisley shawl, with her mild, beaming, 
ordinary, little countenance, arrive at about a 
quarter to eight, at the Thames Street corner 
of Ursine Lane, and there wait patiently until 
her father's official duties were over. She 
became almost as well known in the neighbourhood 
as St. Nicholas Bearcroft, or as the 
famous sanctified pump itself. The fellowship 
porters from Sir John Pigg's wharf touched 
their caps to her; the majestic beadle of St. 
Nicholas (a cunning man, omnipotent over the 
fire escape, king of the keys of the engine 
house, and supposed to know where the fire-
plug was, much better than the turncock) 
spoke her kindly; all the clerks in 
Braddlescroggs's house knew her, nodded to her, 
smiled at her, and privately expressed their 
mutual opinions as to what a beast Braddlescroggs 
was, not to ask that dear little girl in, 
and let her rest herself, or sit by the fire in 
winter. The pot-boy of the "Bear and Ragged 
Staff," in his evening excursions with the 
supper beer, grew quite enamoured (in his 
silent, sheepish fashion) of this affectionate 
daughter, and would, I dare say, had he 
dared, have offered her refreshment from his 
beer-can; nay, even the majestic wealthy Mr. 
Drum, the wholesale grocer and provision 
merchant, who stood all day with his hands 
in his pockets, under his own gibbet-like crane, 
a very Jack Ketch of West India produce, had 
addressed cheering and benevolent words to 
her from the depths of his double chin; had 
conferred figs upon her; had pressed her to 
enter his saccharine smelling warehouse, and 
rest herself upon a barrel of prime navy mess 
beef 
</p>
<p>
When the Beast of Ursine Lane met Bessy 
Simcox, he either scowled at her, or made 
her sarcastic bows, and asked her at what 
pot-house her father was about to get drunk 
that night, and whether he had taught her to 
drink gin, too? Sometimes he growled forth 
his determination to have no "bits of girls" 
hanging about his "place:" sometimes he 
told her that she would not have to come 
many times more, for that he was determined 
on discharging that "drunken old dog," her 
papa. 
</p>
<p>
In the majority of instances, however, he 
passed her without any other notice than 
a scowl, and a savage rattle of the keys and 
silver in his pockets. The little maiden trembled 
fearfully when she saw him, and had 
quiet fits of weeping (in which a corner of the 
Paisley shawl was brought into frequent 
requisition) over against the pump, when he 
had spoken to her. There was a lad called 
William Braddlescroggs, with blue eyes and 
fair hair, who blushed very violently whenever 
he saw Bessy, and had once been bold enough 
to tell her that it was a fine evening. In this 
flagrant crime he was then and there detected 
by his father, who drove him back into the 
warehouse. 
</p>
<p>
"As this is quarter-day, my Bessy," was 
the remark of John Simcox to his daughter, 
one twenty-eighth of March, "as this is 
quarter-day, I think, my child, that I will take 
one glass of ale." 
</p>
<p>
It was about half-past eight, I think, and 
Bessy and her papa were traversing the 
large thoroughfare known as the New Kent 
Road. There is in that vicinity, as you are 
aware, that stunning Champagne Ale House, 
known as the "Leather Bottle." Into that 
stunning ale-house did John Simcox enter, 
leaving his little Bessy outside, with fifteen 
pounds, the balance of what he had already 
expended of his quarter's salary. The night 
was very lowering, and rain appeared to be 
imminent. It came down, presently, in big, 
pattering drops, but John had promised not 
to be long. 
</p>
<p>
Why should I tell, in extenso, the humiliating 
tale of how John Simcox got tipsy that 
night? How he forced all the money, pound 
by pound, from his little daughter? How, 
when after immense labour and trouble, he had 
at last been brought to his own street door, 
he suddenly started off at an unknown tangent 
(running hard and straight) and disappeared. 
How his daughter wandered about, weeping, 
in the pouring rain, seeking him; how, at two 
o'clock in the morning, a doleful party arrived 
at a little house in Camberwell--a very moist 
policeman, a weeping, shivering, drenched 
little girl over whom the municipal had in pity 
thrown his oilskin cape, and a penniless, 
hatless, drunken man, all covered with mud, 
utterly sodden, wretched, and degraded. 
Drop the curtain for pity's sake. 
</p>
<p>
The first impulse of Mrs. Simcox, after 
duly loading her besotted husband with 
reproaches, was to beat Bessy. The anger of 
this matron, generally so gently languid, was 
something fearful to view. An enraged sheep 
is frantic. She was frustrated however, in 
her benevolent intention, first by the policeman, 
afterwards by Bessy herself, who wet, 
fatigued, and miserable (but in an artful and 
designing manner, no doubt), first contrived 
to faint away, and next day chose to fall into 
a high fever. 
</p>
<p>
In this fever--In the access thereof--she 
lay three long weeks. In a lamentable state 
of languor she lay many long weeks more. 
The brokers were in again. The parlour carpet 
was taken up and sent to the pawnbroker's. 
There were no invalid comforts in the house; 
no broth, nor chickens to make it, no arrowroot, 
no sage, no port wine, no anything to 
speak of, that was really wanted. 
</p>
<p>
Stay, I am wrong. There was plenty of 
doctors; there was plenty of doctor's stuff. 
The chemists, apothecaries, and medical 
practitioners of the neighbourhood, treated 
the Simcox family, and the little sick daughter 
in particular, in a liberal and considerate 
manner. No one charged a penny, and all 
were unremitting in attention. Kind-hearted 
Mr. Sphoon, of Walworth, sent in--so to 
speak--a hamper of quinine. Young Tuckett, 
close by, who had just passed the Hall and 
College, and opened his shop, offered to do 
anything for Bessy. He would have dissected 
her, even, I am sure. Great Doctor Bibby 
came from Camberwell Grove, in his own 
carriage, with his own footman with the black 
worsted tags on his shoulder, and majestically 
ordered change of air, and red Port wine for 
Bessy Simcox. A majestic man was Dr. 
Bibby, and a portly, and a deep-voiced and a 
rich. His boots creaked, and his carriage-
springs oscillated; but he left a sovereign on 
the Simcox mantlepiece for all that. 
</p>
<p>
So there was something of those things 
needful in the little house at Camberwell. 
There was, besides, a certain nurse, active, 
devoted, patient, soothing, and gentle. Not 
Mrs. Simcox, who still lay on the sofa, now 
reading the sentimental novels, now moaning 
over the family difficulties. Not the Misses 
Simcox, who, though they did tend their 
sister, did it very fretfully and cross-grainedly, 
and unanimously declared that the child 
made herself out to be a great deal worse than 
she really was. This nurse had rather a red 
nose, and a tremulous hand. He came home 
earlier from the City now; but he never stopped 
at the stunning Champagne Ale House. 
He had not been to the "Admiral Benbow" 
for seven weeks. He sat by his daughter's 
pillow; he read to her; he carried her in his 
arms like a child as she was; he wept over 
the injury he had done her; he promised, 
and meant, and prayed for, amendment. 
</p>
<p>
But what were the attentions of the doctors, 
the hamper of quinine, the sovereign on the 
mantelpiece even, after all? They were but 
drops in the great muddled ocean of the Simcox 
embarrassments. A sovereign would not 
take Bessy to Malvern or Ventnor; the 
quinine would not give her red Port wine and 
change of air. The nurse grew desperate. 
There was no money to be borrowed, none 
to be obtained from the pawnbroker, none 
to be received until next quarter-day--
before which, another month must elapse. 
Should he attempt to obtain a small advance 
of money from the Beast himself--the terrible 
Braddlescroggs? Should he offer him two 
hundred per cent, interest; should he fall 
down on his knees before him; should he 
write him a supplicatory letter; should he? 
</p>
<p>
One evening, Simcox came home from the 
office with many smiles upon his face. He 
had borrowed the money, after many difficulties, 
from the chief clerk. Ten pounds. He 
would have to pay very heavy interest for it, 
but never mind. Mrs. Simcox should take 
Bessy to Ventnor for a fortnight or three 
weeks. Quarter-day would soon come round. 
Soon come round. Now and then his family 
remarked, that the many smiles dropped from 
their papa's countenance like a mask, and 
that, underneath, he wore a look rather 
haggard, rather weary, rather terrible; but then, 
you see, he would have to pay such a heavy 
interest for the ten pounds. Mrs. Simcox was 
delighted at the prospect of her country trip; 
poor Bessy smiled and thanked her papa; and 
the two Miss Simcoxes, who had their own 
private conviction that an excursion to the 
sea-side was the very thing for them, to air 
their beauty as it were, and not for that 
designing bit of a thing, Bessy, with her pale 
face; the two Miss Simcoxes, I say, went to 
bed in a huff. 
</p>
<p>
To the pleasant Island of Wight in the 
British Channel, and the county of 
Hampshire, did the little convalescent from Camberwell 
and her parent proceed. Bessy gathered 
shells and sea weed, and bought sand pictures 
on cardboard by the Undercliff, and sand in 
bottles, and saw the donkey at Carisbroke 
Castle, and wondered at Little St. Lawrence 
Church, and the magnificent yachting dandies 
at Cowes and Ryde, until her pale face grew 
quite rosy, and her dark eyes had something 
of a sparkle in them. Her mamma lay on the 
sofa as usual, exhausted the stock of 
sentimental novels in the Ventnor circulating 
library, varying these home occupations 
occasionally by taking exercise in a wheel-chair, 
and "nagging" at Bessy. The pair came 
back to London together, and were at the 
little mansion at Camberwell about a week 
before quarter-day. The peccant Simcox had 
been exemplarily abstemious during their 
absence; but his daughters had not been able 
to avoid remarking that he was silent, 
reserved, and anxious looking. You see he had 
to pay such heavy interest for the ten pounds 
he had borrowed of the chief clerk. 
</p>
<p>
Three days before quarter-day, it was ten 
minutes to eight P. M., and Bessy Simcox was 
waiting for her father. She was confident, 
hopeful, cheerful now; she thanked God for 
her illness and the change it had wrought in 
her dear papa. Ten minutes to eight, and a 
hot summer's evening. She was watching the 
lamp-lighter going round with his ladder and 
his little glimmering lantern, when she was 
accosted by one of Mr. Braddlescroggs's 
porters. He was an ugly, forbidding man, with 
a vicious-looking fur cap (such as porters of 
workhouses and wicked skippers of colliers 
wear), and had never before saluted or spoken 
to her. She began to tremble violently when 
John Malingerer (a special favourite of the 
Beast's, if he could have favoured any one, 
and supposed to be a porter after his own 
heart), addressed her. 
</p>
<p>
"Hi!" said the porter, "you're wanted." 
</p>
<p>
"Me--wanted? Where? By whom?" 
stammered Bessy. 
</p>
<p>
Bessy followed him, still trembling. The 
porter walked before her, looming like the 
genius of Misfortune. He led her through 
dingy wareroom after wareroom, counting 
house after counting house, where the clerks 
all were silent and subdued. He led her at 
last into a dingy sanctum, dimly lighted by 
one shaded lamp. In this safe there were 
piles of dingy papers and more dingy ledgers; 
with great piles of accounts on hooks in 
the wall, with their long iron necks and 
white bodies, like ghosts of dead bills who 
had hanged themselves; a huge iron safe 
throwing hideous shadows against the wall, 
and three silent men. 
</p>
<p>
That is to say: 
</p>
<p>
John Simcox, white, trembling, and with 
wild eyes. 
</p>
<p>
The Beast, neither more nor less a Beast 
than he usually was. 
</p>
<p>
A tall man with a very sharp shirt collar, 
great coat, a black stock; very thin iron 
grey hair; a face which looked as if it had 
once been full of wrinkles and furrows 
which had been half ironed out; very peculiar 
and very heavy boots, brown Berlin 
gloves, and a demeanour which confirmed 
you immediately in a conviction that were 
you to strike at him violently with a sledge 
hammer, his frame would give forth in 
response no fleshy "thud," but a hard metallic 
ring. 
</p>
<p>
The Beast was standing up: his back 
against a tall desk on spectral legs, his hands 
in his pockets. So also, standing, in a corner, 
was Simcox. So also, not exactly 
anywhere but somewhere, somehow, and about 
Simcox, and about Bessy, and particularly 
about the door and the iron safe, in which 
he seemed to take absorbing interest, was 
the tall man in the peculiar boots. 
</p>
<p>
"Come here, my girl," said the grating 
voice of Barnard Braddlescroggs the Beast. 
</p>
<p>
My girl came there, to the foot of a table, 
as she was desired. She heard the grating 
voice; she heard, much louder, the beating 
of her own heart; she heard, loudest of all, 
a dreadful voice crying within her, crying 
over and over again that papa had borrowed 
ten pounds, and that he would have to pay 
very heavy interest for it, and that quarter 
day would soon come round, soon come 
round. 
</p>
<p>
"This person's name is Lurcher," pursued 
the Beast. 
</p>
<p>
The person coughed. The cough struck 
on the girl's heart like a knell. One. 
</p>
<p>
"He is an officer." 
</p>
<p>
An officer of what? Of the Household 
Brigade; of the yeomanry cavalry; of the 
Sheriff of Middlesex's batallion, a custom-
house officer, a naval officer, a relieving 
officer? But Bessy knew in a moment. 
She might have known it at first from the 
peculiar boots the officer wore--boots as no 
other officer, or man, or woman can wear. 
But her own heart told her. It said plainly: 
"This is a police officer, and he has come to 
take your father into custody." 
</p>
<p>
It was all told directly. Oh Bessy, Bessy! 
The ten pounds borrowed from the chief 
clerk, for which he would have to pay such 
heavy interest. The ten pounds were 
borrowed from the Petty Cash. The miserable 
Simcox's account was fifteen pounds 
deficient; he had promised to refund the money 
on quarter-day; he had begged and prayed 
for time; the Beast was inexorable, and 
Lurcher, the officer, was there to take him 
to prison for embezzlement. 
</p>
<p>
"You daughter of this man," said the 
Beast, "you must go home without him. 
You tell his wife and the rest of his people, 
that I have locked him up, and that I'll 
transport him, for robbery." 
</p>
<p>
"Robbery, no, sir," cried poor Simcox from 
the corner. "Before God, no! It was only 
for--"
</p>
<p>
"Silence!" said the Beast. "I'll prosecute 
you, I'll transport you, I'll hang you. By 
G--, I'll reform you, somehow." "Girl," he 
continued, turning to Bessy. "Go home. 
Stop! I'll send a clerk with you to see if there 
are any of my goods at home. I dare say 
there are, and you'll move 'em to-night. You 
won't though. I'll have a search-warrant. 
I'll put you all in gaol. I'll transport you all. 
Come here, one of you fellows in the office" 
(this with a roar) "and go with this girl 
to Camberwell. Lurcher, take the rascal 
away." 
</p>
<p>
What was poor Bessy to do? What could 
she do but fall down on her knees, clasping 
those stern knees before her? What could 
she do, but amid sobs and broken articulation 
say that it was all her fault? That it was for 
her, her dear papa had taken the money. 
That for her use it had been spent. What 
could she do but implore the Beast, for the 
love of heaven, for the love of his own son, 
for the love of his dead father and mother, to 
spare the object of his wrath, to send her to 
prison, to take all they had, to show them 
mercy, as he hoped mercy to be shown to him 
hereafter. 
</p>
<p>
She did all this and more. It was good, 
though pitiful, to see the child on her knees 
in her mean dress, with her streammg eyes, 
and her poor hair all hanging about her eyes, 
and to hear her artless, yet passionate 
supplications. The Beast moved not muscle nor 
face; but it is upon record that Mr. Lurcher, 
after creaking about on the peculiar boots for 
some seconds, turned aside into the shadow of 
the iron safe, and blew his nose. 
</p>
<p>
"Lurcher," observed the Beast, "Wait a 
moment before I give this man into your 
charge." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Lurcher bent some portion of his body 
between his occiput and his spine, and, 
considering himself temporarily relieved from the 
custody of his prisoner, threw the whole force 
of his contemplative energies into the iron 
safe, in which, as a subject, he appeared 
immediately to bury himself. 
</p>
<p>
"Come here!" was the monosyllabic 
command of the Beast; addressed both to father 
and daughter. He led them into yet an inner 
sanctum, a sort of cupboard, full of books 
and papers, where there was a dreadful screw 
copying press, like an instrument of torture 
in the Inquisition. 
</p>
<p>
"I will spare your father, child, and retain 
him in his situation," continued the Beast, 
without ever taking his hands out, of his 
pockets, or altering an inflection of his voice, 
"on these, and these conditions only. My 
housekeeper is old and blind, and I shall soon 
turn her adrift, and let her go to the 
workhouse--everybody says so, I believe. The 
short time she will remain, she will be able to 
instruct you in as much as I shall require 
of you. You will have to keep this house for 
me and my clerks, and you must never quit 
it save once in six weeks, for six hours at a 
time; and I expect you to adhere to this 
engagement for two years. All communication 
between you and your family, save during 
your hours of liberty, I strictly prohibit. 
You will have twenty pounds a year as wages, 
half of which can go to augment your father's 
salary. At the same time I shall require 
from him a written acknowledgement that he 
has embezzled my moneys; and if you quit 
my service I shall use it against him, ruin him, 
and imprison him. Make up your mind 
quickly, for the policeman is waiting. 
</p>
<p>
What was poor Bessy to do? To part 
from her dear father, never to see him save at 
intervals, and then only for a short time; to 
know that he was in the same house, and not 
be able to run and embrace him. All this was 
hard, very hard, but what would not Bessy do 
to save her father from ruin and disgrace and 
a prison? She would have laid down her 
life for him, she would have cheerfully 
consented never to see him again--till the great 
day comes when we shall all meet to part no 
more. She consented; Mr. Lurcher was 
previously spoken to and dismissed; the 
Beast subsided into his usual taciturnity; 
Bessy led her stricken, broken, trembling 
parent home. They passed through the long, 
dingy warerooms, the clerks whispering as 
they passed. 
</p>
<p>
Bessy's wardrobe was not sufficiently 
voluminous to occasion the expenditure of any 
very great time in packing. It was soon put 
up in a very small, shabby black box, studded 
with brass nails--many of them deficient. 
This, with Bessy herself, arrived at nine 
o'clock the next morning, as per agreement, 
at the Cheapside corner of Ursine Lane, where 
one of Mr. Braddlescroggs's porters was in 
waiting, who brought Bessy and her box to 
the dismal Manchester warehouse owned by 
the Beast of Ursine Lane. 
</p>
<p>
And here, in the top floor of this lugubrious 
mansion, lived, for two long years, Bessy 
Simcox. At stated periods she saw her family 
for a few hours, and then went back to her 
prison house. She carved the beef and mutton 
for the hungry clerks, she mended their 
linen, she gave out candles, she calculated 
washing bills. The old, old story of Beauty 
and the Beast was being done over again in 
Ursine Lane, Cheapside. Bessy ripened into 
a Beauty, in this dismal hot-house; and the 
Beast was, as I have told you he always was. 
Beauty dwelt in no fairy palace; surrounded 
by no rose bushes, no sweet-smelling gardens, 
no invisible hands to wait on her at supper. 
It was all hard, stern, uncompromising 
reality. She had to deal with an imperious, 
sullen, brutal master. Every body knew it. 
She dealt with him as Bessy had the art of 
dealing with every one. She bore with him 
meekly, gently, patiently. She strove to win 
his forbearance, his respect. She won them 
both, and more--his love. 
</p>
<p>
Yes, his love! Don't be afraid; the Beast 
never changed to Prince Azor. He never lay 
among the rose-bushes sick to death, and 
threatening to die unless Beauty married 
him. But at the end of the two years, when 
their contract was at an end, and when its 
fulfilment had given him time to know Bessy 
well, and to save the father through the child, 
he besought Bessy to remain with him in the 
same capacity, offering her munificent terms 
and any degree of liberty she required as 
regarded communication with her family. 
Bessy stayed. She stayed two years; she 
stayed three; she stays there now, to 
witness, if I lie. 
</p>
<p>
Not alone, however. It occurred to William 
B., junior--the lad with the blue eyes and 
fair hair--to grow up to be a tall young man, 
and to fall violently in love with the pretty 
little housekeeper. It occurred to his father, 
instead of smiting him on the hip immediately, 
or eating him up alive in wild beast fashion, 
to tell him he was a very sensible fellow, and 
to incite Bessy (we must call her Beauty 
now) to encourage his addresses, which 
indeed, dear little puss! she was nothing loth 
to do. So Beauty was married. Not to the 
Beast, but to the Beast's son; and Beauty 
and William and the Beast all removed to a 
pretty house in the prettiest country near 
London, where they live to this day, again to 
witness if I lie. 
</p>
<p>
The Beast is a Beast no longer. Everybody 
admits that he is not a Beast now; 
some few are even doubtful whether he ever 
was a Beast. He carries on the Ursine Lane 
business (in partnership with his son) still, 
and is a very rough-headed and rough-voiced 
old man. But the rough kernel and rough 
integument are worn away from his heart, 
and he is genial and jovial among his 
dependants. Charitable in secret, he had always 
been, even in his most brutish times; and 
you are not to believe (for Braddlescroggs 
talked nonsense sometimes and he knew it) 
that the old housekeeper, when she became 
blind or bedridden, was sent adrift or to the 
workhouse; that old John Simcox was not 
allowed sufficient funds for his pipe and his 
glass (in strict moderation) at the Admiral 
Benbow; or that the two Misses Simcox, 
when they married at last (after superhuman 
exertions,) went dowerless. No. The Beast 
remembered, and was generous to them all. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE ANGEL'S STORY.</title>
<poem>
<poem1>Through the blue and frosty heavens,</poem1>
<poem2>Christmas stars were shining bright;</poem2>
<poem1>The glistening lamps of the great City</poem1>
<poem2>Almost matched their gleaming light;</poem2>
<poem1>And the winter snow was lying,</poem1>
<poem2>And the winter winds were sighing.</poem2>
<poem1>Long ago one Christmas night.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>While from every tower and steeple.</poem1>
<poem2>Pealing bells were sounding clear,</poem2>
<poem1>(Never with such tones of gladness,</poem1>
<poem2>Save when Christmas time is near)</poem2>
<poem1>Many a one that night was merry,</poem1>
<poem2>Who had toiled through all the year.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>That night saw old wrongs forgiven,</poem1>
<poem2>Friends, long parted, reconcile;</poem2>
<poem1>Voices, all unused to laughter,</poem1>
<poem2>Eyes that had forgot to smile.</poem2>
<poem1>Anxious hearts that feared the morrow,</poem1>
<poem2>Freed from all their cares awhile.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Rich and poor felt the same blessing</poem1>
<poem2>From the gracious season fall;</poem2>
<poem1>Joy and plenty in the cottage,</poem1>
<poem2>Peace and feasting in the hall:</poem2>
<poem1>And the voices of the children</poem1>
<poem2>Ringing clear above it all!</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Yet one house was dim and darkened;</poem1>
<poem2>Gloom, and sickness, and despair</poem2>
<poem1>Abiding in the gilded chamber,</poem1>
<poem2>Climbing up the marble stair.</poem2>
<poem1>Stilling even the voice of mourning--</poem1>
<poem2>For a child lay dying there.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Silken curtains fell around him.</poem1>
<poem2>Velvet carpets hushed the tread,</poem2>
<poem1>Many costly toys were lying,</poem1>
<poem2>All unheeded, by his bed;</poem2>
<poem1>And his tangled golden ringlets</poem1>
<poem2>Were on downy pillows spread.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>All the skill of the great City</poem1>
<poem2>To save that little life was vain;</poem2>
<poem1>That little thread from being broken:</poem1>
<poem1>That fatal word from being spoken;</poem1>
<poem2>Nay, his very mother's pain,</poem2>
<poem1>And the mighty love within her,</poem1>
<poem2>Could not give him health again.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And she knelt there still beside him,</poem1>
<poem2>She alone with strength to smile,</poem2>
<poem1>And to promise he should suffer</poem1>
<poem2>No more in a little while,</poem2>
<poem1>And with murmur'd song and story</poem1>
<poem2>The long weary hours beguile.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Suddenly an unseen Presence</poem1>
<poem2>Checked these constant mourning cries,</poem2>
<poem1>Stilled the little heart's quick fluttering,</poem1>
<poem2>Raised the blue and wondering eyes.</poem2>
<poem1>Fixed on some mysterious vision,</poem1>
<poem2>With a startled sweet surprise.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>For a radiant angel hovered</poem1>
<poem2>Smiling o'er the little bed;</poem2>
<poem1>White his raiment, from his shoulders</poem1>
<poem2>Snowy dove-like pinions spread,</poem2>
<poem1>And a starlike light was shining</poem1>
<poem2>In a Glory round his head.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>While, with tender love, the angel,</poem1>
<poem2>Leaning o'er the little nest,</poem2>
<poem1>In his arms the sick child folding,</poem1>
<poem2>Laid him gently on his breast.</poem2>
<poem1>Sobs and wailings from the mother,</poem1>
<poem2>And her darling was at rest.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>So the angel, slowly rising.</poem1>
<poem2>Spread his wings; and, through the air,</poem2>
<poem1>Bore the pretty child, and held him</poem1>
<poem2>On his heart with loving care,</poem2>
<poem1>A red branch of blooming roses</poem1>
<poem2>Placing softly by him there.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>While the child thus clinging, floated</poem1>
<poem2>Towards the mansions of the Blest,</poem2>
<poem1>Gazing from his shining guardian</poem1>
<poem2>To the flowers upon his breast,</poem2>
<poem1>Thus the angel spake, still smiling</poem1>
<poem2>On the little heavenly guest:</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Know, O little one! that heaven</poem1>
<poem2>Does no earthly thing disdain.</poem2>
<poem1>Man's poor joys find there an echo</poem1>
<poem2>Just as surely as his pain;</poem2>
<poem1>Love, on earth so feebly striving,</poem1>
<poem2>Lives divine in Heaven again!</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Once in yonder town below us</poem1>
<poem2>In a poor and narrow street,</poem2>
<poem1>Dwelt a little sickly orphan,</poem1>
<poem2>Gentle aid, or pity sweet,</poem2>
<poem1>Never in life's ragged pathway</poem1>
<poem2>Guided his poor tottering feet.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"All the striving anxious forethought</poem1>
<poem2>That should only come with age,</poem2>
<poem1>Weighed upon his baby spirit,</poem1>
<poem2>Showed him soon life's sternest page;</poem2>
<poem1>Grim Want was his nurse, and Sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>Was his only heritage!</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"All too weak for childish pastimes</poem1>
<poem2>Drearily the hours spend;</poem2>
<poem1>On his hands so small and trembling</poem1>
<poem2>Leaning his poor aching head.</poem2>
<poem1>Or, through dark and painful hours,</poem1>
<poem2>Lying sleepless on no bed.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Dreaming strange and longing fancies</poem1>
<poem2>Of cool forests far away;</poem2>
<poem1>Dreams of rosy happy children,</poem1>
<poem2>Laughing merrily at play;</poem2>
<poem1>Coming home through green lanes, bearing</poem1>
<poem2>Trailing branches of white May.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Scarce a glimpse of the blue heavens</poem1>
<poem2>Gleamed above the narrow street,</poem2>
<poem1>And the sultry air of Summer</poem1>
<poem2>(That you called so warm and sweet,)</poem2>
<poem1>Fevered the poor Orphan, dwelling</poem1>
<poem2>In the crowded alley's heat.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"One bright day, with feeble footsteps</poem1>
<poem2>Slowly forth he dared to crawl.</poem2>
<poem1>Through the crowded city's pathways,</poem1>
<poem2>Till he reached a garden-wall;</poem2>
<poem1>Where 'mid princely halls and mansions</poem1>
<poem2>Stood the lordliest of all.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"There were trees with giant branches</poem1>
<poem2>Velvet glades where shadows hide;</poem2>
<poem1>There were sparkling fountains glancing,</poem1>
<poem2>Flowers whose rich luxuriant pride</poem2>
<poem1>Wafted a breath of precious perfume</poem1>
<poem2>To the child who stood outside.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"He against the gate of iron</poem1>
<poem2>Pressed his wan and wistful face,</poem2>
<poem1>Gazing with an awe struck pleasure</poem1>
<poem2>At the glories of the place;</poem2>
<poem1>Never had his fairest day-dream</poem1>
<poem2>Shone with half such wondrous grace.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"You were playing in that garden,</poem1>
<poem2>Throwing blossoms in the air,</poem2>
<poem1>And laughing when the petals floated</poem1>
<poem2>Downward on your golden hair:</poem2>
<poem1>And the fond eyes watching o'er you.</poem1>
<poem1>And the splendour spread before you</poem1>
<poem2>Told, a House's Hope was there.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"When your servants, tired of seeing</poem1>
<poem2>His pale face of want and woe,</poem2>
<poem1>Turning to the ragged Orphan,</poem1>
<poem2>Gave him coin, and bade him go.</poem2>
<poem1>Down his cheeks so thin and wasted,</poem1>
<poem2>Bitter tears began to flow.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"But that look of childish sorrow</poem1>
<poem2>On your tender young heart fell,</poem2>
<poem1>And you plucked the reddest roses</poem1>
<poem2>From the tree you loved so well.</poem2>
<poem1>Passing them through the stern grating,</poem1>
<poem2>With the gentle word, 'Farewell!'</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Dazzled by the fragrant treasure</poem1>
<poem2>And the gentle voice he heard,</poem2>
<poem1>In the poor forlorn boy's spirit,</poem1>
<poem2>Joy the sleeping Seraph stirred;</poem2>
<poem1>In his hand he clasped the flowers.</poem1>
<poem2>In his heart the loving word.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"So he crept to his poor garret,</poem1>
<poem2>Poor no more, but rich and bright;</poem2>
<poem1>For the holy dreams of childhood--</poem1>
<poem2>Love, and Rest, and Hope, and Light--</poem2>
<poem1>Floated round the Orphan's pillow</poem1>
<poem2>Through the starry summer night.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Day dawned, yet the vision lasted;</poem1>
<poem2>All too weak to rise he lay;</poem2>
<poem1>Did he dream that none spoke harshly--</poem1>
<poem2>All were strangely kind that day?</poem2>
<poem1>Yes; he thought his treasured roses</poem1>
<poem2>Must have charmed all ills away.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"And he smiled, though they were fading;</poem1>
<poem2>One by one their leaves were shed;</poem2>
<poem1>'Such bright things could never perish,</poem1>
<poem2>They would bloom again,' he said.</poem2>
<poem1>When the next day's sun had risen,</poem1>
<poem2>Child and flowers both were dead.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Know, dear little one! our Father</poem1>
<poem2>Does no gentle deed disdain;</poem2>
<poem1>And in hearts that beat in heaven.</poem1>
<poem2>Still all tender thoughts remain;</poem2>
<poem1>Love on the cold earth remaining</poem1>
<poem2>Lives divine and pure again!"</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Thus the angel ceased, and gently</poem1>
<poem2>O'er his little burthen leant;</poem2>
<poem1>While the child gazed from the shining</poem1>
<poem2>Loving eyes that o'er him bent.</poem2>
<poem1>To the blooming roses by him,</poem1>
<poem2>Wondering what that mystery meant.</poem2>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then the radiant angel answered,</poem1>
<poem2>And with holy meaning smiled:</poem2>
<poem1>"Ere your tender, loving spirit</poem1>
<poem2>Sin and the hard world defiled,</poem2>
<poem1>Mercy gave me leave to seek you;</poem1>
<poem2>I was once that little child!"</poem2>
</poem>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE SQUIRE'S STORY.</title>
<p>
In the year seventeen hundred and sixty-
nine, the little town of Barford was thrown 
into a state of great excitement by the 
intelligence that a gentleman (and "quite the 
gentleman," said the landlord of the George 
Inn), had been looking at Mr. Clavering's old 
house. This house was neither in the town 
nor in the country. It stood on the outskirts 
of Barford, on the road-side leading to Derby. 
The last occupant had been a Mr. Clavering--
a Northumberland gentleman of good family--
who had come to live in Barford when he 
was but a younger son; but when some elder 
branches of the family died, he had returned 
to take possession of the family estate. The 
house of which I speak was called the White 
House, from its being covered with a greyish 
kind of stucco. It had a good garden to the 
back, and Mr. Clavering had built capital 
stables, with what were then considered the 
latest improvements. The point of good 
stabling was expected to let the house, as it 
was in a hunting county; otherwise it had 
few recommendations. There were many 
bed-rooms; some entered through others, 
even to the number of five, leading one 
beyond the other; several sitting-rooms of the 
small and poky kind, wainscotted round with 
wood, and then painted a heavy slate colour; 
one good dining-room, and a drawing-room 
over it, both looking into the garden, with 
pleasant bow-windows. 
</p>
<p>
Such was the accommodation offered by 
the White House. It did not seem to be 
very tempting to strangers, though the good 
people of Barford rather piqued themselves 
on it, as the largest house in the town; and 
as a house in which "townspeople" and 
"county people" had often met at Mr. 
Clavering's friendly dinners. To appreciate 
this circumstance of pleasant recollection, you 
should have lived some years in a little country 
town, surrounded by gentlemen's seats. 
You would then understand how a bow or a 
courtesy from a member of a county family 
elevates the individuals who receive it almost 
as much, in their own eyes, as the pair of 
blue garters fringed with silver did Mr. 
Bickerstaff's ward. They trip lightly on air for a 
whole day afterwards. Now Mr. Clavering 
was gone, where could town and county 
mingle? 
</p>
<p>
I mention these things that you may have 
an idea of the desirability of the letting of 
the White House in the Barfordites' imagination; 
and to make the mixture thick and 
slab, you must add for yourselves the bustle, 
the mystery, and the importance which every 
little event either causes or assumes in a 
small town; and then, perhaps, it will be no 
wonder to you that twenty ragged little 
urchins accompanied "the gentleman" aforesaid 
to the door of the White House; and 
that, although he was above an hour inspecting 
it under the auspices of Mr. Jones, the 
agent's clerk, thirty more had joined 
themselves on to the wondering crowd before his 
exit, and awaited such crumbs of intelligence 
as they could gather before they were threatened 
or whipped out of hearing distance. 
Presently out came "the gentleman" and the 
lawyer's clerk. The latter was speaking as 
he followed the former over the threshold. 
The gentleman was tall, well-dressed, handsome; 
but there was a sinister, cold look in 
his quick-glancing, light blue eye, which a 
keen observer might not have liked. There 
were no keen observers among the boys, 
and ill-conditioned gaping girls. But they 
stood too near; inconveniently close; and 
the gentleman, lifting up his right hand, in 
which he carried a short riding whip, dealt 
one or two sharp blows to the nearest, with 
a look of savage enjoyment on his face as they 
moved away whimpering and crying. An 
instant after, his expression of countenance had 
changed. 
</p>
<p>
"Here!" said he, drawing out a handful of 
money, partly silver, partly copper, and throwing 
it into the midst of them. "Scramble 
for it! fight it out, my lads! come this afternoon, 
at three, to the George, and I'll throw 
you out some more." So the boys hurrahed 
for him as he walked off with the agent's clerk. 
He chuckled to himself, as over a pleasant 
thought. "I'll have some fun with those 
lads," he said; "I'll teach 'em to come prowling 
and prying about me. I'll tell you what 
I'll do. I'll make the money so hot in the 
fire-shovel that it shall burn their fingers. 
You come and see the faces and the howling. 
I shall be very glad if you will 
dine with me at two; and by that time I 
may have made up my mind about the 
house."
</p>
<p>
Mr. Jones, the agent's clerk, agreed to come 
to the George at two, but, somehow, he had 
a distaste for his entertainer. Mr. Jones would 
not like to have said, even to himself, that a 
man with a purse full of money, who kept 
many horses, and spoke familiarly of noblemen--
above all, who thought of taking the 
White House--could be anything but a gentleman; 
but still the uneasy wonder as to who 
this Mr. Robinson Higgins could be, filled the 
clerk's mind long after Mr. Higgins, Mr. 
Higgins's servants, and Mr. Higgins's stud, had 
taken possession of the White House. 
</p>
<p>
The White House was re-stuccoed (this 
time of a pale yellow colour), and put into 
thorough repair by the accommodating and 
delighted landlord; while his tenant seemed 
inclined to spend any amount of money on 
internal decorations, which were showy and 
effective in their character, enough to make 
the White House a nine days' wonder to the 
good people of Barford. The slate-coloured 
paints became pink, and were picked out 
gold; the old fashioned bannisters were 
replaced by newly gilt ones; but above all, the 
stables were a sight to be seen. Since the 
days of the Roman Emperor never was there 
such provision made for the care, the comfort, 
and the health of horses. But every one 
said it was no wonder, when they were led 
through Barford, covered up to their eyes, 
but curving their arched and delicate necks, 
and prancing with short high steps, in 
repressed eagerness. Only one groom came 
with them; yet they required the care of 
three men. Mr. Higgins, however, preferred 
engaging two lads out of Barford; and 
Barford highly approved of his preference. Not 
only was it kind and thoughtful to give 
employment to the lounging lads themselves, 
but they were receiving such a training in 
Mr. Higgins' stables as might fit them for 
Doncaster or Newmarket. The district of 
Derbyshire in which Barford was situated, 
was too close to Leicestersire not to support 
a hunt and a pack of hounds. The master 
of the hounds was a certain Sir Harry 
Manley, who was <em>aut</em> a huntsman <em>aut nullus</em>. 
He measured a man by "the length of his 
fork," not by the expression of his countenance, 
or the shape of his head. But as Sir 
Harry was wont to observe, there was such 
a thing as too long a fork, so his approbation 
was withheld until he had seen a man on 
horseback; and if his seat there was square 
and easy, his hand light, and his courage 
good, Sir Harry hailed him as a brother. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Higgins attended the first meet of the 
season, not as a subscriber but as an amateur. 
The Barford huntsmen piqued themselves on 
their bold riding; and their knowledge of 
the country came by nature; yet this new 
strange man, whom nobody knew, was in at 
the death sitting on his horse, both well 
breathed and calm, without a hair turned on 
the sleek skin of the latter, supremely 
addressing the old huntsman as he hacked off 
the tail of the fox; and he, the old man, who 
was testy even under Sir Harry's slightest 
rebuke, and flew out on any member of the 
hunt that dared to utter a word against his 
sixty years' experience as stable-boy, groom, 
poacher, and what not; he, old Isaac Wormeley, 
was meekly listening to the wisdom of 
this stranger, only now and then giving one 
of his quick, up-turning, cunning glances, 
not unlike the sharp o'er-canny looks of the 
poor deceased Reynard, round whom the 
hounds were howling, unadmonished by the 
short whip, which was now tucked into 
Wormeley's well-worn pocket. When Sir 
Harry rode into the copse--full of dead 
brushwood and wet tangled grass--and was 
followed by the members of the hunt, as 
one by one they cantered past, Mr. Higgins 
took off his cap and bowed--half deferentially, 
half insolently--with a lurking smile in the 
corner of his eye at the discomfited looks 
of one or two of the laggards. "A famous 
run, sir," said Sir Harry. "The first time 
you have hunted in our country, but I hope 
we shall see you often." 
</p>
<p>
"I hope to become a member of the hunt, 
sir," said Mr. Higgins. 
</p>
<p>
"Most happy--proud, I'm sure, to receive 
so daring a rider among us. You took the 
Cropper-Gate, I fancy; while some of our 
friends here"--scowling at one or two 
cowards by the way of finishing his speech. 
"Allow me to introduce myself--master of 
the hounds" he fumbled in his waistcoat 
pocket for the card on which his name was 
formally inscribed. "Some of our friends 
here are kind enough to come home with 
me to dinner; might I ask for the honour?" 
</p>
<p>
"My name is Higgins," replied the stranger, 
bowing low. "I am only lately come 
to occupy the White House at Barford, and 
I have not as yet presented my letters of 
introduction." 
</p>
<p>
"Hang it!" replied Sir Harry; "a man 
with a seat like yours, and that good brush 
in your hand, might ride up to any door in 
the county (I am a Leicestershire man!), and 
be a welcome guest. Mr. Higgins, I shall 
be proud to become better acquainted with 
you over my dinner table." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Higgins knew pretty well how to 
improve the acquaintance thus begun. He 
could sing a good song, tell a good story, 
and was well up in practical jokes; with 
plenty of that keen worldly sense, which 
seems like an instinct in some men, and 
which in this case taught him on whom he 
might play off such jokes with impunity 
from their resentment, and with a security 
of applause from the more boisterous, 
vehement, or prosperous. At the end of 
twelve months Mr. Robinson Higgins was, 
out-and-out, the most popular member of 
Barford hunt; had beaten all the others by 
a couple of lengths, as his first patron, Sir 
Harry, observed one evening, when they 
were just leaving the dinner-table of an old 
hunting squire in the neighbourhood. 
</p>
<p>
"Because, you know," said Squire Hearn, 
holding Sir Harry by the button--"I mean, 
you see, this young spark is looking sweet 
upon Catherine; and she's a good girl, and 
will have ten thousand pounds down the day 
she's married, by her mother's will; and--
excuse me, Sir Harry--but I should not like 
my girl to throw herself away." 
</p>
<p>
Though Sir Harry had a long ride before 
him, and but the early and short light of a 
new moon to take it in, his kind heart was 
so much touched by Squire Hearn's 
trembling, tearful anxiety, that he stopped, and 
turned back into the dining-room to say, 
with more asseverations than I care to give: 
</p>
<p>
"My good Squire, I may say, I know that 
man pretty well by this time; and a better 
fellow never existed. If I had twenty 
daughters, he should have the pick of them." 
</p>
<p>
Squire Hearn never thought of asking the 
grounds for his old friend's opinion of Mr. 
Higgins; it had been given with too much 
earnestness for any doubts to cross the old 
man's mind as to the possibility of its not 
being well founded. Mr. Hearn was not a 
doubter or a thinker, or suspicious by nature; 
it was simply his love for Catherine, his only 
child, that prompted his anxiety in this case; 
and after what Sir Harry had said, the old 
man could totter with an easy mind, though 
not with very steady legs, into the drawing-
room, where his bonny blushing daughter 
Catherine and Mr. Higgins stood close 
together on the hearth-rug--he whispering, 
she listening with downcast eyes. She 
looked so happy, so like her dead mother had 
looked when the Squire was a young man, 
that all his thought was how to please her 
most. His son and heir was about to be 
married, and bring his wife to live with the 
Squire; Barford and the White House were 
not distant an hour's ride; and, even as these 
thoughts passed through his mind, he asked 
Mr. Higgins if he could not stay all night--
the young moon was already set--the roads 
would be dark--and Catherine looked up 
with a pretty anxiety, which, however, had 
not much doubt in it, for the answer. 
</p>
<p>
With every encouragement of this kind 
from the old Squire, it took everybody rather 
by surprise when one morning it was discovered 
that Miss Catherine Hearn was missing; 
and when, according to the usual fashion in 
such cases, a note was found, saying that she 
had eloped with "the man of her heart," and 
gone to Gretna Green, no one could imagine 
why she could not quietly have stopped at 
home and been married in the parish church. 
She had always been a romantic, sentimental 
girl; very pretty, and very affectionate, 
and very much spoiled, and very much wanting 
in common sense. Her indulgent father 
was deeply hurt at this want of confidence 
in his never-varying affection; but when his 
son came, hot with indignation from the 
Baronet's (his future father-in-law's house, 
where every form of law and ceremony was 
to accompany his own impending marriage,) 
Squire Hearn pleaded the cause of the young 
couple with imploring cogency, and protested 
that it was a piece of spirit in his daughter, 
which he admired and was proud of. 
However, it ended with Mr. Nathaniel Hearn's 
declaring that he and his wife would have 
nothing to do with his sister and her 
husband. "Wait till you've seen him, Nat!" said 
the old Squire, trembling with his distressful 
anticipations of family discord, "He's an 
excuse for any girl. Only ask Sir Harry's 
opinion of him." "Confound Sir Harry! 
So that a man sits his horse well. Sir Harry 
cares nothing about anything else. Who is 
this man--this fellow? Where does he come 
from? What are his means? Who are his 
family?" 
</p>
<p>
"He comes from the south--Surrey or 
Somersetshire, I forget which; and he pays 
his way well and liberally. There's not a 
tradesman in Barford but says he cares no 
more for money than for water; he spends 
like a prince, Nat. I don't know who his 
family are, but he seals with a coat of arms, 
which may tell you if you want to know,--
and he goes regularly to collect his rents 
from his estates in the south. Oh, Nat! if 
you would but be friendly, I should be as 
well pleased with Kitty's marriage as any 
father in the country." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Nathaniel Hearn gloomed, and 
muttered an oath or two to himself. The poor 
old father was reaping the consequences of 
his weak indulgence to his two children. 
Mr. and Mrs. Nathaniel Hearn kept apart 
from Catherine and her husband; and Squire 
Hearn durst never ask them to Levison Hall, 
though it was his own house. Indeed, he 
stole away as if he were a culprit whenever 
he went to visit the White House; and if he 
passed a night there, he was fain to equivocate 
when he returned home the next day; an 
equivocation which was well interpreted by 
the surly, proud Nathaniel. But the younger 
Mr. and Mrs. Hearn were the only people 
who did not visit at the White House. Mr. 
and Mrs. Higgins were decidedly more popular 
than their brother and sister-in-law. She 
made a very pretty sweet-tempered hostess, 
and her education had not been such as to 
make her intolerant of any want of refinement 
in the associates who gathered round 
her husband. She had gentle smiles for 
towns-people as well as country people; and 
unconsciously played an admirable second in 
her husband's project of making himself 
universally popular. 
</p>
<p>
But there is some one to make ill-natured 
remarks, and draw ill-natured conclusions 
from very simple premises, in every place; 
and in Barford this bird of ill-omen was a 
Miss Pratt. She did not hunt--so Mr. 
Higgins's admirable riding did not call out her 
admiration. She did not drink--so the well-
selected wines, so lavishly dispensed among 
his guests, could never mollify Miss Pratt. 
She could not bear comic songs, or buffo 
stories--so, in that way, her approbation 
was impregnable. And these three secrets 
of popularity constituted Mr. Higgins's great 
charm. Miss Pratt sat and watched. Her 
face looked immoveably grave at the end of 
any of Mr. Higgins's best stories; but there 
was a keen, needle-like glance of her 
unwinking little eyes, which Mr. Higgins felt 
rather than saw, and which made him shiver, 
even on a hot day, when it fell upon him. 
Miss Pratt was a dissenter, and, to propitiate 
this female Mordecai, Mr. Higgins asked the 
dissenting minister whose services she 
attended to dinner; kept himself and his 
company in good order; gave a handsome donation 
to the poor of the chapel. All in vain--
Miss Pratt stirred not a muscle more of 
her face towards graciousness; and Mr. 
Higgins was conscious that, in spite of all his 
open efforts to captivate Mr. Davis, there 
was a secret influence on the other side, 
throwing in doubts and suspicions, and evil 
interpretations of all he said or did. Miss 
Pratt, the little plain old maid, living on 
eighty pounds a year, was the thorn in the 
popular Mr. Higgins's side, although she had 
never spoken one uncivil word to him; 
indeed, on the contrary, had treated him with 
a stiff and elaborate civility. 
</p>
<p>
The thorn--the grief to Mrs. Higgins was 
this. They had no children! Oh! how she 
would stand and envy the careless busy 
motion of half-a-dozen children; and then, when 
observed, move on with a deep, deep sigh of 
yearning regret. But it was as well. 
</p>
<p>
It was noticed that Mr. Higgins was 
remarkably careful of his health. He ate, drank, 
took exercise, rested, by some secret rules of 
his own; occasionally bursting into an excess, 
it is true, but only on rare occasions--such 
as when he returned from visiting his estates 
in the south, and collecting his rents. That 
unusual exertion and fatigue--for there were 
no stage coaches within forty miles of Barford, 
and he, like most country gentlemen of the 
day, would have preferred riding if there had 
been--seemed to require some strange excess 
to compensate for it; and rumours went 
through the town, that he shut himself up, 
and drank enormously for some days after his 
return. But no one was admitted to these 
orgies. 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
One day--they remembered it well afterwards--
the hounds met not far from the town; 
and the fox was found in a part of the wild 
heath, which was beginning to be enclosed by 
a few of the more wealthy towns-people, who 
were desirous of building themselves houses 
rather more in the country than those they 
had hitherto lived in. Among these the 
principal was a Mr. Dudgeon, the attorney of 
Barford, and the agent for all the county families 
about. The firm of Dudgeon had managed 
the leases, the marriage settlements, and the 
wills, of the neighbourhood for generations. 
Mr. Dudgeon's father had the responsibility 
of collecting the land-owner's rents just as the 
present Mr. Dudgeon had at the time of which 
I speak: and as his son and his son's son have 
done since. Their business was an hereditary 
estate to them; and with something of the old 
feudal feeling, was mixed a kind of proud 
humility at their position towards the squires 
whose family secrets they had mastered, and 
the mysteries of whose fortunes and estates 
were better known to the Messrs. Dudgeon 
than to themselves. 
</p>
<p>
Mr. John Dudgeon had built himself a house 
on Wildbury Heath; a mere cottage, as he 
called it; but though only two stories high, 
it spread out far and wide, and work-people 
from Derby had been sent for on purpose to 
make the inside as complete as possible. The 
gardens too were exquisite in arrangement, if 
not very extensive; and not a flower was 
grown in them but of the rarest species. It 
must have been somewhat of a mortification 
to the owner of this dainty place when, on 
the day of which I speak, the fox, after a long 
race, during which he had described a circle 
of many miles, took refuge in the garden; but 
Mr. Dudgeon put a good face on the matter 
when a gentleman hunter, with the careless 
insolence of the squires of those days and 
that place, rode across the velvet lawn, and 
tapping at the window of the dining-room 
with his whip handle, asked permission--no! 
that is not it--rather, informed Mr. Dudgeon 
of their intention--to enter his garden in a 
body, and have the fox unearthed. Mr. 
Dudgeon compelled himself to smile assent, with 
the grace of a masculine Griselda; and then 
he hastily gave orders to have all that the 
house afforded of provision set out for luncheon, 
guessing rightly enough that six hours' 
run would give even homely fare an acceptable 
welcome. He bore without wincing the 
entrance of the dirty boots into his exquisitely 
clean rooms; he only felt grateful for the 
care with which Mr. Higgins strode about, 
laboriously and noiselessly moving on the tip 
of his toes, as he reconnoitred the rooms with 
a curious eye. 
</p>
<p>
"I'm going to build a house myself. Dudgeon; 
and, upon my word, I don't think I 
could take a better model than yours." 
</p>
<p>
"Oh! my poor cottage would be too small 
to afford any hints for such a house as you 
would wish to build, Mr. Higgins," replied Mr. 
Dudgeon, gently rubbing his hands nevertheless 
at the compliment. 
</p>
<p>
"Not at all! not at all! Let me see. You 
have dining-room, drawing-room"--he 
hesitated, and Mr. Dudgeon filled up the blank as 
he expected. 
</p>
<p>
"Four sitting-rooms and the bed-rooms. 
But allow me to show you over the house. I 
confess I took some pains in arranging it, and, 
though far smaller than what you would 
require, it may nevertheless, afford you some 
hints." 
</p>
<p>
So they left the eating gentlemen with 
their mouths and their plates quite full, and 
the scent of the fox overpowering that of the 
hasty rashers of ham; and they carefully 
inspected all the ground-floor rooms. Then 
Mr. Dudgeon said: 
</p>
<p>
"If you are not tired, Mr. Higgins--it is 
rather my hobby, so you must pull me up if 
you are--we will go up stairs, and I will show 
you my sanctum." 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Dudgeon's sanctum was the centre 
room, over the porch, which formed a 
balcony, and which was carefully filled with 
choice flowers in pots. Inside, there were all 
kinds of elegant contrivances for hiding the 
real strength of all the boxes and chests 
required by the particular nature of Mr. 
Dudgeon's business; for although his office 
was in Barford, he kept (as he informed Mr. 
Higgins) what was the most valuable here, 
as being safer than an office which was locked 
up and left every night. But, as Mr. Higgins 
reminded him with a sly poke in the side, 
when next they met, his own house was not 
over secure. A fortnight after the gentleman 
of the Barford hunt lunched there, Mr. 
Dudgeon's strong-box, in his sanctum 
upstairs, with the mysterious spring bolt to the 
window invented by himself, and the secret 
of which was only known to the inventor and 
a few of his most intimate friends, to whom 
he had proudly shown it;--this strong-box, 
containing the collected Christmas rents of 
half-a-dozen landlords, (there was then no 
bank nearer than Derby,) was rifled; and the 
secretly rich Mr. Dudgeon had to stop his 
agent in his purchases of paintings by Flemish 
artists, because the money was required to 
make good the missing rents. 
</p>
<p>
The Dogberries and Verges of those days 
were quite incapable of obtaining any clue to 
the robber or robbers; and though one or 
two vagrants were taken up and brought 
before Mr. Dunover and Mr. Higgins, the 
magistrates who usually attended in the courtroom 
at Barford, there was no evidence 
brought against them, and after a couple of 
nights' durance in the lock-ups they were set 
at liberty. But it became a standing joke 
with Mr. Higgins to Mr. Dudgeon, from time 
to time, whether he could recommend him a 
place of safety for his valuables; or, if he had 
made any more inventions lately for securing 
houses from robbers. 
</p>
<p>
About two years after this time--about 
seven years after Mr. Higgins had been 
married--one Tuesday evening, Mr. Davis was 
sitting reading the news in the coffee-room 
of the George-inn. He belonged to a club of 
gentlemen who met there occasionally to play 
at whist, to read what few newspapers and 
magazines were published in those days, to 
chat about the market at Derby, and prices 
all over the country. This Tuesday night it 
was a black frost; and few people were in 
the room. Mr. Davis was anxious to finish 
an article in the "Gentleman's Magazine;" 
indeed, he was making extracts from it, 
intending to answer it, and yet unable with his 
small income to purchase a copy. So he 
staid late; it was past nine, and at ten o'clock 
the room was closed. But while he wrote, 
Mr. Higgins came in. He was pale and 
haggard with cold; Mr. Davis, who had had for 
some time sole possession of the fire, moved 
politely on one side, and handed to the new 
comer the sole London newspaper which the 
room afforded. Mr. Higgins accepted it, and 
made some remark on the intense coldness 
of the weather; but Mr. Davis was too full 
of his article, and intended reply, to fall into 
conversation readily. Mr. Higgins hitched 
his chair nearer to the fire, and put his feet 
on the fender, giving an audible shudder. He 
put the newspaper on one end of the table 
near him, and sat gazing into the red embers 
of the fire, crouching down over them as if 
his very marrow were chilled. At length he 
said: 
</p>
<p>
"There is no account of the murder at Bath 
in that paper?" Mr. Davis, who had finished 
taking his notes, and was preparing to go 
stopped short, and asked: 
</p>
<p>
"Has there been a murder at Bath? No! 
I have not seen anything of it--who was 
murdered?" 
</p>
<p>
"Oh! it was a shocking, terrible murder!" 
said Mr. Higgins not raising his look from 
the fire, but gazing on, his eyes dilated till the 
whites were seen all around them. "A 
terrible murder! I wonder what will become of 
the murderer? I can fancy the red glowing 
centre of that fire--look and see how infinitely 
distant it seems, and how the distance 
magnifies it into something awful and unquenchable." 
</p>
<p>
"My dear sir, you are feverish; how you 
shake and shiver!" said Mr. Davis, thinking 
privately that his companion had symptoms 
of fever, and that he was wandering in his 
mind. 
</p>
<p>
"Oh, no!" said Mr. Higgins. "I am not 
feverish. It is the night which is so cold." 
And for a time he talked with Mr. Davis 
about the article in the "Gentleman's Magazine," 
for he was rather a reader himself, and 
could take more interest in Mr. Davis's 
pursuits than most of the people at Barford. At 
length it drew near to ten, and Mr. Davis rose 
up to go home to his lodgings. 
</p>
<p>
"No, Davis, don't go. I want you here. 
We will have a bottle of port together, and 
that will put Saunders in good humour. I 
want to tell you about this murder," he 
continued, dropping his voice, and speaking 
hoarse and low. "She was an old woman, 
and he killed her, sitting reading her Bible 
by her own fireside!" He looked at Mr. 
Davis with a strange searching gaze, as if 
trying to find some sympathy in the horror 
which the idea presented to him. 
</p>
<p>
"Who do you mean, my dear sir? What 
is this murder you are so full of? No one 
has been murdered here." 
</p>
<p>
"No, you fool! I tell you it was in Bath!" 
said Mr. Higgins, with sudden passion; and 
then calming himself to most velvet smoothness 
of manner, he laid his hand on Mr. 
Davis's knee, there, as they sat by the fire, and 
gently detaining him, began the narration of 
the crime he was so full of; but his voice and 
manner were constrained to a stony quietude; 
he never looked in Mr. Davis's face; once 
or twice, as Mr. Davis remembered afterwards, 
his grip tightened like a compressing 
vice. 
</p>
<p>
"She lived in a small house in a quiet old-
fashioned street, she and her maid. People 
said she was a good old woman; but for all 
that she hoarded and hoarded, and never gave 
to the poor. Mr. Davis, it is wicked not to 
give to the poor--wicked--wicked, is it not? 
I always give to the poor, for once I read in 
the Bible that 'Charity covereth a multitude 
of sins.' The wicked old woman never gave, 
but hoarded her money, and saved, and saved. 
Some one heard of it; I say she threw a 
temptation in his way, and God will punish 
her for it. And this man--or it might be a 
woman, who knows?--and this person--heard 
also that she went to church in the mornings, 
and her maid in the afternoons; and so--
while the maid was at church, and the street 
and the house quite still, and the darkness of 
a winter afternoon coming on--she was 
nodding over the Bible--and that, mark you! is a 
sin, and one that God will avenge sooner or 
later; and a step came in the dusk up the 
stair, and that person I told you of, stood in 
the room. At first he--no! At first, it is 
supposed--for, you understand, all this is 
mere guess work, it is supposed that he asked 
her civilly enough to give him her money, or 
tell him where it was; but the old miser 
defied him, and would not ask for mercy and 
give up her keys, even when he threatened 
her, but looked him in the face as if he had 
been a baby--Oh, God! Mr. Davis, I once 
dreamt when I was a little innocent boy that 
I should commit a crime like this, and I 
wakened up crying; and my mother comforted 
me--that is the reason I tremble so now, 
that and the cold, for it is very, very cold!" 
</p>
<p>
"But did he murder the old lady?" asked 
Mr. Davis. "I beg your pardon, sir, but I 
am interested by your story." 
</p>
<p>
"Yes! he cut her throat; and there she 
lies yet in her quiet little parlor, with her face 
upturned and all ghastly white, in the middle 
of a pool of blood. Mr. Davis, this wine 
is no better than water; I must have some 
brandy!" 
</p>
<p>
Mr. Davis was horror-struck by the story, 
which seemed to have fascinated him as much 
as it had done his companion. 
</p>
<p>
"Have they got any clue to the murderer?" 
said he. Mr. Higgins drank down half a 
tumbler of raw brandy before he answered. 
</p>
<p>
"No! no clue whatever. They will never 
be able to discover him, and I should not 
wonder--Mr. Davis--I should not wonder if 
he repented after all, and did bitter penance 
for his crime; and if so--will there be mercy 
for him at the last day?" 
</p>
<p>
"God knows," said Mr. Davis with 
solemnity. "It is an awful story," continued 
he, rousing himself; "I hardly like to leave 
this warm light room and go out into the 
darkness after hearing it. But it must be 
done," buttoning on his great coat--"I can 
only say I hope and trust they will find out 
the murderer, and hang him. If you'll take 
my advice, you'll have bed warmed, and drink 
a treacle-posset just the last thing; and, if 
you'll allow me, I'll send you my answer to 
Philologus before it goes up to old Urban." 
</p>
<p>
The next morning Mr. Davis went to call on 
Miss Pratt, who was not very well; and by 
way of being agreeable and entertaining, he 
related to her all he had heard the night before 
about the murder in Bath, and really he made 
a very pretty connected story out of it, and 
interested Miss Pratt very much in the fate 
of the old lady--partly because of a similarity 
in their situations; for she also hoarded 
money, and had but one servant, and stopped 
at home alone on Sunday afternoons to allow 
her servant to go to church. 
</p>
<p>
"And when did all this happen?" she 
asked. 
</p>
<p>
"I don't know if Mr. Higgins named the 
day; and yet I think it must have been this 
very last Sunday." 
</p>
<p>
"And to-day is Wednesday. Ill news 
travels fast." 
</p>
<p>
"Yes, Mr. Higgins thought it might have 
been in the London newspaper." 
</p>
<p>
"That it could never be. Where did Mr. 
Higgins learn all about it?" 
</p>
<p>
"I don't know, I did not ask; I think he 
only came home yesterday: he had been 
south to collect his rents, somebody said." 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pratt grunted. She used to vent her 
dislike and suspicions of Mr. Higgins in a 
grunt whenever his name was mentioned. 
</p>
<p>
"Well, I shan't see you for some days. 
Godfrey Merton has asked me to go and stay 
with him and his sister; and I think it will 
do me good. Besides," added she, "these 
winter evenings; and these murderers at large 
in the country; I don't quite like living with 
only Peggy to call to in case of need." 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pratt went to stay with her cousin Mr. 
Merton. He was an active magistrate, and 
enjoyed his reputation as such. One day he 
came in, having just received his letters. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
"Bad account of the morals of your little 
town here, Jessy!" said he, touching one of 
his letters. "You've either a murderer among 
you, or some friend of a murderer. Here's a 
poor old lady at Bath had her throat cut last 
Sunday week; and I've a letter from the 
Home Office, asking to lend them 'my very 
efficient aid,' as they are pleased to call it, 
towards finding out the culprit. It seems he 
must have been thirsty, and of a comfortable 
jolly turn; for before going to his horrid work 
he tapped a barrel of ginger wine the old lady 
had set by to work; and he wrapped the 
spigot round with a piece of a letter taken out 
of his pocket, as may be supposed; and this 
piece of a letter was found afterwards; there 
are only these letters on the outside, 'ns, 
Esq.,-arford,-egworth,' which some one has 
ingeniously made out to mean Barford, near 
Kegworth. On the other side there is some 
allusion to a race-horse, I conjecture, though 
the name is singular enough; 'Church-and-
King-and-down-with-the-Rump.'" 
</p>
<p>
Miss Pratt caught at this name immediately; 
it had hurt her feeling as a dissenter only 
a few months ago, and she remembered it 
well. 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Nat Hearn has--or had (as I am 
speaking in the witness-box, as it were, I 
must take care of my tenses), a horse with 
that ridiculous name." 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Nat Hearn," repeated Mr. Merton, 
making a note of the intelligence; then he 
recurred to his letter from the Home Office 
again. 
</p>
<p>
"There is also a piece of a small key, broken 
in the futile attempt to open a desk--well, 
well. Nothing more of consequence. The 
letter is what we must rely upon." 
</p>
<p>
"Mr. Davis said that Mr. Higgins told him--" 
Miss Pratt began. 
</p>
<p>
"Higgins!" exclaimed Mr. Merton, "<em>ns</em>. 
Is it Higgins, the blustering fellow that ran 
away with Nat Hearn's sister?" 
</p>
<p>
"Yes!" said Miss Pratt. "But though he 
has never been a favourite of mine--" 
</p>
<p>
"<em>ns</em>," repeated Mr. Merton. "It is too 
horrible to think of; a member of the hunt--kind 
old Squire Hearn's son-in-law! Who else 
have you in Barford with names that end in 
ns?" 
</p>
<p>
"There's Jackson, and Higginson, and 
Blenkinsop, and Davis, and Jones. Cousin! 
One thing strikes me--how did Mr. Higgins 
know all about it to tell Mr. Davis on Tuesday 
what had happened on Sunday afternoon?" 
</p>
<p>
There is no need to add much more. Those 
curious in lives of the highwaymen may find 
the name of Higgins as conspicuous among 
those annals as that of Claude Duval. Kate 
Hearn's husband collected his rents on the 
highway, like many other "gentlemen" of 
the day; but having been unlucky in one or 
two of his adventures, and hearing exaggerated 
accounts of the hoarded wealth of the 
old lady at Bath, he was led on from robbery 
to murder, and was hung for his crime at 
Derby, in seventeen hundred and seventy-
five. 
</p>
<p>
He had not been an unkind husband; and 
his poor wife took lodgings in Derby to be 
near him in his last moments; his awful last 
moments. Her old father went with her 
everywhere but into her husband's cell; and 
wrung her heart by constantly accusing 
himself of having promoted her marriage with a 
man of whom he knew so little. He 
abdicated his squireship in favour of his son 
Nathaniel. Nat. was prosperous, and the 
helpless silly father could be of no use to him; 
but to his widowed daughter the foolish fond 
old man was all in all; her knight, her protector, 
her companion, her most faithful loving 
companion. Only he ever declined assuming 
the office of her counsellor--shaking his head 
sadly, and saying--
</p>
<p>
"Ah! Kate, Kate! if I had had more wisdom 
to have advised thee better, thou need'st 
not have been an exile here in Brussels, shrinking 
from the sight of every English person as 
if they knew thy story." 
</p>
<p>
I saw the White House not a month ago; 
it was to let, perhaps for the twentieth time 
since Mr. Higgins occupied it; but still the 
tradition goes in Barford that once upon a 
time a highwayman lived there, and amassed 
untold treasures; and that the ill-gotten 
wealth yet remains walled up in some 
unknown concealed chamber; but in what part 
of the house, no one knows. 
</p>
<p>
Will any of you become tenants and try to 
find out this mysterious closet? I can furnish 
the exact address to any applicant who wishes 
for it. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>UNCLE GEORGE'S STORY.</title>
<p>
We had devoted the morning before my 
wedding day to the arrangement of those 
troublesome, delightful, endless little affairs, 
which the world says must be set in order on 
such occasions; and late in the afternoon, we 
walked down, Charlotte and myself, to take a 
last bachelor and maiden peep at the home 
which, next day, was to be ours in partnership. 
Goody Barnes, already installed as our 
cook and housekeeper, stood at the door, 
ready to receive us as we crossed the market-
place to inspect our cottage for the twentieth 
time,--cottage by courtesy,--next door to my 
Father's mansion, by far the best and 
handsomest in the place. It was some distance 
from Charlotte's house, where she and her 
widowed mother lived;--all the way down 
the lime-tree avenue, then over the breezy 
common, besides traversing the principal and 
only street, which terminated in the village 
market place. 
</p>
<p>
The front of our house was quakerlike, in 
point of neatness and humility. But enter. 
It is not hard to display good taste when the 
banker's book puts no veto on the choice 
gems of furniture, which give the finishing 
touch to the whole. Then pass through, and 
bestow a glance upon our living rooms looking 
down upon that greatest of luxuries, a 
terraced garden, commanding the country--
and not a little of that country mine already--
the farm which my father had given me, to 
keep me quiet and contented at home. For 
the closing perspective of our view, there was 
the sea, like a bright blue rampart rising 
before us. White-sailed vessels, or self-willed 
steamers, flitted to and fro for our amusement. 
</p>
<p>
We tripped down the terrace steps, and of 
course looked in upon the little artificial 
grotto to the right, which I had caused to be 
lined throughout with foreign shells and 
glittering spars,--more gifts from my ever-
bountiful father. Charlotte and I went laughingly 
along the straight gravel walk, flanked on 
each side with a regiment of dahlias; that led 
us to the little gate, opening to give us 
admission to my father's own pleasure-ground 
and orchard. 
</p>
<p>
The dear old man was rejoiced to receive 
us. A daughter was what he so long had 
wished for. We hardly knew whether to 
smile, or weep for joy, as we all sat together 
on the same rustic bench, overshadowed by 
the tulip-tree, which some one said my father 
had himself brought from North America. 
But of the means by which he become 
possessed of many of his choicest treasures, he 
never breathed a syllable to me. His father, 
I very well knew, was nothing more than a 
homely farmer, cultivating no great extent of 
not too productive sea-side land; but 
Charlotte's lace dress which she was to wear 
tomorrow--again another present from him--
was, her mother proudly pronounced, valuable 
and handsome enough for a princess. 
</p>
<p>
Charlotte half whispered, half said aloud, 
that she had no fear now that Richard Leroy, 
her boisterous admirer, would dare to attempt 
his reported threat to carry her off to the 
continent in his cutter. Richard's name 
made my father frown, so we said no more; 
we lapsed again into that dreamy state of 
silent enjoyment, which was the best expression 
of our happiness. 
</p>
<p>
Leroy's father was called a farmer; but 
on our portion of the English coast there are 
many things that are well understood rather 
than clearly and distinctly expressed; and no 
one had ever enlightened my ignorance. My 
father was on speaking terms with him, that 
was all; courteous, but distant; half timid, 
half mysterious. He discouraged my childish 
intimacy with Richard; yet he did not 
go so far as to forbid it. Once, when I urged 
him to allow me to accompany young Leroy 
in his boat, to fish in the Channel one calm 
and bright summer morning, he peremptorily 
answered, "No! I do not wish you to learn 
to be a smuggler." But then, he instantly 
checked himself, and afterwards was more 
anxious and kind to me than ever. Still 
Richard and I continued playfellows until we 
grew up, and both admired Charlotte. He 
would have made a formal proposal for her 
hand, if the marked discouragement of her 
family had not shut out every opportunity. 
This touched his pride, and once made him 
declare, in an off-hand way, that it would cost 
him but very little trouble to land such a 
light cargo as that, some pleasant evening, in 
France, or even on one of the Azore Islands, 
if orange groves and orange blossoms were 
what my lady cared about. It is 
wonderful how far, and how swiftly, heedless 
words do fly when once they are uttered. Such 
speeches did not close the breach, but instead, 
laid the first foundation for one of those 
confirmed estrangements which village 
neighbourhoods only know. The repugnance 
manifested by Charlotte's friends was partly 
caused by the mystery which hung to 
Richard's ample means. The choice was 
unhesitatingly made in my favour. In consequence, 
as a sort of rejected candidate, Richard Leroy 
really did lie, amongst us, under an 
unexpressed and indefinite ban, which was by no 
means likely to be removed by the roystering, 
scornful air of superiority with which he 
mostly spoke of, looked at, and treated us. 
</p>
<p>
Charlotte and I took leave of my father on 
that grey September evening with the full 
conviction that every blessing was in store for 
us which affection and wealth had the power 
to procure. Over the green, and up the 
lime-tree avenue, and then, good-night, my 
lady-love! Good-night, thus parting, for the 
very last time. To-morrow--ah! think of 
to-morrow. The quarters of the church 
clock strike half-past nine. Good-night, 
dear mother-in-law. And, once more, good-
night, Charlotte! 
</p>
<p>
It was somewhat early to leave; but my 
father's plans required it. He desired that 
we should be married, not at the church of 
the village where we all resided, but at one 
distant a short walk, in which he took a 
peculiar interest--where he had selected the 
spot for a family burial-place, and where he 
wished the family registers to be kept. It 
was a secluded hamlet; and my father had 
simply made the request that I would lodge 
for a while at a farm-house there, in order 
that the wedding might be performed at the 
place he fixed his heart upon. My duty and 
my interest were to obey. 
</p>
<p>
"Good night, Charlotte," had not long 
been uttered, before I was fairly on the way 
to my temporary home. Our village, and its 
few scattered lights, were soon left behind, 
and I then was upon the open down, walking 
on with a springing step. On one side was 
spread the English Channel: and from time 
to time I could mark the appearance of 
the light at Cape Grinez, on the French 
coast opposite. There it was, coming and 
going, flashing out and dying away, with 
never-ceasing coquetry. The cliff lay between 
my path and the sea. There was no danger; 
for, although the moon was not up, it was 
bright starlight. I knew every inch of the 
way as well as I did my father's garden walks. 
In September, however, mists will rise; and, 
as I approached the valley, there came the 
offspring of the pretty stream which ran 
through it, something like a light cloud 
running along the ground before the wind. Is 
there a night-fog coming on? Perhaps there 
may be. If so, better steer quite clear of the 
cliff, by means of a gentle circuit inland. It 
is quite impossible to miss the valley; and, 
once in the valley, it is equally difficult to 
miss the hamlet. Richard Leroy has been 
frequently backward and forward the last few 
evenings: it would be strange if we should 
chance to meet here, and on such an occasion. 
</p>
<p>
On, and still on, cheerly. In a few minutes 
more I shall reach the farm, and then, to pass 
one more solitary night is almost a pleasurable 
delay, a refinement in happiness. I could 
sing and dance for joy. Yes, dance all alone, 
on the elastic turf! There: just one foolish 
caper; just one----
</p>
<p>
Good God! is this not the shock of an 
earthquake? I hasten to advance another 
step, but the ground beneath me quivers and 
sinks. I grasp at the side of a yawning pitfall, 
but grasp in vain. Down, down, down, I fall 
headlong. 
</p>
<p>
When my senses returned, and I could look 
about me, the moon had risen, and was shining 
in at the treacherous hole through which 
I had fallen. A glance was only too sufficient 
to explain my position. Why had I always 
so foolishly refused to allow the farmer to 
meet me half way, and accompany me to his 
house every evening; knowing, as I did know, 
how the chalk and limestone of the district 
had been undermined in catacombs, sinuous 
and secret for wells, flint, manure, building, 
materials, and other purposes? My poor 
father and Charlotte! 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
Patience. It can hardly be possible that 
now, on the eve of marriage, I am suddenly 
doomed to a lingering death. The night 
must be passed here, and daylight will show 
some means of escape, I will lie down on 
this heap of earth that fell under me. 
</p>
<p>
Amidst despairing thoughts, and a hideous 
waking nightmare, daylight slowly came. 
</p>
<p>
The waning moon had not revealed the 
extremity of my despair; but now it was 
clearly visible that I had fallen double the 
height I supposed. But for the turf which 
had fallen under me, I must have been killed 
on the spot. The hole was too large for me 
to creep up, by pressing against it with my 
back and knees; and there were no friendly 
knobs or protuberances visible up its smooth 
sides. The chasm increased in diameter as it 
descended; like an inverted funnel. I might 
possibly climb up a wall; but could I creep 
along a ceiling? 
</p>
<p>
I shouted as I lay; no one answered. I 
shouted again--and again. Then I thought 
that too much shouting would exhaust my 
strength, and unfit me for the task of mounting. 
I measured with my eye the distance 
from stratum to stratum of each well-marked 
layer of chalk. And then, the successive 
beds of flint--they gave me the greatest 
hopes. If footholes could only be cut! 
Though the feat was difficult, it might be 
practicable. The attempt must be made. 
</p>
<p>
I arose, stiff and bruised. No matter. The 
first layer of flints was not more than seven 
or eight feet overhead. Those once reached, 
I could secure a footing, and obtain a first 
starting-place for escape. I tried to climb to 
them with my feet and hands. Impossible! 
the crumbling wall would not support half 
my weight. As fast as I attempted to get 
handhold or footing, it fell in fragments to the 
ground. 
</p>
<p>
But, a better thought--to dig it away, and 
make a mound so high that, by standing on 
it, I could manage to reach the flint with 
my hands. I had my knife to help me; 
and, after much hard work, my object was 
accomplished, and I got within reach of the 
shelf. 
</p>
<p>
My hands had firm hold of the horizontal 
flint. They were cut with clinging; but I 
found that, by raising myself, and then 
thrusting my feet into the chalk and marl, I 
could support myself with one hand only, 
leaving the other free to work. I did work; 
clearing away the chalk above the flint, so as 
to give me greater standing room. At last, I 
thought I might venture upon the ledge itself. 
By a supreme effort, I reached the shelf; but 
moisture had made the chalk unctuous and 
slippery to the baffled grasp. It was in vain 
to think of mounting higher, with no point 
of support, no firm footing. A desperate leap 
across the chasm afforded not the slightest 
hope; because, even if successful, I could not 
for one moment maintain the advantage 
gained. I was determined to remain on the 
ledge of flint. Another moment, and a 
rattling on the floor soon taught me my 
powerlessness. Down sunk the chalk beneath my 
weight; and the stony table fell from its 
fixture, only just failing to crush me under it. 
Stunned, and cut, and bruised, I spent some 
time prostrated by half conscious but acute 
sensations of misery. Sleep, which as yet I 
had not felt, began to steal over me, but could 
gain no mastery. With each moment of 
incipient unconsciousness, Charlotte was 
presented to me, first, in her wedding-dress; 
next, on our terrace beckoning me gaily from 
the garden below; then, we were walking 
arm-in-arm in smiling conversation; or seated 
happily together in my father's library. But 
the full consciousness which rapidly succeeded 
presented each moment the hideous truth. It 
was now broad day; and I realised Charlotte's 
sufferings. I beheld her awaiting me in her 
bridal dress; now hastening to the window, 
and straining her sight over the valley, in the 
hope of my approach; now stricken down by 
despair at my absence. My father, too, whose 
life had been always bound up in mine! These 
fancies destroyed my power of thought. I 
felt wild and frenzied. I raved and shouted, 
and then listened, knowing no answer could 
come. 
</p>
<p>
But an answer did come: a maddening 
answer. The sound of bells, dull, dead, and 
in my hideous well-hole, just distinguishable. 
They rang out my marriage peal. Why was 
I not buried alive when I first fell? 
</p>
<p>
I could have drunk blood, in my thirst, had 
it been offered to me. Die I must, I felt full 
well; but let me not die with my mouth in 
flame? Then came the struggle of sleep; and 
then fitful, tantalising dreams. Charlotte 
appeared to me plucking grapes, and dropping 
them playfully into my mouth; or catching 
water in the hollow of her hand, from the 
little cascade in our grotto, and I drank. But 
hark! drip, drip, and again drip! Is this 
madness still? No. There must be water 
oozing somewhere out of the sides of this 
detested hole. Where the treacherous wall is 
slimiest, where the green patches are brightest 
and widest spread on the clammy sides of 
my living sepulchre, there will be the spot to 
dig and to search. 
</p>
<p>
Again the knife. Every blow gives a 
more dead and hollow sound. The chalk 
dislodged is certainly not moister; but the 
blade sticks fast into wood--the wood of a 
cask; something slowly begins to trickle 
down. It is brandy! 
</p>
<p>
Brandy! shall I taste it? Yet, why not? 
I did; and soon for a time remembered 
nothing. 
</p>
<p>
I retained a vivid and excited consciousness 
up to one precise moment, which might have 
been marked by a stop-watch, and then all 
outward things were shut out, as suddenly as 
as if a lamp had been extinguished. A 
long and utter blank succeeded. I have no 
further recollection either of the duration of 
time, or of any bodily suffering. Had I died 
by alcoholic poison--and it is a miracle the 
brandy did not kill me--then would have 
been the end of my actual and conscious 
existence. My senses were dead. If what 
happened afterwards had occurred at that time, 
there would have been no story for you to 
listen to. 
</p>
<p>
Once more, a burning thirst. Hunger had 
entirely passed away. I looked up, and all 
was dark; not even the stars or the cloudy 
sky were to be seen at the opening of my 
cavern. A shower of earth and heavy stones 
fell upon me as I lay. I still was barely awake 
and conscious, and a groan was the only 
evidence which escaped me that I had again 
recovered the use of my senses. 
</p>
<p>
"Halloa! What's that down there?" said 
a voice whose tone was familiar to me. I 
uttered a faint but frantic cry. 
</p>
<p>
I heard a moment's whispering, and the 
hollow echo of departing footsteps, and then 
all was still again. The voice over head once 
more addressed me. 
</p>
<p>
"Courage, George; keep up your spirits! 
In two minutes I will come and haul you. 
Don't you know me?" 
</p>
<p>
I then did know that it could be no other 
than my old rival, Richard Leroy. Before I 
could collect my thoughts, a light glimmered 
against one side of the well; and then, in the 
direction opposite the fallen table of flint, and 
just over it, Richard appeared, with a lantern 
in one hand, and a rope tied to a stick across 
it in the other. 
</p>
<p>
"Have you strength enough left to sit upon 
this, and to hold by the rope while I haul you 
up?" 
</p>
<p>
"I think I have," I said. I got the stick 
under me, and held by the rope to keep 
steady on my seat. Richard planted his 
feet firmly on the edge of his standing-
place, and hauled me up. By a sleight of 
hand and an effort of strength, in which 
I was too weak to render him the least 
assistance, he landed me at the mouth of a 
subterranean gallery opening into the well. I 
could just see, on looking back, that if I had 
only maintained my position on the ledge of 
flint, and improved it a little, I might, by a 
daring and vigorous leap, have sprung to the 
entrance of this very gallery. But those ideas 
were now useless. I was so thoroughly worn 
out that I could scarcely stand, and an 
entreaty for water preceded even my expression 
of thanks. 
</p>
<p>
"You shall drink your fill in one instant, 
and I am heartily glad to have helped you: 
but first let me mention one thing. It is 
understood that you keep my secret. You 
cannot leave this place--unless I blindfold 
you, which would be an insult--without 
learning the way to return to it; and of course, 
what you see along the galleries are to you 
nothing but shadows and dreams. Have I 
your promise?" 
</p>
<p>
I was unable to make any other reply than 
to seize his hand, and burst into tears. How 
I got from the caverns to the face of the cliff, 
how thence to the beach, the secluded hamlet, 
and the sleeping village, does really seem 
to my memory like a vision. On the way 
across the downs, Leroy stopped once or 
twice, more for the sake of resting my aching 
limbs, than of taking breath or repose 
himself. During those intervals, he quietly 
remarked to me how prejudiced and unfair we 
had all of us been to him; that as for 
Charlotte he considered her as a child, a little 
sister, almost even as a baby plaything. She 
was not the woman for him; he for his part, 
liked a girl with a little more of the devil 
about her. No doubt he could have carried 
her off; and no doubt she would have loved 
him desperately a fortnight afterwards. But, 
when he had once got her, what should he 
have done with such a blue-eyed milk-and-
water angel as that? Nothing serious to 
annoy us had ever entered his head. And 
my father ought not quite to forget the 
source of his own fortune, and hold himself 
aloof from his equals; although he might be 
lying quiet in harbour at present. Really it 
was a joke, that, instead of eloping with the 
bride, he should be bringing home the eloped 
bridegroom! 
</p>
<p>
I fainted when he carried me into my 
father's house, and I remembered no more 
than his temporary adieu. But afterwards, 
all went on slowly and surely. My father 
and Richard became good friends, and the old 
gentleman acquired such influence over him, 
that Leroy's "pleasure trips" soon became 
rare, and finally ceased altogether. At the last 
run, he brought a foreign wife over with him, 
and nothing besides--a Dutch woman of great 
beauty and accomplishments; who, as he 
said, was as fitting a helpmate for him, as 
Charlotte, he acknowledged, was for me. He 
also took a neighbouring parish church and 
its appurtenances into favour, and settled down 
as a landsman within a few miles of us. And, 
if our families continue to go on in the friendly 
way they have done for the last few years, it 
seems likely that a Richard may conduct a 
Charlotte, to enter their names together in a 
favourite register book. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE COLONEL'S STORY.</title>
<p>
Until I was fifteen I lived at home with 
my widowed mother and two sisters. My 
mother was the widow of an officer, who was 
killed in one of the battles with Hyder Ali, 
and enjoyed a pension from the Indian Government. 
I was the youngest; and soon after 
my fifteenth birthday she died suddenly. My 
sisters went to India on the invitation of a 
distant relation of my mother; and I was sent 
to school, where I was very unhappy. You 
will, therefore, easily imagine with what 
pleasure I received a visit from a handsome 
jovial old gentleman, who told me that he 
was my father's elder half-brother; that they 
had been separated by a quarrel early in life, 
but that now, being a widower and childless, 
he had found me out, and determined to 
adopt me. 
</p>
<p>
The truth was, the old man loved company; 
and that as his chief income--a large one--
was derived from a mine, near which he lived, 
in a very remote part of the country, he was 
well pleased to have a young companion who 
looked like a gentleman, and could be useful 
as carver, cellar-keeper, and secretary. 
</p>
<p>
Installed in his house, a room was assigned 
to me, and I had a servant, and a couple of 
excellent horses. He made me understand 
that I need give myself no further anxiety on 
the subject of my future, that I might abandon 
the idea of proceeding to India in the 
Company's service, where a cadetship had been 
secured for me; and that so long as I conformed 
to his ways, it was no matter whether I studied 
or not; in fact, it was no matter what I did. 
</p>
<p>
Some time after becoming thus settled at 
Beechgrove Hall, my uncle's attacks of gout, 
in spite of the generous living he adopted as 
a precaution, became so severe, that he was 
unable to stir out except in a wheeled chair, 
and it was with difficulty that he was lifted 
occasionally into his carriage. The 
consequence was, that to me all his business 
naturally fell, and although he grumbled at losing 
my society and attention, he was obliged to 
send me to London to watch the progress of 
a canal bill, in which he was deeply interested. 
It was my first visit to London. I was well 
provided with introductions and with funds. 
My uncle's business occupied me in the 
morning, for I dreaded his displeasure too 
much to neglect it; but in the evenings I 
plunged into every amusement, with all the 
keen zest of novelty and youth. 
</p>
<p>
I cannot say that up to that period I had 
never been in love. My uncle had twice 
seriously warned me that if I made a fool of 
myself for anything less than a large fortune, 
he would never forgive me. "If, Sir," he 
said, when, on the second occasion, he saw 
me blush and tremble--for I was too proud 
and too self-willed to bear patiently such 
control--"If, Sir, you like to make an ass of 
yourself for a pretty face, like Miss Willington, 
with her three brothers and five sisters, 
half of whom you'd have to keep, you may 
do it with your own money; you shall not do 
it with mine." 
</p>
<p>
I told my only confidant. Dr. Creeleigh, 
of this; he answered me, "You have only 
about a hundred and twenty a year of your 
own from the estate you inherited from your 
father, and you are living with your horses 
and dogs at the rate of five hundred a year. 
How would you like to see your wife and 
children dressed and housed like the curate--
poor Mr. Serge. Your uncle can't live for 
ever." The argument was enough for me, 
who had only found Clara Willington the best 
partner in a country dance. My time was 
not come. 
</p>
<p>
My lodgings in London were in a large, old-
fashioned house in Westminster--formerly 
the residence of a nobleman--which was a 
perfect caravanserai, in the number and variety 
of its inmates. The best rooms were let to 
Members of Parliament and persons like 
myself; but, in the upper floor, many persons 
of humbler means but genteel pretensions 
had rooms. Here, I frequently met on the 
stairs, carrying a roll of music, a tall, elegant 
female figure, dressed in black, and closely 
veiled; sometimes, when I had to step on 
one side, a slight bow was exchanged, but for 
several weeks that was all. At length my 
curiosity was piqued; the neat ankles, a 
small white hand, a dark curl peeping out of 
the veil, made me anxious to know more. 
</p>
<p>
Inquiries discreetly applied to Mrs. Gough, 
the housekeeper, told me enough to make me 
wish to know still more. Her name was Laura 
Delacourt: not more than twenty, or twenty-
two years of age; she had lived four years 
previously with her husband in the best 
apartments in the house in great luxury for 
one winter. Mr. Delacourt was a Frenchman 
and a gambler; very handsome and very 
dissipated; it seemed as if it was her fortune 
they were spending. Mrs. Gough said it was 
enough to make one's heart break to see that 
young pretty creature sitting up in her ball 
dress when her husband had sent her home 
alone, and remained to play until daylight. 
They went away, and nothing more was heard 
of them until just before my arrival. About 
that time Madame Delacourt became very 
humble, had taken a room on the third floor: 
had only mentioned her husband to say he 
was dead, and now apparently lived by giving 
music lessons. 
</p>
<p>
It would be too long a story to tell how, by 
making the old houskeeper my ambassador, 
by anonymous presents of fruit and game, by 
offering to take music lessons, and by professing 
to require large quantities of music copied, 
I made first the acquaintance, and then 
became the intimate friend of Madame 
Delacourt. While keeping me at a freezing 
distance, and insisting on always having present 
at our interviews a half servant, half companion, 
of that indescribable age, figure, and 
appearance that is only grown in France, she 
step by step confided to me her history. An 
English girl, born in France, the daughter of 
a war prisoner at Verdun, married to the 
very handsome Monsieur Delacourt at sixteen, 
by a mother who was herself anxious to make 
a second marriage. In twelve months, 
Monsieur Delacourt had expended her small 
fortune, and deserted her for an opera dancer of 
twice her age. 
</p>
<p>
All this, told with a charming accent in 
melancholy tones--she looking on me sadly 
with a face which, for expression, I have 
never seen equalled--produced an impression 
which those only can understand who have 
been themselves young and in love. 
</p>
<p>
For weeks this went on, without one sign 
of encouragement on her part, except that she 
allowed me to sit with her in the evenings, 
while her bonne faddled at some interminable 
work, and she sang--O! how divinely! She 
would receive no presents directly from me; 
but I sent them anonymously, and dresses 
and furniture and costly trifles and books 
reached her daily. I spoke at last; and then 
she stopped me with a cold faint smile, saying, 
"Cease! I must not listen to you." She 
pleaded her too recent widowhood, but I 
persevered; and, after a time, conquered. 
</p>
<p>
She knew my small fortune and large 
expectations; she knew that our marriage must 
be a secret; but she was willing to live 
anywhere, and was well content to quit a life in 
which she had known so much trouble. 
</p>
<p>
Before the session ended, we were married 
in an obscure church in the City, with no one 
present but the clerk and the pew-opener. We 
spent the few following days at a small inn, 
in a fishing village. Then I had to leave town 
and carry out the plan I had proposed. I left 
my wife in lodgings, under an assumed name, 
at a town within forty miles of our residence. 
I had some time previously persuaded my 
uncle to let me take a lease from Lord 
Mardall of some untouched mineral ground, on 
very favourable terms, in a wild, thinly 
peopled district, which was only visited by the 
gentry for field sports. This afforded me an 
excuse for being away from home one or two 
days every week. 
</p>
<p>
Not far from the mines was the remains of 
a forest, and coverts abounding in game. In 
a little sloping dell, one of the Lord Mardall's 
ancestors had built a small shooting lodge, and 
one of the keepers in charge had planted 
there fruit trees, and ornamental trees, for 
which he had a taste, being the son of a 
gardener. On this wild nest, miles away from any 
other residence, I had fixed my mind. It was 
half in ruins, and there was no difficulty in 
obtaining possession. With money and workmen 
at my command, very soon a garden 
smiled, and a fountain bubbled at Orchard 
Spring; roses and climbing plants covered 
the steep hill side, and the small stone cottage 
was made, at a slight expense, a wonder of 
comfort. The cage being ready, I brought 
my bird there. The first months were all 
joy, all happiness. My uncle only complained 
that I had lost my jovial spirits. 
</p>
<p>
I counted every day until the day when I 
could mount my horse and set off for the new 
mines. Five and twenty miles to ride over a 
rough mountain road; two fords to cross, 
often swelled by winter rains; but day or 
night, moonlight or dark, I dashed along, 
pressing too often my willing horse with loose 
rein up and down steep hills; all lost in love 
and anxious thought I rode, until in the 
distance the plashing sound of the mountain 
torrent rolling over our garden cascade, told me 
I was near my darling. 
</p>
<p>
My horse's footsteps were heard, and 
before I had passed the avenue the door flew 
open, the bright fire blazed out, and Laura 
came forward to receive me in her arms. 
</p>
<p>
I had begged her to get everything she 
might require from London, and have it sent, 
to avoid all suspicion, to the nearest port, and 
then brought by her own servant, a country 
clown, with a horse and cart; and I had given 
her a cheque book, signed in blank. After 
a time I saw signs of extravagance; in furniture, 
in dress, but especially in jewels. I 
remonstrated gently, and was met first with 
tears, then sullen fits. I learned that Laura 
had a temper for which I was quite unprepared. 
</p>
<p>
The ice was broken; no more pleasant 
holidays at Orchard Spring. The girl, once so 
humble, now assumed a haughty, jealous air; 
every word was a cause of offence; I never 
came when wanted or stayed as long as I was 
required; half my time was spent in scenes of 
reproach, of tears, hysterics, lamentations; 
peace was only to be purchased by some costly 
present. Our maid servant, a simple country 
girl, stood amazed; the meek angel had 
become a tigress. I loved her still, but feared 
her; yet even love began to fail before so 
much violence. A dreadful idea began slowly 
to intrude itself into my mind. Was she tired 
of me? Was her story of her life true? Had 
she ever loved me? The next time that I 
made up my banker's book, I was shocked to 
find that, in the short time since my last 
remonstrance, Laura had drawn a large sum of 
money. I lost no time in galloping to Orchard 
Spring. She was absent. Where was she? 
No one knew. Severe cross-examination 
brought out that she had been away two 
days; I had not been expected that week. I 
thought I should have choked. 
</p>
<p>
In the midst I heard the steps of her horse. 
She came in and confronted me. Looking 
most beautiful and most demoniacal, she defied 
me; she threatened to expose me to my uncle; 
declared she had never loved me, but had taken 
me for a home. At length her frenzy rose to 
such a height, that she struck me. Then all 
the violent pent-up rage of my heart broke 
out. I know not what passed, until I found 
myself galloping furiously across the mountain 
ridge that divided the county. Obliged 
to slacken my pace in passing through a ford, 
some one spoke to me; how I answered I 
know not. Whatever it was, it was a mad 
answer. 
</p>
<p>
I listened to nothing, and pressed on my 
weary steed until just before reaching the 
moorland, when, descending into a water-
course, he fell on his head, throwing me over 
with such force, that for some time I lay 
senseless. I came to myself to find my poor 
horse standing over me dead lame. I led 
him on to the inn door, and knocked. It 
was midnight, and I was not readily 
admitted. The landlord, when he saw me, 
started back with an explanation of horror. 
My face and shirt were covered with blood. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
Worn-out, bruised, and exhausted by 
fatigue and passion, I slept. I was rudely 
awakened, and found myself in the custody 
of two constables. Two mounted 
gamekeepers, and Lord Mardall, had followed and 
traced me to the inn. 
</p>
<p>
"On what charge?" I asked amazed. 
</p>
<p>
"For murder," said Lord Mardall. 
</p>
<p>
"The lady at Orchard Spring," said one 
of the gamekeepers. 
</p>
<p>
I was examined before magistrates; but 
was unable to give any coherent answers; 
and was committed to the county jail. My 
uncle remitted me a sum of money for my 
defence, and desired never to see me again. 
</p>
<p>
I will give you a description of my trial 
from the newspapers. 
</p>
<break/>
<p>
The prisoner had clandestinely married 
a lady of great beauty and unknown family, 
probably in station beneath himself, and had 
placed her under an assumed name in a lonely 
cottage. After a season of affection, quarrels 
had broken out, which, as would be 
proved by the servant, had constantly 
increased in violence. On the last occasion 
when the unfortunate victim was seen alive 
by her servant, a quarrel of a most fearful 
description had commenced. It was 
something about money. The servant had been 
so much alarmed, that she had left the cottage 
and gone down to her mother's, a mile away 
over the hill, where she had previously been 
ordered to go to obtain some poultry. From 
something that passed her mother would not 
allow her to return. It would then be proved 
that Lord Mardall, attracted by the howling 
of a dog, when out shooting the next morning, 
had entered the open door of the cottage, 
and had there found the prisoner's wife dead, 
with a severe fracture of the skull. The 
prisoner had been pursued, from some 
information as to his usual course, and found 
asleep in the chimney corner of the Moor 
Inn, his clothes and shirt deeply stained with 
blood. It could be proved that he had washed 
his face and hands immediately on entering, 
and attributed the blood to the fall from his 
horse. But on examination no cuts were 
found on his person sufficient to cause such 
an effusion of blood. 
</p>
<p>
But when Lord Mardall was called, he 
deposed to two facts which produced a great 
impression in favour of the prisoner. He saw 
the body at five o'clock, and it was scarcely 
cold. He had found in one of the victim's 
hands a lock of hair, which she had evidently 
torn from her assailant in her struggles; which 
had been desperate. He had sealed it up, and 
never let it out of his possession. The nails 
of her other hand were broken, and were 
marked with blood. She had no rings on 
either of her hands, though she was in the 
habit of wearing a great number; there were 
marks of rings, and of one which seemed to 
have been violently torn off. A packet of 
plate had been found on the kitchen table, a 
knife, and a loaf marked with blood. 
</p>
<p>
Counsel were not allowed to speak for the 
defence in those days, and the prisoner was 
not in a condition to speak on the evidence 
against him. Witnesses for the defence were 
called, who proved that the lady wore 
frequently certain peculiar bracelets. The 
prisoner, who seemed stupefied by his emotions, 
declined to say anything; but his counsel, 
asked the maid-servant, and also the farmer 
who occasionally sold meat to Orchard Spring, 
if they should know the rings and bracelets 
if they saw them. 
</p>
<p>
He then called Richard Perkins, jailor of 
the county prison, and asked him these 
questions: 
</p>
<p>
"Had you any prisoner committed about 
the same time as the prisoner at the bar? 
</p>
<p>
"I had a man called Hay-making Dick, for 
horse-stealing, the day after the discovery of 
the murder." 
</p>
<p>
"Was it a valuable horse?" 
</p>
<p>
"No; it was a mare, blind of one eye, very 
old, and with a large fen spavin. I knew her 
well; used to drive her in the gaol cart; but 
when warm she was faster than anything 
about." 
</p>
<p>
"Do you suppose Hay-making Dick took 
the mare to sell?" 
</p>
<p>
"Certainly not. She would not fetch a 
crown, except to those that knew her. No 
doubt he had been up to some mischief, and 
wanted to get out of the county, only luckily 
he rode against the blacksmith that owned 
the mare and was taken." 
</p>
<p>
The judge thought these questions irrelevant; 
but after some conversation, permitted 
the examination to go on. 
</p>
<p>
"Has Perkins searched the prisoner, and 
has he found anything of value?" 
</p>
<p>
The jailor produced two bracelets, four 
rings--a diamond hoop, one a seal ring--
and a canvass wheat-bag containing gold, 
with several French coins. On one of the 
bracelets was engraved "Charles to Laura," 
and a date. In answer to another question, 
he had found several severe scratches on 
Dick's face, made apparently by nails, which 
he declared had been done in an up and down 
fight at Broad-green Fair. Also a severe raw 
scar on his left temple, as if hair had been 
pulled out. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
At this stage of the proceedings, by order 
of the judge, the prisoner Dick was brought 
up. The lock of hair taken by Lord Mardall 
from the murdered lady's hand was compared 
with Dick's head. It matched exactly, 
although Dick's hair had been cut short and 
washed. Then Mr. Monley gave evidence, 
that when he met the prisoner, on the night 
of the murder, immediately after he had left 
the cottage, there certainly was no blood on 
his face or dress. The landlord of the Moon 
Inn was called, and deposed, that he found 
the corn, placed before the Prisoner's horse, 
uneaten and much stained with blood. On 
examining the horse's tongue, he saw that it 
had been half-bitten off in the fall the animal 
had suffered. No doubt the blood had dripped 
over the young Squire. 
</p>
<p>
It was a bright moonlight night shining in 
the prisoner's face. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
The judge summed up for an acquittal, and 
the jury gave a verdict of Not Guilty, without 
leaving the box. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
A week after, Haymaking Dick made an 
attempt to break out of prison, in which he 
knocked out the brains of a turnkey with his 
irons. He was tried and condemned for this, 
and when hope of escape was gone, he called 
a favourite turnkey to him and said, "Bill, I 
killed the French woman, I knew she always 
had plenty of money and jewels, and I 
watched my opportunity to get 'em." 
</p>
<p>
Thus ends the newspaper reports. My 
uncle died of gout in his stomach on the day 
of the trial, and died almost insolvent. By 
Lord Mardall's influence I received an 
appointment from the East India Company, and 
afterwards a commission in their irregular 
service. 
</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>THE SCHOLAR'S STORY.</title>
<p>
I PERCEIVE a general fear on the part of this 
pleasant company, that I am going to burst 
into black-letter, and beguile the time by 
being as dry as ashes. No, there is no such 
fear, you can assure me? I am glad to hear 
it; but I thought there was. 
</p>
<p>
At any rate, both to relieve your minds 
and to place myself beyond suspicion, I will 
say at once that my story is a ballad. It was 
taken down, as I am going to repeat it, 
seventy-one years ago, by the mother of the 
person who communicated it to M. Villemarque 
when he was making his collection of Breton 
Ballards. It is slightly confirmed by the 
chronicles and Ecclesiastical Acts of the time; 
but no more of them or you really will 
suspect me. It runs, according to my version, 
thus. 
</p>
<section>I.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>Sole child of her house, a lovely maid,</poem1>
<poem1>In the lordly halls of Rohan played.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Played till thirteen, when her sire was bent</poem1>
<poem1>To see her wed; and she gave consent.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And many a lord of high degree</poem1>
<poem1>Came suing her chosen knight to be;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>But amongst them all there pleased her none</poem1>
<poem1>Save the noble Count Mathieu alone;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Lord of the Castle of Tongoli,</poem1>
<poem1>A princely knight of Italy.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>To him so courteous, true and brave,</poem1>
<poem1>Her heart the maiden freely gave.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Three years since the day they first were wed</poem1>
<poem1>In peace and in bliss away had sped,</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>When tidings came on the winds abroad,</poem1>
<poem1>That all were to take the cross of God.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then spake the Count like a noble knight:</poem1>
<poem1>"Aye first in birth should be first in fight!</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"And, since to this Paynim war I must,</poem1>
<poem1>Dear cousin, I leave thee here in trust.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"My wife and my child I leave to thee;</poem1>
<poem1>Guard them, good clerk, as thy life for me!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Early next morn, from his castle gate,</poem1>
<poem1>As rode forth the knight in bannered state,</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Down the marble steps, all full of fears,</poem1>
<poem1>The lady hied her with moans and tears--</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The loving, sweet lady, sobbing wild--</poem1>
<poem1>And laid on her breast her baby child.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>She ran to her lord with a breathless speed,</poem1>
<poem1>As backward she reined his fiery steed;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>She caught and she clasped him round the knee;</poem1>
<poem1>She wept and she prayed him piteously:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Oh stay with me, stay! my lord, my love!</poem1>
<poem1>Go not, I beg, by the saints above;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Leave me not here alone, I pray,</poem1>
<poem1>To weep on your baby's face alway!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The knight was touched with her sad despair,</poem1>
<poem1>And fondly gazed on her face so fair;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And stretched out his hand, and stooping low,</poem1>
<poem1>Raised her up straight to his saddle-bow;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And held her pressed to his bosom then,</poem1>
<poem1>And kissed her o'er and o'er again.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Come, dry these tears, my little Joan;</poem1>
<poem1>A single year, it will soon be flown!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>His baby dear in his arms he took,</poem1>
<poem1>And looked on him with a proud, fond look:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"My boy, when thou'rt a man," said he,</poem1>
<poem1>"Wilt ride to the wars along with me?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then away he spurred across the plain,</poem1>
<poem1>And old and young they wept amain;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Both rich and poor, wept every one;</poem1>
<poem1>But that same clerk--ah! he wept none.</poem1>
</poem>
<section>II.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>The treacherous clerk one morning tide,</poem1>
<poem1>With artful speeches the lady plied:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Lo! ended now is that single year,</poem1>
<poem1>And ended too is the war I hear;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"But yet, thy lord to return to thee,</poem1>
<poem1>Would seem in no haste at all to be.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Now, ask of your heart, my lady dear,</poem1>
<poem1>Is there no other might please it here?</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Need wives still keep themselves unwed,</poem1>
<poem1>E'en though their husband should not be dead?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Silence! thou wretched clerk!" cried she,</poem1>
<poem1>"Thy heart is filled full of sin, I see.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"When my lord returns, if I whisper him,</poem1>
<poem1>Thou know'st he'll tear thee limb from limb."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>As soon as the clerk thus answered she,</poem1>
<poem1>He stole to the kennel secretly.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>He called to the hound so swift and true,</poem1>
<poem1>The hound that his lord loved best, he knew</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>It came to his call--leapt up in play:</poem1>
<poem1>One gash in the throat, and dead it lay.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>As trickled the blood from out the throat,</poem1>
<poem1>He dipped in that red ink and wrote:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>A letter he wrote with a liar's heed,</poem1>
<poem1>And sent it straight to the camp with speed.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And these were the words the letter bore:</poem1>
<poem1>"Dear lord your wife she is fretting sore.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Fretting and grieving, your wife so dear,</poem1>
<poem1>For a sad mischance befallen here.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Chasing the doe on the mountain-side,</poem1>
<poem1>Thy beautiful greyhound burst and died.''</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The Count so guileless then answer made,</poem1>
<poem1>And thus to his faithless cousin said:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Now bid my own little wife, I pray,</poem1>
<poem1>To fret not for this mischance one day.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"My hound is dead--well! money have I</poem1>
<poem1>Another, when I come back, to buy.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Yet she'd better not hunt agen,</poem1>
<poem1>For hunters are oft but wildish men."</poem1>
</poem>
<section>III.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>The miscreant clerk once more he came,</poem1>
<poem1>As she wept in her bower, to the peerless dame.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"O lady, with weeping night and day,</poem1>
<poem1>Your beauty is fading fast away."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"And what care I though it fading be,</poem1>
<poem1>When my own dear lord comes not to me!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Thy own dear lord has, I fancy, wed</poem1>
<poem1>Another ere this, or else he's dead.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"The Moorish maidens though dark are fair,</poem1>
<poem1>And gold in plenty have got to spare;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"The Moorish chiefs on the battle plain</poem1>
<poem1>Thousands as valiant as he have slain.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"If he's wed another--Oh curse, not fret;</poem1>
<poem1>Or, if he's dead--why straight forget!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"If he's wed another I'll die," she said;</poem1>
<poem1>"And I'll die likewise, if he be dead!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"In case one chances to lose the key,</poem1>
<poem1>No need for burning the box, I see.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"'Twere wiser, if I might speak my mind</poem1>
<poem1>A new and a better key to find."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Now hold, thou wretched clerk, thy tongue,</poem1>
<poem1>'Tis foul with lewdness--more rotten than dung."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>As soon as the clerk thus answered she,</poem1>
<poem1>He stole to the stable secretly.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>He looked at his lord's own favourite steed,</poem1>
<poem1>Unmatched for beauty, for strength and speed;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"White as an egg, and more smooth to touch,</poem1>
<poem1>Light as a bird, and for fire none such;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>On nought had she fed since she was born,</poem1>
<poem1>Save fine chopped heath and the best of corn.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Awhile the bonny white mare he eyed,</poem1>
<poem1>Then struck his dirk in her velvet side;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And when the bonny white mare lay dead,</poem1>
<poem1>Again to the Count he wrote and said:</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Of a fresh mischance I now send word,</poem1>
<poem1>But let it not vex thee much, dear lord;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Hasting back from a revel last night,</poem1>
<poem1>My lady rode on thy favourite white--</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"So hotly rode, it stumbled and fell,</poem1>
<poem1>And broke both legs as I grieve to tell."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The Count then answered, "Ah! woe is me</poem1>
<poem1>My bonny white mare no more to see?</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"My mare she has killed; my hound killed too;</poem1>
<poem1>Good cousin now give her council true.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Yet scold her not either; but say from me,</poem1>
<poem1>To no more revels at night must she.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Not horses' legs alone, I fear,</poem1>
<poem1>But wively vows may be broken there!"</poem1>
</poem>
<section>IV.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>The clerk a few days let pass and then</poem1>
<poem1>Back to the charge returned agen.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Lady, now yield, or you die!" said he:</poem1>
<poem1>"Choose which you will--choose speedily!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Ten thousand deaths would I rather die,</poem1>
<poem1>Than shame upon me my God should cry!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The clerk when he saw he nought might gain,</poem1>
<poem1>No more could his smothered wrath contain;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>So soon as those words had left her tongue,</poem1>
<poem1>His dagger right at her head he flung.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>But swift her white angel, hovering nigh,</poem1>
<poem1>Turned it aside as it flashed her by.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The lady straight to her chamber flew,</poem1>
<poem1>And bolt and bar behind her drew.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The clerk his dagger snatched up and shook,</poem1>
<poem1>And grinned with an angry ban-dog's look.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Down the broad stairs in his rage came he,</poem1>
<poem1>Two steps at a time, two steps and three.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then on to the nurse's room he crept,</poem1>
<poem1>Where softly the winsome baby slept--</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Softly, and sweetly, and all alone:</poem1>
<poem1>One arm from the silken cradle thrown--</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>One little round arm just o'er it laid,</poem1>
<poem1>Folded the other beneath his head;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>His little white breast--ah! hush! be still!</poem1>
<poem1>Poor mother, go now and weep your fill!</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Away to his room the clerk then sped,</poem1>
<poem1>And wrote a letter in black and red;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>In haste, post haste, to the Count wrote he:</poem1>
<poem1>"There is need, dear lord, sore need of thee!</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Oh speed now, speed, to thy castle back,</poem1>
<poem1>For all runs riot, and runs to wrack.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Thy hound is killed, and thy mare is killed,</poem1>
<poem1>But not for these with grief I'm filled.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Nor is it for these thou wilt care;</poem1>
<poem1>Thy darling is dead! thy son, thy heir!</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"The sow she seized and devoured him all,</poem1>
<poem1>While thy wife was dancing at the ball;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Dancing there with the miller gay,</poem1>
<poem1>Her young gallant, as the people say."</poem1>
</poem>
<section>V.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>That letter came to the valiant knight,</poem1>
<poem1>Hastening home from the Paynim fight;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>With trumpet sound, from the Eastern strand,</poem1>
<poem1>Hastening home to his own dear land.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>So soon as he read the missive through,</poem1>
<poem1>Fearful to see his anger grew.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The scroll in his mailed hand he took,</poem1>
<poem1>And crumpled it up with a furious look;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>To bits with his teeth he tore the sheet,</poem1>
<poem1>And spat them out at his horse's feet.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Now quick to Brittany, quick, my men,</poem1>
<poem1>The homes that you love to see again!</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Thou loitering squire! ride yet more quick,</poem1>
<poem1>Or my lance shall teach thee how to prick!"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>But when he stood at his castle gate,</poem1>
<poem1>Three lordly blows he struck it straight;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Three angry blows he struck thereon,</poem1>
<poem1>Which made them tremble every one.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>The clerk he heard, and down he hied,</poem1>
<poem1>And opened at once the portal wide.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Oh cursed cousin, that this should be!</poem1>
<poem1>Did I not trust my wife to thee?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>His spear down the traitor's throat he drove,</poem1>
<poem1>Till out at his back the red point clove.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>Then up he rushed to the bridal bower,</poem1>
<poem1>Where drooped his lady like some pale flower.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>And ere she could speak a single word,</poem1>
<poem1>She fell at his feet beneath his sword.</poem1>
</poem>
<section>VI.</section>
<poem>
<poem1>''O holy priest! now tell to me</poem1>
<poem1>What didst thou up at the castle see?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"I saw a grief and a terror more</poem1>
<poem1>Than ever I saw on earth, before.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"I saw a martyr give up her breath,</poem1>
<poem1>And her slayer sorrowing e'en to death."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"O holy priest! now tell to me</poem1>
<poem1>What didst thou down at the crossway see?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"I saw a corpse that all mangled lay,</poem1>
<poem1>And the dogs and ravens made their prey."</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"O holy priest! now tell to me</poem1>
<poem1>What didst thou next in the churchyard see?"</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"By a new-made grave in soft moonlight,</poem1>
<poem1>I saw a fair lady clothed in white;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"Nursing a little child on her knee--</poem1>
<poem1>A dark red wound on his breast had he.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"A noble hound lay couched at her right,</poem1>
<poem1>A steed at her left of bonniest white;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"The first a gash in his throat had wide,</poem1>
<poem1>And this as deep a stab in its side.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"They raised their heads to the lady's knee,</poem1>
<poem1>And they licked their soft hands tenderly.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"She gently patted their necks, the while</poem1>
<poem1>Smiling, though stilly, a fair sweet smile.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"The child, as it fain its love would speak.</poem1>
<poem1>Caressed and fondled its mother's cheek.</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"But down went the moon then silently.</poem1>
<poem1>And my eyes no more their forms could see;</poem1>
</poem>
<poem>
<poem1>"But I heard a bird from out the skies</poem1>
<poem1>Warbling a song of Paradise!"</poem1>
</poem>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>NOBODY'S STORY.</title>
<p>
He lived on the bank of a mighty river, 
broad and deep, which was always silently 
rolling on to a vast undiscovered ocean. It 
had rolled on, ever since the world began. It 
had changed its course sometimes, and turned 
into new channels, leaving its old ways dry 
and barren; but it had ever been upon the 
flow, and ever was to flow until Time shall be 
no more. Against its strong, unfathomable 
stream, nothing made head. No living 
creature, no flower, no leaf, no particle of animate 
or inanimate existence, ever strayed back from 
the undiscovered ocean. The tide of the river 
set resistlessly towards it; and the tide 
never stopped, any more than the earth stops 
in its circling round the sun. 
</p>
<p>
He lived in a busy place, and he worked 
very hard to live. He had no hope of ever 
being rich enough to live a month without 
hard work, but he was quite content, God 
knows, to labour with a cheerful will. He 
was one of an immense family, all of whose 
sons and daughters gained their daily bread 
by daily work, prolonged from their rising up 
betimes until their lying down at night. 
Beyond this destiny he had no prospect, and he 
sought none. 
</p>
<p>
There was over-much drumming, trumpeting, 
and speechmaking, in the neighbourhood 
where he dwelt; but he had nothing to do 
with that. Such clash and uproar came from 
the Bigwig family, at the unaccountable 
proceedings of which race he marvelled much. 
They set up the strangest statues, in iron, 
marble, bronze, and brass, before his door; 
and darkened his house with the legs and 
tails of uncouth images of horses. He 
wondered what it all meant, smiled in a rough 
good-humoured way he had, and kept at his 
hard work. 
</p>
<p>
The Bigwig family (composed of all the 
stateliest people thereabouts, and all the 
noisiest) had undertaken to save him the trouble 
of thinking for himself, and to manage him 
and his affairs. "Why truly," said he, "I 
have little time upon my hands; and if you 
will be so good as to take care of me, in 
return for the money I pay over"--for the 
Bigwig family were not above his money--"I 
shall be relieved and much obliged, considering 
that you know best." Hence the drumming, 
trumpeting, and speechmaking, and the 
ugly images of horses which he was expected 
to fall down and worship. 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
"I don't understand all this," said he, 
rubbing his furrowed brow confusedly. "But 
it has a meaning, may be, if I could find it 
out." 
</p>
<p>
"It means," returned the Bigwig family, 
suspecting something of what he said, "honour 
and glory in the highest, to the highest merit." 
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
"Oh!" said he. And he was glad to hear 
that. 
</p>
<p>
But, when he looked among the images in 
iron, marble, bronze, and brass, he failed to 
find a rather meritorious countryman of his, 
once the son of a Warwickshire wool-dealer, 
or any single countryman whomsoever of that 
kind. He could find none of the men whose 
knowledge had rescued him and his children 
from terrific and disfiguring disease, whose 
boldness had raised his forefathers from the 
condition of serfs, whose wise infancy had 
opened a new and high existence to the 
humblest, whose skill had filled the working man's 
world with accumulated wonders. Whereas, 
he did find others whom he knew no good of, 
and even others whom he knew much ill of. 
</p>
<p>
"Humph!" said he. "I don't quite understand 
it." 
</p>
<p>
So, he went home, and sat down by his 
fire-side to get it out of his mind. 
</p>
<p>
Now, his fire-side was a bare one, all hemmed 
in by blackened streets; but it was a 
precious place to him. The hands of his wife 
were hardened with toil, and she was old 
before her time; but she was dear to him. His 
children, stunted in their growth, bore traces 
of unwholesome nurture; but they had beauty 
in his sight. Above all other things, it was 
an earnest desire of this man's soul that his 
children should be taught. "If I am 
sometimes missed," said he, "for want of 
knowledge, at least let them know better, and avoid 
my mistakes. If it is hard to me to reap the 
harvest of pleasure and instruction that is 
stored in books, let it be easier to them." 
</p>
<p>
But, the Bigwig family broke out into violent 
family quarrels concerning what it was lawful 
to teach to this man's children. Some of 
the family insisted on such a thing being 
primary and indispensable above all other 
things; and others of the family insisted on 
such another thing being primary and 
indispensable above all other things; and 
the Bigwig family, rent into factions, wrote 
pamphlets, held convocations, delivered charges, 
orations, and all varieties of discourses; 
impounded one another in courts Lay and 
courts Ecclesiastical; threw dirt, exchanged 
pummellings, and fell together by the ears 
in unintelligible animosity. Meanwhile, this 
man, in his short evening snatches at his 
fire-side, saw the demon Ignorance arise 
there, and take his children to itself. He 
saw his daughter perverted into a heavy 
slatternly drudge; he saw his son go moping 
down the ways of low sensuality, to brutality 
and crime; he saw the dawning light of 
intelligence in the eyes of his babies so changing 
into cunning and suspicion, that he could 
have rather wished them idiots. 
</p>
<p>
"I don't understand this any the better," 
said he; "but I think it cannot be right. Nay, 
by the clouded Heaven above me, I protest 
against this as my wrong!" 
</p>
<p>
Becoming peaceable again (for his passion 
was usually short lived, and his nature kind), 
he looked about him on his Sundays and 
holidays, and he saw how much monotony and 
weariness there was, and thence how 
drunkenness arose wth all its train of ruin. Then 
he appealed to the Bigwig family, and said, 
"We are a labouring people, and I have 
a glimmering suspicion in me that labouring 
people of whatever condition, were made--by 
a higher intelligence than yours, as I poorly 
understand it--to be in need of mental 
refreshment and recreation. See what we fall 
into, when we rest without it. Come! Amuse 
me harmlessly, show me something, give me 
an escape!" 
</p>
<p>
But, here the Bigwig family fell into a state 
of uproar absolutely deafening. When some 
few voices were faintly heard, proposing to 
show him the wonders of the world, the greatness 
of creation, the mighty changes of time, 
the workings of nature and the beauties of 
art--to show him these things, that is to say, 
at any period of his life when he could look 
upon them--there arose among the Bigwigs 
such roaring and raving, such pulpiting and 
petitioning, such maundering and memorialising, 
such name-calling and dirt-throwing, 
such a shrill wind of parliamentary questioning 
and feeble replying--where "I dare not" 
waited on "I would"--that the poor fellow 
stood aghast, staring wildly around. 
</p>
<p>
"Have I provoked all this," said he, with 
his hands to his affrighted ears, "by what 
was meant to be an innocent request, plainly 
arising out of my familiar experience, and the 
common knowledge of all men who choose to 
open their eyes? I don't understand, and I am 
not understood. What is to come of such a 
state of things?" 
</p>
<p>
He was bending over his work, often asking 
himself the question, when the news began to 
spread that a pestilence had appeared among 
the labourers, and was slaying them by 
thousands. Going forth to look about him, he 
soon found this to be true. The dying and 
the dead were mingled in the close and tainted 
houses among which his life was passed. 
New poison was distilled into the always 
murky, always sickening air. The robust 
and the weak, old age and infancy, the father 
and the mother, all were stricken down 
alike. 
</p>
<p>
What means of fight had he? He remained 
where he was, and saw those who were dearest 
to him die. A kind preacher came to him, 
and would have said some prayers to soften 
his heart in his gloom, but he replied: 
</p>
<p>
"O what avails it, missionary, to come to 
me, a man condemned to residence in this 
foetid place, where every sense becomes a 
torment, and where every minute of my 
numbered days is new mire added to the heap 
under which I lie oppressed! But, give me my 
first glimpse of Heaven, through a little of its 
light and air; give me pure water; help me 
to be clean; lighten this heavy atmosphere 
and heavy life, in which our spirits sink, and 
we become the indifferent and callous 
creatures you too often see us; gently and kindly 
take the bodies of those who die among us, 
out of the small room where we grow to be so 
familiar with the awful change that even its 
sanctity is lost to us; and, Teacher, then I 
will hear--none know better than you, how 
willingly--of Him whose thoughts were so 
much with the poor, and who had compassion 
for all human sorrow!" 
</p>
<p>
He was at his work again, solitary and sad, 
when his Master came and stood near to him, 
dressed in black. He, also, had suffered 
heavily. His young wife, his beautiful and good 
young wife, was dead; so, too, his only child. 
</p>
<p>
"Master, 'tis hard to bear--I know it--but 
be comforted. I would give you comfort, if 
I could." 
</p>
<p>
The Master thanked him from his heart, 
but, said he, "O you labouring men! The 
calamity began among you. If you had but 
lived more healthy and decently, I should not 
be the widowed and bereft mourner that I 
am this day." 
</p>
<p>
"Master," returned the other, shaking his 
head, "I have begun to understand a little 
that most calamities will come from us, as 
this one did, and that none will stop at our 
poor doors, until we are united with that great 
squabbling family yonder, to do the things 
that are right. We cannot live healthily and 
decently, unless they who undertook to 
manage us provide the means. We cannot be 
instructed, unless they will teach us; we 
cannot be rationally amused, unless they will 
amuse us; we cannot but have some false 
gods of our own, while they set up so many 
of theirs in all the public places. The evil 
consequences of imperfect instruction, the evil 
consequences of pernicious neglect, the evil 
consequences of unnatural restraint and the 
denial of humanizing enjoyments, will all 
come from us, and none of them will stop 
with us. They will spread far and wide. 
They always do; they always have done--
just like the pestilence. I understand so 
much, I think, at last." 
</p>
<p>
But the Master said again, "O you labouring 
men! how seldom do we ever hear of you, 
except in connection with some trouble!" 
</p>
<p>
"Master," he replied, "I am Nobody, and 
little likely to be heard of, (nor yet much 
wanted to be heard of, perhaps) except when 
there is some trouble. But it never begins 
with me, and it can never end with me. As 
sure as Death, it comes down to me, and it 
goes up from me." 
</p>
<p>
There was so much reason in what he said, 
that the Bigwig family, getting wind of it, 
and being horribly frightened by the late 
desolation, resolved to unite with him to do the 
things that were right--at all events, so far 
as the said things were associated with the 
direct prevention, humanly speaking, of 
another pestilence. But as their fear wore off, 
which it soon began to do, they resumed their 
falling out among themselves, and did nothing. 
Consequently the scourge appeared again--
low down as before--and spread avengingly 
upward as before, and carried off vast 
numbers of the brawlers. But not a man among 
them ever admitted, if in the least degree he 
ever perceived, that he had anything to do 
with it. 
</p>
<p>
So Nobody lived and died in the old, old, 
old way; and this, in the main, is the whole 
of Nobody's story. 
</p>
<p>
Had he no name, you ask? Perhaps it 
was Legion. It matters little what his name 
was. Let us call him Legion. 
</p>
<p>
If you were ever in the Belgian villages 
near the field of Waterloo, you will have 
seen, in some quiet littie church, a monument 
erected by faithful companions in arms to the 
memory of Colonel A, Major B, Captains C, 
D and E, Lieutenants F and G, Ensigns H, 
I and J, seven non-commissioned officers, and 
one hundred and thirty rank and file, who fell 
in the discharge of their duty on the memorable 
day. The story of Nobody is the story 
of the rank and file of the earth. They bear 
their share of the battle; they have their 
part in the victory; they fall; they leave no 
name but in the mass. The march of the 
proudest of us leads to the dusty way by 
which they go. O! Let us think of them 
this year at the Christmas fire, and not forget 
them when it is burnt out. 
</p>
</chapter>
</book>
