<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>Dr. Marigold's Prescriptions</title>
<subtitle>(All The Year Round Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1865</date>
<!--
TODO Both speaking at once... table?
-->
</info>

<prefix>
<info title="Doctor Marigold's Prescriptions"/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>ALL THE YEAR ROUND.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<hr/>
<centre>CHRISTMAS, 1865.</centre>
<centre>Price 4d.</centre>
</prefix>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken Immediately."/>
<p>I am a Cheap Jack, and my own father's 
name was Willum Marigold. It was in his 
lifetime supposed by some that his name was 
William, but my own father always consistently 
said, No, it was Willum. On which point I 
content myself with looking at the argument this 
way:--If a man is not allowed to know his own 
name in a free country, how much is he allowed 
to know in a land of slavery? As to looking at 
the argument through the medium of the Register, 
Willum Marigold come into the world 
before Registers come up much--and went out 
of it too. They wouldn't have been greatly in 
his line neither, if they had chanced to come up 
before him.</p>
<p>I was born on the Queen's highway, but it 
was the King's at that time. A doctor was 
fetched to my own mother by my own father, 
when it took place on a common; and in consequence 
of his being a very kind gentleman, and 
accepting no fee but a tea-tray, I was named 
Doctor, out of gratitude and compliment to 
him. There you have me. Doctor Marigold.</p>
<p>I am at present a middle-aged man of a 
broadish build, in cords, leggings, and a sleeved 
waistcoat the strings of which is always gone 
behind. Repair them how you will, they go like 
fiddle-strings. You have been to the theatre, and 
you have seen one of the wiolin-players screw up 
his wiolin, after listening to it as if it had been 
whispering the secret to him that it feared it was 
out of order, and then you have heard it snap. 
That's as exactly similar to my waistcoat, as a 
waistcoat and a wiolin can be like one another.</p>
<p>I am partial to a white hat, and I like a shawl 
round my neck wore loose and easy. Sitting 
down is my favourite posture. If I have a taste 
in point of personal jewellery, it is mother-of-pearl 
buttons. There you have me again, as 
large as life.</p>
<p>The doctor having accepted a tea-tray, you'll 
guess that my father was a Cheap Jack before 
me. You are right. He was. It was a pretty 
tray. It represented a large lady going along a 
serpentining up-hill gravel-walk, to attend a little 
church. Two swans had likewise come astray 
with the same intentions. When I call her a 
large lady, I don't mean in point of breadth, for 
there she fell below my views, but she more than 
made it up in heighth; her heighth and slimness 
was--in short THE heighth of both.</p>
<p>I often saw that tray, after I was the 
innocently smiling cause (or more likely screeching 
one) of the doctor's standing it up on a table 
against the wall in his consulting-room. Whenever 
my own father and mother were in that 
part of the country, I used to put my head (I 
have heard my own mother say it was flaxen 
curls at that time, though you wouldn't know 
an old hearth-broom from it now, till you come 
to the handle and found it wasn't me) in at the 
doctor's door, and the doctor was always glad 
to see me, and said, "Aha, my brother 
practitioner! Come in, little M.D. How are your 
inclinations as to sixpence?"</p>
<p>You can't go on for ever, you'll find, nor yet 
could my father nor yet my mother. If you 
don't go off as a whole when you are about 
due, you're liable to go off in part and two 
to one your head's the part. Gradually my 
father went off his, and my mother went off 
hers. It was in a harmless way, but it put out 
the family where I boarded them. The old 
couple, though retired, got to be wholly and 
solely devoted to the Cheap Jack business, and 
were always selling the family off. Whenever 
the cloth was laid for dinner, my father began 
rattling the plates and dishes, as we do in our 
line when we put up crockery for a bid, only he 
had lost the trick of it, and mostly let 'em drop 
and broke 'em. As the old lady had been used to 
sit in the cart, and hand the articles out one by 
one to the old gentleman on the footboard to 
sell, just in the same way she handed him every 
item of the family's property, and they disposed 
of it in their own imaginations from morning 
to night. At last the old gentleman, lying 
bedridden in the same room with the old lady, cries 
out in the old patter, fluent, after having been 
silent for two days and nights: "Now here, my 
jolly companions every one--which the 
Nightingale club in a village was held, At the sign of 
the Cabbage and Shears, Where the singers no 
doubt would have greatly excelled, But for 
want of taste voices and ears--now here, my 
jolly companions every one, is a working model 
of a used-up old Cheap Jack, without a tooth 
in his head, and with a pain in every bone: so 
like life that it would be just as good if it 
wasn't better, just as bad if it wasn't worse, 
and just as new if it wasn't worn out. Bid 
for the working model of the old Cheap Jack, 
who has drunk more gunpowder-tea with the 
ladies in his time than would blow the lid off 
a washerwoman's copper, and carry it as many 
thousands of miles higher than the moon as 
nought nix nought, divided by the national 
debt, carry nothing to the poor-rates, three 
under, and two over. Now my hearts of oak 
and men of straw, what do you say for the 
lot? Two shillings, a shilling, tenpence, eightpence, 
sixpence, fourpence. Twopence? Who 
said twopence? The gentleman in the 
scarecrow's hat? I am ashamed of the gentleman 
in the scarecrow's hat. I really am ashamed of 
him for his want of public spirit. Now I'll tell 
you what I'll do with you. Come! I'll throw 
you in a working model of a old woman that 
was married to the old Cheap Jack so long ago, 
that upon my word and honour it took place in 
Noah's Ark, before the Unicorn could get in 
to forbid the banns by blowing a tune upon his 
horn. There now! Come! What do you say 
for both? I'll tell you what I'll do with you. 
I don't bear you malice for being so backward. 
Here! If you make me a bid that'll only 
reflect a little credit on your town, I'll throw you 
in a warming-pan for nothing, and lend you a 
toasting-fork for life. Now come; what do you 
say after that splendid offer? Say two pound, 
say thirty shillings, say a pound, say ten shillings, 
say five, say two and six. You don't say 
even two and six? You say two and three? 
No. You shan't have the lot for two and three. 
I'd sooner give it you, if you was good looking 
enough. Here! Missis! Chuck the old man 
and woman into the cart, put the horse to, and 
drive 'em away and bury 'em!" Such were the 
last words of Willum Marigold, my own father, 
and they were carried out, by him and by his 
wife my own mother on one and the same 
day, as I ought to know, having followed as 
mourner.</p>
<p>My father had been a lovely one in his time 
at the Cheap Jack work, as his dying observations 
went to prove. But I top him. I don't 
say it because it's myself, but because it has 
been universally acknowledged by all that has 
had the means of comparison. I have worked 
at it. I have measured myself against other 
public speakers, Members of Parliament, Platforms, 
Pulpits, Counsel learned in the law--and 
where I have found 'em good, I have took a bit 
of imitation from 'em, and where I have found 
'em bad, I have let 'em, alone. Now I'll tell 
you what. I mean to go down into my grave 
declaring that of all the callings ill used in 
Great Britain, the Cheap Jack calling is the 
worst used. Why ain't we a profession? Why 
ain't we endowed with privileges? Why are 
we forced to take out a hawkers' license, when 
no such thing is expected of the political 
hawkers? Where's the difference betwixt us? 
Except that we are Cheap Jacks and they are 
Dear Jacks, <em>I</em> don't see any difference but 
what's in our favour.</p>
<p>For look here! Say it's election-time. I am 
on the footboard of my cart in the market-place 
on a Saturday night. I put up a general 
miscellaneous lot. I say: "Now here my free and 
independent woters, I'm a going to give you 
such a chance as you never had in all your born 
days, nor yet the days preceding. Now I'll 
show you what I am a going to do with you. 
Here's a pair of razors that'll shave you closer 
than the Board of Guardians, here's a flat-iron 
worth its weight in gold, here's a frying-pan 
artificially flavoured with essence of beefsteaks 
to that degree that you've only got for the rest 
of your lives to fry bread and dripping in it 
and there you are replete with animal food, 
here's a genuine chronometer watch in such a 
solid silver case that you may knock at the door 
with it when you come home late from a social 
meeting and rouse your wife and family and 
save up your knocker for the postman, and 
here's half a dozen dinner plates that you may 
play the cymbals with to charm the baby when 
it's fractious. Stop! I'll throw you in another 
article and I'll give you that, and it's a rolling-pin, 
and if the baby can only get it well into its 
mouth when its teeth is coming and rub the 
gums once with it, they'll come through double, 
in a fit of laughter equal to being tickled. Stop 
again! I'll throw you in another article, 
because I don't like the looks of you, for you 
haven't the appearance of buyers unless I lose 
by you, and because I'd rather lose than not 
take money to-night, and that's a looking-glass 
in which you may see how ugly you look 
when you don't bid. What do you say now? 
Come! Do you say a pound? Not you, for 
you haven't got it. Do you say ten shillings? 
Not you, for you owe more to the tallyman. 
Well then, I'll tell you what I'll do with you. 
I'll heap 'em all on the footboard of the cart--there 
they are! razors, flat-iron, frying-pan, 
chronometer watch, dinner plates, rolling-pin, 
and looking-glass--take 'em all away for four 
shillings, and I'll give you sixpence for your 
trouble!" This is me, the Cheap Jack. But 
on the Monday morning, in the same marketplace, 
comes the Dear Jack on the hustings--<em>his</em> 
cart--and what does <em>he</em> say? "Now my free 
and independent woters, I am a going to give 
you such a chance" (he begins just like me) "as 
you never had in all your born days, and that's 
the chance of sending Myself to Parliament. 
Now I'll tell you what I am a going to do for 
you. Here's the interests of this magnificent 
town promoted above all the rest of the civilised 
and uncivilised earth. Here's your railways 
carried, and your neighbours' railways jockeyed. 
Here's all your sons in the Post-office. Here's 
Britannia smiling on you. Here's the eyes of 
Europe on you. Here's uniwersal prosperity 
for you, repletion of animal food, golden cornfields, 
gladsome homesteads, and rounds of 
applause from your own hearts, all in one lot and 
that's myself. Will you take me as I stand? 
You won't? Well then, I'll tell you what I'll 
do with you. Come now! I'll throw you in 
anything you ask for. There! Church-rates, 
abolition of church-rates, more malt tax, no malt 
tax, uniwersal education to the highest mark or 
uniwersal ignorance to the lowest, total abolition 
of flogging in the army or a dozen for every private 
once a month all round, Wrongs of Men or 
Rights of Women,--only say which it shall be, 
take 'em or leave 'em, and I'm of your opinion 
altogether, and the lot's your own on your own 
terms. There! You won't take it yet? Well then, 
I'll tell you what I'll do with you. Come! You 
<em>are</em> such free and independent woters, and I <em>am</em> 
so proud of you--you <em>are</em> such a noble and 
enlightened constituency, and I <em>am</em> so ambitious 
of the honour and dignity of being your member, 
which is by far the highest level to which the 
wings of the human mind can soar--that I'll 
tell you what I'll do with you. I'll throw 
you in all the public-houses in your magnificent 
town for nothing. Will that content you? It 
won't? You won't take the lot yet? Well 
then, before I put the horse in and drive away, 
and make the offer to the next most magnificent 
town that can be discovered, I'll tell you what 
I'll do. Take the lot, and I'll drop two thousand 
pound in the streets of your magnificent 
town for them to pick up that can. Not 
enough? Now look here. This is the very 
furthest that I'm a going to. I'll make it two 
thousand five hundred. And still you won't? 
Here, missis! Put the horse--no, stop half a 
moment, I shouldn't like to turn my back upon 
you neither for a trifle, I'll make it two thousand 
seven hundred and fifty pound. There! 
Take the lot on your own terms, and I'll count 
out two thousand seven hundred and fifty pound 
on the footboard of the cart, to be dropped in 
the streets of your magnificent town for them 
to pick up that can. What do you say? Come 
now! You won't do better, and you may do 
worse. You take it? Hooray! Sold again, 
and got the seat!"</p>
<p>These Dear Jacks soap the people shameful, 
but we Cheap Jacks don't. We tell 'em 
the truth about themselves to their faces, and 
scorn to court 'em. As to wenturesomeness 
in the way of puffing up the lots, the Dear 
Jacks beat us hollow. It is considered in 
the Cheap Jack calling that better patter can 
be made out of a gun than any article we put up 
from the cart, except a pair of spectacles. I 
often hold forth about a gun for a quarter of an 
hour, and feel as if I need never leave off. But 
when I tell 'em what the gun can do, and what 
the gun has brought down, I never go half so 
far as the Dear Jacks do when they make 
speeches in praise of <em>their</em> guns--their great 
guns that set 'em on to do it. Besides, I'm 
in business for myself, I ain't sent down into 
the market-place to order, as they are. Besides 
again, my guns don't know what I say in their 
laudation, and their guns do, and the whole concern 
of 'em have reason to be sick and ashamed 
all round. These are some of my arguments 
for declaring that the Cheap Jack calling 
is treated ill in Great Britain, and for turning 
warm when I think of the other Jacks in question 
setting themselves up to pretend to look 
down upon it.</p>
<p>I courted my wife from the footboard of the 
cart. I did indeed. She was a Suffolk young 
woman, and it was in Ipswich market-place 
right opposite the corn-chandler's shop. I had 
noticed her up at a window last Saturday that 
was, appreciating highly. I had took to her, 
and I had said to myself, "If not already disposed 
of, I'll have that lot." Next Saturday 
that come, I pitched the cart on the same pitch, 
and I was in very high feather indeed, keeping 
'em laughing the whole of the time and getting 
off the goods briskly. At last I took out of 
my waistcoat-pocket, a small lot wrapped in 
soft paper, and I put it this way (looking up 
at the window where she was). "Now here 
my blooming English maidens is an article, the 
last article of the present evening's sale, which 
I offer to only you the lovely Suffolk Dumplings 
biling over with beauty, and I won't take a bid 
of a thousand pound for, from any man alive. 
Now what is it? Why, I'll tell you what it is. 
It's made of fine gold, and it's not broke though 
there's a hole in the middle of it, and it's stronger 
than any fetter that ever was forged, though 
it's smaller than any finger in my set of ten. 
Why ten? Because when my parents made 
over my property to me, I tell you true, there 
was twelve sheets, twelve towels, twelve tablecloths, 
twelve knives, twelve forks, twelve tablespoons, 
and twelve teaspoons, but my set 
of fingers was two short of a dozen and could 
never since be matched. Now what else is it? 
Come I'll tell you. It's a hoop of solid gold, 
wrapped in a silver curl-paper that I myself 
took off the shining locks of the ever beautiful 
old lady in Threadneedle-street, London city. 
I wouldn't tell you so if I hadn't the paper to 
show, or you mightn't believe it even of me. 
Now what else is it? It's a man-trap and a 
handcuff, the parish stocks and a leg-lock, all 
in gold and all in one. Now what else is it? 
It's a wedding ring. Now I'll tell you what I'm 
a-going to do with it. I'm not a-going to offer 
this lot for money, but I mean to give it to the 
next of you beauties that laughs, and I'll pay 
her a visit to-morrow morning at exactly half 
after nine o'clock as the chimes go, and I'll take 
her out for a walk to put up the banns." <em>She</em> 
laughed, and got the ring handed up to her. 
When I called in the morning, she says, "Oh 
dear! It's never you and you never mean it?" 
"It's ever me," says I, "and I am ever yours, and 
I ever mean it." So we got married, after being 
put up three times--which, by-the-by, is quite in 
the Cheap Jack way again, and shows once more 
how the Cheap Jack customs pervade society.</p>
<p>She wasn't a bad wife, but she had a temper. 
If she could have parted with that one article 
at a sacrifice, I wouldn't have swopped her away 
in exchange for any other woman in England. 
Not that I ever did swop her away, for we lived 
together till she died, and that was thirteen 
year. Now my lords and ladies and gentlefolks 
all, I'll let you into a secret, though you 
won't believe it. Thirteen year of temper in 
a Palace would try the worst of you, but thirteen 
year of temper in a Cart would try the 
best of you. You are kept so very close to it in 
a cart, you see. There's thousands of couples 
among you, getting on like sweet ile upon a 
whetstone in houses five and six pairs of stairs 
high, that would go to the Divorce Court in a 
cart. Whether the jolting makes it worse, I 
don't undertake to decide, but in a cart it does 
come home to you and stick to you. Wiolence 
in a cart is <em>so</em> wiolent, and aggrawation in a 
cart is <em>so</em> aggrawating.</p>
<p>We might have had such a pleasant life! A 
roomy cart, with the large goods hung outside 
and the bed slung underneath it when on the 
road, an iron pot and a kettle, a fireplace for the 
cold weather, a chimney for the smoke, a hanging 
shelf and a cupboard, a dog, and a horse. 
What more do you want? You draw off upon a 
bit of turf in a green lane or by the roadside, 
you hobble your old horse and turn him grazing, 
you light your fire upon the ashes of the last 
visitors, you cook your stew, and you wouldn't 
call the Emperor of France your father. But 
have a temper in the cart, flinging language and 
the hardest goods in stock at you, and where 
are you then? Put a name to your feelings.</p>
<p>My dog knew as well when she was on the 
turn as I did. Before she broke out, he would 
give a howl, and bolt. How he knew it, was a 
mystery to me, but the sure and certain knowledge 
of it would wake him up out of his 
soundest sleep, and he would give a howl, and 
bolt. At such times I wished I was him.</p>
<p>The worst of it was, we had a daughter born 
to us, and I love children with all my heart. 
When she was in her furies, she beat the child. 
This got to be so shocking as the child got to 
be four or five year old, that I have many a 
time gone on with my whip over my shoulder, 
at the old horse's head, sobbing and crying 
worse than ever little Sophy did. For how 
could I prevent it? Such a thing is not to 
be tried with such a temper--in a cart--without 
coming to a fight. It's in the natural 
size and formation of a cart to bring it to a 
fight. And then the poor child got worse 
terrified than before, as well as worse hurt 
generally, and her mother made complaints to 
the next people we lighted on, and the word 
went round, "Here's a wretch of a Cheap Jack 
been a beating his wife."</p>
<p>Little Sophy was such a brave child! She 
grew to be quite devoted to her poor father, 
though he could do so little to help her. She 
had a wonderful quantity of shining dark hair, 
all curling natural about her. It is quite 
astonishing to me now, that I didn't go tearing 
mad when I used to see her run from her mother 
before the cart, and her mother catch her by 
this hair, and pull her down by it, and beat her.</p>
<p>Such a brave child I said she was. Ah! with 
reason.</p>
<p>"Don't you mind next time, father dear," 
she would whisper to me, with her little face 
still flushed, and her bright eyes still wet; "if 
I don't cry out, you may know I am not much 
hurt. And even if I do cry out, it will only be 
to get mother to let go and leave off." What 
I have seen the little spirit bear--for me--
without crying out!</p>
<p>Yet in other respects her mother took great 
care of her. Her clothes were always clean and 
neat, and her mother was never tired of working 
at 'em. Such is the inconsistency in things. 
Our being down in the marsh country in 
unhealthy weather, I consider the cause of Sophy's 
taking bad low fever; but however she took 
it, once she got it she turned away from her 
mother for evermore, and nothing would 
persuade her to be touched by her mother's hand. 
She would shiver and say "No, no, no," when 
it was offered at, and would hide her face on my 
shoulder, and hold me tighter round the neck.</p>
<p>The Cheap Jack business had been worse 
than ever I had known it, what with one thing 
and what with another (and not least what with 
railroads, which will cut it all to pieces, I expect 
at last), and I was run dry of money. For 
which reason, one night at that period of little 
Sophy's being so bad, either we must have come 
to a dead-lock for victuals and drink, or I must 
have pitched the cart as I did.</p>
<p>I couldn't get the dear child to lie down or 
leave go of me, and indeed I hadn't the heart 
to try, so I stepped out on the footboard with 
her holding round my neck. They all set up a 
laugh when they see us, and one chuckle-headed 
Joskin (that I hated for it) made the bidding, 
"tuppence for her!"</p>
<p>"Now, you country boobies," says I, feeling 
as if my heart was a heavy weight at the end of 
a broken sash-line, "I give you notice that I am 
a going to charm the money out of your pockets, 
and to give you so much more than your money's 
worth that you'll only persuade yourselves to 
draw your Saturday night's wages ever again 
arterwards, by the hopes of meeting me to lay 'em 
out with, which you never will, and why not? 
Because I've made my fortune by selling my 
goods on a large scale for seventy-five per cent 
less than I give for 'em, and I am consequently 
to be elevated to the House of Peers next week, 
by the title of the Duke of Cheap and Markis 
Jackaloorul. Now let's know what you want 
to-night, and you shall have it. But first of all, 
shall I tell you why I have got this little girl 
round my neck? You don't want to know? 
Then you shall. She belongs to the Fairies. 
She's a fortune-teller. She can tell me all 
about you in a whisper, and can put me up to 
whether you're a-going to buy a lot or leave it. 
Now do you want a saw? No, she says you 
don't, because you're too clumsy to use one. 
Else here's a saw which would be a lifelong 
blessing to a handy man, at four shillings, at 
three and six, at three, at two and six, at two, 
at eighteenpence. But none of you shall have 
it at any price, on account of your well-known 
awkwardness which would make it manslaughter. 
The same objection applies to this set of three 
planes which I won't let you have neither, so 
don't bid for 'em. Now I am a-going to ask her 
what you do want. (Then I whispered, "Your 
head burns so, that I am afraid it hurts you bad, 
my pet," and she answered, without opening her 
heavy eyes, "Just a little, father.") Oh! This 
little fortune-teller says it's a memorandum-book 
you want. Then why didn't you mention it? 
Here it is. Look at it. Two hundred super-fine 
hot-pressed wire-wove pages--if you don't 
believe me, count 'em--ready ruled for your 
expenses, an everlastingly-pointed pencil to put 
'em down with, a double-bladed penknife to 
scratch 'em out with, a book of printed tables 
to calculate your income with, and a camp-stool 
to sit down upon while you give your mind to 
it! Stop! And an umbrella to keep the moon 
off when you give your mind to it on a pitch dark 
night. Now I won't ask you how much for 
the lot, but how little? How little are you 
thinking of? Don't be ashamed to mention it, 
because my fortune-teller knows already. (Then 
making believe to whisper, I kissed her, and she 
kissed me.) Why, she says you're thinking of 
as little as three and threepence! I couldn't 
have believed it, even of you, unless she told me. 
Three and threepence! And a set of printed 
tables in the lot that'll calculate your income 
up to forty thousand a year! With an income 
of forty thousand a year, you grudge three and 
sixpence. Well then, I'll tell you my opinion. 
I so despise the threepence, that I'd sooner 
take three shillings. There. For three shillings, 
three shillings, three shillings! Gone. 
Hand 'em over to the lucky man."</p>
<p>As there had been no bid at all, everybody 
looked about and grinned at everybody, while I 
touched little Sophy's face and asked her if 
she felt faint or giddy. "Not very, father. It 
will soon be over." Then turning from the 
pretty patient eyes, which were opened now, 
and seeing nothing but grins across my lighted 
grease-pot, I went on again in my Cheap Jack 
style. "Where's the butcher?" (My sorrowful 
eye had just caught sight of a fat young 
butcher on the outside of the crowd.) She 
says the good luck is the butcher's. "Where 
is he?" Everybody handed on the blushing 
butcher to the front, and there was a roar, and 
the butcher felt himself obliged to put his 
hand in his pocket and take the lot. The party 
so picked out, in general does feel obliged to 
take the lot--good four times out of six. Then 
we had another lot the counterpart of that one, 
and sold it sixpence cheaper, which is always 
wery much enjoyed. Then we had the spectacles. 
It ain't a special profitable lot, but I put 'em on, 
and I see what the Chancellor of the Exchequer 
is going to take off the taxes, and I see what the 
sweetheart of the young woman in the shawl is 
doing at home, and I see what the Bishops has 
got for dinner, and a deal more that seldom fails 
to fetch 'em up in their spirits; and the better 
their spirits, the better their bids. Then we 
had the ladies' lot--the teapot, tea-caddy, glass 
sugar basin, half a dozen spoons, and caudle-cup--and 
all the time I was making similar 
excuses to give a look or two and say a word 
or two to my poor child. It was while the 
second ladies' lot was holding 'em enchained that 
I felt her lift herself a little on my shoulder, to 
look across the dark street. "What troubles 
you, darling?" "Nothing troubles me, father. 
I am not at all troubled. But don't I 
see a pretty churchyard over there?" "Yes, 
my dear." "Kiss me twice, dear father, and 
lay me down to rest upon that churchyard 
grass so soft and green." I staggered back into 
the cart with her head dropped on my shoulder, 
and I says to her mother, "Quick. Shut the 
door! Don't let those laughing people see!" 
"What's the matter?" she cries. "O, woman, 
woman," I tells her, "you'll never catch my 
little Sophy by her hair again, for she has 
flown away from you!"</p>
<p>Maybe those were harder words than I 
meant 'em, but from that time forth my wife 
took to brooding, and would sit in the cart or 
walk beside it, hours at a stretch, with her arms 
crossed and her eyes looking on the ground. 
When her furies took her (which was rather 
seldomer than before) they took her in a new 
way, and she banged herself about to that extent 
that I was forced to hold her. She got 
none the better for a little drink now and then, 
and through some years I used to wonder as 
I plodded along at the old horse's head whether 
there was many carts upon the road that 
held so much dreariness as mine, for all my 
being looked up to as the King of the Cheap 
Jacks. So sad our lives went on till one 
summer evening, when as we were coming 
into Exeter out of the further West of England, 
we saw a woman beating a child in a 
cruel manner, who screamed, "Don't beat me! 
O mother, mother, mother!" Then my wife 
stopped her ears and ran away like a wild 
thing, and next day she was found in the river.</p>
<p>Me and my dog were all the company left in 
the cart now, and the dog learned to give a 
short bark when they wouldn't bid, and to give 
another and a nod of his head when I asked him: 
"Who said half-a-crown? Are you the 
gentleman, sir, that offered half-a-crown?" He 
attained to an immense heighth of popularity, 
and I shall always believe taught himself entirely 
out of his own head to growl at any person in 
the crowd that bid as low as sixpence. But he 
got to be well on in years, and one night when 
I was conwulsing York with the spectacles, he 
took a conwulsion on his own account upon the 
very footboard by me, and it finished him.</p>
<p>Being naturally of a tender turn, I had dreadful 
lonely feelings on me arter this. I conquered 
'em at selling times, having a reputation 
to keep (not to mention keeping myself), but 
they got me down in private and rolled upon me. 
That's often the way with us public characters. 
See us on the footboard, and you'd give pretty 
well anything you possess to be us. See us off 
the footboard, and you'd add a trifle to be off 
your bargain. It was under those circumstances 
that I come acquainted with a giant. I might 
have been too high to fall into conversation with 
him, had it not been for my lonely feelings. 
For the general rule is, going round the country, 
to draw the line at dressing up. When a man 
can't trust his getting a living to his undisguised 
abilities, you consider him below your sort. 
And this giant when on view figured as a 
Roman.</p>
<p>He was a languid young man, which I 
attribute to the distance betwixt his extremities. 
He had a little head and less in it, he had 
weak eyes and weak knees, and altogether you 
couldn't look at him without feeling that there 
was greatly too much of him both for his joints 
and his mind. But he was an amiable though 
timid young man (his mother let him out, and 
spent the money), and we come acquainted when 
he was walking to ease the horse betwixt two 
fairs. He was called Rinaldo di Velasco, his 
name being Pickleson.</p>
<p>This giant otherwise Pickleson mentioned to 
me under the seal of confidence, that beyond 
his being a burden to himself, his life was made 
a burden to him, by the cruelty of his master 
towards a step-daughter who was deaf and 
dumb. Her mother was dead, and she had no 
living soul to take her part, and was used most 
hard. She travelled with his master's caravan 
only because there was nowhere to leave her, 
and this giant otherwise Pickleson did go so 
far as to believe that his master often tried to 
lose her. He was such a very languid young 
man, that I don't know how long it didn't take 
him to get this story out, but it passed through 
his defective circulation to his top extremity in 
course of time.</p>
<p>When I heard this account from the giant 
otherwise Pickleson, and likewise that the poor 
girl had beautiful long dark hair, and was often 
pulled down by it and beaten, I couldn't see the 
giant through what stood in my eyes. Having 
wiped 'em, I give him sixpence (for he was kept 
as short as he was long), and he laid it out in 
two threepennorths of gin-and-water, which so 
brisked him up, that he sang the Favourite 
Comic of Shivery Shakey, ain't it cold. A 
popular effect which his master had tried every 
other means to get out of him as a Roman, 
wholly in vain.</p>
<p>His master's name was Mim, a wery hoarse 
man and I knew him to speak to. I went to 
that Fair as a mere civilian, leaving the cart 
outside the town, and I looked about the back 
of the Vans while the performing was going on, 
and at last sitting dozing against a muddy cart-wheel, 
I come upon the poor girl who was deaf 
and dumb. At the first look I might almost 
have judged that she had escaped from the Wild 
Beast Show, but at the second I thought better 
of her, and thought that if she was more cared 
for and more kindly used she would be like my 
child. She was just the same age that my own 
daughter would have been, if her pretty head 
had not fell down upon my shoulder that 
unfortunate night.</p>
<p>To cut it short, I spoke confidential to Mim 
while he was beating the gong outside betwixt 
two lots of Pickleson's publics, and I put it to 
him, "She lies heavy on your own hands; 
what'll you take for her?" Mim was a most 
ferocious swearer. Suppressing that part of his 
reply, which was much the longest part, his reply 
was, "A pair of braces." "Now I'll tell you," 
says I, "what I'm a going to do with you. I'm 
a going to fetch you half a dozen pair of the 
primest braces in the cart, and then to take her 
away with me." Says Mim (again ferocious), 
"I'll believe it when I've got the goods, and no 
sooner." I made all the haste I could, lest he 
should think twice of it, and the bargain was 
completed, which Pickleson he was thereby so 
relieved in his mind that he come out at his little 
back door, longways like a serpent, and give 
us Shivery Shakey in a whisper among the wheels 
at parting.</p>
<p>It was happy days for both of us when Sophy 
and me began to travel in the cart. I at once 
give her the name of Sophy, to put her ever 
towards me in the attitude of my own daughter. 
We soon made out to begin to understand one 
another through the goodness of the Heavens, 
when she knowed that I meant true and kind by 
her. In a very little time she was wonderful fond 
of me. You have no idea what it is to have any 
body wonderful fond of you, unless you have 
been got down and rolled upon by the lonely 
feelings that I have mentioned as having once 
got the better of me.</p>
<p>You'd have laughed--or the rewerse--it's 
according to your disposition--if you could have 
seen me trying to teach Sophy. At first I was 
helped--you'd never guess by what--milestones. 
I got some large alphabets in a box, all 
the letters separate on bits of bone, and say we 
was going to WINDSOR, I give her those letters in 
that order, and then at every milestone I showed 
her those same letters in that same order again, 
and pointed towards the abode of royalty. 
Another time I give her C A R T, and then 
chalked the same upon the cart. Another time 
I give her D O C T O R   M A R I G O L D, 
and hung a corresponding inscription outside 
my waistcoat. People that met us might stare 
a bit and laugh, but what did <em>I</em> care if she 
caught the idea? She caught it after long 
patience and trouble, and then we did begin to 
get on swimmingly, I believe you! At first she 
was a little given to consider me the cart, and 
the cart the abode of royalty, but that soon 
wore off.</p>
<p>We had our signs, too, and they was hundreds 
in number. Sometimes, she would sit looking at 
me and considering hard how to communicate 
with me about something fresh--how to ask me 
what she wanted explained--and then she was 
(or I thought she was; what does it signify?) so 
like my child with those years added to her, that 
I half believed it was herself, trying to tell me 
where she had been to up in the skies, and what 
she had seen since that unhappy night when she 
flied away. She had a pretty face, and now that 
there was no one to drag at her bright dark hair 
and it was all in order, there was a something 
touching in her looks that made the cart most 
peaceful and most quiet, though not at all 
melancolly. [N.B. In the Cheap Jack patter, 
we generally sound it, lemonjolly, and it gets a 
laugh.]</p>
<p>The way she learnt to understand any look of 
mine was truly surprising. When I sold of a 
night, she would sit in the cart unseen by them 
outside, and would give a eager look into my 
eyes when I looked in, and would hand me 
straight the precise article or articles I wanted. 
And then she would clap her hands and laugh for 
joy. And as for me, seeing her so bright, and 
remembering what she was when I first lighted 
on her, starved and beaten and ragged, leaning 
asleep against the muddy cart-wheel, it give 
me such heart that I gained a greater heighth of 
reputation than ever, and I put Pickleson down 
(by the name of Mim's Travelling Giant otherwise 
Pickleson) for a fypunnote in my will.</p>
<p>This happiness went on in the cart till she 
was sixteen year old. By which time I began to 
feel not satisfied that I had done my whole duty 
by her, and to consider that she ought to have 
better teaching than I could give her. It drew 
a many tears on both sides when I commenced 
explaining my views to her, but what's right is 
right and you can't neither by tears nor laughter 
do away with its character.</p>
<p>So I took her hand in mine, and I went with 
her one day to the Deaf and Dumb Establishment 
in London, and when the gentleman come 
to speak to us, I says to him: "Now I'll tell 
you what I'll do with you sir. I am nothing 
but a Cheap Jack, but of late years I have laid 
by for a rainy day notwithstanding. This is my 
only daughter (adopted) and you can't produce 
a deafer nor a dumber. Teach her the most 
that can be taught her, in the shortest separation 
that can be named--state the figure for it--and 
I am game to put the money down. I won't 
bate you a single farthing sir but I'll put down 
the money here and now, and I'll thankfully 
throw you in a pound to take it. There!" The 
gentleman smiled, and then, "Well, well," says 
he, "I must first know what she has learnt 
already. How do you communicate with her?" 
Then I showed him, and she wrote in printed 
writing many names of things and so forth, and 
we held some sprightly conversation, Sophy and 
me, about a little story in a book which the 
gentleman showed her and which she was able to 
read. "This is most extraordinary," says the 
gentleman; "is it possible that you have been her 
only teacher?" "I have been her only teacher, 
sir," I says, "besides herself." "Then," says 
the gentleman, and more acceptable words was 
never spoke to me, "you're a clever fellow, and 
a good fellow." This he makes known to Sophy, 
who kisses his hands, claps her own, and laughs 
and cries upon it.</p>
<p>We saw the gentleman four times in all, and 
when he took down my name and asked how in 
the world it ever chanced to be Doctor, it come 
out that he was own nephew by the sister's 
side, if you'll believe me, to the very Doctor 
that I was called after. This made our footing 
still easier, and he says to me:</p>
<p>"Now Marigold, tell me what more do you 
want your adopted daughter to know?"</p>
<p>"I want her sir to be cut off from the world as 
little as can be, considering her deprivations, and 
therefore to be able to read whatever is wrote, 
with perfect ease and pleasure."</p>
<p>"My good fellow," urges the gentleman, 
opening his eyes wide, "why <em>I</em> can't do that 
myself!"</p>
<p>I took his joke and give him a laugh (knowing 
by experience how flat you fall without it) 
and I mended my words accordingly.</p>
<p>"What do you mean to do with her afterwards?" 
asks the gentleman, with a sort of a 
doubtful eye. "To take her about the country?"</p>
<p>"In the cart sir, but only in the cart. She 
will live a private life, you understand, in the 
cart. I should never think of bringing her 
infirmities before the public. I wouldn't make a 
show of her, for any money."</p>
<p>The gentleman nodded and seemed to approve.</p>
<p>"Well," says he, "can you part with her for 
two years?"</p>
<p>"To do her that good--yes, sir."</p>
<p>"There's another question," says the gentleman, 
looking towards her: "Can she part with 
you for two years?"</p>
<p>I don't know that it was a harder matter of 
itself (for the other was hard enough to me), 
but it was harder to get over. However, she 
was pacified to it at last, and the separation 
betwixt us was settled. How it cut up both of us 
when it took place, and when I left her at the 
door in the dark of an evening, I don't tell. But 
I know this:--remembering that night, I shall 
never pass that same establishment without a 
heart-ache and a swelling in the throat, and I 
couldn't put you up the best of lots in sight of 
it with my usual spirit--no, not even the gun, 
nor the pair of spectacles--for five hundred 
pound reward from the Secretary of State for 
the Home Department, and throw in the honour 
of putting my legs under his mahogany arterwards.</p>
<p>Still, the loneliness that followed in the cart 
was not the old loneliness, because there was a 
term put to it however long to look forward to, 
and because I could think, when I was anyways 
down, that she belonged to me and I 
belonged to her. Always planning for her coming 
back, I bought in a few months' time another 
cart, and what do you think I planned to do 
with it? I'll tell you. I planned to fit it up 
with shelves, and books for her reading, and to 
have a seat in it where I could sit and see her 
read, and think that I had been her first teacher. 
Not hurrying over the job, I had the fittings 
knocked together in contriving ways under my 
own inspection, and here was her bed in a berth 
with curtains, and there was her reading-table, 
and here was her writing-desk, and elsewhere 
was her books in rows upon rows, picters and 
no picters, bindings and no bindings, gilt-edged 
and plain, just as I could pick 'em up for her 
in lots up and down the country, North and 
South and West and East, Winds liked best 
and winds liked least, Here and there and 
gone astray, Over the hills and far away. And 
when I had got together pretty well as many 
books as the cart would neatly hold, a new 
scheme come into my head which, as it turned 
out, kept my time and attention a good deal 
employed and helped me over the two years 
stile.</p>
<p>Without being of an awaricious temper, I like 
to be the owner of things. I shouldn't wish, 
for instance, to go partners with yourself in the 
Cheap Jack cart. It's not that I mistrust you, 
but that I'd rather know it was mine. 
Similarly, very likely you'd rather know it was 
yours. Well! A kind of a jealousy began to 
creep into my mind when I reflected that all 
those books would have been read by other 
people long before they was read by her. It 
seemed to take away from her being the owner 
of 'em like. In this way, the question got into 
my head:--Couldn't I have a book new-made 
express for her, which she should be the first to 
read?</p>
<p>It pleased me, that thought did, and as I 
never was a man to let a thought sleep (you 
must wake up all the whole family of thoughts 
you've got and burn their nightcaps, or you 
won't do in the cheap Jack line), I set to 
work at it. Considering that I was in the habit 
of changing so much about the country, and 
that I should have to find out a literary character 
here to make a deal with, and another literary 
character there to make a deal with, as 
opportunities presented, I hit on the plan that 
this same book should be a general miscellaneous 
lot--like the razors, flat-iron, chronometer 
watch, dinner plates, rolling-pin, and 
looking-glass--and shouldn't be offered as a single 
indiwidual article like the spectacles or the gun. 
When I had come to that conclusion, I come 
to another, which shall likewise be yours.</p>
<p>Often had I regretted that she never had 
heard me on the footboard, and that she never 
could hear me. It ain't that <em>I</em> am vain, but 
that <em>you</em> don't like to put your own light under 
a bushel. What's the worth of your reputation, 
if you can't convey the reason for it to 
the person you most wish to value it? Now 
I'll put it to you. Is it worth sixpence, 
fippence, fourpence, threepence, twopence, a 
penny, a halfpenny, a farthing? No, it ain't. 
Not worth a farthing. Very well then. My 
conclusion was, that I would begin her book 
with some account of myself. So that, through 
reading a specimen or two of me on the 
footboard, she might form an idea of my merits 
there. I was aware that I couldn't do myself 
justice. A man can't write his eye (at least <em>I</em> 
don't know how to), nor yet can a man write his 
voice, nor the rate of his talk, nor the quickness 
of his action, nor his general spicy way. But 
he can write his turns of speech, when he 
is a public speaker--and indeed I have 
heard that he very often does, before he 
speaks 'em.</p>
<p>Well! Having formed that resolution, then 
come the question of a name. How did I 
hammer that hot iron into shape? This way. 
The most difficult explanation I had ever had 
with her was, how I come to be called Doctor, 
and yet was no Doctor. After all, I felt that I 
had failed of getting it correctly into her mind, 
with my utmost pains. But trusting to her 
improvement in the two years, I thought that I 
might trust to her understanding it when she 
should come to read it as put down by my own 
hand. Then I thought I would try a joke with 
her and watch how it took, by which of 
itself I might fully judge of her understanding 
it. We had first discovered the mistake we had 
dropped into, through her having asked me to 
prescribe for her when she had supposed me to 
be a Doctor in a medical point of view, so 
thinks I, "Now, if I give this book the name 
of my Prescriptions, and if she catches the idea 
that my only Prescriptions are for her amusement 
and interest--to make her laugh in a 
pleasant way, or to make her cry in a pleasant 
way--it will be a delightful proof to both of us 
that we have got over our difficulty. It fell 
out to absolute perfection. For when she saw 
the book, as I had it got up--the printed and 
pressed book--lying on her desk in her cart, and 
saw the title, DOCTOR MARIGOLD'S PRESCRIPTIONS, 
she looked at me for a moment with astonishment, 
then fluttered the leaves, then broke 
out a laughing in the charmingest way, then felt 
her pulse and shook her head, then turned the 
pages pretending to read them most attentive, 
then kissed the book to me, and put it to her 
bosom with both her hands. I never was better 
pleased in all my life!</p>
<p>But let me not anticipate. (I take that expression 
out of a lot of romances I bought for her. 
I never opened a single one of 'em--and I have 
opened many--but I found the romancer saying 
"let me not anticipate." Which being so, I 
wonder why he did anticipate, or who asked him 
to it.) Let me not, I say, anticipate. This same 
book took up all my spare time. It was no 
play to get the other articles together in the 
general miscellaneous lot, but when it come 
to my own article! There! I couldn't have 
believed the blotting, nor yet the buckling 
to at it, nor the patience over it. Which 
again is like the footboard. The public have 
no idea.</p>
<p>At last it was done, and the two years' time 
was gone after all the other time before it, and 
where it's all gone to, Who knows? The new cart 
was finished--yellow outside, relieved with 
wermillion and brass fittings--the old horse was 
put in it, a new 'un and a boy being laid on for 
the Cheap Jack cart--and I cleaned myself up to 
go and fetch her. Bright cold weather it was, 
cart-chimneys smoking, carts pitched private 
on a piece of waste ground over at Wandsworth 
where you may see 'em from the Sou' Western 
Railway when not upon the road. (Look out 
of the right-hand window going down.)</p>
<p>"Marigold," says the gentleman, giving his 
hand hearty, "I am very glad to see you."</p>
<p>"Yet I have my doubts, sir," says I, "if you 
can be half as glad to see me, as I am to see 
you."</p>
<p>"The time has appeared so long; has it, 
Marigold?"</p>
<p>"I won't say that, sir, considering its real 
length; but----"</p>
<p>"What a start, my good fellow!"</p>
<p>Ah! I should think it was! Grown such a 
woman, so pretty, so intelligent, so expressive! 
I knew then that she must be really like my 
child, or I could never have known her, standing 
quiet by the door.</p>
<p>"You are affected," says the gentleman in a 
kindly manner.</p>
<p>"I feel, sir," says I, "that I am but a rough 
chap in a sleeved waistcoat."</p>
<p>"<em>I</em> feel," says the gentleman, "that it was 
you who raised her from misery and degradation, 
and brought her into communication with 
her kind. But why do we converse alone 
together, when we can converse so well with her? 
Address her in your own way."</p>
<p>"I am such a rough chap in a sleeved 
waistcoat, sir," says I, "and she is such a 
graceful woman, and she stands so quiet at the 
door!"</p>
<p>"Try if she moves at the old sign," says the 
gentleman.</p>
<p>They had got it up together o' purpose to 
please me! For when I give her the old sign, she 
rushed to my feet, and dropped upon her knees, 
holding up her hands to me with pouring tears 
of love and joy; and when I took her hands 
and lifted her, she clasped me round the neck 
and lay there; and I don't know what a fool I 
didn't make of myself, until we all three settled 
down into talking without sound, as if there 
was a something soft and pleasant spread over 
the whole world for us.</p>
<break/>
<p>Now I'll tell you what I am a going to do 
with you. I am a going to offer you the general 
miscellaneous lot, her own book, never read by 
anybody else but me, added to and completed 
by me after her first reading of it, eight-and-forty 
printed pages, six-and-ninety columns, 
Whiting's own work, Beaufort House to wit, 
thrown off by the steam-ingine, best of paper, 
beautiful green wrapper, folded like clean linen 
come home from the clear-starcher's, and so 
exquisitely stitched that, regarded as a piece 
of needlework alone it's better than the sampler 
of a seamstress undergoing a Competitive 
Examination for Starvation before the Civil 
Service Commissioners--and I offer the lot 
for what? For eight pound? Not so much. 
For six pound? Less. For four pound? 
Why, I hardly expect you to believe me, but 
that's the sum. Four pound! The stitching 
alone cost half as much again. Here's 
forty-eight original pages, ninety-six original 
columns, for four pound. You want more for 
the money? Take it. Three whole pages of 
advertisements of thrilling interest thrown in for 
nothing. Read 'em and believe 'em. More? 
My best of wishes for your merry Christmases 
and your happy New Years, your long lives and 
your true prosperities. Worth twenty pound 
good if they are delivered as I send them. 
Remember! Here's a final prescription added, 
"To be taken for life," which will tell you 
how the cart broke down, and where the journey 
ended. You think Four Pound too much? And 
still you think so? Come! I'll tell you what 
then. Say Four Pence, and keep the secret.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="Not To Be Taken At Bed-Time."/>
<p>This is the legend of a house called the Devil's 
Inn, standing in the heather on the top of the 
Connemara mountains, in a shallow valley 
hollowed between five peaks. Tourists sometimes 
come in sight of it on September evenings; 
a crazy and weather-stained apparition, with the 
sun glaring at it angrily between the hills, and 
striking its shattered window-panes. Guides 
are known to shun it, however.</p>
<p>The house was built by a stranger, who came 
no one knew whence, and whom the people 
nicknamed Coll Dhu (Black Coll), because of his 
sullen bearing and solitary habits. His dwelling 
they called the Devil's Inn, because no tired 
traveller had ever been asked to rest under its roof, 
nor friend known to cross its threshold. No 
one bore him company in his retreat but a 
wizen-faced old man, who shunned the good-morrow 
of the trudging peasant when he made 
occasional excursions to the nearest village for 
provisions for himself and master, and who was 
as secret as a stone concerning all the antecedents 
of both.</p>
<p>For the first year of their residence in the 
country, there had been much speculation as to 
who they were, and what they did with themselves 
up there among the clouds and eagles. 
Some said that Coll Dhu was a scion of the old 
family from whose hands the surrounding lands 
had passed; and that, embittered by poverty 
and pride, he had come to bury himself in solitude, 
and brood over his misfortunes. Others 
hinted of crime, and flight from another country; 
others again whispered of those who were 
cursed from their birth, and could never smile, 
nor yet make friends with a fellow-creature till 
the day of their death. But when two years 
had passed, the wonder had somewhat died out, 
and Coll Dhu was little thought of, except when 
a herd looking for sheep crossed the track of a 
big dark man walking the mountains gun in 
hand, to whom he did not dare say "Lord save 
you!" or when a housewife rocking her cradle 
of a winter's night, crossed herself as a gust of 
storm thundered over her cabin-roof, with the 
exclamation, "Oh, then, it's Coll Dhu that has 
enough o' the fresh air about his head up there 
this night, the crature!"</p>
<p>Coll Dhu had lived thus in his solitude for some 
years, when it became known that Colonel 
Blake, the new lord of the soil, was coming to 
visit the country. By climbing one of the peaks 
encircling his eyrie, Coll could look sheer down a 
mountain-side, and see in miniature beneath him, 
a grey old dwelling with ivied chimneys and 
weather-slated walls, standing amongst straggling 
trees and grim warlike rocks, that gave it the 
look of a fortress, gazing out to the Atlantic 
for ever with the eager eyes of all its windows, 
as if demanding perpetually, "What tidings from 
the New World?"</p>
<p>He could see now masons and carpenters 
crawling about below, like ants in the sun, 
overrunning the old house from base to chimney, 
daubing here and knocking there, tumbling down 
walls that looked to Coll, up among the clouds, 
like a handful of jackstones, and building up 
others that looked like the toy fences in a 
child's Farm. Throughout several months he 
must have watched the busy ants at their task 
of breaking and mending again, disfiguring and 
beautifying; but when all was done he had not 
the curiosity to stride down and admire the 
handsome paneling of the new billiard-room, 
nor yet the fine view which the enlarged 
bay-window in the drawing-room commanded of the 
watery highway to Newfoundland.</p>
<p>Deep summer was melting into autumn, and 
the amber streaks of decay were beginning 
to creep out and trail over the ripe purple of 
moor and mountain, when Colonel Blake, his 
only daughter, and a party of friends, arrived in 
the country. The grey house below was alive 
with gaiety, but Coll Dhu no longer found an 
interest in observing it from his eyrie. When 
he watched the sun rise or set, he chose to ascend 
some crag that looked on no human habitation. 
When he sallied forth on his excursions, 
gun in hand, he set his face towards the most 
isolated wastes, dipping into the loneliest valleys, 
and scaling the nakedest ridges. When he 
came by chance within call of other excursionists, 
gun in hand he plunged into the shade of 
some hollow, and avoided an encounter. Yet it 
was fated, for all that, that he and Colonel Blake 
should meet.</p>
<p>Towards the evening of one bright September 
day, the wind changed, and in half an hour the 
mountains were wrapped in a thick blinding mist. 
Coll Dhu was far from his den, but so well had he 
searched these mountains, and inured himself to 
their climate, that neither storm, rain, nor fog, 
had power to disturb him. But while he stalked 
on his way, a faint and agonised cry from a 
human voice reached him through the smothering 
mist. He quickly tracked the sound, and gained 
the side of a man who was stumbling along in 
danger of death at every step.</p>
<p>"Follow me!" said Coll Dhu to this man, 
and, in an hour's time, brought him safely to the 
lowlands, and up to the walls of the eager-eyed 
mansion.</p>
<p>"I am Colonel Blake," said the frank soldier, 
when, having left the fog behind him, they stood 
in the starlight under the lighted windows. 
"Pray tell me quickly to whom I owe my 
life."</p>
<p>As he spoke, he glanced up at his benefactor, 
a large man with a sombre sun-burned 
face.</p>
<p>"Colonel Blake," said Coll Dhu, after a strange 
pause, "your father suggested to my father to 
stake his estates at the gaming table. They 
were staked, and the tempter won. Both are 
dead; but you and I live, and I have sworn to 
injure you."</p>
<p>The colonel laughed good humouredly at the 
uneasy face above him.</p>
<p>"And you began to keep your oath to-night 
by saving my life?" said he. "Come! I am a 
soldier, and know how to meet an enemy; but I 
had far rather meet a friend. I shall not be happy 
till you have eaten my salt. We have merrymaking 
to-night in honour of my daughter's 
birthday. Come in and join us?"</p>
<p>Coll Dhu looked at the earth doggedly.</p>
<p>"I have told you," he said, "who and what 
I am, and I will not cross your threshold."</p>
<p>But at this moment (so runs my story) a 
French window opened among the flower-beds 
by which they were standing, and a vision 
appeared which stayed the words on Coll's tongue. 
A stately girl, clad in white satin, stood framed 
in the ivied window, with the warm light from 
within streaming around her richly-moulded 
figure into the night. Her face was as pale as 
her gown, her eyes were swimming in tears, but a 
firm smile sat on her lips as she held out both 
hands to her father. The light behind her, 
touched the glistening folds of her dress--the 
lustrous pearls round her throat--the coronet of 
blood-red roses which encircled the knotted 
braids at the back of her head. Satin, pearls, 
and roses--had Coll Dhu, of the Devil's Inn, 
never set eyes upon such things before?</p>
<p>Evleen Blake was no nervous tearful miss. 
A few quick words--"Thank God! you're safe; 
the rest have been home an hour"--and a tight 
pressure of her father's fingers between her own 
jewelled hands, were all that betrayed the 
uneasiness she had suffered.</p>
<p>"Faith, my love, I owe my life to this brave 
gentleman!" said the blithe colonel. "Press 
him to come in and be our guest, Evleen. He 
wants to retreat to his mountains, and lose himself 
again in the fog where I found him; or, 
rather, where he found me! Come, sir" (to 
Coll), "you must surrender to this fair besieger."</p>
<p>An introduction followed. "Coll Dhu!" 
murmured Evleen Blake, for she had heard the 
common tales of him; but with a frank welcome 
she invited her father's preserver to taste the 
hospitality of that father's house.</p>
<p>"I beg you to come in, sir," she said; "but 
for you our gaiety must have been turned into 
mourning. A shadow will be upon our mirth 
if our benefactor disdains to join in it."</p>
<p>With a sweet grace, mingled with a certain 
hauteur from which she was never free, 
she extended her white hand to the tall looming 
figure outside the window; to have it grasped 
and wrung in a way that made the proud girl's 
eyes flash their amazement, and the same little 
hand clench itself in displeasure, when it had 
hid itself like an outraged thing among the 
shining folds of her gown. Was this Coll Dhu 
mad, or rude?</p>
<p>The guest no longer refused to enter, but 
followed the white figure into a little study 
where a lamp burned; and the gloomy stranger, 
the bluff colonel, and the young mistress of the 
house, were fully discovered to each other's 
eyes. Evleen glanced at the new comer's dark 
face, and shuddered with a feeling of indescribable 
dread and dislike; then, to her father, 
accounted for the shudder after a popular 
fashion, saying lightly: "There is some one 
walking over my grave."</p>
<p>So Coll Dhu was present at Evleen Blake's 
birthday ball. Here he was, under a roof 
which ought to have been his own, a stranger, 
known only by a nickname, shunned and solitary. 
Here he was, who had lived among the 
eagles and foxes, lying in wait with a fell purpose, 
to be revenged on the son of his father's foe 
for poverty and disgrace, for the broken heart 
of a dead mother, for the loss of a self-slaughtered 
father, for the dreary scattering of brothers and 
sisters. Here he stood, a Samson shorn of his 
strength; and all because a haughty girl had 
melting eyes, a winning mouth, and looked 
radiant in satin and roses.</p>
<p>Peerless where many were lovely, she moved 
among her friends, trying to be unconscious 
of the gloomy fire of those strange eyes which 
followed her unweariedly wherever she went. 
And when her father begged her to be gracious 
to the unsocial guest whom he would fain 
conciliate, she courteously conducted him to see 
the new picture-gallery adjoining the drawing-rooms; 
explained under what odd circumstances 
the colonel had picked up this little painting or 
that; using every delicate art her pride would 
allow to achieve her father's purpose, whilst 
maintaining at the same time her own personal 
reserve; trying to divert the guest's oppressive 
attention from herself to the objects 
for which she claimed his notice. Coll Dhu 
followed his conductress and listened to her 
voice, but what she said mattered nothing; nor 
did she wring many words of comment or reply 
from his lips, until they paused in a retired corner 
where the light was dim, before a window from 
which the curtain was withdrawn. The sashes 
were open, and nothing was visible but water; 
the night Atlantic, with the full moon riding high 
above a bank of clouds, making silvery tracks 
outward towards the distance of infinite mystery 
dividing two worlds. Here the following little 
scene is said to have been enacted.</p>
<p>"This window of my father's own planning, 
is it not creditable to his taste?" said the young 
hostess, as she stood, herself glittering like a 
dream of beauty, looking on the moonlight.</p>
<p>Coll Dhu made no answer; but suddenly, it 
is said, asked her for a rose from a cluster of 
flowers that nestled in the lace on her bosom.</p>
<p>For the second time that night Evleen Blake's 
eyes flashed with no gentle light. But this man 
was the saviour of her father. She broke off a 
blossom, and with such good grace, and also 
with such queen-like dignity as she might 
assume, presented it to him. Whereupon, 
not only was the rose seized, but also the hand 
that gave it, which was hastily covered with 
kisses.</p>
<p>Then her anger burst upon him.</p>
<p>"Sir," she cried, "if you are a gentleman 
you must be mad! If you are not mad, then 
you are not a gentleman!"</p>
<p>"Be merciful," said Coll Dhu; "I love you. 
My God, I never loved a woman before! Ah!" 
he cried, as a look of disgust crept over her 
face, "you hate me. You shuddered the first 
time your eyes met mine. I love you, and you 
hate me!"</p>
<p>"I do," cried Evleen, vehemently, forgetting 
everything but her indignation. "Your presence 
is like something evil to me. Love me?--your 
looks poison me. Pray, sir, talk no more to me 
in this strain."</p>
<p>"I will trouble you no longer," said Coll Dhu. 
And, stalking to the window, he placed one 
powerful hand upon the sash, and vaulted from 
it out of her sight.</p>
<break/>
<p>Bare-headed as he was, Coll Dhu strode off 
to the mountains, but not towards his own 
home. All the remaining dark hours of that 
night he is believed to have walked the labyrinths 
of the hills, until dawn began to scatter the clouds 
with a high wind. Fasting, and on foot from sunrise 
the morning before, he was then glad enough 
to see a cabin right in his way. Walking in, he 
asked for water to drink, and a corner where 
he might throw himself to rest.</p>
<p>There was a wake in the house, and the 
kitchen was full of people, all wearied out with 
the night's watch; old men were dozing over 
their pipes in the chimney-corner, and here and 
there a woman was fast asleep with her head on a 
neighbour's knee. All who were awake crossed 
themselves when Coll Dhu's figure darkened the 
door, because of his evil name; but an old man 
of the house invited him in, and offering him 
milk, and promising him a roasted potato 
by-and-by, conducted him to a small room off the 
kitchen, one end of which was strewed with 
heather, and where there were only two women 
sitting gossiping over a fire.</p>
<p>"A thraveller," said the old man, nodding 
his head at the women, who nodded back, as if 
to say "he has the traveller's right." And 
Coll Dhu flung himself on the heather, in the 
furthest corner of the narrow room.</p>
<p>The women suspended their talk for a while; 
but presently, guessing the intruder to be 
asleep, resumed it in voices above a whisper. 
There was but a patch of window with the grey 
dawn behind it, but Coll could see the figures 
by the firelight over which they bent: an old 
woman sitting forward with her withered hands 
extended to the embers, and a girl reclining 
against the hearth wall, with her healthy face, 
bright eyes, and crimson draperies, glowing by 
turns in the flickering blaze.</p>
<p>"I do' know," said the girl, "but it's the 
quarest marriage iver I h'ard of. Sure it's not 
three weeks since he tould right an' left that he 
hated her like poison!"</p>
<p>"Whist, asthoreen!" said the colliagh, bending 
forward confidentially; "throth an' we all 
know that o' him. But what could he do, the 
crature! When she put the burragh-bos on 
him!"</p>
<p>"The <em>what</em>?" asked the girl.</p>
<p>"Then the burragh-bos machree-o? That's 
the spanchel o' death, avourneen; an' well she 
has him tethered to her now, bad luck to 
her!"</p>
<p>The old woman rocked herself and stifled 
the Irish cry breaking from her wrinkled lips 
by burying her face in her cloak.</p>
<p>"But what is it?" asked the girl, eagerly. 
"What's the burragh-bos, anyways, an' where 
did she get it?"</p>
<p>"Och, och! it's not fit for comin' over to 
young ears, but cuggir (whisper), acushla! It's 
a sthrip o' the skin o' a corpse, peeled from the 
crown o' the head to the heel, without crack or 
split, or the charrm's broke; an' that, rowled 
up, an' put on a sthring roun' the neck o' the wan 
that's cowld by the wan that wants to be loved. 
An' sure enough it puts the fire in their hearts, 
hot an' sthrong, afore twinty-four hours is 
gone."</p>
<p>The girl had started from her lazy attitude, 
and gazed at her companion with eyes dilated 
by horror.</p>
<p>"Marciful Saviour!" she cried. "Not a sowl 
on airth would bring the curse out o' heaven by 
sich a black doin'!"</p>
<p>"Aisy, Biddeen alanna! an' there's wan that 
does it, an' isn't the divil. Arrah, asthoreen, 
did ye niver hear tell o' Pexie na Pishrogie, 
that lives betune two hills o' Maam Turk?"</p>
<p>"I h'ard o' her," said the girl, breathlessly.</p>
<p>"Well, sorra bit lie, but it's hersel' that does 
it. She'll do it for money any day. Sure they 
hunted her from the graveyard o' Salruck, 
where she had the dead raised; an' glory be to 
God! they would ha' murthered her, only they 
missed her thracks, an' couldn't bring it home to 
her afther."</p>
<p>"Whist, a-wauher" (my mother), said the 
girl; "here's the thraveller gettin' up to set off 
on his road again! Och, then, it's the short 
rest he tuk, the sowl!"</p>
<p>It was enough for Coll, however. He had 
got up, and now went back to the kitchen, 
where the old man had caused a dish of potatoes 
to be roasted, and earnestly pressed his 
visitor to sit down and eat of them. This Coll 
did readily; having recruited his strength by a 
meal, he betook himself to the mountains again, 
just as the rising sun was flashing among the 
waterfalls, and sending the night mists drifting 
down the glens. By sundown the same evening 
he was striding over the hills of Maam Turk, 
asking of herds his way to the cabin of one Pexie 
na Pishrogie.</p>
<p>In a hovel on a brown desolate heath, with 
scared-looking hills flying off into the distance 
on every side, he found Pexie: a yellow-faced 
hag, dressed in a dark-red blanket, with elf-locks 
of coarse black hair protruding from under an 
orange kerchief swathed round her wrinkled 
jaws. She was bending over a pot upon her 
fire, where herbs were simmering, and she looked 
up with an evil glance when Coll Dhu darkened 
her door.</p>
<p>"The burragh-bos is it her honour wants?" 
she asked, when he had made known his errand. 
"Ay, ay; but the arighad, the arighad (money) 
for Pexie. The burragh-bos is ill to get."</p>
<p>"I will pay," said Coll Dhu, laying a sovereign 
on the bench before her.</p>
<p>The witch sprang upon it, and chuckling, 
bestowed on her visitor a glance which made even 
Coll Dhu shudder.</p>
<p>"Her honour is a fine king," she said, "an' 
her is fit to get the burragh-bos. Ha! ha! her 
sall get the burragh-bos from Pexie. But the 
arighad is not enough. More, more!"</p>
<p>She stretched out her claw-like hand, and 
Coll dropped another sovereign into it. Whereupon 
she fell into more horrible convulsions of 
delight.</p>
<p>"Hark ye!" cried Coll. "I have paid you 
well, but if your infernal charm does not work, 
I will have you hunted for a witch!"</p>
<p>"Work!" cried Pexie, rolling up her eyes. "If 
Pexie's charrm not work, then her honour come 
back here an' carry these bits o' mountain away 
on her back. Ay, her will work. If the colleen 
hate her honour like the old diaoul hersel', still an' 
withal her will love her honour like her own 
white sowl afore the sun sets or rises. That, 
(with a furtive leer,) or the colleen dhas go wild 
mad afore wan hour."</p>
<p>"Hag!" returned Coll Dhu; "the last part 
is a hellish invention of your own. I heard 
nothing of madness. If you want more money, 
speak out, but play none of your hideous tricks 
on me."</p>
<p>The witch fixed her cunning eyes on him, and 
took her cue at once from his passion.</p>
<p>"Her honour guess thrue," she simpered; 
"it is only the little bit more arighad poor 
Pexie want."</p>
<p>Again the skinny hand was extended. Coll 
Dhu shrank from touching it, and threw his 
gold upon the table.</p>
<p>"King, king!" chuckled Pexie. "Her honour 
is a grand king. Her honour is fit to get the 
burragh-bos. The colleen dhas sall love her 
like her own white sowl. Ha, ha!"</p>
<p>"When shall I get it?" asked Coll Dhu, impatiently.</p>
<p>"Her honour sall come back to Pexie in so 
many days, do-deag (twelve), so many days, fur 
that the burragh-bos is hard to get. The lonely 
graveyard is far away, an' the dead man is hard 
to raise----"</p>
<p>"Silence!" cried Coll Dhu; "not a word 
more. I will have your hideous charm, but 
what it is, or where you get it, I will not 
know."</p>
<p>Then, promising to come back in twelve days, 
he took his departure. Turning to look back 
when a little way across the heath, he saw Pexie 
gazing after him, standing on her black hill in 
relief against the lurid flames of the dawn, seeming 
to his dark imagination like a fury with all 
hell at her back.</p>
<p>At the appointed time Coll Dhu got the promised 
charm. He sewed it with perfumes into 
a cover of cloth of gold, and slung it to a 
fine-wrought chain. Lying in a casket which had once 
held the jewels of Coil's broken-hearted mother, 
it looked a glittering bauble enough. Meantime 
the people of the mountains were cursing 
over their cabin fires, because there had been 
another unholy raid upon their graveyard, and 
were banding themselves to hunt the criminal 
down.</p>
<break/>
<p>A fortnight passed. How or where could 
Coll Dhu find an opportunity to put the charm 
round the neck of the colonel's proud daughter? 
More gold was dropped into Pexie's greedy 
claw, and then she promised to assist him in his 
dilemma.</p>
<p>Next morning the witch dressed herself in 
decent garb, smoothed her elf-locks under a 
snowy cap, smoothed the evil wrinkles out of her 
face, and with a basket on her arm locked the 
door of the hovel, and took her way to the lowlands. 
Pexie seemed to have given up her 
disreputable calling for that of a simple 
mushroom-gatherer. The housekeeper at the 
grey house bought poor Muireade's mushrooms 
of her every morning. Every morning she left 
unfailingly a nosegay of wild flowers for Miss 
Evleen Blake, "God bless her! She had never 
seen the darling young lady with her own two 
longing eyes, but sure hadn't she heard tell of 
her sweet purty face, miles away!" And at last, 
one morning, whom should she meet but Miss 
Evleen herself returning alone from a ramble. 
Whereupon poor Muireade "made bold" to 
present her flowers in person.</p>
<p>"Ah," said Evleen, "it is you who leave me 
the flowers every morning? They are very 
sweet."</p>
<p>Muireade had sought her only for a look at 
her beautiful face. And now that she had seen 
it, as bright as the sun, and as fair as the lily, 
she would take up her basket and go away 
contented. Yet she lingered a little longer.</p>
<p>"My lady never walk up big mountain?" said 
Pexie.</p>
<p>"No," Evleen said, laughing; she feared she 
could not walk up a mountain.</p>
<p>"Ah yes; my lady ought to go, with more 
gran' ladies an' gentlemen, ridin' on purty little 
donkeys, up the big mountain. Oh, gran' things 
up big mountain for my lady to see!"</p>
<p>Thus she set to work, and kept her listener 
enchained for an hour, while she related 
wonderful stories of those upper regions. And as 
Evleen looked up to the burly crowns of the 
hills, perhaps she thought there might be sense 
in this wild old woman's suggestion. It ought 
to be a grand world up yonder.</p>
<p>Be that as it may, it was not long after this 
when Coll Dhu got notice that a party from 
the grey house would explore the mountains 
next day; that Evleen Blake would be of the 
number; and that he, Coll, must prepare to 
house and refresh a crowd of weary people, who 
in the evening should be brought, hungry and 
faint, to his door. The simple mushroom 
gatherer should be discovered laying in her humble 
stock among the green places between the hills, 
should volunteer to act as guide to the party, 
should lead them far out of their way through 
the mountains and up and down the most toilsome 
ascents and across dangerous places; to 
escape safely from which, the servants should 
be told to throw away the baskets of provisions 
which they carried.</p>
<p>Coll Dhu was not idle. Such a feast was set 
forth, as had never been spread so near the clouds 
before. We are told of wonderful dishes furnished 
by unwholesome agency, and from a place 
believed much hotter than is necessary for 
purposes of cookery. We are told also how Coll 
Dhu's barren chambers were suddenly hung with 
curtains of velvet, and with fringes of gold; 
how the blank white walls glowed with delicate 
colours and gilding; how gems of pictures sprang 
into sight between the panels; how the tables 
blazed with plate and gold, and glittered with 
the rarest glass; how such wines flowed, as the 
guests had never tasted; how servants in the 
richest livery, amongst whom the wizen-faced 
old man was a mere nonentity, appeared, and 
stood ready to carry in the wonderful dishes, 
at whose extraordinary fragrance the eagles 
came pecking to the windows, and the foxes 
drew near the walls, snuffing. Sure enough, in 
all good time, the weary party came within sight 
of the Devil's Inn, and Coll Dhu sallied forth to 
invite them across his lonely threshold. Colonel 
Blake (to whom Evleen, in her delicacy, had 
said no word of the solitary's strange behaviour 
to herself) hailed his appearance with delight, 
and the whole party sat down to Coil's banquet 
in high good humour. Also, it is said, in much 
amazement at the magnificence of the mountain 
recluse.</p>
<p>All went in to Coll's feast, save Evleen Blake, 
who remained standing on the threshold of the 
outer door; weary, but unwilling to rest there; 
hungry, but unwilling to eat there. Her white 
cambric dress was gathered on her arms, crushed 
and sullied with the toils of the day; her bright 
cheek was a little sun-burned; her small dark 
head with its braids a little tossed, was bared 
to the mountain air and the glory of the sinking 
sun; her hands were loosely tangled in the strings 
of her hat; and her foot sometimes tapped the 
threshold stone. So she was seen.</p>
<p>The peasants tell that Coll Dhu and her father 
came praying her to enter, and that the 
magnificent servants brought viands to the threshold; 
but no step would she move inward, no morsel 
would she taste.</p>
<p>"Poison, poison!" she murmured, and threw 
the food in handfuls to the foxes, who were 
snuffing on the heath.</p>
<p>But it was different when Muireade, the 
kindly old woman, the simple mushroom-gatherer, 
with all the wicked wrinkles smoothed 
out of her face, came to the side of the hungry 
girl, and coaxingly presented a savoury mess of 
her own sweet mushrooms, served on a common 
earthen platter.</p>
<p>"An' darlin', my lady, poor Muireade her 
cook them hersel', an' no thing o' this house 
touch them or look at poor Muireade's mushrooms."</p>
<p>Then Evleen took the platter and ate a 
delicious meal. Scarcely was it finished when a 
heavy drowsiness fell upon her, and, unable to 
sustain herself on her feet, she presently sat 
down upon the door-stone. Leaning her head 
against the framework of the door, she was 
soon in a deep sleep, or trance. So she was 
found.</p>
<p>"Whimsical, obstinate little girl!" said the 
colonel, putting his hand on the beautiful 
slumbering head. And taking her in his arms, he 
carried her into a chamber which had been (say 
the story-tellers) nothing but a bare and sorry 
closet in the morning, but which was now fitted 
up with Oriental splendour. And here on a 
luxurious couch she was laid, with a crimson 
coverlet wrapping her feet. And here in the 
tempered light coming through jewelled glass, 
where yesterday had been a coarse rough-hung 
window, her father looked his last upon her 
lovely face.</p>
<p>The colonel returned to his host and friends, 
and by-and-by the whole party sallied forth to 
see the after-glare of a fierce sunset swathing 
the hills in flames. It was not until they had 
gone some distance that Coll Dhu remembered 
to go back and fetch his telescope. He was not 
long absent. But he was absent long enough 
to enter that glowing chamber with a stealthy 
step, to throw a light chain around the neck of 
the sleeping girl, and to slip among the folds of 
her dress the hideous glittering burragh-bos.</p>
<p>After he had gone away again, Pexie came 
stealing to the door, and, opening it a little, 
sat down on the mat outside, with her cloak 
wrapped round her. An hour passed, and Evleen 
Blake still slept, her breathing scarcely stirring 
the deadly bauble on her breast. After that, she 
began to murmur and moan, and Pexie pricked up 
her ears. Presently a sound in the room told that 
the victim was awake and had risen. Then Pexie 
put her face to the aperture of the door and 
looked in, gave a howl of dismay, and fled from 
the house, to be seen in that country no more.</p>
<p>The light was fading among the hills, and 
the ramblers were returning towards the Devil's 
Inn, when a group of ladies who were considerably 
in advance of the rest, met Evleen Blake 
advancing towards them on the heath, with 
her hair disordered as by sleep, and no covering 
on her head. They noticed something bright, like 
gold, shifting and glancing with the motion of her 
figure. There had been some jesting among them 
about Evleen's fancy for falling asleep on the 
door-step instead of coming in to dinner, and 
they advanced laughing, to rally her on the subject. 
But she stared at them in a strange way, 
as if she did not know them, and passed on. 
Her friends were rather offended, and 
commented on her fantastic humour; only one 
looked after her, and got laughed at by her 
companions for expressing uneasiness on the 
wilful young lady's account.</p>
<p>So they kept their way, and the solitary 
figure went fluttering on, the white robe blushing, 
and the fatal burragh-bos glittering in the 
reflexion from the sky. A hare crossed her 
path, and she laughed out loudly, and clapping 
her hands, sprang after it. Then she 
stopped and asked questions of the stones, 
striking them with her open palm because they 
would not answer. (An amazed little herd 
sitting behind a rock, witnessed these strange 
proceedings.) By-and-by she began to call 
after the birds, in a wild shrill way, startling 
the echoes of the hills as she went along. A 
party of gentlemen returning by a dangerous 
path, heard the unusual sound and stopped to 
listen.</p>
<p>"What is that?" asked one.</p>
<p>"A young eagle," said Coll Dhu, whose face 
had become livid; "they often give such 
cries."</p>
<p>"It was uncommonly like a woman's voice!" 
was the reply; and immediately another wild 
note rang towards them from the rocks above: 
a bare saw-like ridge, shelving away to some 
distance ahead, and projecting one hungry tooth 
over an abyss. A few more moments and they 
saw Evleen Blake's light figure fluttering out 
towards this dizzy point.</p>
<p>"My Evleen!" cried the colonel, recognising 
his daughter, "she is mad to venture on such a 
spot!"</p>
<p>"Mad!" repeated Coll Dhu. And then 
dashed off to the rescue with all the might and 
swiftness of his powerful limbs.</p>
<p>When he drew near her, Evleen had almost 
reached the verge of the terrible rock. Very 
cautiously he approached her, his object being 
to seize her in his strong arms before she was 
aware of his presence, and carry her many 
yards away from the spot of danger. But in a 
fatal moment Evleen turned her head and saw 
him. One wild ringing cry of hate and horror, 
which startled the very eagles and scattered a 
flight of curlews above her head, broke from her 
lips. A step backward brought her within a 
foot of death.</p>
<p>One desperate though wary stride, and she 
was struggling in Coll's embrace. One glance 
in her eyes, and he saw that he was striving 
with a mad woman. Back, back, she dragged 
him, and he had nothing to grasp by. The rock 
was slippery and his shod feet would not cling 
to it. Back, back! A hoarse panting, a dire 
swinging to and fro; and then the rock was 
standing naked against the sky, no one was 
there, and Coll Dhu and Evleen Blake lay 
shattered far below.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken At The Dinner-Table."/>
<p>Does any one know who gives the names to 
our streets? Does any one know who invents 
the mottoes which are inserted in the cracker-papers, 
along with the sugar-plums?--I don't 
envy him his intellectual faculties, by-the-by, and 
I suspect him to be the individual who translates 
the books of the foreign operas. Does any 
one know who introduces the new dishes, 
Kromeski's, and such-like? Does any one know 
who is responsible for new words, such as shunt 
and thud, shimmer, ping (denoting the crack of 
the rifle), and many others? Does any one 
know who has obliged us to talk for ever about 
"fraternising" and "cropping up"? Does any 
one know the Sage to whom perfumers apply 
when they have invented a shaving-soap, or hair-wash, 
and who furnishes the trade with such 
names for their wares as Rypophagon, Euxesis, 
Depilatory, Bostrakeison? Does any one know 
who makes the riddles?</p>
<p>To the last question--only--I answer, Yes; 
<em>I</em> know.</p>
<p>In a certain year, which, I don't mind 
mentioning may be looked upon as included in 
the present century, I was a little boy--a sharp 
little boy, though I say it, and a skinny little 
boy. The two qualities not unfrequently go 
together. I will not mention what my age was at 
the time, but I was at school not far from 
London, and I was of an age when it is 
customary, or <em>was</em> customary, to wear a jacket and 
frill.</p>
<p>In riddles, I had at that early age a profound 
and solemn joy. To the study of those problems, 
I was beyond measure addicted, and in the 
collecting of them I was diligent in the extreme. 
It was the custom at the time for certain periodicals 
to give the question of a conundrum in one 
number, and the answer in the next. There 
was an interval of seven days and nights 
between the propounding of the question, and 
the furnishing of the reply. What a time was 
that for me! I sought the solution of the 
enigma, off and on (generally on), during the 
leisure hours of the week (no wonder I was 
skinny!), and sometimes, I am proud to remember, 
I became acquainted with the answer before 
the number containing it reached me from the 
official source. There was another kind of 
puzzle which used to appear when my sharp 
and skinny boyhood was at its sharpest and 
skinniest, by which I was much more perplexed 
than by conundrums or riddles conveyed in 
mere words. I speak of what may be called 
symbolical riddles--rebus is, I believe, their 
true designation--little squalid woodcuts 
representing all sorts of impossible objects huddled 
together in incongruous disorder; letters of the 
alphabet, at times, and even occasionally fragments 
of words, being introduced here and there, 
to add to the general confusion. Thus you would 
have: a Cupid mending a pen, a gridiron, the 
letter x, a bar of music, p. u. g. and a fife--
you would have these presented to you on a 
certain Saturday, with the announcement that 
on the following Saturday there would be 
issued an explanation of the mysterious and terrific 
jumble. That explanation would come, but with 
it new difficulties worse than the former. A 
birdcage, a setting sun (not like), the word 
"snip," a cradle, and some quadruped to which 
it would have puzzled Buffon himself to give a 
name. With these problems I was not successful, 
never having solved but one in my life, as 
will presently appear. Neither was I good at 
poetical riddles, in parts--slightly forced--as 
"My first is a boa-constrictor, My second's a 
Roman lictor, My third is a Dean and Chipter, 
And my whole goes always on tip-ter." These 
were too much for me.</p>
<p>I remember on one occasion accidentally 
meeting with a publication in which there was 
a rebus better executed than those to which I 
had been accustomed, and which mystified me 
greatly. First of all there was the letter A; 
then came a figure of a clearly virtuous man 
in a long gown, with a scrip, and a staff, and 
a cockle-shell on his hat; then followed a 
representation of an extremely old person with 
flowing white hair and beard; the figure 2 
was the next symbol, and beyond this was a 
gentleman on crutches, looking at a five-barred 
gate. Oh, how that rebus haunted me! It was 
at a sea-side library that I met with it during 
the holidays, and before the next number came 
out I was back at school. The publication in 
which this remarkable picture had appeared was 
an expensive one, and quite beyond my means, 
so there was no way of getting at the explanation. 
Determined to conquer, and fearing that 
one of the symbols might escape my memory, 
I wrote them down in order. In doing so, an 
interpretation flashed upon me. A--Pilgrim--
Age--To--Cripple--Gate. Ah! was it the 
right one? Had I triumphed, or had I failed? 
My anxiety on the subject attained such a 
pitch at last, that I determined to write to the 
editor of the periodical in which the rebus had 
appeared, and implore him to take compassion 
upon me and relieve my mind. To that 
communication I received no answer. Perhaps there 
was one in the notices to correspondents--but 
then I must have purchased the periodical to 
get it.</p>
<p>I mention these particulars because they had 
something--not a little--to do with a certain 
small incident which, small though it was, had 
influence on my after life. The incident in 
question was the composition of a riddle by the 
present writer. It was composed with difficulty, 
on a slate; portions of it were frequently rubbed 
out, the wording of it gave me a world of 
trouble, but the work was achieved at last. 
"Why," it was thus that I worded it in its 
final and corrected form, "Why does a young 
gentleman who has partaken freely of the pudding, 
which at this establishment precedes the 
meat, resemble a meteor?--Because he's 
effulgent--a full gent!"</p>
<p>Hopeful, surely! Nothing unnaturally 
premature in the composition. Founded on a 
strictly boyish grievance. Possessing a certain 
archological interest in its reference to the now 
obsolete practice of administering pudding before 
meat at educational establishments, with the view 
of damping the appetite (and constitution) of the 
pupils.</p>
<p>Though inscribed upon perishable and greasy 
slate, in ephemeral slate-pencil, my riddle lived. 
It was repeated. It became popular. It was 
all over the school, and at last it came to the ears 
of the master. That unimaginative person had 
no taste for the fine arts. I was sent for, 
interrogated as to whether this work of art was 
the product of my brain, and, having given an 
answer in the affirmative, received a distinct, 
and even painful, punch on the head, accompanied 
by specific directions to inscribe straightway 
the words "Dangerous Satirising," two 
thousand times, on the very slate on which my 
riddle had been originally composed.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding this act of despotism on the 
part of the unappreciative Beast who invariably 
treated me as if I were not profitable (when I 
knew the contrary), my reverence for the great 
geniuses who have excelled in the department 
of which I am speaking, grew with my growth, 
and strengthened with &amp;c. Think of the 
pleasure, the rapture, which Riddles afford to 
persons of wholesomely constituted mind! Think 
of the innocent sense of triumph felt by the 
man who propounds a riddle to a company, to 
every member of which it is a novelty. He 
alone is the proprietor of the answer. His 
is a glorious position. He keeps everybody 
waiting. He wears a calm and placid smile. 
He has the rest at his mercy. He is happy--
innocently happy.</p>
<p>But who makes the Riddles?</p>
<p>I <sc>DO</sc>.</p>
<p>Am I going to let out a great mystery? 
Am I going to initiate the uninitiated? Am I 
going to let the world know <em>how it is done?</em></p>
<p>Yes. I am.</p>
<p>It is done in the main by the Dictionary; but 
the consultation of that work of reference, with 
a view to the construction of riddles, is a process 
so bewildering--it puts such a strain upon the 
faculties--that at first you cannot work at it for 
more than a quarter of an hour at once. The process 
is terrific. First of all you get yourself 
thoroughly awake and on the alert--it is good to 
run the fingers through the hair roughly at this 
crisis--then you take your Dictionary, and, 
selecting a particular letter, you go down the 
column, stopping at every word that looks in the 
slightest degree promising, drawing back from 
it as artists draw back from a picture to see it 
the better, twisting it, and turning it, and if it 
yield nothing, passing on to the next. With 
the substantives you occupy yourself in an 
especial manner, as more may be done with them 
than with any of the other parts of speech; 
while as to the words with two meanings, you 
must be in a bad state indeed, or have particularly 
ill luck, if you fail to get something out 
of them.</p>
<p>Suppose that you are going in for a day's 
riddling--your dinner depending on the success 
of your efforts. I take your Dictionary, and 
open it at hap-hazard. You open, say, among 
the Fs, and you go to work.</p>
<p>You make several stoppages as you go down 
the column. You pause naturally at the word 
Felt. It is a past participle of the verb to feel, 
and it is a substance used in making hats. You 
press it hard. Why is a hatter--No--Why may 
a hatter invariably be looked upon as a 
considerate person? Because he has always <em>felt</em> 
for--No. That won't do. You go on. "Fen"--
a chance here for a well-timed thing about the 
Fenian Brotherhood. This is worth a struggle, 
and you make a desperate one. A Fen is a 
marsh. In a marsh there is mud. Why was 
it always to be expected that the Irish rebels 
must ultimately stick in the mud? Because 
theirs was a Fen-ian movement.--Intolerable! 
Yet you are loth to abandon the subject. A 
Fen is a Morass. More-ass. Why is an Irish 
rebel more ass than knave? No, again it won't 
do!</p>
<p>Disconsolate, but dogged, you go on till you 
arrive at "Fertile." Fer-tile. Tile--Tile, a Hat. 
Why is a Hat made of Beaver, like land that 
always yields fine crops? Because it may be 
called Fertile (Fur-tile). That will do. Not 
first-class, but it will do. Riddling is very like 
fishing. Sometimes you get a small trout, 
sometimes a large one. This is a small trout, but it 
shall go into the basket, nevertheless. And now 
you are fairly warming to your work. You come 
to "Forgery." You again make a point. 
Forgery. For-gery--For Jerry. A complicated 
riddle of a high order. Intricate, and of the 
Coleridge kind. Why--No, If--If a gentleman, 
having a favourite son of tender years, named 
Jeremiah, were in the course of dessert to put a 
pear in his pocket, stating, as he did so, that the 
fruit was intended for his beloved boy, why, 
in making such an explanation, would he mention 
a certain act of felony once punishable by 
death?--Because he would say that it was 
Forgery--For Jerry. Into the basket.</p>
<p>It never rains but it pours. Another complex 
one, of the same type. Fungus! If a 
well-bred lady should, in sport, poke her cousin 
<em>Augustus</em> in the ribs with her lilac and white 
parasol, and hurt him, what vegetable product 
would she mention in facetiously apologising? 
Fungus. Fun Gus! In with it.</p>
<p>The Fs being exhausted, you take a short 
rest. Then, screwing your faculties up afresh, 
and seizing the Dictionary again, you open it 
once more. Cs this time lie before you, a page 
of Cs. You pause, hopeful, at corn. The 
word has two meanings, it ought to answer. 
It shall be made to answer. This is a case of 
a peculiar kind. You determine to construct a 
riddle by rule. There is no genius needed here. 
The word has two meanings; both shall be used; 
it is a mechanical process. Why is a reaper at 
his work, like a chiropodist?--Because he's a 
corn-cutter. Made by rule, complete, impregnable; 
but yet not interesting. The Cs are not 
propitious, and you apply to the Bs. In your 
loitering mood you drop down upon the word 
"Bring," and with idiotcy at hand sit gazing 
at it. Suddenly you revive--Bring, Brought, 
Brought up. Brought up will do. Why is the 
coal-scuttle which Mary has conveyed from the 
kitchen to the second floor, like an infant put 
out to dry-nurse?--Because it's brought up by 
hand. You try once more, and this time it is 
the letter H on which your hopes depend. The 
columns under H, duly perused, bring you in due 
time to Horse. Why is a horse attached to the 
vehicle of a miser, like a war-steamer of the 
present day?--Because he's driven by a screw. 
Another? Hoarse. Why is a family, the 
members of which have always been subject to 
sore-throats, like "The Derby?"--Because it's 
a hoarse-race (Horse-race).</p>
<p>It is by no means always the case, however, 
that the Dictionary affords so large a yield as 
this. It is hard work--exhausting work--and, 
worst of all, <em>there is no end to it</em>. You get, after 
a certain time, incapable of shaking off the shop 
even in your moments of relaxation. Nay, worse. 
You feel as if you ought to be always at it, lest you 
should miss a good chance, that would never 
return. It is this that makes epigrammatic literature 
wearing. If you go to the play, if you take 
up a newspaper, if you ensconce yourself in a 
corner with a blessed work of fiction, you find 
yourself still pursued and haunted by your 
profession. The dialogue to which you listen 
when you go to the theatre, the words of the 
book you are reading, may suggest something, 
and it behoves you to be on the look-out. 
Horrible and distracting calling! You may 
get rid of your superfluous flesh more quickly 
by going through a course of riddling, than by 
running up-hill in blankets for a week together, 
or going through a systematic course of Turkish 
baths.</p>
<p>Moreover, the cultivator of epigrammatic 
literature has much to undergo in the disposal 
of his wares, when they are once ready for the 
market. There is a public sale for them, and, 
between ourselves, there is a private ditto. 
The public demand for the article, which it has 
been so long my lot to supply, is not large, nor, 
I am constrained to say, is it entirely cordial. 
The periodicals in which your rebus or your 
conundrum appears hebdomadally, are not 
numerous; nor are the proprietors of such journals 
respectfully eager for this peculiar kind of 
literature. The conundrum or the rebus will 
knock about the office for a long time, and, perhaps, 
only get inserted at last because it fits a 
vacant space. When we are inserted, we always--
always mind--occupy an ignoble place. We 
come in at the bottom of a column, or occupy 
the very last lines of the periodical in which we 
appear--in company with that inevitable game 
at chess in which white is to check-mate in four 
moves. One of the best riddles--the best, I 
think, that I ever made--was knocking about at 
the office of a certain journal six weeks before 
it got before the public. It ran thus: Why is 
a little man who is always telling long stories 
about nothing, like a certain new kind of rifle? 
ANSWER: Because he's a small-bore.</p>
<p>This work was the means of bringing me 
acquainted with the fact that there was a Private 
as well as a Public sale for the productions of 
the epigrammatic artist. A gentleman, who did 
not give his name--neither will I give it, though 
I know it well--called at the office of the 
periodical in which this particular riddle appeared, 
on the day succeeding its publication, and asked 
for the name and address of its author. The 
sub-editor of the journal, a fast friend of mine, 
to whom I owe many a good turn, furnished 
him with both, and, on a certain day, a middle-aged 
gentleman of rather plethoric appearance, 
with a sly twinkle in his eye, and with 
humorous lines about his mouth--both eye and 
mouth were utter impostors, for my friend had 
not a particle of humour in his composition--
came gasping up my stairs, and introducing 
himself as an admirer of genius--"and therefore," 
he added, with a courteous wave of the 
hand, "your very humble servant"--wished to 
know whether it would suit my purpose to 
supply him, from time to time, with certain 
specimens of epigrammatic literature, now a 
riddle, now an epigram, now a short story that 
could be briefly and effectively told, all of which 
should be guaranteed to be entirely new and 
original, which should be made over wholly and 
solely to him, and to which no other human 
being should have access on any consideration 
whatever. My gentleman added that he was 
prepared to pay very handsomely for what he 
had, and, indeed, mentioned terms which caused 
me to open my eyes to the fullest extent of 
which those organs are capable.</p>
<p>I soon found out what my friend Mr. Price 
Scrooper was at. I call him by this name 
(which is fictitious, but something like his own), 
for the sake of convenience. He was a diner-out, 
who held a somewhat precarious reputation, 
which, by hook or crook, he had acquired 
as a sayer of good things, a man sure to have 
the last new story at the end of his tongue. 
Mr. Scrooper liked dining-out above all things, 
and the horror of that day when there should 
come a decline in the number of his invitations 
was always before his eyes. Thus it came 
about that relations were established between 
us--between me, the epigrammatic artist, and 
Price Scrooper, the diner-out.</p>
<p>I fitted him with a good thing or two even 
on the very day of his paying me a first visit. 
I gave him a story which I remembered to have 
heard my father tell when I was an infant--a 
perfectly safe story, which had been buried for 
years in oblivion. I supplied him with a riddle 
or two which I happened to have by me, and 
which were so very bad that no company could 
ever suspect them of a professional origin. I set 
him up in epigram for some time, and he set me 
up in the necessaries of life for some time, and 
so we parted mutually satisfied.</p>
<p>The commercial dealings thus satisfactorily 
established were renewed steadily and at 
frequent intervals. Of course, as in all earthly 
relations, there were not wanting some 
unpleasant elements to qualify the generally 
comfortable arrangements. Mr. Scrooper would 
sometimes complain that some of the 
witticisms with which I had supplied him, had 
failed in creating an effect--had hardly proved 
remunerative, in short. What could I reply? 
I could not tell him that this was his fault. 
I told him a story given by Isaac Walton, of a 
clergyman who, hearing a sermon preached by 
one of his cloth with immense effect, asked for 
the loan of it. On returning the sermon, 
however, after having tried it on his own 
congregation, he complained that it had proved a 
total failure, and that his audience had 
responded in no degree to his eloquence. The 
answer of the original proprietor of the sermon 
was crushing: "I lent you," he said, "indeed, 
my fiddle, but not my fiddle-stick;" meaning, 
as Isaac explains, rather unnecessarily, "the 
manner and intelligence with which the sermon 
was to be delivered."</p>
<p>My friend did not seem to feel the application 
of this anecdote. I believe he was occupied, 
while I spoke, in committing the story to his 
memory for future use--thus getting it gratuitously 
out of me--which was mean.</p>
<p>In fact, Mr. Scrooper, besides his original 
irreparable deficiency, was getting old and 
stupid, and would often forget or misapply the 
point of a story, or the answer to a conundrum. 
With these last I supplied him freely, 
working really hard to prepare for his use such 
articles as were adapted to his peculiar exigencies. 
As a diner-out, riddles of a convivial 
sort--alluding to matters connected with the 
pleasures of the table--are generally in request, 
and with a supply of these I fitted Mr. Scrooper, 
much to his satisfaction. Here are some specimens, 
for which I charged him rather heavily:</p>
<p>Why is wine--observe how easily this is 
brought in after dinner--why is wine, made up 
for the British market, like a deserter from the 
army?</p>
<p>Because it's always brandied (branded) before 
it's sent off.</p>
<p>Why is a ship, which has to encounter rough 
weather before it reaches its destination, like a 
certain wine which is usually adulterated with 
logwood and other similar matters?</p>
<p>Because it goes through a vast deal before it 
comes into port.</p>
<p>What portion of the trimming of a lady's 
dress resembles East India sherry of the first 
quality?</p>
<p>That which goes round the Cape.</p>
<p>One of his greatest difficulties, my patron told 
me--for he was as frank with me as a man is with 
his doctor or his lawyer--was in remembering 
which were the houses where he had related a 
certain story, or propounded a certain conundrum; 
who were the people to whom such and 
such a riddle would be fresh; who were the 
people to whom it was already but too familiar. 
Mr. Scrooper had also a habit of sometimes 
asking the answer to a riddle instead of the 
question, which was occasionally productive of 
confusion; or, giving the question properly, he 
would, when his audience became desperate and 
gave it up, supply them with the answer to an 
altogether different conundrum.</p>
<p>One day, my patron came to me in a state 
of high indignation. A riddle--bran(d) new, and for 
which I had demanded a high price, thinking 
well of it myself--had failed, and Mr. Scrooper 
came to me in a rage to expostulate.</p>
<p>"It fell as flat as ditch-water," he said. 
"Indeed, one very disagreeable person said there was 
nothing in it, and he thought there must be 
some mistake. A very nasty thing to say, 
considering that the riddle was given as my own. 
How could I be mistaken in my own riddle?"</p>
<p>"May I ask," said I, politely, "how you 
worded the question?"</p>
<p>"Certainly. I worded it thus: Why are 
we justified in believing that the pilgrims to 
Mecca, undertake the journey with mercenary 
motives?"</p>
<p>"Quite right," said I; "and the answer?"</p>
<p>"The answer," replied my patron, "was as 
you gave it me: Because they go for the sake 
of Mahomet."</p>
<p>"I am not surprised," I said, coldly, for I felt 
that I had been unjustly blamed, "that your 
audience was mystified. The answer, as I gave 
it to you, ran thus: Because they go for the 
sake of the profit (Prophet)!"</p>
<p>Mr. Scrooper subsequently apologised.</p>
<p>I draw near to the end of my narrative. The 
termination is painful, so is that of King Lear. 
The worst feature in it is, that it involves the 
acknowledgment of a certain deplorable piece 
of weakness on my own part.</p>
<p>I was really in the receipt of a very pretty 
little income from Mr. Scrooper, when one 
morning I was again surprised by a visit from 
a total stranger--again, as on a former occasion, 
a middle-aged gentleman--again an individual 
with a twinkling eye and a humorous mouth--
again a diner-out, with two surnames--Mr. 
Kerby Postlethwaite I will call him, which is 
sailing as near the wind as I consider safe.</p>
<p>Mr. Kerby Postlethwaite came on the errand 
which had already brought Mr. Scrooper to the 
top of my stairs. He, too, had seen one of my 
productions in a certain journal (for I still kept 
up my relation with the public press), and he 
too having a similar reputation to maintain, and 
finding his brain at times rather sterile, had 
come to me to make exactly the same 
proposal which had already been made by Mr. 
Price Scrooper.</p>
<p>For a time the singularity of the coincidence 
absolutely took my breath away, and I remained 
staring speechlessly at my visitor in a manner 
which might have suggested to him that I was 
hardly the man to furnish him with anything 
very brilliant. However, I managed to recover 
myself in time. I was very guarded and careful 
in my speech, but finally expressed my readiness 
to come to terms with my new employer. These 
were soon settled: Mr. Kerby Postlethwaite 
having even more liberal views as to this part 
of the business than those entertained by Mr. 
Price Scrooper.</p>
<p>The only difficulty was to supply this 
gentleman quickly enough with what he wanted. 
He was in a hurry. He was going that very 
evening to a dinner-party, and it was supremely 
important that he should distinguish himself. 
The occasion was a special one. It must be 
something good. He would not stick at a trifle 
in the matter of terms, but he did want something 
super-excellent. A riddle--a perfectly 
new riddle--he would like best.</p>
<p>My stores were turned over, my desk was 
ransacked, and still he was not satisfied. 
Suddenly it flashed into my mind that I had 
something by me which would exactly do. The very 
thing; a riddle alluding to a subject of the day; 
a subject just at that time in everybody's mouth. 
One which there would be no difficulty in leading 
up to. In short, a very neat thing indeed. 
There was but one doubt in my mind. Had I 
already sold it to my original employer? That 
was the question, and for the life of me I could 
not answer it with certainty. The life of one 
addicted to such pursuits as mine, is chaotic; 
and with me more particularly, doing an extensive 
public and private trade, it was especially 
so. I kept no books, nor any record of my 
professional transactions. One thing which 
influenced me strongly to believe the riddle to 
be still unappropriated, was, that I had 
certainly received no intelligence as to its success 
or failure from Mr. Scrooper, whereas that 
gentleman never failed to keep me informed on that 
momentous point. I was in doubt, but I ended 
(so princely were the terms offered by my new 
patron) in giving myself the benefit of that 
doubt, and handing over the work of art in 
question to Mr. Kerby Postlethwaite.</p>
<p>If I were to say that I felt comfortable after 
having brought this transaction to a close, I 
should not speak the truth. Horrible 
misgivings filled my mind, and there were 
moments when, if it had been possible to undo 
what was done, I should have taken that 
retrogressive step. This, however, was out of the 
question. I didn't even know where my new 
employer was to be found. I had nothing for it 
but to wait and try my best to feel sanguine.</p>
<p>The circumstances which distinguished the 
evening of that eventful day on which I first 
received a visit from my new patron, were 
subsequently related to me with great accuracy, 
and not without rancorous comment, by both 
of those who sustained leading parts in the 
evening's performances. Yes, terrible to relate, 
on the following day both my patrons came to 
me, overflowing with fury, to tell me what had 
happened, and to denounce me as the first cause 
of the mischief. Both were furious, but my more 
recent acquaintance, Mr. Postlethwaite, was the 
more vehement in his wrath.</p>
<p>It appeared, according to this gentleman's 
statement, that having repaired at the proper 
time to the residence of the gentleman whose 
guest he was to be that evening, and who, 
he took occasion to inform me, was a personage 
of consideration, he found himself in the midst 
of a highly distinguished company. He had 
intended to be the last arrival, but a fellow named 
Scrooper, or Price, or something of that sort--
both names, perhaps--was yet expected. He 
soon arrived, however, Mr. Postlethwaite said, 
and the company went down to dinner.</p>
<p>Throughout the meal, the magnificent nature 
of which I will not dilate upon, these two 
gentlemen were continually at loggerheads. 
They appear--and in this both the accounts 
which reached me tally--to have contradicted 
each other, interrupted each other, cut into each 
other's stories, on every occasion, until that 
sort of hatred was engendered between them 
which Christian gentlemen sharing a meal 
together do sometimes feel towards each other. 
I suspect that each had heard of the other as 
a "diner-out," though they had not met 
before, and that each was prepared to hate the 
other.</p>
<p>Adhering to the Postlethwaitean narrative 
faithfully, I find that all this time, and even 
when most aggravated by the conduct of my 
earliest patron, he was able to comfort himself 
with the reflection that he had by him in store 
the weapon wherewith, when the proper moment 
should arrive, to inflict the coup de grace upon 
his rival. That weapon was my riddle--my riddle 
fitted to a topic of the day.</p>
<p>The moment arrived. I shudder as I proceed. 
The meal was over, the wines had circulated once, 
and Mr. Kerby Postlethwaite began gently 
insidiously and with all the dexterity of an old 
performer, to lead the conversation in the direction 
of THE TOPIC. His place was very near to the 
seat occupied by my original patron, Mr. Price 
Scrooper. What was Mr. Postlethwaite's 
astonishment to hear that gentleman leading such 
conversation, as was within his jurisdiction, 
<em>also</em> in the direction of THE TOPIC! "Does he 
see that I want a lead, and is he playing into 
my hands?" thought my newest client. 
"Perhaps he's not such a bad fellow, after all. I'll 
do as much for him another time." This 
amicable view of the matter was but of brief 
duration. Madness was at hand! Two voices 
were presently heard speaking simultaneously:</p>
<table>
<tr>
<td>MR. PRICE SCROOPER:<br/>The subject suggested a riddle to me this morning, as I was thinking it over.</td>
<td width="5%"> </td>
<td>MR. KERBY POSTLETHWAITE:<br/>A view of the thing struck me in the light of a riddle, this morning, quite suddenly.</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>The two were silent, each having stopped the 
other.</p>
<p>"I beg your pardon," said my first patron, 
with ferocious politeness, "you were saying 
that you----"</p>
<p>"Had made a riddle," replied my second 
patron. "Yes. I think that you also alluded 
to your having done something of the sort?"</p>
<p>"I did."</p>
<p>There was silence all round the table. Some 
illustrious person broke it at last by saying, 
"What a strange coincidence!"</p>
<p>"At all events," cried the master of the house, 
"let us hear one of them. Come, Scrooper, you 
spoke first."</p>
<p>"Mr. Postlethwaite, I insist upon having 
your riddle," said the lady of the house, with 
whom Mr. P. was the favourite.</p>
<p>Under these circumstances both gentlemen 
paused, and then, each bursting forth suddenly, 
there was a renewal of duet.</p>
<table>
<tr>
<td>MR. PRICE SCROOPER:<br/>Why does the Atlantic cable, in its present condition--</td>
<td width="5%"> </td>
<td>MR. KERBY POSTLETHWAITE:<br/>Why does the Atlantic cable, in its present condition--</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>At this there was a general roar and commotion 
among those present. "Our riddles appear to be 
somewhat alike?" remarked Mr. Postlethwaite, 
in a bitter tone, and looking darkly at my first 
patron.</p>
<p>"It is the most extraordinary thing," replied 
that gentleman, "that I ever heard of!"</p>
<p>"Great wits jump," said the illustrious person 
who had previously spoken of an "extraordinary 
coincidence."</p>
<p>"At any rate, let us hear one of them," cried 
the host. "Perhaps they vary after the first 
few words. Come, Scrooper."</p>
<p>"Yes, let us hear one of them to the end," 
said the lady of the house, and she looked at 
Mr. Postlethwaite. This last, however, was sulky. 
Mr. Price Scrooper took advantage of the 
circumstance to come out with the conundrum in 
all its integrity.</p>
<p>"Why," asked this gentleman once more, "is 
the Atlantic cable, in its present condition, like 
a schoolmaster?"</p>
<p>"That is my riddle," said Mr. Postlethwaite, 
as soon as the other had ceased to speak. "I 
made it myself."</p>
<p>"On the contrary, it is mine, I assure you," 
replied Mr. Scrooper, very doggedly. "I composed 
it while shaving this morning."</p>
<p>Here again there was a pause, broken only by 
interjectional expressions of astonishment on the 
part of those who were present--led by the 
illustrious man.</p>
<p>Again the master of the house came to the 
rescue. "The best way of settling it," he said, 
"will be to ascertain which of our two friends 
knows the answer. Whoever knows the answer 
can claim the riddle. Let each of these gentlemen 
write down the answer on a piece of paper, 
fold it up, and give it to me. If the answers 
are identical, the coincidence will indeed be 
extraordinary."</p>
<p>"It is impossible that any one but myself can 
know the answer," remarked my first patron, as 
he wrote on his paper and folded it.</p>
<p>My second patron wrote also, and folded. "The 
answer," he said, "<em>can</em> only be known to me."</p>
<p>The papers were unfolded by the master of 
the house, and read one after the other.</p>
<p>ANSWER written by Mr. Price Scrooper: 
"Because it's supported by buoys (boys)."</p>
<p>ANSWER written by Mr. Kerby Postlethwaite: 
"Because it's supported by buoys (boys)."</p>
<break/>
<p>There was a scene. There were recriminations. 
As I have said, on the following morning 
both gentlemen visited me betimes. They had 
not much to say after all. Were they not both 
in my power?</p>
<p>The curious thing is, that from that time 
dates the decline of my professional eminence. 
Of course, both my patrons took leave of me 
for ever. But I have also to relate that my 
powers of riddling took leave of me also. My 
mornings with the Dictionary became less and 
less productive of results, and, only a fortnight 
ago last Wednesday, I sent to a certain 
weekly publication a rebus presenting the following 
combination of objects: A giraffe, a haystack, 
a boy driving a hoop, the letter X, a 
crescent, a human mouth, the words "I wish," a 
dog standing on its hind legs, and a pair of scales. 
It appeared. It took. It puzzled the public. 
But for the life of me I cannot form the remotest 
idea what it meant, and I am ruined.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="Not To Be Taken For Granted."/>
<p>To-day I, Eunice Fielding, have been looking 
over the journal which I kept of the first few 
weeks of my life in the world, after I left the 
seclusion of the German Moravian school, where 
I was educated. I feel a strange pity for myself, 
the tender ignorant innocent school-girl, freed 
from the peaceful shelter of the Moravian settlement, 
and thrust suddenly into the centre of a 
sorrowful household.</p>
<p>As I turn to this first page, there rises before 
me, like the memory of a former life, a picture 
of the noiseless grass-grown streets of the 
settlement, with the old-fashioned dwellings, and 
the quiet and serene faces looking out kindly 
upon the troop of children passing to the church. 
There is the home of the Single Sisters, with its 
shining and spotless casements; and close beside 
it, is the church where they and we worshipped, 
with its broad central aisle always separating the 
women from the men. I can see the girls in 
their picturesque caps, trimmed with scarlet, and 
the blue ribbons of the matrons, and the pure 
white head-gear of the widows; the burial-ground, 
where the separation is still maintained, 
and where the brethren and the sisters lie in 
undivided graves; and the kindly simple-hearted 
pastor, who was always touched with the feeling 
of our weakness. I see it all, as I turn over the 
pages of my short journal, with just a faint longing 
to return to the repose and innocent ignorance 
which encircled me while I dwelt among them, 
safely shut in from the sorrows of the world.</p>
<p>Nov. 7. At home once more after an absence 
of three years; but home is changed. There 
used to be a feeling of mother's presence everywhere 
about the house, even if she were in the 
remotest room; but now, Susannah and Priscilla 
are wearing her apparel, and as they go in and 
out, and I catch a glimpse of the soft 
dove-coloured folds of the dresses, I look up with a 
start, half in hope of seeing my mother's face 
again. They are much older than I am, for 
Priscilla was ten years of age when I was born, 
and Susannah is three years older than Priscilla. 
They are very grave and serious, and it is well 
known, even in Germany, how religious they 
are. I suppose by the time I am as old as they 
are, I shall be the same.</p>
<p>I wonder if my father ever felt like a child; 
he looks as if he had lived for centuries. Last 
night I could not venture to look too closely into 
his face; but to-day I can see a very kind and 
peaceful expression underlying all the wrinkles 
and lines of care. In his soul there is a calm 
serene depth which no tempest can touch. That 
is plain. He is a good man, I know, though his 
goodness was not talked about at school, as was 
Susannah's and Priscilla's. When the coach set 
me down at the door, and he ran out into the 
street bareheaded, and took me at once into his 
arms, carrying me like a little child into our 
home, all my sorrow upon leaving my school-fellows, 
and the sisters, and our pastor, vanished 
away in the joy of being with him. God helping 
me--and surely he will help me to do this--I 
will be a comfort to my father.</p>
<p>The house is very different to what it was in 
my mother's time. The rooms look gloomy, for 
the walls are damp and mildewed, and the carpets 
are worn threadbare. It seems as if my sister 
had taken no pride in household matters. To 
be sure Priscilla is betrothed to one of the 
brethren, who dwells in Woodbury, about ten 
miles from here. She told me last night what a 
beautiful house he had, and how it was furnished 
with more luxury and costliness than our people 
often care for, inasmuch as we do not seek 
worldly show. She also displayed the fine linen 
she has been preparing for herself, with store of 
dresses, both in silks and stuffs. They looked so 
grand, spread out upon the poor furniture of our 
chamber, that I could not help but cast up in 
my own mind what the cost would be, and I 
inquired how my father's business prospered: at 
which Priscilla coloured, but Susannah uttered a 
low deep groan, which was answer enough.</p>
<p>This morning I unpacked my trunk, and gave 
a letter from the church to each of my sisters. 
It was to make known to them that Brother 
Schmidt, a missionary in the West Indies, desires 
that a fitting wife should be chosen for him by 
casting of lots, and sent out to him. Several of 
the single sisters in our settlement have given in 
their names, and such is the repute of Susannah 
and Priscilla, that they are notified of the 
application, that they may do likewise. Of course 
Priscilla, being already betrothed, has no thought 
of doing so; but Susannah has been deep in 
meditation all day, and now she is sitting opposite 
to me, pale and solemn, her brown hair, in 
which I can detect a silver thread or two, braided 
closely down her thin cheeks; but as she writes, 
a faint blush steals over her face, as if she were 
listening to Brother Schmidt, whom she has 
never seen, and whose voice she never heard. 
She has written her name--I can read it, 
"Susannah Fielding"--in her clear round steady 
hand, and it will be put into the lot with many 
others, from among which one will be drawn out, 
and the name written thereon will be that of 
Brother Schmidt's appointed wife.</p>
<p>Nov. 9. Only two days at home; but what a 
change there is in me. My brain is all confusion, 
and it might be a hundred years since I left 
school. This morning two strangers came to the 
house, demanding to see my father. They were 
rough hard men, whose voices sounded into my 
father's office, where he was busy writing, while 
I sat beside the fire, engaged in household sewing. 
I looked up at the loud noise of their voices, 
and saw him turn deadly pale, and bow his 
white-haired head upon his hands. But he went out 
in an instant, and returning with the strangers, 
bade me go to my sisters. I found Susannah in 
the parlour, looking scared and bewildered, and 
Priscilla in hysterics. After much ado they 
grew calmer, and when Priscilla was lying quiet 
on the sofa, and Susannah had sat down in 
mother's arm-chair to meditate, I crept back to 
my father's office, and rapping softly at the door, 
heard him say, "Come in." He was alone, and 
very sad.</p>
<p>"Father," I asked, "what is the matter?" and 
seeing his dear kind face, I flew to him.</p>
<p>"Eunice," he whispered very tenderly, "I 
will tell you all."</p>
<p>So then as I knelt at his knee, with my eyes 
fastened upon his, he told me a long history of 
troubles, every word of which removed my school-days 
farther and farther from me, and made them 
seem like the close of a finished life. The end of 
all was that these men were sent by his creditors 
to take possession of everything in our old home, 
where my mother had lived and died.</p>
<p>I caught my breath at first, as if I should go 
into hysterics like Priscilla, but I thought what 
good would that do for my father? So after a 
minute or two I was able to look up again 
bravely into his eyes. He then said he had his 
books to examine, so I kissed him, and came 
away.</p>
<p>In the parlour Priscilla was lying still, with 
her eyelids closed, and Susannah was quite lost 
in meditation. Neither of them noticed me 
entering or departing. I went into the kitchen 
to consult Jane about my father's dinner. She 
was rocking herself upon a chair, and rubbing 
her eyes red with her rough apron; and there in 
the elbow-chair which once belonged to my 
grandfather--all the Brethren knew George 
Fielding--sat one of the strangers, wearing a 
shaggy brown hat, from under which he was 
staring fixedly at a bag of dried herbs hanging 
to a hook in the ceiling. He did not bring his 
eyes down, even when I entered, and stood 
thunderstruck upon the door-sill; but he rounded 
up his large mouth, as if he were going to whistle.</p>
<p>"Good morning, sir," I said, as soon as I 
recovered myself; for my father had said we must 
regard these men only as the human instruments 
permitted to bring affliction to us; "will you 
please to tell me your name?"</p>
<p>The stranger fixed his eyes steadily upon me. 
After which he smiled a little to himself.</p>
<p>"John Robins is my name," he said, "and England 
is my nation, Woodbury is my dwelling-place, 
and Christ is my salvation."</p>
<p>He spake in a sing-song tone, and his eyes 
went up again to the bag of marjoram, twinkling 
as if with great satisfaction; and I pondered 
over his reply, until it became quite a comfort to 
me.</p>
<p>"I'm very glad to hear it," I said, at last, 
"because we are religious people, and I was 
afraid you might be different."</p>
<p>"Oh, I'll be no kind of nuisance, miss," he 
answered; "you make yourselves comfortable, 
and only bid Maria, here, to draw me my beer 
regular, and I'll not hurt your feelings."</p>
<p>"Thank you," I said. "Jane, you hear what 
Mr. Robins says. Bring some sheets down to 
air, and make up the bed in the Brothers' chamber. 
You'll find a bible and hymn-book on the 
table there, Mr. Robins." I was leaving the 
kitchen, when this singular man struck his 
clenched fist upon the dresser, with a noise which 
startled me greatly.</p>
<p>"Miss," he said, "don't you put yourself 
about; and if anybody else should ever put you 
out, about anything, remember John Robins 
of Woodbury. I'm your man for anything, 
whether in my line or out of my line; I am, 
by----"</p>
<p>He was about to add something more, but he 
paused suddenly, and his face grew a little more 
red, as he looked up again to the ceiling. So I 
left the kitchen.</p>
<p>I have since been helping my father with his 
books, being very thankful that I was always 
quick at sums.</p>
<p>P.S. I dreamed that the settlement was 
invaded by an army of men, led by John Robins, 
who insisted upon becoming our pastor.</p>
<p>November 10. I have been a journey of fifty 
miles, one half of it by stage-coach. I learned 
for the first time that my mother's brother, a 
worldly rich man, dwells fifteen miles beyond 
Woodbury. He does not belong to our people, 
and he was greatly displeased by my mother's 
marriage. It also appears that Susannah and 
Priscilla were not my mother's own daughters. 
My father had a little forlorn hope that our 
worldly kinsman might be inclined to help us in 
our great extremity; so I went forth with his 
blessings and prayers upon my errand. Brother 
More, who came over to see Priscilla yesterday, 
met me at Woodbury Station, and saw me safely 
on the coach for my uncle's village. He is much 
older than I fancied; and his face is large, and 
coarse, and flabby-looking. I am surprised that 
Priscilla should betroth herself to him. 
However, he was very kind to me, and watched the 
coach out of the inn-yard; but almost before he 
was out of my sight, he was out of my mind, 
and I was considering what I should say to my 
uncle.</p>
<p>My uncle's house stands quite alone in the 
midst of meadows and groves of trees, all of 
which are leafless now, and waved to and fro in 
the damp and heavy air, like funeral plumes. I 
trembled greatly as I lifted the brass knocker, 
which had a grinning face upon it; and I let it 
fall with one loud single rap, which set all the 
dogs barking, and the rooks cawing in the tops 
of the trees. The servant conducted me across a 
low-roofed hall, to a parlour beyond: low-roofed 
also, but large and handsome, with a warm glow 
of crimson, which was pleasant to my eyes, after 
the grey gloom of the November day. It was 
already afternoon; and a tall fine-looking old 
man was lying comfortably upon a sofa fast 
asleep; while upon the other side of the hearth 
sat a dwarfed old lady, who lifted her fore-finger 
with a gesture of silence, and beckoned me to 
take a seat near the fire. I obeyed, and presently 
fell into a meditation.</p>
<p>At length a man's voice broke the silence, 
asking in a drowsy tone,</p>
<p>"What young lass is this?"</p>
<p>"I am Eunice Fielding," I replied, rising with 
reverence to the aged man, my uncle; and he 
gazed upon me with his keen grey eyes, until I 
was abashed, and a tear or two rolled down my 
cheeks in spite of myself, for my heart was very 
heavy.</p>
<p>"By Jove!" he exclaimed, "as like Sophy 
as two peas out of one pod!" and he laughed a 
short laugh, which, in my ears, lacked merriment. 
"Come here, Eunice," he added, "and 
kiss me."</p>
<p>Whereupon I walked gravely across the open 
space between us, and bent my face to his; but 
he would have me to sit upon his knee, and I, 
who had been at no time used to be fondled 
thus, even by my father, sat there uncomfortably.</p>
<p>"Well, my pretty one," said my uncle, "what 
is your errand and request to me? Upon my 
soul, I feel ready to promise thee anything."</p>
<p>As he spake, I bethought me of King Herod, 
and the sinful dancing-girl, and my heart sank 
within me; but at last I took courage, as did 
Esther the queen, and I made known my urgent 
business to him, telling him, even with tears, 
that my father was threatened with a prison, if 
he could find none to befriend him.</p>
<p>"Eunice," said my uncle, after a very long 
silence, "I will make a bargain with you and your 
father. He stole away my favourite sister from 
me, and I never saw her face again. I've no 
children, and I'm a rich man. If your father will 
give you up to me, keeping no claim upon you--
even to never seeing your face again, if I so will 
it--then I will pay all his debts, and adopt you 
as my own daughter."</p>
<p>Before he could finish all these words, I sprang 
away from him, feeling more angered than I had 
ever done in my life.</p>
<p>"It could never be," I cried. "My father 
could never give me up, and I will never leave 
him."</p>
<p>"Be in no hurry to decide, Eunice," he said; 
"your father has two other daughters. I will 
give you an hour to reflect."</p>
<p>Upon that he and his wife left me alone in the 
pleasant room. My mind was firmly made up 
from the beginning. But as I sat before the 
glowing fire, it seemed as if all the bleak cold 
days of the coming winter trooped up and 
gathered round me, chilling the warm atmosphere 
of the room, and touching me with icy 
fingers, until I trembled like a coward. So I 
opened my little lot-book, which our pastor had 
given unto me, and I looked anxiously at the many 
slips of paper it contained. Many times I had 
drawn a lot from it, and found but vague counsel 
and comfort. But I now drew therefrom again, 
and the words upon the lot were, "Be of good 
courage!" Then I was greatly strengthened.</p>
<p>When the hour was ended, my uncle returned, 
and urged me with many worldly persuasions and 
allurements, mingled with threatenings, until at 
length I grew bold to answer him according to 
his snares.</p>
<p>"It is an evil thing," I said, "to tempt a child 
to forsake her father. Providence has put it into 
your power to lessen the sorrows of your fellow-creatures, 
but you seek to add to them. I would 
rather dwell with my father in a jail, than with 
you in a palace."</p>
<p>I turned and left him, finding my way out 
through the hall into the deepening twilight. It 
was more than a mile from the village through 
which the coach passed; and the hedge-banks 
rose high on each side of the deep lane. Though 
I walked very swiftly, the night came on before 
I had proceeded far from my uncle's house, with 
such thick gloom and fog that I could almost feel 
the darkness. "Be of good courage, Eunice!" 
said I; and to drive away the fears which lay in 
wait for me if I yielded but a little, I lifted up 
my voice, and began to sing our Evening Hymn.</p>
<p>Suddenly a voice a little way before me, took 
up the tune, in a clear deep rich tone, like that 
of the Brother who taught us music in the Settlement. 
As I stopped instantly, my heart leaping 
up with fear and a strange gladness, the 
voice before me ceased singing also.</p>
<p>"Good night," it said. There was such 
kindness and frankness and sweetness in the 
voice, that I trusted it at once.</p>
<p>"Wait for me," I said; "I am lost in the 
night, and I want to find my way to Longville."</p>
<p>"I am going there too," said the voice, to which 
I drew nearer each moment; and immediately I 
saw a tall dark figure in the mist beside me.</p>
<p>"Brother," I said, trembling a little, though 
wherefore I knew not. "are we far from Longville?"</p>
<p>"Only ten minutes' walk," he answered, in a 
blithe tone, which cheered me not a little. 
"Take my arm, and we shall soon be there."</p>
<p>As my hand rested on his arm lightly, I felt 
a sense of great support and protection. As we 
came near the lighted window of the village inn, 
we looked into one another's faces. His was 
pleasant and handsome, like some of the best 
pictures I have ever seen. I do not know why, 
but I thought of the Angel Gabriel.</p>
<p>"We are at Longville," he said; "tell me 
where I can take you to."</p>
<p>"Sir," I answered, for I could not say Brother 
to him in the light; "I wish first to get to 
Woodbury."</p>
<p>"To Woodbury," he repeated, "at this time 
of night, and alone! There is a return coach 
coming up in a few minutes, by which I travel to 
Woodbury. Will you accept of my escort 
there?"</p>
<p>"Sir, I thank you," I answered; and I stood 
silent beside him, until the coach lamps shone 
close upon us in the fog. The stranger opened 
the door, but I hung back with a foolish feeling 
of shame at my poverty, which it was needful to 
conquer.</p>
<p>"We are poor people," I stammered. "I 
must travel outside."</p>
<p>"Not such a winter's night as this," he said. 
"Jump in."</p>
<p>"No, no," I replied, recovering my senses, "I 
shall go outside." A decent country woman, with 
a child, were already seated on the top of the 
coach, and I quickly followed them. My seat 
was the outer one, and hung over the wheels. 
The darkness was so dense that the fitful glimmer 
of the coach-lamps upon the leafless hedge-rows 
was the only light to be seen. All else was black, 
pitchy night. I could think of nothing but my 
father, and the jail opening to imprison him. 
Presently I felt a hand laid firmly on my arm, 
and Gabriel's voice spake to me:</p>
<p>"Your seat is a dangerous one," he said. "A 
sudden jerk might throw you off."</p>
<p>"I am so miserable," I sobbed, all my courage 
breaking down; and in the darkness I buried 
my face in my hands, and wept silently; and 
even as I wept, the bitterness of my sorrow was 
assuaged.</p>
<p>"Brother," I said--for in the darkness I could 
call him so again. "I am only just come home 
from school, and I have not learned the ways and 
troubles of the world yet."</p>
<p>"My child," he answered, in a low tone, "I 
saw you lean your head upon your hands and 
weep. Can I be of any help to you?"</p>
<p>"No," I replied; "the sorrow belongs to me 
only, and to my house."</p>
<p>He said no more, but I felt his arm stretched 
out to form a barrier across the space where I 
might have fallen; and so through the black 
night we rode on to Woodbury.</p>
<p>Brother More was awaiting me at the coach-office. 
He hurried me away, scarcely giving me 
time to glance at Gabriel, who stood looking 
after me. He was eager to hear of my interview 
with my uncle; when I told him of my failure, 
he grew thoughtful, saying little until I was in 
the railway carriage, when he leaned forward 
and whispered, "Tell Priscilla I will come over 
in the morning."</p>
<p>Brother More is a rich man; perhaps, for Priscilla's 
sake, he will free my father.</p>
<p>Nov. 11. I dreamed last night that Gabriel 
stood beside me, saying, "I come to bring thee 
glad tidings." But as I listened eagerly, he 
sighed, and vanished away.</p>
<p>Nov. 15. Brother More is here every day, but 
he says nothing about helping my father. If 
help does not come soon, he will be cast into 
prison. Peradventure, my uncle will relent, and 
offer us some easier terms. If it were only to 
live half my time with him, I would consent to 
dwell in his house, even as Daniel and the three 
children dwelt unharmed in the court of Babylon. 
I will write to him to that effect.</p>
<p>Nov. 19. No answer from my uncle. To-day, 
going to Woodbury with Priscilla, who wished 
to converse with the pastor of the church there, 
I spent the hour she was engaged with him in 
finding my way to the jail, and walking round 
the outside of its gloomy and massive walls. I 
felt very mournful and faint-hearted, thinking of 
my poor father. At last, being very weary, I 
sat down on the step at the gateway, and looked 
into my little lot-book again. Once more I drew 
the verse, "Be of good courage." Just then, 
Brother More and Priscilla appeared. There 
was a look upon his face which I disliked, 
but I remembered that he was to be my 
sister's husband, and I rose and offered him 
my hand, which he tucked up under his arm, 
his fat hand resting upon it. So we three 
walked to and fro under the prison walls. 
Suddenly, in a garden sloping away beneath us, I 
perceived him whom I call Gabriel (not knowing 
any other name), with a fair sweet-looking young 
woman at his side. I could not refrain from 
weeping, for what reason I cannot tell, unless it 
be my father's affairs. Brother More returned 
home with us, and sent John Robins away. 
John Robins desired me to remember him, which 
I will as long as I live.</p>
<p>Nov. 20. Most miserable day. My poor father 
is in jail. At dinner-time to-day two most 
evil-looking men arrested him. God forgive me for 
wishing they were dead! Yet my father spake 
very patiently and gently.</p>
<p>"Send for Brother More," he said, after a 
pause, "and act according to his counsel."</p>
<p>So after a little while they carried him away.</p>
<p>What am I to do?</p>
<p>Nov. 30. Late last night we were still 
discoursing as to our future plans. Priscilla thinks 
Brother More will hasten their marriage, and 
Susannah has an inward assurance that the lot 
will fall to her to be Brother Schmidt's wife. 
She spake wisely of the duties of a missionary's 
life, and of the grace needed to fulfil them. But 
I could think of nothing but my father trying to 
sleep within the walls of the jail.</p>
<p>Brother More says he thinks he can see a way 
to release my father, only we are all to pray that 
we may have grace to conquer our self-will. I 
am sure I am willing to do anything, even to 
selling myself into slavery, as some of our first 
missionaries did in the slave-times in the West 
Indies. But in England one cannot sell one's 
self, though I would be a very faithful servant. 
I want to get at once a sum large enough to 
pay our debts. Brother More bids me not spoil 
my eyes with crying.</p>
<p>Dec. 1. The day on which my father was 
arrested, I made a last appeal to my uncle. This 
morning I had a brief note from him, saying he 
had commissioned his lawyer to visit me, and 
state the terms on which he was willing to aid 
me. Even as I read it, his lawyer desired to see 
me alone. I went to the parlour, trembling 
with anxiety. It was no other than Gabriel who 
stood before me, and I took heart, remembering 
my dream that he appeared to me, saying, "I 
come to bring thee glad tidings."</p>
<p>"Miss Eunice Fielding," he said, in his pleasant 
voice, and looking down upon me with a 
smile which seemed to shed sunshine upon my 
sad and drooping spirit.</p>
<p>"Yes," I answered, my eyes falling foolishly 
before his; and I beckoned to him to resume his 
seat, while I stood leaning against my mother's 
great arm-chair.</p>
<p>"I have a hard message for you," said Gabriel; 
"your uncle has dictated this paper, 
which must be signed by you and your father. 
He will release Mr. Fielding, and settle one 
hundred pounds a year upon him, on condition 
that he will retire to some German Moravian 
settlement, and that you will accept the former 
terms."</p>
<p>"I cannot," I cried bitterly. "Oh! sir, ought 
I to leave my father?"</p>
<p>"I am afraid not," he answered, in a low 
voice.</p>
<p>"Sir," I said, "you must please say 'no' to 
my uncle."</p>
<p>"I will," he replied, "and make it sound as 
gently as I can. You have a friend in me, Miss 
Eunice."</p>
<p>His voice lingered upon Eunice, as if it were 
no common name to him, but something rare and 
pleasing. I never heard it spoken so pleasantly 
before. After a little while he rose to take his 
leave.</p>
<p>"Brother," I said, giving him my hand, "farewell."</p>
<p>"I shall see you again, Miss Eunice," he 
answered.</p>
<p>He saw me again sooner than he expected, for 
I travelled by the next train to Woodbury, and, 
as I left the dark carriage in which I journeyed, 
I saw him alight from another part of the train, 
and at the same instant his eyes fell upon me.</p>
<p>"Where are you going to now, Eunice?" he 
demanded.</p>
<p>It seemed a pleasanter greeting than if he had 
called me Miss. I told him I knew my way to 
the jail, for that I had been not long ago to look 
at the outside of it. I saw the tears stand in his 
eyes, but, without speaking, he drew my hand 
through his arm, and I silently, but with a very 
lightened heart, walked beside him to the great 
portal of my father's prison.</p>
<p>We entered a square court, with nothing to 
be seen save the grey winter sky lying, as it 
were flat, overhead; and there was my father, 
pacing to and fro, with his arms crossed upon 
his breast and his head bowed down, as if it 
would never be raised again. I cried aloud, and 
ran and fell on his neck, and knew nothing more 
until I opened my eyes in a small bare room, and 
felt my father holding me in his arms, and Gabriel 
kneeling before me, chafing my hands, and 
pressing his lips upon them.</p>
<p>Afterwards Gabriel and my father conferred 
together; but before long Brother More arrived, 
whereupon Gabriel departed. Brother More 
said, solemnly:</p>
<p>"That man is a wolf in sheep's clothing, and 
our Eunice is a tender lamb."</p>
<p>I cannot believe that Gabriel is a wolf.</p>
<p>Dec. 2. I have taken a room in a cottage near 
the jail, the abode of John Robins and his wife, 
a decent tidy woman. So I can spend every day 
with my father.</p>
<p>Dec. 13. My father has been in prison a whole 
fortnight. Brother More went over to see Priscilla 
last night, and this morning he is to lay 
before us his plan for my father's release. I am 
going to meet him at the jail.</p>
<p>When I entered the room, my father and 
Brother More looked greatly perturbed, and my 
poor father leaned back in his chair, as if 
exhausted after a long conflict.</p>
<p>"Speak to her, brother," he said.</p>
<p>Then Brother More told us of a heavenly vision 
which had appeared to him, directing him to break 
off his betrothal to Priscilla, and to take me--
<em>me!</em>--for his wife. After which he awoke, and 
these words abode in his mind, "The dream is 
certain, and the interpretation thereof sure."</p>
<p>"Therefore, Eunice," he said, in an awful 
voice, "do you and Priscilla see to it, lest you 
should be found fighting against the Lord."</p>
<p>I was struck dumb as with a great shock, but 
I heard him add these words:</p>
<p>"I was also instructed in the vision, to set 
your father free, upon the day that you become 
my wife."</p>
<p>"But," I said at last, my whole heart recoiling 
from him, "this would be a shameful wrong to 
Priscilla. It cannot be a vision from Heaven, but 
a delusion and snare. Marry Priscilla, and set my 
father free? Surely, surely, it was a lying vision."</p>
<p>"No," he said, fastening his gaze upon me; 
"I chose Priscilla rashly of my own judgment. 
Therein I erred; but I have promised her half 
her dowry as a compensation for my error."</p>
<p>"Father," I cried, "surely I ought to have 
some direction also, as well as he. Why should 
only he have a vision?" Then I added that I 
would go home and see Priscilla, and seek a 
sign for my own guidance.</p>
<p>December 14. Priscilla was ill in bed when I 
reached home, and refused to see me. I arose at 
five o'clock this morning, and stole down into the 
parlour. As I lighted the lamp, the parlour looked 
forlorn and deserted, and yet there lingered about 
it a ghostly feeling, as if perhaps my mother, and 
the dead children whom I never saw, had been 
sitting on the hearth in the night, as we sat in the 
daytime. Maybe she knew of my distress, and 
had left some tokens for my comfort and counsel. 
My Bible lay upon the table, but it was closed; 
her angel fingers had not opened it upon any 
verse that might have guided me. There was no 
mode of seeking direction, save by casting of 
lots.</p>
<p>I cut three little slips of paper of one length, 
and exactly similar--<em>three</em>, though surely I only 
needed two. Upon the first I wrote, "To be 
Brother More's wife," and upon the second, "To 
be a Single Sister." The third lay upon the desk, 
blank and white, as if waiting for some name to 
be written upon it, and suddenly all the chilly 
cold of the winter morning passed into a sultry 
heat, until I threw open the casement, and let 
the frosty air breathe upon my face. I said in 
my own heart I would leave myself a chance, 
though my conscience smote me for that word 
"chance." So I laid the three slips of paper 
between the leaves of my Bible, and sat down 
opposite to them, afraid of drawing the lot which 
held the secret of my future life.</p>
<p>There was no mark to guide me in the choice 
of one slip of paper from another; and I dared 
not stretch out my hand to draw one of them. For 
I was bound to abide by the solemn decision. It 
seemed too horrible to become Brother More's 
wife; and to me the Sisters' Home, where the 
Single Sisters dwell, having all things in common, 
seems dreary and monotonous and somewhat 
desolate. But if I should draw the blank 
paper! My heart fluttered; again and again 
I stretched out my hand, and withdrew it; 
until at last the oil in the lamp being spent, its 
light grew dimmer and dimmer, and, fearful of 
being still longer without guidance, I snatched 
the middle lot from between the leaves of my 
Bible. There was only a glimmer of dying light, 
by which I read the words, "To be Brother 
More's wife."</p>
<p>That is the last entry in my journal, written 
three years ago.</p>
<p>When Susannah came down stairs and entered 
the parlour, she found me sitting before my desk, 
almost in an idiotic state, with that miserable lot 
in my hand. There was no need to explain it to 
her; she looked at the other slip of paper, one 
blank, and the other inscribed, "To be a Single 
Sister," and she knew I had been casting lots. 
I remember her crying over me a little, and 
kissing me with unaccustomed tenderness; and 
then she returned to ber chamber, and I heard 
her speaking to Priscilla in grave and sad tones. 
After that, we were all passive; even Priscilla was 
stolidly resigned. Brother More came over, and 
Susannah informed him of the irrevocable lot 
which I had drawn; but besought him to refrain 
from seeing me that day; and he left me alone 
to grow somewhat used to the sense of my 
wretchedness.</p>
<p>Early the next morning I returned to Woodbury; 
my only consolation being the thought 
that my dear father would be set free, and might 
live with me in wealth and comfort all the rest of 
his life. During the succeeding days I scarcely 
left his side, never suffering Brother More to be 
alone with me; and morning and night John 
Robins or his wife accompanied me to the gate 
of the jail, and waited for me to return with them 
to their cottage.</p>
<p>My father was to be set free, only on my 
wedding-day, and the marriage was hurried on. 
Many of Priscilla's store of wedding garments 
were suitable for me. Every hour brought my 
doom nearer.</p>
<p>One morning, in the gloom and twilight of a 
December dawn, I suddenly met Gabriel in my 
path. He spake rapidly and earnestly, but I 
scarcely knew what he said, and I answered, falteringly:</p>
<p>"I am going to be married to Brother Joshua 
More on New Year's-day, and he will then 
release my father."</p>
<p>"Eunice," he cried, standing before me in the 
narrow path, "you can never marry him. I 
know the fat hypocrite. Good Heaven! I love 
you a hundred times better than he does. Love! 
The rascal does not know what it means."</p>
<p>I answered not a word, for I felt afraid both 
of myself and him, though I did not believe 
Gabriel to be a wolf in sheep's clothing.</p>
<p>"Do you know who I am?" he asked.</p>
<p>"No," I whispered.</p>
<p>"I am your uncle's nephew by marriage," he 
said, "and I have been brought up in his house. 
Break off this wicked marriage with the fellow 
More, and I will engage to release your father. 
I am young, and can work. I will pay your 
father's debts."</p>
<p>"It is impossible," I replied. "Brother More 
has had a heavenly vision, and I have drawn the 
lot. There is no hope. I must marry him upon 
New Year's-day."</p>
<p>Then Gabriel persuaded me to tell him the 
whole story of my trouble. He laughed a little, 
and bade me be of good comfort; and I could 
not make him understand how impossible it was 
that I should contend against the dispensation 
of the lot.</p>
<p>Always when I was with my father I strove 
to conceal my misery, talking to him of the 
happy days we should spend together some time. 
Likewise I sang within the walls of the prison, 
the simple hymns which we had been wont to 
sing in the peaceful church at school amid a 
congregation of serene hearts, and I strengthened 
my own heart and my father's by the recollected 
counsels of my dear lost pastor. Thus my father 
guessed little of my hidden suffering, and looked 
forward with hope to the day that would throw 
open his prison doors.</p>
<p>Once I went to the pastor, dwelling in Woodbury, 
and poured out my heart to him--save that 
I made no mention of Gabriel--and he told me 
it was often thus with young girls before their 
marriage, but that I had a clear leading; he also 
told me that Brother More was a devout man, 
and I should soon love and reverence him as my 
husband.</p>
<p>At length the last day of the year came; a 
great day among our people, when we drew our 
lot for the following year. Everything seemed 
at an end. All hope fled from me, if there ever 
had been any hope in my heart. I left my father 
early in the evening, for I could no longer conceal 
my wretchedness; yet when I was outside 
the prison walls I wandered to and fro, hovering 
about it, as if these days, miserable as they had 
been, were happy to those which were drawing 
near. Brother More had not been near us all day, 
but doubtless he was busy in his arrangements 
to release my father. I was still lingering under 
the great walls, when a carriage drove up 
noiselessly--for the ground was sprinkled with soft 
snow--and Gabriel sprang out, and almost 
clasped me in his arms.</p>
<p>"My dear Eunice," he said, "you must come 
with me at once. Our uncle will save you from 
this hateful marriage."</p>
<p>I do not know what I should have done had 
not John Robins called out from the driver's 
seat, "All right, Miss Eunice; remember John 
Robins."</p>
<p>Upon that I left myself in Gabriel's hands, and 
he lifted me into the carriage, wrapping warm 
coverings about me. It seemed to me no other 
than a happy dream, as we drove noiselessly 
along snowy roads, with the pale wan light of 
the young moon falling upon the white country, 
and now and then shining upon the face of Gabriel, 
as he leaned forward from time to time to 
draw the wrappers closer round me.</p>
<p>We might have been three hours on the way, 
when we turned into a by-road, which presently I 
recognised as the deep lane wherein I had first 
met Gabriel. We were going then to my uncle's 
house. So with a lightened heart I stepped out 
of the carriage, and entered his doors for the 
second time.</p>
<p>Gabriel conducted me into the parlour which 
I had seen before, and placed me in a chair upon 
the hearth, removing my shawl and bonnet with 
a pleasant and courteous care; and he was standing 
opposite to me, regarding me with a smile 
upon his handsome face, when the door opened 
and my uncle entered.</p>
<p>"Come and kiss me, Eunice," he said; and I 
obeyed him wonderingly.</p>
<p>"Child," he continued, stroking my hair back 
from my face, "you would not come to me of 
your own will, so I commissioned this young 
fellow to kidnap you. We are not going to have 
you marry Joshua More. I cannot do with him 
as my nephew. Let him marry Priscilla."</p>
<p>There was such a hearty tone in my uncle's 
voice, that for a moment I felt comforted, 
though I knew that he could not set aside my 
lot. So he seated me beside him, while I still 
looked with wonderment into his face.</p>
<p>"I am going to draw a lot for you," he said, 
with an air of merriment; "what would my little 
rosebud say to her fat suitor, if she knew that 
her father was a freed man at this moment?"</p>
<p>I dared not look into his face or into Gabriel's. 
For I remembered that I myself had sought for a 
token; and that no earthly power could set aside 
that, or the heavenly vision also, which Brother 
More had seen.</p>
<p>"Uncle," I said, shuddering, "I have no 
voice in this matter. I drew the lot fairly, and 
I must abide by it. You cannot help me."</p>
<p>"We will see," he answered; "it is New 
Year's-eve, you know, and time to draw again. 
The lot will neither be to become Brother More's 
wife, nor a Single Sister, I promise you. We 
shall draw the blank this time!"</p>
<p>While I yet wondered at these words, I heard 
a sound of footsteps in the hall, and the door 
opened, and my beloved father stood upon the 
threshold, stretching out his arms to me. How 
he came there I knew not; but I flew to him 
with a glad cry, and hid my face upon his 
breast.</p>
<p>"You are welcome, Mr. Fielding," said my 
uncle; "Phil!"--it did now appear that Gabriel's 
name was Philip--"bring Mr. More this 
way."</p>
<p>I started with fright and wonder, and my 
father also looked troubled, and drew me nearer 
to his side. Brother More entered with a 
cowardly and downcast mien, which made him 
appear a hundred-fold more repulsive in my 
eyes, as he stood near the door, with his craven 
face turned towards us.</p>
<p>"Mr. More," said my uncle, "I believe you 
are to marry my niece, Eunice Fielding, tomorrow?"</p>
<p>"I did not know she was your niece," he 
answered, in an abject tone. "I would not have 
presumed----"</p>
<p>"But the heavenly vision, Mr. More?" interrupted 
my uncle.</p>
<p>He looked round for a moment, with a spiritless 
glance, and his eyes sank.</p>
<p>"It was a delusion," he muttered.</p>
<p>"It was a lie!" said Gabriel.</p>
<p>"Mr. More," continued my uncle, "if the 
heavenly vision be true, it will cost you the sum 
of five thousand five hundred pounds, the amount 
in which you are indebted to me, with sundry 
sums due to my nephew here. Yet if it be true, 
you must abide by it, of course."</p>
<p>"It was not true," he answered; "the vision 
was concerning Priscilla, to whom I was 
betrothed. I was ensnared to change the name 
to that of Eunice."</p>
<p>"Then go and marry Priscilla," said my uncle, 
good humouredly. "Philip, take him away."</p>
<p>But Priscilla would have no more to do with 
Brother More, and shortly afterwards she settled 
among the Single Sisters in the same settlement 
where I had lived my quiet and peaceful youth. 
Her store of wedding garments, which had been 
altered to fit me, came in at last for Susannah, 
who was chosen to be the wife of Brother 
Schmidt, according to her inward assurance; 
and she went out to join him in the West Indies, 
from whence she writes many happy letters. I 
was troubled for a time about my lot, but certainly 
if Brother More'a vision was concerning 
Priscilla, I could not be required to abide by it. 
Moreover, I never saw him again. My uncle 
and father, who had never met before, formed a 
close friendship, and my uncle would hear of nothing 
but that we should dwell together in his 
large mansion, where I might be as a daughter 
unto both of them. People say we have left 
the Church of the United Brethren; but it is 
not so. Only, as I had found one evil man 
within it, so also I have found some good men 
without it.</p>
<p>Gabriel is not one of the Brethren.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken In Water."/>
<p>Minnie, my blessed little wife, and I, had 
been just one month married. We had returned 
only two days from our honeymoon tour at 
Killarney. I was a junior partner in the firm 
of Schwarzmoor and Laddock, bankers, 
Lombard-street (I must conceal real names), and I 
had four days more of my leave of absence still 
to enjoy. I was supremely happy in my bright 
new cottage south-west of London, and was 
revelling in delicious idleness on that bright 
October morning, watching the great yellow 
leaves fall in the sunshine. Minnie sat by me 
under the hawthorn-tree; otherwise, I should 
not have been supremely happy.</p>
<p>Little Betsy, Minnie's maid, came fluttering 
down the garden with an ominous-looking letter 
in her hand.</p>
<p>It was a telegram from Mr. Schwarzmoor. It 
contained only these words:</p>
<p>"We want you to start to the Continent 
directly with specie. Neapolitan loan. No delay. 
Transactions of great importance since you left. 
Sorry to break up holiday. Be at office by 6.30. 
Start from London Bridge by 9.15, and catch 
Dover night boat."</p>
<p>"Is the boy gone?"</p>
<p>"Boy did not leave it, sir. Elderly gentleman, 
going to Dawson's, brought it. The 
office boy was out, and the gentleman happened 
to be coming past our house."</p>
<p>"Herbert dear, you won't go, you mustn't 
go," said Minnie, leaning on my shoulder, and 
bending down her face. "Don't go."</p>
<p>"I must, my dearest. The firm has no one to 
trust to, but me, in such a case. It is but a 
week's absence. I must start in ten minutes, 
and catch the 4.20 on its way up."</p>
<break/>
<p>"That was a very important telegram," I said 
sharply to the station-master, "and you ought not 
to have sent it by any unknown and unauthorised 
person. Who <em>was</em> this old gentleman, pray?"</p>
<p>"Who was it, Harvey?" said the station-master, 
rather sulkily, to the porter.</p>
<p>"Old gent, sir, very respectable, as comes to 
the Dawsons', the training-stables. Has horses 
there."</p>
<p>"Do not let that sort of thing occur again, 
Mr. Jennings," I said, "or I shall be obliged to 
report it. I wouldn't have had that telegram 
mislaid, for a hundred pounds."</p>
<p>Mr. Jennings, the station-master, grumbled 
something, and then boxed the telegraph boy's 
ears. Which seemed to do him (Mr. Jennings) 
good.</p>
<break/>
<p>"We were getting very anxious," said Mr. 
Schwarzmoor, as I entered the bank parlour, 
only three minutes late. "Very anxious, weren't 
we, Goldrick?"</p>
<p>"Very anxious," said the little neat head 
clerk. "Very anxious."</p>
<p>Mr. Schwarzmoor was a full faced man of about 
sixty, with thick white eyebrows and a red face--
a combination which gave him an expression 
of choleric old age. He was a shrewd severe 
man of business: a little impetuous and fond of 
rule, but polite, kind, and considerate.</p>
<p>"I hope your charming wife is quite well. 
Sorry, indeed, to break up your holiday; but 
no help for it, my dear fellow. There is the specie 
in those two iron boxes, enclosed in leather to 
look like samples. They are fastened with letter-locks, 
and contain a quarter of a million in gold. 
The Neapolitan king apprehends a rebellion." 
(It was three years before Garibaldi's victories.) 
"You will take the money to Messrs. Pagliavicini 
and Rossi, No. 172 Toledo, Naples. The names 
that open the locks are, on the one with the 
white star on the cover, Masinisa; on the one 
with the black star, Cotopaxo. Of course you 
will not forget the talismanic words. Open the 
boxes at Lyons, to make sure that all is safe. 
Talk to no one. Make no friends on the road. 
Your commission is of vast importance."</p>
<p>"I shall pass," said I, "for a commercial traveller."</p>
<p>"Pardon me for my repeated cautions, Blamyre, 
but I am an older man than you, and 
know the danger of travelling with specie. If 
your purpose was known to-night in Paris, your 
road to Marseilles would be as dangerous as if 
all the galley-slaves at Toulon had been let loose 
in special chase of you. I do not doubt your 
discretion: I only warn you to be careful. Of 
course, you go armed?"</p>
<p>I opened my coat, and showed a belt under my 
waistcoat, with a revolver in it. At which warlike 
spectacle the old clerk drew back in alarm.</p>
<p>"Good!" said Mr. Schwarzmoor. "But one 
grain of prudence is worth five times the five 
bullets in those five barrels. You will stop in 
Paris to-morrow to transact business with 
Lefebre and Desjeans, and you will go on by the 
12.15 (night) to Marseilles, catching the boat on 
Friday. We will telegraph to you at Marseilles. 
Are the letters for Paris ready, Mr. Hargrave?"</p>
<p>"Yes, sir, nearly ready. Mr. Wilkins is hard 
at them."</p>
<break/>
<p>I reached Dover by midnight, and instantly 
engaged four porters to carry my specie chests 
down the stone steps leading from the pier to the 
Calais boat. The first was taken on board quite 
safely; but while the second was being carried 
down, one of the men slipped, and would 
certainly have fallen into the water, had he not been 
caught in the arms of a burly old Indian officer, 
who, laden with various traps, and urging forward 
his good-natured but rather vulgar wife, 
was preceding me.</p>
<p>"Steady there, my lad," he said. "Why, 
what have you got there? Hardware?"</p>
<p>"Don't know, sir; I only know it's heavy 
enough to break any man's back," was the rough 
answer, as the man thanked his questioner in his 
blunt way.</p>
<p>"These steps, sir, are very troublesome for 
bringing down heavy goods," said an obliging 
voice behind me. "I presume, sir, from your 
luggage, that we are of the same profession?"</p>
<p>I looked round as we just then stepped on 
board. The person who addressed me was a 
tall thin man, with a long and rather Jewish nose, 
and a narrow elongated face. He wore a greatcoat 
too short for him, a flowered waistcoat, 
tight trousers, a high shirt collar, and a light 
sprigged stiff neckcloth.</p>
<p>I replied that I <em>had</em> the honour to be a 
commercial traveller, and that I thought we 
were going to have a rough night of it.</p>
<p>"Decidedly dirty night," he replied; "and 
I advise you, sir, to secure a berth at once. The 
boat, I see, is very crowded."</p>
<p>I went straight to my berth, and lay down for 
an hour; at the end of that time I got up and 
looked around me. At one of the small tables 
sat half a dozen of the passengers, including 
the old Indian and my old-fashioned interrogator. 
They were drinking bottled porter, 
and appeared very sociable. I rose and joined 
them, and we exchanged some remarks not 
complimentary to night travelling.</p>
<p>"By Jove, sir, it is simply unbearable!" said 
the jovial Major Baxter (for he soon told us his 
name); "it is as stifling as Peshawah when the 
hot Tinsang wind is blowing; suppose we three 
go on deck and take a little air? My wife 
suffers in these crossings; she's invisible, I know, 
till the boat stops. Steward, bring up some more 
bottled porter."</p>
<p>When we got on deck, I saw, to my extreme 
surprise, made conspicuous by their black and 
white stars, four other cases exactly similar to 
mine, except that they had no painted brand upon 
them. I could hardly believe my eyes; but 
there they were; leather covers, letter-locks, 
and all.</p>
<p>"Those are mine, sir," remarked Mr. Levison 
(I knew my fellow-commercial's name from the 
captain's having addressed him by it). "I 
am travelling for the house of Mackintosh. 
Those cases contain waterproof paletots, the 
best made. Our house has used such cases for 
forty years. It is sometimes inconvenient, this 
accidental resemblance of luggage--leads to 
mistakes. Your goods are much heavier than 
my goods, as I judge? Gas improvements, 
railway chairs, cutlery, or something else in 
iron?"</p>
<p>I was silent, or I made some vague reply.</p>
<p>"Sir," said Levison, "I augur well of your 
future; trade secrets should be kept inviolate. 
Don't you think so, sir?"</p>
<p>The major thus appealed to, replied, "Sir, by 
Jove, you're right! One cannot be too careful 
in these days. Egad, sir, the world is a mass of 
deceit."</p>
<p>"There's Calais light!" cried some one at 
that moment; and there it was, straight ahead, 
casting sparkles of comfort over the dark water.</p>
<p>I thought no more of my travelling companions. 
We parted at Paris: I went my way 
and they went their way. The major was going 
to pay a visit at Dromont, near Lyons; thence he 
would go to Marseilles en route for Alexandria. 
Mr. Levison was bound for Marseilles, like 
myself and the major, but not by my train--at 
least he feared not--as he had much to do in 
Paris.</p>
<p>I had transacted my business in the French 
capital, and was on my way to the Palais Royal, 
with M. Lefebre fils, a great friend of mine. It 
was about six o'clock, and we were crossing the 
Rue St. Honor, when there passed us a tall 
Jewish-looking person, in a huge white 
mackintosh, whom I recognised as Mr. Levison. 
He was in a hired open carriage, and his 
four boxes were by his side. I bowed to him, 
but he did not seem to notice me.</p>
<p>"Eh bien! That drle, who is that?" said 
my friend, with true Parisian superciliousness.</p>
<p>I replied that it was only a fellow-passenger, 
who had crossed with me the night before.</p>
<p>In the very same street I ran up against the 
major and his wife, on their way to the railway 
station.</p>
<p>"Infernal city, this," said the major; "smells 
so of onion. I should like, if it was mine, to wash 
it out, house by house; 'tain't wholesome, 'pon 
my soul 'tain't wholesome. Julia, my dear, 
this is my pleasant travelling companion of last 
night. By-the-by, just saw that commercial 
traveller! Sharp business man that: no sightseeing 
about <em>him</em>. Bourse and bank all day,--
senior partner some day."</p>
<p>"And how many more?" said my friend 
Lefebre, when we shook hands and parted with 
the jolly major. "That is a good boy--he 
superabounds--he overflows--but he is one 
of your epicurean lazy officers, I am sure. 
Your army, it must be reformed, or India will 
slip from you like a handful of sand--vous verrez, 
mon cher."</p>
<p>Midnight came, and I was standing at the terminus, 
watching the transport of my luggage, 
when a cab drove up, and an Englishman leaping 
out asked the driver in excellent French for 
change for a five-franc piece. It was Levison; 
but I saw no more of him, for the crowd just 
then pushed me forward.</p>
<p>I took my seat with only two other persons 
in the carriage--two masses of travelling cloak 
and capote--two bears, for all I could see to 
the contrary.</p>
<p>Once away from the lights of Paris, and in the 
pitch dark country, I fell asleep and dreamed 
of my dear little wife, and our dear little home. 
Then a feeling of anxiety ran across my mind. 
I dreamed that I had forgotten the words with 
which to open the letter-locks. I ransacked 
mythology, history, science, in vain. Then I 
was in the banking parlour at No. 172 Toledo, 
Naples, threatened with instant death by a file of 
soldiers, if I did not reveal the words, or explain 
where the boxes had been hid; for I had hidden 
them for some inscrutable no reason. At that 
moment an earthquake shook the city, a flood of 
fire rolled past beneath the window, Vesuvius 
had broken loose and was upon us. I cried in 
my agony--"Gracious Heaven, reveal to me 
those words!" when I awoke.</p>
<p>"Dromont! Dromont! Dix minutes d'arrte, 
messieurs."</p>
<p>Half blinded with the sudden light, I stumbled 
to the buffet, and asked for a cup of coffee, when 
three or four noisy young English tourists came 
hurrying in, surrounding a quiet imperturbable 
elderly commercial traveller. It was actually 
Levison again! They led him along in triumph, 
and called for champagne.</p>
<p>"Yes! yes!" the leader said. "You must 
have some, old fellow. We have won three games, 
you know, and you held such cards, too. Come 
along, look alive, you fellow with the nightcap--
Cliquot--gilt top, you duffer. You shall have 
your revenge before we get to Lyons, old chap."</p>
<p>Levison chattered good humouredly about 
the last game, and took the wine. In a few 
minutes the young men had drunk their champagne, 
and had gone out to smoke. In another 
moment Levison caught my eye.</p>
<p>"Why, good gracious," he said, "who'd have 
thought of this! Well, I am glad to see you. 
Now, my dear sir, you must have some champagne 
with me. Here, another bottle, monsieur, 
if you please. I hope, long before we get to 
Lyons, to join you, my dear sir. I am tired of 
the noise of those youngsters. Besides, I object 
to high stakes, on principle."</p>
<p>The moment the waiter brought the champagne, 
Levison took the bottle.</p>
<p>"No," he said; "I never allow any one to 
open wine for me." He turned his back from 
me to remove the wire; removed it; and was 
filling my glass; when up dashed a burly hearty 
man to shake hands with me--so awkward in 
his heartiness that he broke the champagne 
bottle. Not a drop of the wine was saved. 
It was the major--hot as usual, and in a 
tremendous bustle.</p>
<p>"By Jove, sir; dooced sorry. Let me order 
another bottle. How are you, gentlemen? Lucky, 
indeed, to meet you both again. Julia's with 
the luggage. We can be very cozy together. 
More champagne here. What's bottle in 
French? Most shameful thing! Those French 
friends of Julia's were gone off to Biarritz, 
pretending to have forgotten that we were coming--
after six weeks with us in London, too! 
Precious shabby, not to put too fine a point upon it. 
By Jove, sir, there's the bell. We'll all go in the 
same carriage. They will not bring that champagne."</p>
<p>Levison looked rather annoyed. "I shall 
not see you," he said, "for a station or two. 
I must join those boys, and let them give me 
my revenge. Cleared me out of twenty guineas! 
I have not been so imprudent since I was first 
on the road. Good-bye, Major Baxter--good-bye, 
Mr. Blamyre!"</p>
<p>I wondered how this respectable old fellow, 
who so keenly relished his game at whist, had 
got hold of my name; but I remembered in a 
moment that he must have seen the direction on 
my luggage.</p>
<p>Flashes of crimson and green lights, a shout 
from some pointsman, a glimpse of rows of 
poplars, and lines of suburban houses, and we 
once more plunged into the yielding darkness.</p>
<p>I found the major very droll and pleasant, 
but evidently ruled by his fussy, good-natured, 
managing, masculine wife. He was full of 
stories of bungalows, compounds, and the hills; 
in all of which narrations he was perpetually 
interrupted by Mrs. Baxter.</p>
<p>"By Jove, sir!" he said, "I wish I could 
sell out, and go into your line of business. I 
am almost sick of India--it deranges one's liver 
so infernally."</p>
<p>"Now, John, how can you go on so! You 
know you never had a day's illness in all your 
life, except that week when you smoked out a 
whole box of Captain Mason's cheroots."</p>
<p>"Well, I pulled through it, Julia," said the 
major, striking himself a tremendous blow on 
the chest; "but I've been an unlucky devil as 
to promotion--always bad luck in everything. 
If I bought a horse, it made a point of going 
lame next day; never went in a train but it 
broke down."</p>
<p>"Now don't, John; pray don't go on so," 
said Mrs. Baxter, "or I shall really be very 
angry. Such nonsense! You'll get your step in 
time. Be patient, like me, major; take things 
more quietly. I hope you put a direction on 
that hat-box of yours? Where is the sword-case? 
If it wasn't for me, major, you'd get to 
Suez with nothing but the coat on your back."</p>
<p>Just then, the train stopped at Charmont, 
and in tripped Levison, with his white mackintosh 
over his arm, and his bundle of umbrellas 
and sticks.</p>
<p>"No more sovereign points for me!" he said, 
producing a pack of cards. "But if you and the 
major and Mrs. Baxter would like a rubber--
shilling points--I'm for you. Cut for partners."</p>
<p>We assented with pleasure. We cut for 
partners. I and Mrs. Baxter against the major 
and Levison. We won nearly every game. 
Levison played too cautiously, and the major 
laughed, talked, and always forgot what cards 
were out.</p>
<p>Still it killed the time; the red and black 
turned up, changed, and ran into remarkable 
sequences; and the major's flukes and 
extraordinary luck in holding (not in playing) cards 
amused us, we laughed at Levison's 
punctilious care, and at Mrs. Baxter's avarice for 
tricks, and were as pleasant a party as the dim 
lamp of a night-train ever shone on. I could think 
of little, nevertheless, but my precious boxes.</p>
<p>There we were rushing through France, seeing 
nothing, heeding nothing, and having as little to 
do with our means of transit as if we had been 
four Arabian princes, seated on a flying 
enchanted carpet.</p>
<p>The game gradually grew more intermittent, 
the conversation more incessant. Levison, stiff 
of neckcloth as ever, and imperturbable and 
punctilious as ever, became chatty. He grew 
communicative about his business.</p>
<p>"I have at last," he said, in his precise and 
measured voice, "after years of attention to the 
subject, discovered the great secret which the 
waterproofers have so long coveted; how to let 
out the heated air of the body, and yet at the 
same time to exclude the rain. On my return 
to London, I offer this secret to the Mackintosh 
firm for ten thousand pounds; if they 
refuse the offer, I at once open a shop in Paris, 
call the new fabric Magentosh, in honour of the 
emperor's great Italian victory, and sit down and 
quietly realise a cool million--that's my way!"</p>
<p>"That's the real business tone," said the 
major, admiringly.</p>
<p>"Ah, major," cried his wife, ever ready to 
improve a subject, "if you had only had a little 
of Mr. Levison's prudence and energy, then, 
indeed, you'd have been colonel of your regiment 
before this."</p>
<p>Mr. Levison then turned the conversation to 
the subject of locks.</p>
<p>"I always use the letter-lock myself," he said. 
"My two talismanic words are TURLURETTE 
and PAPAGAYO--two names I once heard in 
an old French farce--who could guess them? 
It would take the adroitest thief seven hours to 
decipher even one. You find letter-locks safe, 
sir?" (He turned to me.)</p>
<p>I replied dryly that I did, and asked what 
time our train was due at Lyons.</p>
<p>"We are due at Lyons at 4.30," said the 
major; "it is now five to four. I don't know 
how it is, but I have a sort of presentiment 
tonight of some break-down. I am always in for it. 
When I went tiger-hunting, it was always my 
elephant that the beast pinned. If some of us 
were ordered up to an unhealthy out-of-the-way 
fort, it was always my company. It may be 
superstitious, I own, but I feel we shall have a 
break-down before we get to Marseilles. How fast 
we're going! Only see how the carriage rocks!"</p>
<p>I unconsciously grew nervous, but I 
concealed it. Could the major be a rogue, planning 
some scheme against me? But no: his red 
bluff face, and his clear good-natured guileless 
eyes, refuted the suspicion.</p>
<p>"Nonsense, be quiet, major; that's the way 
you always make a journey disagreeable," said 
his wife, arranging herself for sleep. Then 
Levison began talking about his early life, and 
how, in George the Fourth's time, he was 
travelling for a cravat house in Bond-street. He 
grew eloquent in favour of the old costume.</p>
<p>"Low Radical fellows," he said, "run down 
the first gentleman in Europe, as he was justly 
called. I respect his memory. He was a wit, 
and the friend of wits; he was lavishly generous, 
and disdained poor pitiful economy. He 
dressed well, sir; he looked well, sir; he was 
a gentleman of perfect manners. Sir, this is a 
slovenly and shabby age. When I was young, no 
gentleman ever travelled without at least two 
dozen cravats, four whalebone stiffeners, and an 
iron to smooth the tie, and produce a thin equal 
edge to the muslin. There were no less, sir, than 
eighteen modes of putting on the cravat; there 
was the cravate  la Diane, the cravate  
l'Anglaise, the cravate au nud Gordien, the 
cravate----"</p>
<p>The train jolted, moved on, slackened, 
stopped.</p>
<p>The major thrust his head out of window, 
and shouted to a passing guard:</p>
<p>"Where are we?"</p>
<p>"Twenty miles from Lyons--Fort Rouge, 
monsieur."</p>
<p>"What is the matter? Anything the matter?"</p>
<p>An English voice answered from the next 
window:</p>
<p>"A wheel broken, they tell us. We shall 
have to wait two hours, and transfer the luggage."</p>
<p>"Good Heaven!" I could not help exclaiming.</p>
<p>Levison put his head out of window. "It is 
but too true," he said, drawing it in again; 
"two hours' delay at least, the man says. 
Tiresome, very--but such things will happen on 
the road; take it coolly. We'll have some 
coffee and another rubber. We must each look 
to our own luggage; or, if Mr. Blamyre goes in 
and orders supper, I'll see to it all. But, good 
gracious, what is that shining out there by the 
station lamps? Hei, monsieur!" (to a passing 
gendarme whom the major had hailed), "what 
is going on at the station?"</p>
<p>"Monsieur," said the gendarme, saluting, 
"those are soldiers of the First Chasseurs; 
they happened to be at the station on their 
way to Chlons; the station-master has sent 
them to surround the luggage-van, and see to 
the transfer of the baggage. No passenger is 
to go near it, as there are government stores of 
value in the train."</p>
<p>Levison spat on the ground and muttered 
execrations to himself:--I supposed at French 
railways.</p>
<p>"By Jove, sir, did you ever see such clumsy 
carts?" said Major Baxter, pointing to two 
country carts, each with four strong horses, 
that were drawn up under a hedge close to the 
station; for we had struggled on as far as the 
first turn-table, some hundred yards from the 
first houses of the village of Fort Rouge.</p>
<p>Levison and I tried very hard to get near our 
luggage, but the soldiers sternly refused our 
approach. It gave me some comfort, however, 
to see my chests transferred carefully, with 
many curses on their weight. I saw no sign of 
government stores, and I told the major so.</p>
<p>"Oh, they're sharp," he replied, "dooced 
sharp. Maybe the empress's jewels--one little 
package only, perhaps; but still not difficult to 
steal in a night confusion."</p>
<p>Just then there was a shrill piercing whistle, 
as if a signal. The horses in the two carts tore 
into a gallop, and flew out of sight.</p>
<p>"Savages, sir; mere barbarians still," 
exclaimed the major; "unable to use railways even 
now we've given them to them."</p>
<p>"Major!" said his wife, in a voice of awful 
reproof, "spare the feelings of these foreigners, 
and remember your position as an officer and a 
gentleman."</p>
<p>The major rubbed his hands, and laughed 
uproariously.</p>
<p>"A pack of infernal idiots," cried Levison; 
"they can do nothing without soldiers; soldiers 
here, soldiers there, soldiers everywhere."</p>
<p>"Well, these precautions are sometimes 
useful, sir," said Mrs. B.; "France is a place 
full of queer characters. The gentleman next 
you any day at a table d'hte may be a 
returned convict. Major, you remember that case 
at Cairo three years ago?"</p>
<p>"Cairo, Julia my dear, is not in France."</p>
<p>"I know that, major, I hope. But the house 
was a French hotel, and that's the same thing." 
Mrs. B. spoke sharply.</p>
<p>"I shall have a nap, gentlemen. For my part, 
I'm tired," said the major, as we took our 
places in the Marseilles train, after three hours' 
tedious delay. "The next thing will be the 
boat breaking down, I suppose."</p>
<p>"Major, you wicked man, don't fly out against 
Providence," said his wife.</p>
<p>Levison grew eloquent again about the Prince 
Regent, his diamond epaulettes, and his inimitable 
cravats; but Levison's words seemed 
to lengthen, and gradually became inaudible to 
me, until I heard only a soothing murmur, and 
the rattle and jar of the wheels.</p>
<p>Again my dreams were nervous and uneasy. I 
imagined I was in Cairo, threading narrow dim 
streets, where the camels jostled me and the 
black slaves threatened me, and the air was 
heavy with musk, and veiled faces watched me 
from latticed casements above. Suddenly a rose 
fell at my feet. I looked up, and a face like my 
Minnie's, only with large liquid dark eyes like an 
antelope's, glanced forth from behind a water-vase 
and smiled. At that moment, four Mamelukes 
appeared, riding down the street at full 
gallop, and came upon me with their sabres flashing. 
I dreamed I had only one hope, and that was 
to repeat the talismanic words of my letter-locks. 
Already I was under the hoofs of the Mamelukes' 
horses. I cried out with great difficulty, 
"Cotopaxo! Cotopaxo!" A rough shake awoke me. 
It was the major, looking bluff but stern.</p>
<p>"Why, you're talking in your sleep!" he said; 
"why the devil do you talk in your sleep? Bad 
habit. Here we are at the breakfast-place."</p>
<p>"What was I talking about?" I asked, with 
ill-concealed alarm.</p>
<p>"Some foreign gibberish," returned the major.</p>
<p>"Greek, I think," said Levison; "but I was 
just off too."</p>
<p>We reached Marseilles. I rejoiced to see its 
almond-trees and its white villas. I should feel 
safer when I was on board ship, and my treasure 
with me. I was not of a suspicious temperament, 
but I had thought it remarkable that during that 
long journey from Lyons to the seaboard, I had 
never fallen asleep without waking and finding 
an eye upon me--either the major's or his wife's. 
Levison had slept during the last four hours 
incessantly. Latterly, we had all of us grown silent, 
and even rather sullen. Now we brightened up.</p>
<p>"Htel de Londres! Htel de l'Univers! 
Htel Imprial!" cried the touts, as we stood 
round our luggage, agreeing to keep together.</p>
<p>"Htel Imprial, of course," said the major; 
"best house."</p>
<p>A one-eyed saturnine half-caste tout shrunk 
up to us.</p>
<p>"Htel Imprial, sare. I am Htel Imprial; 
all full; not a bed; no--pas de tout--no use, 
sare!"</p>
<p>"Hang it! the steamer will be the next 
thing to fail."</p>
<p>"Steamer, sare--accident with boiler; won't 
start till minuit et vingt minutes--half-past 
midnight, sare."</p>
<p>"Where shall we go?" said I, turning round 
and smiling at the three blank faces of my 
companions. "Our journey seems doomed to be 
unlucky. Let us redeem it by a parting supper. 
My telegraphing done, I am free till half-past 
eleven."</p>
<p>"I will take you," said Levison, "to a small 
but very decent hotel down by the harbour. 
The Htel des Etrangers."</p>
<p>"Cursd low nasty crib--gambling place!" 
said the major, lighting a cheroot, as he got into 
an open fly.</p>
<p>Mr. Levison drew himself up in his punctilious 
way. "Sir," he said, "the place is in new 
hands, or I would not have recommended the 
house, you may rely upon it."</p>
<p>"Sir," said the major, lifting his broad-brimmed 
white hat, "I offer you my apologies. 
I was not aware of that."</p>
<p>"My dear sir, never mention the affair again."</p>
<p>"Major, you're a hot-headed simpleton," were 
Mrs. B.'s last words, as we drove off together.</p>
<p>As we entered a bare-looking salon with a 
dinner-table in the middle and a dingy billiard-table 
at one end, the major said to me, "I shall 
go and wash and dress for the theatre, and then 
take a stroll while you do your telegraphing. 
Go up first, Julia, and see the rooms."</p>
<p>"What slaves we poor women are!" said Mrs. 
B., as she sailed out.</p>
<p>"And I," said Levison, laying down his railway 
rug, "shall go out and try and do some 
business before the shops shut. We have agents 
here in the Canabire."</p>
<p>"Only two double-bedded rooms, sare," said 
the one-eyed tout, who stood over the luggage.</p>
<p>"That will do," said Levison, promptly, and 
with natural irritation at our annoyances. "My 
friend goes by the boat to-night; he does not 
sleep here. His luggage can be put in my 
room, and he can take the key, in case he comes 
in first."</p>
<p>"Then now we are all right," said the major. 
"So far, so good!"</p>
<p>When I got to the telegraph-office, I found a 
telegram from London awaiting me. To my 
surprise and horror, it contained only these 
words:</p>
<letter>
<p>"You are in great danger. Do not wait a 
moment on shore. There is a plot against you. 
Apply to the prefect for a guard."</p>
</letter>
<p>It must be the major, and I was in his hands! 
That rough hearty manner of his was all a trick. 
Even now, he might be carrying off the chests. 
I telegraphed back:</p>
<letter>
<p>"Safe at Marseilles. All right up to this."</p>
</letter>
<p>Thinking of the utter ruin of our house if I 
were robbed, and of dear Minnie, I flew back to 
the hotel, which was situated in a dirty narrow 
street near the harbour. As I turned down the 
street, a man darted from a doorway and seized 
my arm. It was one of the waiters. He said 
hurriedly, in French: "Quick, quick, monsieur; 
Major Baxter is anxious to see you, instantly, in 
the salon. There is no time to lose."</p>
<p>I ran to the hotel, and darted into the salon. 
There was the major pacing up and down in 
extraordinary excitement; his wife was looking 
anxiously out of window. The manner of both 
was entirely changed. The major ran up and 
seized me by the hand. "I am a detective 
officer, and my name is Arnott," he said. "That 
man Levison is a notorious thief. He is at this 
moment in his room, opening one of your specie 
chests. You must help me to nab him. I knew 
his little game, and have check-mated him. But 
I wanted to catch him in the act. Julia, finish 
that brandy-and-water while Mr. Blamyre and 
myself transact our business. Have you got a 
revolver, Mr. Blamyre, in case he shows fight? 
I prefer this." (He pulled out a staff.)</p>
<p>"I have left my revolver in the bedroom," 
I breathlessly exclaimed.</p>
<p>"That's bad; never mind, he is not likely to 
hit us in the flurry. He may not even think of 
it. You must rush at the door at the same 
moment as I do. These foreign locks are never 
any good. It's No. 15. Gently!"</p>
<p>We came to the door. We listened a 
moment. We could hear the sound of money 
chinking in a bag. Then a low dry laugh, as 
Levison chuckled over the word he had heard me 
utter in my sleep. "Cotopaxo--ha! ha!"</p>
<p>The major gave the word, and we both rushed 
at the door. It shook, splintered, was driven in. 
Levison, revolver in hand, stood over the open 
box, ankle deep in gold. He had already filled a 
huge digger's belt that was round his waist, and 
a courier's bag that hung at his side. A carpet 
bag, half full, lay at his feet, and, as he let it 
fall to open the window bolt, it gushed forth a 
perfect torrent of gold. He did not utter a 
word. There were ropes at the window, as if 
he had been lowering, or preparing to lower, 
bags into the side alley. He gave a whistle 
and some vehicle could be heard to drive furiously 
off.</p>
<p>"Surrender, you gallows-bird! I know you," 
cried the major. "Surrender! I've got you now, 
old boy."</p>
<p>Levison's only reply was to pull the trigger 
of the revolver; fortunately, there was no 
discharge. I had forgotten to cap it.</p>
<p>"The infernal thing is not capped. One for 
you, Bobby," he said quietly. Then hurling it 
at the major with a sudden fury, he threw open 
the window and leaped out.</p>
<p>I leaped after him--it was a ground floor 
room--raising a hue and cry. Arnott remained 
to guard the money.</p>
<p>A moment more and a wild rabble of soldiers, 
sailors, mongrel idlers, and porters, were pursuing 
the flying wretch with screams and hoots, 
as in the dim light (the lamps were just beginning 
to be kindled) we tore after him, doubling 
and twisting like a hare, among the obstacles 
that crowded the quay. Hundreds of blows 
were aimed at him; hundreds of hands were 
stretched to seize him; he wrested himself from 
one; he felled another; he leaped over a third; 
a Zouave's clutch was all but on him, when suddenly 
his foot caught in a mooring ring, and he 
fell headlong into the harbour. There was a 
shout as he splashed and disappeared in the dark 
water, near which the light of only one lamp 
moved and glittered. I ran down the nearest 
steps and waited while the gendarmes took a boat 
and stolidly dragged with hooks for the body.</p>
<p>"They are foxes, these old thieves. I remember 
this man here at Toulon. I saw him branded. 
I knew his face again in a moment. He has 
dived under the shipping, got into some barge 
and hid. You'll never see him again," said an old 
grey gendarme who had taken me into the boat.</p>
<p>"Yes we shall, for here he is!" cried a second, 
stooping down and lifting a body out of the water 
by the hair.</p>
<p>"Oh, he <em>was</em> an artful file," said a man 
from a boat behind us. It was Arnott. "Just 
came to see how you were getting on, sir. 
It's all right with the money; Julia's minding 
it. I often said that fellow would catch 
it some day, now he's got it. He all but had 
you, Mr. Blamyre. He'd have cut your throat 
when you were asleep, rather than miss the 
money. But I was on his track. He didn't 
know me. This was my first cruise for some 
time against this sort of rogue. Well; his name 
is off the books; that's one good thing. Come, 
comrades, bring that body to land. We must 
strip him of the money he has upon him, which at 
least did one good thing while in his possession--
it sent the scoundrel to the bottom."</p>
<p>Even in death, the long face looked craftily 
respectable when we turned it to the lamp-light.</p>
<p>Arnott told me all, in his jovial way, on my 
return to the hotel, where I loaded him and Mrs. 
B. (another officer) with thanks. On the night 
I started, he had received orders from the London 
head office to follow me, and watch Levison. 
He had not had time to communicate 
with my partners. The driver of our train had 
been bribed to make the engine break down at 
Fort Rouge, where Levison's accomplices were 
waiting with carts to carry off the luggage in 
the confusion and darkness, or even during a 
sham riot and fight. This plan Arnott had 
frustrated by getting the police to telegraph 
from Paris, for soldiers to be sent from Lyons, 
and be kept in readiness, at the station. The 
champagne he spilt had been drugged. 
Levison, defeated in his first attempt, had then 
resolved to try other means. My unlucky 
disclosure of the mystery of the letter-lock had 
furnished him with the power of opening that 
one chest. The break-down of the steamer, 
which was accidental (as far as could ever be 
ascertained), gave him a last opportunity.</p>
<p>That night, thanks to Arnott, I left Marseilles 
with not one single piece of money lost. The 
journey was prosperous. The loan was effected 
on very profitable terms. Our house has flourished 
ever since, and Minnie and I have flourished 
likewise--and increased.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken With A Grain Of Salt."/>
<p>I have always noticed a prevalent want 
of courage, even among persons of superior 
intelligence and culture, as to imparting their 
own psychological experiences when those have 
been of a strange sort. Almost all men are 
afraid that what they could relate in such wise 
would find no parallel or response in a listener's 
internal life, and might be suspected or laughed 
at. A truthful traveller who should have seen 
some extraordinary creature in the likeness 
of a sea-serpent, would have no fear of 
mentioning it; but the same traveller having had 
some singular presentiment, impulse, vagary of 
thought, vision (so-called), dream, or other 
remarkable mental impression, would hesitate 
considerably before he would own to it. To 
this reticence I attribute much of the obscurity 
in which such subjects are involved. 
We do not habitually communicate our experiences 
of these subjective things, as we do our 
experiences of objective creation. The 
consequence is, that the general stock of experience 
in this regard appears exceptional, and really 
is so, in respect of being miserably imperfect.</p>
<p>In what I am going to relate I have no 
intention of setting up, opposing, or supporting, 
any theory whatever. I know the history of 
the Bookseller of Berlin, I have studied the 
case of the wife of a late Astronomer Royal as 
related by Sir David Brewster, and I have 
followed the minutest details of a much more 
remarkable case of Spectral Illusion occurring 
within my private circle of friends. It may be 
necessary to state as to this last that the sufferer 
(a lady) was in no degree, however distant, 
related to me. A mistaken assumption on that 
head, might suggest an explanation of a part of 
my own case--but only a part--which would 
be wholly without foundation. It cannot be 
referred to my inheritance of any developed 
peculiarity, nor had I ever before any at all 
similar experience, nor have I ever had any at 
all similar experience since.</p>
<p>It does not signify how many years ago, or 
how few, a certain Murder was committed in 
England, which attracted great attention. We 
hear more than enough of Murderers as they 
rise in succession to their atrocious eminence, 
and I would bury the memory of this particular 
brute, if I could, as his body was buried, in 
Newgate Jail. I purposely abstain from giving 
any direct clue to the criminal's individuality.</p>
<p>When the murder was first discovered, no 
suspicion fell--or I ought rather to say, for I 
cannot be too precise in my facts, it was nowhere 
publicly hinted that any suspicion fell--on the 
man who was afterwards brought to trial. As 
no reference was at that time made to him in 
the newspapers, it is obviously impossible that 
any description of him can at that time have 
been given in the newspapers. It is essential 
that this fact be remembered.</p>
<p>Unfolding at breakfast my morning paper, 
containing the account of that first discovery, I 
found it to be deeply interesting, and I read it 
with close attention. I read it twice, if not three 
times. The discovery had been made in a bedroom, 
and, when I laid down the paper, I was 
aware of a flash--rush--flow--I do not know 
what to call it--no word I can find is satisfactorily 
descriptive--in which I seemed to see that 
bedroom passing through my room, like a picture 
impossibly painted on a running river. Though 
almost instantaneous in its passing, it was 
perfectly clear; so clear that I distinctly, and with 
a sense of relief, observed the absence of the 
dead body from the bed.</p>
<p>It was in no romantic place that I had this 
curious sensation, but in chambers in Piccadilly, 
very near to the corner of Saint James's-street. 
It was entirely new to me. I was in my easy-chair 
at the moment, and the sensation was 
accompanied with a peculiar shiver which 
started the chair from its position. (But it is 
to be noted that the chair ran easily on castors.) 
I went to one of the windows (there are two in 
the room, and the room is on the second floor) 
to refresh my eyes with the moving objects 
down in Piccadilly. It was a bright autumn 
morning, and the street was sparkling and cheerful. 
The wind was high. As I looked out, it 
brought down from the Park a quantity of fallen 
leaves, which a gust took, and whirled into a 
spiral pillar. As the pillar fell and the leaves 
dispersed, I saw two men on the opposite side 
of the way, going from West to East. They 
were one behind the other. The foremost man 
often looked back over his shoulder. The second 
man followed him, at a distance of some 
thirty paces, with his right hand menacingly 
raised. First, the singularity and steadiness of 
this threatening gesture in so public a thoroughfare, 
attracted my attention; and next, the more 
remarkable circumstance that nobody heeded it. 
Both men threaded their way among the other 
passengers, with a smoothness hardly consistent 
even with the action of walking on a pavement, 
and no single creature that I could see, gave 
them place, touched them, or looked after them. 
In passing before my windows, they both stared 
up at me. I saw their two faces very distinctly, 
and I knew that I could recognise them anywhere. 
Not that I had consciously noticed anything 
very remarkable in either face, except that the 
man who went first had an unusually lowering 
appearance, and that the face of the man who 
followed him was of the colour of impure wax.</p>
<p>I am a bachelor, and my valet and his wife 
constitute my whole establishment. My occupation 
is in a certain Branch Bank, and I wish 
that my duties as head of a Department were as 
light as they are popularly supposed to be. They 
kept me in town that autumn, when I stood in 
need of change. I was not ill, but I was not 
well. My reader is to make the most that can 
be reasonably made of my feeling jaded, having 
a depressing sense upon me of a monotonous life, 
and being "slightly dyspeptic." I am assured by 
my renowned doctor that my real state of 
health at that time justifies no stronger description, 
and I quote his own from his written 
answer to my request for it.</p>
<p>As the circumstances of the Murder, gradually 
unravelling, took stronger and stronger possession 
of the public mind, I kept them away from 
mine, by knowing as little about them as was 
possible in the midst of the universal excitement. 
But I knew that a verdict of Wilful Murder had 
been found against the suspected Murderer, and 
that he had been committed to Newgate for trial. 
I also knew that his trial had been postponed 
over one Sessions of the Central Criminal Court, 
on the ground of general prejudice and want of 
time for the preparation of the defence. I may 
further have known, but I believe I did not, 
when, or about when, the Sessions to which his 
trial stood postponed would come on.</p>
<p>My sitting-room, bedroom, and dressing-room, 
are all on one floor. With the last, there is no 
communication but through the bedroom. True, 
there is a door in it, once communicating with 
the staircase; but a part of the fitting of my 
bath has been--and had then been for some 
years--fixed across it. At the same period, and 
as a part of the same arrangement, the door had 
been nailed up and canvased over.</p>
<p>I was standing in my bedroom late one night, 
giving some directions to my servant before he 
went to bed. My face was towards the only 
available door of communication with the dressing-room, 
and it was closed. My servant's back 
was towards that door. While I was speaking 
to him I saw it open, and a man look in, who 
very earnestly and mysteriously beckoned to me. 
That man was the man who had gone second of 
the two along Piccadilly, and whose face was of 
the colour of impure wax.</p>
<p>The figure, having beckoned, drew back and 
closed the door. With no longer pause than 
was made by my crossing the bedroom, I opened 
the dressing-room door, and looked in. I had a 
lighted candle already in my hand. I felt no 
inward expectation of seeing the figure in the 
dressing-room, and I did not see it there.</p>
<p>Conscious that my servant stood amazed, I 
turned round to him, and said: "Derrick, could 
you believe that in my cool senses I fancied I 
saw a----" As I there laid my hand upon his 
breast, with a sudden start he trembled violently, 
and said, "O Lord yes, sir! A dead man 
beckoning!"</p>
<p>Now, I do not believe that this John Derrick, 
my trusty and attached servant for more than 
twenty years, had any impression whatever of 
having seen any such figure, until I touched 
him. The change in him was so startling when 
I touched him, that I fully believe he derived 
his impression in some occult manner from me 
at that instant.</p>
<p>I bade John Derrick bring some brandy, and 
I gave him a dram, and was glad to take one 
myself. Of what had preceded that night's 
phenomenon, I told him not a single word. 
Reflecting on it, I was absolutely certain that I 
had never seen that face before, except on the 
one occasion in Piccadilly. Comparing its 
expression when beckoning at the door, with its 
expression when it had stared up at me as I 
stood at my window, I came to the conclusion 
that on the first occasion it had sought to fasten 
itself upon my memory, and that on the second 
occasion it had made sure of being immediately 
remembered.</p>
<p>I was not very comfortable that night, though 
I felt a certainty, difficult to explain, that the 
figure would not return. At daylight, I fell into 
a heavy sleep, from which I was awakened by 
John Derrick's coming to my bedside with a 
paper in his hand.</p>
<p>This paper, it appeared, had been the subject 
of an altercation at the door between its bearer 
and my servant. It was a summons to me to 
serve upon a Jury at the forthcoming Sessions 
of the Central Criminal Court at the Old Bailey. 
I had never before been summoned on such a 
Jury, as John Derrick well knew. He believed--
I am not certain at this hour whether with 
reason or otherwise--that that class of Jurors 
were customarily chosen on a lower qualification 
than mine, and he had at first refused to 
accept the summons. The man who served it 
had taken the matter very coolly. He had said 
that my attendance or non-attendance was 
nothing to him; there the summons was; and I 
should deal with it at my own peril, and not at 
his.</p>
<p>For a day or two I was undecided whether to 
respond to this call, or take no notice of it. I 
was not conscious of the slightest mysterious bias, 
influence, or attraction, one way or other. Of that 
I am as strictly sure as of every other statement 
that I make here. Ultimately I decided, as a 
break in the monotony of my life, that I would 
go.</p>
<p>The appointed morning was a raw morning in 
the month of November. There was a dense 
brown fog in Piccadilly, and it became positively 
black and in the last degree oppressive East of 
Temple Bar. I found the passages and staircases 
of the Court House flaringly lighted with gas, 
and the Court itself similarly illuminated. I 
<em>think</em> that until I was conducted by officers into 
the Old Court and saw its crowded state, I did 
not know that the Murderer was to be tried that 
day. I <em>think</em> that until I was so helped into the 
Old Court with considerable difficulty, I did not 
know into which of the two Courts sitting, my 
summons would take me. But this must not be 
received as a positive assertion, for I am not 
completely satisfied in my mind on either point.</p>
<p>I took my seat in the place appropriated to 
Jurors in waiting, and I looked about the Court 
as well as I could through the cloud of fog and 
breath that was heavy in it. I noticed the black 
vapour hanging like a murky curtain outside the 
great windows, and I noticed the stifled sound 
of wheels on the straw or tan that was littered 
in the street; also, the hum of the people 
gathered there, which a shrill whistle, or a louder 
song or hail than the rest, occasionally pierced. 
Soon afterwards the Judges, two in number, 
entered and took their seats. The buzz in the 
Court was awfully hushed. The direction was 
given to put the Murderer to the bar. He 
appeared there. And in that same instant I 
recognised in him, the first of the two men who 
had gone down Piccadilly.</p>
<p>If my name had been called then, I doubt if I 
could have answered to it audibly. But it was 
called about sixth or eighth in the panel, and I was 
by that time able to say "Here!" Now, observe. 
As I stepped into the box, the prisoner, who 
had been looking on attentively but with no sign 
of concern, became violently agitated, and 
beckoned to his attorney. The prisoner's wish 
to challenge me was so manifest, that it occasioned 
a pause, during which the attorney, 
with his hand upon the dock, whispered with 
his client, and shook his head. I afterwards 
had it from that gentleman, that the prisoner's 
first affrighted words to him were, "<em>At all 
hazards challenge that man!</em>" But, that as he 
would give no reason for it, and admitted that 
he had not even known my name until he heard 
it called and I appeared, it was not done.</p>
<p>Both on the ground already explained, that I 
wish to avoid reviving the unwholesome memory 
of that Murderer, and also because a detailed 
account of his long trial is by no means indispensable 
to my narrative, I shall confine myself 
closely to such incidents in the ten days and 
nights during which we, the Jury, were kept 
together, as directly bear on my own curious 
personal experience. It is in that, and not in the 
Murderer, that I seek to interest my reader. It 
is to that, and not to a page of the Newgate 
Calendar, that I beg attention.</p>
<p>I was chosen Foreman of the Jury. On the 
second morning of the trial, after evidence had 
been taken for two hours (I heard the church 
clocks strike), happening to cast my eyes over 
my brother-jurymen, I found an inexplicable 
difficulty in counting them. I counted them several 
times, yet always with the same difficulty. In 
short, I made them one too many.</p>
<p>I touched the brother-juryman whose place 
was next me, and I whispered to him, "Oblige 
me by counting us." He looked surprised by 
the request, but turned his head and counted. 
"Why," says he, suddenly, "we are Thirt----; 
but no, it's not possible. No. We are twelve."</p>
<p>According to my counting that day, we were 
always right in detail, but in the gross we were 
always one too many. There was no appearance--
no figure--to account for it; but I had 
now an inward foreshadowing of the figure that 
was surely coming.</p>
<p>The Jury were housed at the London Tavern. 
We all slept in one large room on separate 
tables, and we were constantly in the charge 
and under the eye of the officer sworn to hold us 
in safe-keeping. I see no reason for suppressing 
the real name of that officer. He was intelligent, 
highly polite, and obliging, and (I was glad 
to hear) much respected in the City. He had 
an agreeable presence, good eyes, enviable black 
whiskers, and a fine sonorous voice. His name 
was Mr. Harker.</p>
<p>When we turned into our twelve beds at 
night, Mr. Harker's bed was drawn across the 
door. On the night of the second day, not being 
disposed to lie down, and seeing Mr. Harker 
sitting on his bed, I went and sat beside him, 
and offered him a pinch of snuff. As Mr. 
Harker's hand touched mine in taking it from 
my box, a peculiar shiver crossed him, and he 
said: "Who is this!"</p>
<p>Following Mr. Harker's eyes and looking 
along the room, I saw again the figure I 
expected--the second of the two men who had 
gone down Piccadilly. I rose, and advanced a 
few steps; then stopped, and looked round at 
Mr. Harker. He was quite unconcerned, 
laughed, and said in a pleasant way, "I thought 
for a moment we had a thirteenth juryman, without 
a bed. But I see it is the moonlight."</p>
<p>Making no revelation to Mr. Harker, but 
inviting him to take a walk with me to the end of 
the room, I watched what the figure did. It 
stood for a few moments by the bedside of each 
of my eleven brother-jurymen, close to the 
pillow. It always went to the right-hand side 
of the bed, and always passed out crossing the 
foot of the next bed. It seemed from the action 
of the head, merely to look down pensively at 
each recumbent figure. It took no notice of me, 
or of my bed, which was that nearest to Mr. 
Harker's. It seemed to go out where the moonlight 
came in, through a high window, as by an 
arial flight of stairs.</p>
<p>Next morning at breakfast, it appeared that 
everybody present had dreamed of the murdered 
man last night, except myself and Mr. Harker.</p>
<p>I now felt as convinced that the second man 
who had gone down Piccadilly was the murdered 
man (so to speak), as if it had been borne into 
my comprehension by his immediate testimony. 
But even this took place, and in a manner for 
which I was not at all prepared.</p>
<p>On the fifth day of the trial, when the case for 
the prosecution was drawing to a close, a 
miniature of the murdered man, missing from 
his bedroom upon the discovery of the deed, and 
afterwards found in a hiding-place where the 
Murderer had been seen digging, was put in 
evidence. Having been identified by the witness 
under examination, it was handed up to the 
Bench, and thence handed down to be inspected 
by the Jury. As an officer in a black gown was 
making his way with it across to me, the figure 
of the second man who had gone down Piccadilly, 
impetuously started from the crowd, caught the 
miniature from the officer, and gave it to me 
with its own hands, at the same time saying in a 
low and hollow tone--before I saw the miniature, 
which was in a locket--"<em>I was younger then, 
and my face was not then drained of blood.</em>" It 
also came between me and the brother juryman 
to whom I would have given the miniature, and 
between him and the brother juryman to whom 
he would have given it, and so passed it on 
through the whole of our number, and back 
into my possession. Not one of them, however, 
detected this.</p>
<p>At table, and generally when we were shut 
up together in Mr. Harker's custody, we had 
from the first naturally discussed the day's 
proceedings a good deal. On that fifth day, 
the case for the prosecution being closed, and 
we having that side of the question in a 
completed shape before us, our discussion was more 
animated and serious. Among our number was 
a vestryman--the densest idiot I have ever seen 
at large--who met the plainest evidence with 
the most preposterous objections, and who was 
sided with by two flabby parochial parasites; 
all the three empanelled from a district so 
delivered over to Fever that they ought to have 
been upon their own trial, for five hundred 
Murders. When these mischievous blockheads 
were at their loudest, which was towards 
midnight while some of us were already preparing 
for bed, I again saw the murdered man. He 
stood grimly behind them, beckoning to me. 
On my going towards them and striking into 
the conversation, he immediately retired. This 
was the beginning of a separate series of 
appearances, confined to that long room in which 
we were confined. Whenever a knot of my 
brother jurymen laid their heads together, I 
saw the head of the murdered man among 
theirs. Whenever their comparison of notes 
was going against him, he would solemnly and 
irresistibly beckon to me.</p>
<p>It will be borne in mind that down to the 
production of the miniature on the fifth day of 
the trial, I had never seen the Appearance in 
Court. Three changes occurred, now that we 
entered on the case for the defence. Two of 
them I will mention together, first. The figure 
was now in Court continually, and it never there 
addressed itself to me, but always to the person 
who was speaking at the time. For instance. 
The throat of the murdered man had been cut 
straight across. In the opening speech, for 
the defence, it was suggested that the 
deceased might have cut his own throat. At that 
very moment, the figure with its throat in the 
dreadful condition referred to (this it had 
concealed before) stood at the speaker's elbow, 
motioning across and across its windpipe, now 
with the right hand, now with the left, vigorously 
suggesting to the speaker himself, the 
impossibility of such a wound having been 
self-inflicted by either hand. For another instance. 
A witness to character, a woman, deposed to 
the prisoner's being the most amiable of mankind. 
The figure at that instant stood on the 
floor before her, looking her full in the face, 
and pointing out the prisoner's evil countenance 
with an extended arm and an outstretched finger.</p>
<p>The third change now to be added, impressed 
me strongly, as the most marked and striking 
of all. I do not theorise upon it; I accurately 
state it, and there leave it. Although the 
Appearance was not itself perceived by those 
whom it addressed, its coming close to such 
persons was invariably attended by some 
trepidation or disturbance on their part. It 
seemed to me as if it were prevented by laws 
to which I was not amenable, from fully revealing 
itself to others, and yet as if it could, 
invisibly, dumbly and darkly, overshadow their 
minds. When the leading counsel for the 
defence suggested that hypothesis of suicide and 
the figure stood at the learned gentleman's 
elbow, frightfully sawing at its severed throat, 
it is undeniable that the counsel faltered in his 
speech, lost for a few seconds the thread of his 
ingenious discourse, wiped his forehead with his 
handkerchief, and turned extremely pale. When 
the witness to character was confronted by the 
Appearance, her eyes most certainly did follow 
the direction of its pointed finger, and rest in 
great hesitation and trouble upon the prisoner's 
face. Two additional illustrations will suffice. 
On the eighth day of the trial, after the pause 
which was every day made early in the afternoon 
for a few minutes' rest and refreshment, 
I came back into Court with the rest of the 
Jury, some little time before the return of the 
Judges. Standing up in the box and looking 
about me, I thought the figure was not there, 
until, chancing to raise my eyes to the gallery, I 
saw it bending forward and leaning over a very 
decent woman, as if to assure itself whether the 
Judges had resumed their seats or not. 
Immediately afterwards, that woman screamed, fainted, 
and was carried out. So with the venerable, 
sagacious, and patient Judge who conducted the 
trial. When the case was over, and he settled 
himself and his papers to sum up, the murdered 
man entering by the Judges' door, advanced 
to his Lordship's desk, and looked eagerly 
over his shoulder at the pages of his notes 
which he was turning. A change came over his 
Lordship's face; his hand stopped; the peculiar 
shiver that I knew so well, passed over him; 
he faltered, "Excuse me, gentlemen, for a few 
moments. I am somewhat oppressed by the 
vitiated air;" and did not recover until he had 
drunk a glass of water.</p>
<p>Through all the monotony of six of those interminable 
ten days--the same Judges and others 
on the bench, the same Murderer in the dock, the 
same lawyers at the table, the same tones of question 
and answer rising to the roof of the court, 
the same scratching of the Judge's pen, the same 
ushers going in and out, the same lights kindled 
at the same hour when there had been any 
natural light of day, the same foggy curtain outside 
the great windows when it was foggy, the same 
rain pattering and dripping when it was rainy, 
the same footmarks of turnkeys and prisoner 
day after day on the same sawdust, the same 
keys locking and unlocking the same heavy 
doors--through all the wearisome monotony 
which made me feel as if I had been Foreman of 
the Jury for a vast period of time, and Piccadilly 
had flourished coevally with Babylon, the 
murdered man never lost one trace of his 
distinctness in my eyes, nor was he at any 
moment less distinct than anybody else. I 
must not omit, as a matter of fact, that I never 
once saw the Appearance which I call by the 
name of the murdered man, look at the Murderer. 
Again and again I wondered, "Why does he 
not?" But he never did.</p>
<p>Nor did he look at me, after the production of 
the miniature, until the last closing minutes of 
the trial arrived. We retired to consider, at 
seven minutes before ten at night. The idiotic 
vestryman and his two parochial parasites gave 
us so much trouble, that we twice returned into 
Court, to beg to have certain extracts from the 
Judge's notes re-read. Nine of us had not the 
smallest doubt about those passages, neither, I 
believe, had any one in Court; the dunderheaded 
triumvirate however, having no idea 
but obstruction, disputed them for that very 
reason. At length we prevailed, and finally 
the Jury returned into Court at ten minutes 
past twelve.</p>
<p>The murdered man at that time stood directly 
opposite the Jury-box, on the other side of the 
Court. As I took my place, his eyes rested on 
me, with great attention; he seemed satisfied, 
and slowly shook a great grey veil, which he 
carried on his arm for the first time, over his 
head and whole form. As I gave in our verdict 
"Guilty," the veil collapsed, all was gone, and 
his place was empty.</p>
<p>The Murderer being asked by the Judge, 
according to usage, whether he had anything to say 
before sentence of Death should be passed upon 
him, indistinctly muttered something which was 
described in the leading newspapers of the 
following day as "a few rambling, incoherent, and 
half-audible words, in which he was understood 
to complain that he had not had a fair trial, 
because the Foreman of the Jury was prepossessed 
against him." The remarkable declaration that 
he really made, was this: "<em>My Lord, I knew I 
was a doomed man when the Foreman of my Jury 
came into the box. My Lord, I knew he would 
never let me off, because, before I was taken, he 
somehow got to my bedside in the night, woke me, 
and put a rope round my neck.</em>"</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken And Tried."/>
<p>There can hardly be seen anywhere, a prettier 
village than Cumner, standing on the brow of a 
hill which commands one of the finest views in 
England, and flanked by its broad breezy common, 
the air of which is notorious for clearness 
and salubrity. The high road from Dring, for 
the most part shut in by the fences of gentlemen's 
seats, opens out when it reaches this 
common, and, separating from the Tenelms road, 
ascends in a north-westerly direction till it 
comes in sight of Cumner. Every step is 
against the collar, yet so gradual is the ascent, 
that you scarcely realise it until, turning, you 
behold the magnificent panorama spread around 
and beneath.</p>
<p>The village consists chiefly of one short street 
of somewhat straggling houses, among which 
you observe its little post-office, its police 
station, its rustic public-house (the Dunstan 
Arms), whose landlord also holds the general 
shop across the way; and its two or three 
humble lodging-houses. Facing you as you 
enter the street, which is a cul-de-sac, is the 
quaint old church, standing not more than a 
bow-shot from the Rectory. There is something 
primitive and almost patriarchal in this quiet 
village, where the pastor lives surrounded by his 
flock, and can scarcely move from his own gate 
without finding himself in the midst of them.</p>
<p>Cumner Common is skirted on three sides by 
dwellings, varying in size and importance, from 
the small butcher's shop standing in its own 
garden, and under the shadow of its own apple-trees, 
to the pretty white house where the 
curate lodges, and the more pretentious abodes 
of those who are, or consider themselves, 
gentry. It is bounded on the east by the low 
stone wall and gateway of Mr. Malcolmson's 
domain; the modest dwelling of Simon Eade, 
that gentleman's bailiff, half covered with 
creepers, the autumnal hues of which might rival 
the brightest specimens of American foliage; 
lastly, by the high brick wall (with its door in the 
centre), which completely shuts in Mr. Gibbs's 
"place." On the south side runs the high road to 
Tenelms, skirting the great Southanger property, 
of which Sir Oswald Dunstan is proprietor.</p>
<p>Hardly could the pedestrian tourist, on his 
way from Dring, fail to pause at the rustic stile 
nearly opposite the blacksmith's forge, and, 
resting upon it, gaze down on the magnificent 
prospect of wood and water spread at his feet--
a prospect to which two ancient cedars form no 
inappropriate foreground. That stile is not often 
crossed, for the footpath from it leads only to 
the farm called the Plashetts; but it is very 
constantly used as a resting-place. Many an 
artist has sketched the view from it; many a 
lover has whispered tender words to his mistress 
beside it; many a weary tramp has rested his or 
her feet on the worn stone beneath.</p>
<p>This stile was once the favourite resort of 
two young lovers, inhabitants of the district, 
and soon to be united. George Eade, the 
only son of Mr. Malcolmson's bailiff, was a 
stalwart good-looking young fellow of some 
six-and-twenty, who worked for that gentleman 
under his father, and was in the receipt of 
liberal wages. Honest, steady, and fond of 
self-cultivation, he was capable, if not clever--
persevering, if not rapid--an excellent 
specimen of an honest English peasant. But 
he had certain peculiarities of disposition and 
temper, which served to render him 
considerably less popular than his father. He was 
reserved; feeling strongly, but with difficulty 
giving expression to his feelings; susceptible 
to, and not easily forgiving, injuries; singularly 
addicted to self-accusation and remorse. 
His father, a straightforward open-hearted man 
of five-and-forty, who had raised himself by sheer 
merit from the position of a labourer to that of 
the trusted manager of Mr. Malcolmson's 
property, was highly respected by that gentleman, 
and by the whole country-side. His mother, 
feeble in health, but energetic of spirit, was one 
of the most excellent of women.</p>
<p>This couple, like many of their class, had 
married imprudently early, and had struggled 
through many difficulties in consequence: burying, 
one after another, three sickly children in 
the little churchyard at Cumner where they 
hoped one day themselves to lie. On the one 
son that remained to them their affections were 
centred. The mother, especially, worshipped 
her George with an admiring love that partook 
of idolatry. She was not without some of 
the weaknesses of her sex. She was jealous; 
and when she discovered the flame which had 
been kindled in the heart of her son by the soft 
blue eyes of Susan Archer, her feelings 
towards that rosy-cheeked damsel were not those 
of perfect charity. True, the Archers were 
people who held themselves high, occupying 
a large farm under Sir Oswald Dunstan; and 
they were known to regard Susan's attachment 
as a decided lowering of herself and them. 
That attachment had sprung up, as is not 
unfrequently the case, in the hop-gardens. The 
girl had been ailing for some time, and her 
shrewd old doctor assured her father that there 
was no tonic so efficacious as a fortnight's 
hop-picking in the sunny September weather. 
Now there were but few places to which so 
distinguished a belle as Susan could be permitted 
to go for such a purpose; but her family knew 
and respected the Eades, and to Mr. Malcolmson's 
hop-grounds she was accordingly sent. 
The tonic prescribed produced the desired effect. 
She lost her ailments; but she lost her heart too.</p>
<p>George Eade was good looking, and up to 
that time had never cared for woman. The 
love he conceived for the gentle, blue-eyed 
girl was of that all-absorbing character which 
natures stern and concentrated like his, are fitted 
to feel, and to feel but once in a lifetime. It 
carried all before it. Susan was sweet tempered 
and simple hearted, of a yielding disposition, 
and, though not unconscious of her beauty, 
singularly little spoilt by the consciousness. She 
gave her whole heart to the faithful earnest 
man whom she reverenced as her superior 
in moral strength, if not in outward circumstances. 
They exchanged no rings on the 
balmy evening which witnessed their plighted 
faith, but he took from her hat the garland 
of hops she had laughingly twisted round 
it, and looking down upon her sweet face 
with a great love in his brown eyes, whispered, 
"I shall keep this whilst I live, and have 
it buried with me when I die!"</p>
<p>But, there was a certain Geoffrey Gibbs, 
the owner of the "Place" on Cumner Common, 
who had paid, and was still paying, 
marked attention to the beautiful Susan. This 
man, originally in trade, had chanced, some years 
before, to see in the newspapers a notice that if 
he would apply to a certain lawyer in London, 
he would hear of something greatly to his 
advantage. He did so, and the result was, his 
acquisition of a comfortable independence, left 
him by a distant kinsman whom he had never 
so much as seen. This windfall changed his 
whole prospects and manner of life, but not his 
character, which had always been that of an 
unmitigated snob. In outward circumstances, 
however, he was a gentleman living on his 
income, and, as such, the undoubted social 
superior of the Archers, who were simply 
tenant-farmers. Hence their desire that Susan 
should favour his suit. Some people were of 
opinion, that he had no serious intention of 
marrying the girl; and Susan herself always 
encouraged this notion; adding, that were he 
ten times as rich, and a hundred times as devoted 
as he represented himself to be, she would die 
rather than accept the cross-grained monster.</p>
<p>He <em>was</em> frightful; less from defects of feature 
than from utter disproportion of form, 
and a sinister expression of countenance, far 
worse than actual ugliness. His legs were as 
short as his body and hands were long, while 
his head would have been well suited to the 
frame of a Hercules; giving him a top-heavy 
appearance that was singularly ungraceful. 
His eyebrows were shaggy and overhanging, 
his eyes small and malicious looking, his nose 
was beak-shaped, his mouth immense, with 
thick sensual lips. He wore huge false-looking 
chains, outrageous shirt-pins and neckcloths, and 
cutaway sporting coats of astounding colours. 
He was a man who delighted in frightening 
inoffensive females, in driving within an inch 
of a lady's pony-carriage, or in violently 
galloping past some timid girl on horseback, 
and chuckling at her scared attempts to 
restrain her plunging steed. Like all bullies, he 
was of course a coward at heart.</p>
<p>Between this man and George Eade a keen 
hatred existed. George despised as well as 
detested Gibbs. Gibbs envied as much as he 
abhorred the more fortunate peasant, who was 
beloved where he met with nothing but coldness 
and rebuffs.</p>
<p>Susan's heart was indeed wholly George's, yet 
it was only when her health had again begun to 
fail, that her father was frightened into a most 
unwilling consent to their union; which consent 
no sooner became known to Mr. Malcolmson, 
than he voluntarily raised the young man's wages, 
and undertook to put in repair for him a cottage 
of his own, not far from that of Simon Eade.</p>
<p>But, when the news of the approaching marriage 
reached the ears of Gibbs, his jealous fury 
was aroused to the utmost. He rushed down 
to the Plashetts, and, closeting himself with 
Mr. Archer, made brilliant offers of settlement 
on Susan, if she would consent even now 
to throw over her lover, and become his wife. 
But he only succeeded in distressing the girl, 
and tantalising her father. Willingly, indeed, 
would the latter have acceded to his wishes, but 
he had passed his solemn word to George, and 
Susan held him to it. No sooner, however, was 
Gibbs gone, than the old man burst into loud 
lamentations over what he called her 
self-sacrifice; and her eldest brother coming in, 
joined in reproaching her for refusing prospects 
so advantageous. Susan was weak, and easily 
influenced. She was cut to the heart by their 
cruel words, and went out to meet her lover 
with her spirits depressed, and her eyes red 
and swollen. George, shocked at her appearance, 
listened with indignation to her agitated 
recital of what had passed.</p>
<p>"Keep your carriage, indeed!" he exclaimed, 
with bitter scorn. "Does your father make 
more count of a one-horse shay than of true 
love such as mine? And a fellow like Gibbs, 
too! That I wouldn't trust a dog with!"</p>
<p>"Father don't see it so," the girl sobbed out. 
"Father says he'd make a very good husband, 
once we was married. And I'd be a lady, and 
dress fine, and have servants! Father thinks 
so much of that!"</p>
<p>"So it seems; but don't you be led by him, 
Susan, darling! 'Tisn't riches and fine clothes 
that makes folks' happiness--'tis better things! 
See here, my girl----" He stopped short, and 
faced her with a look of unutterable emotion. "I 
love ye so true, that if I thought--if I thought 
it'd be for your good to marry this fellow--if I 
thought ye'd be happier with him than with me, 
I'd--I'd give ye up, Susan! Yes--and never 
come near ye more! I would indeed!"</p>
<p>He paused, and, raising his hand with a gesture 
that had in it a rude solemnity very 
impressive, repeated once more, "<em>I would indeed!</em> 
But ye'd not be happy with Geoffrey Gibbs. 
Ye'd be miserable--ill-used, perhaps. He ain't 
a man to make any woman happy--I'm as sure 
o' that, as that I stand here. He's bad at heart--
downright cruel. And I!--what I promise, 
I'll act up to--O! steady. I'll work for you, 
and slave for you, and--and love you true!"</p>
<p>He drew her towards him as he spoke, and 
she, reassured by his words, nestled lovingly to 
his side. And so they walked on for some 
moments in silence.</p>
<p>"And, darling," he added, presently, "I've 
that trust--that faith--in me--that once we're 
married, and you're mine--safe--so's no one can 
come between us, I'll get on; and who knows 
but ye may ride in your carriage yet. Folks do 
get on, when they've a mind to, serious."</p>
<p>She looked up at him with fond admiring 
eyes. She honoured him for his strength, all 
the more because of her own weakness.</p>
<p>"I don't want no carriage," she murmured; 
"I want nothing but you, George. 'Tisn't I, 
you know, that wish things different--'tis 
father----"</p>
<p>The moon had risen, the beautiful bright 
September moon, nearly at the full; and its 
light shone on the lovers as they retraced their 
steps through the silent Southanger woods--
how solemn and lovely at that hour!--towards 
Susan's home. And before they had reached 
the gate of the Plashetts, her sweet face was 
again bright with smiles, and it had been agreed 
between them that to avoid a repetition of such 
attempts on the part of Gibbs, and such scenes 
with her father, she should propose to go to her 
aunt's, Miss Jane Archer's, at Ormiston, for a 
fortnight of the three weeks that yet remained 
before the marriage should take place.</p>
<p>She acted on this idea, and George took advantage 
of her absence to attend a sale on the 
other side of the county, and procure certain 
articles of furniture required for their new home. 
Once away, he obtained leave to prolong his 
stay with a friend till the time of Susan's 
return. It was pleasanter for him not to be at 
home at this period. His mother seemed to 
grow more averse to his marriage, the nearer it 
approached; declaring that no good could 
possibly come of union with a girl who had been 
too much waited upon and flattered, to make a 
good wife for a plain hard-working man. These 
remarks, indescribably galling to the lover 
because not wholly without foundation, had given 
rise to more than one dispute between his 
mother and him, which had not tended to 
diminish the half-unconscious dislike the good 
woman felt towards her future daughter-in-law.</p>
<p>When George returned home after his 
fortnight's holiday, he found, instead of the expected 
letter from his betrothed announcing her arrival 
at the Plashetts, one addressed to him in a strange 
hand, and containing the following words:</p>
<letter>
<p>"George Eade, you are being done. Look to 
G. G. </p>
<right>"A WELL-WISHER."</right>
</letter>
<p>Perplexed at so mysterious a communication, 
he was somewhat annoyed to find that Gibbs 
had quitted Cumner from the very day after his 
own departure, and was still absent. This 
struck him as remarkable; but Susan had 
written him only a week before, a letter so full 
of tenderness that he could not bring himself 
to entertain a single doubt of her truth. But 
on the very next morning, his mother handed 
him a letter from Farmer Archer, enclosing 
one from his sister, informing him that her 
niece had left her house clandestinely two days 
before, to be married to Mr. Gibbs. It appeared 
that the girl had gone, as on previous occasions, 
to spend the day with a cousin, and that not 
returning at night, it was concluded she had settled 
to sleep there. The next morning had brought, 
instead of herself, the announcement of her 
marriage.</p>
<p>On reading this news, George was at first 
conscious of but one feeling. Utter incredulity. 
There must be some error somewhere; the thing 
could not be. While his father, with tears 
in his honest eyes, exhorted him to bear up like 
a man under this blow, and his mother indignantly 
declared that a girl who could so conduct 
herself was indeed a good riddance, he sat silent, 
half stupified. Such a breach of faith seemed, to 
his earnest and loyal nature, simply impossible.</p>
<p>Another half-hour brought confirmation that 
could not be doubted. James Wilkins, Mr. 
Gibbs's man-servant, came grinning and 
important, with a letter for George, which had 
been enclosed in one from his master to himself. 
It was from Susan, and signed with her new name.</p>
<p>"I know," it said, "that for what I have 
done, I shall be without excuse in your eyes--
that you will hate and despise me as much as you 
have hitherto loved and trusted me. I know that 
I have behaved to you very, very bad, and I 
don't ask you to forgive me. I know you can't. 
But I do ask you to refrain from vengeance. It 
can't bring back the past. Oh, George! if ever 
you cared for me, listen to what I entreat now. 
Hate and despise me--I don't expect no other--
but don't you revenge my ill conduct on 
anyone. Forget all about me--that's the best 
thing for both of us. It would have been better 
if we had never beheld one another."</p>
<p>Much more followed in the same strain--
weak, self-accusing, fearful of consequences--
wholly unworthy of George.</p>
<p>He gazed at the letter, holding it in those 
strong sinewy hands that would have toiled for 
her so hard and so faithfully. Then, without a 
word, he held it out to his father, and left the 
room. They heard him mount the narrow stairs, 
lock himself into his little garret, and they 
heard no more.</p>
<p>After a while his mother went to him. 
Although personally relieved at her son's release, 
that feeling was entirely absorbed in tender 
and loving pity for what she knew must be his 
sufferings. He was sitting by the little casement, 
a withered branch of hops upon his knee. 
She went and laid her cheek to his.</p>
<p>"Have patience, lad!" she said, with earnest 
feeling. "Try--try--to have faith, and comfort'll 
be sent ye in time. It's hard to bear, I know--
dreadful hard and bitter--but for the poor 
parents' sakes who loves ye so dear, try and 
bear it."</p>
<p>He looked up at her with cold tearless eyes. 
"I will," he said, in a hard voice. "Don't ye 
see I <em>am</em> trying?"</p>
<p>His glance was dull and hopeless. How she 
longed that tears would come and relieve his 
bursting heart!</p>
<p>"She wasn't worthy of ye, my boy. I always 
told ye----"</p>
<p>But he stopped her with a stern gesture.</p>
<p>"Mother! Not a word o' that, nor of her, 
from this hour. What she's done ain't so 
very bad after all. <em>I'm</em> all right--<em>I</em> am. Father 
and you shan't see no difference in me, leastways, 
not if you'll forbear naming of her ever, 
ever again. She's turned my heart to stone, 
that's all! No great matter!"</p>
<p>He laid his hand on his broad chest and 
heaved a great gasping sigh. "This morning I 
had a heart o' flesh here," he said; "now it's a 
cold, heavy stone. But it's no great matter."</p>
<p>"Oh, don't ye speak like that, my lad!" his 
mother cried, bursting into tears, and throwing 
her arms around him. "It kills me to hear ye!"</p>
<p>But he gently unwound those arms, and 
kissing her on the cheek, led her to the door. 
"I must go to work now," he said; and, 
descending the stairs before her, he quitted the 
cottage with a firm step.</p>
<p>From that hour no one heard him speak 
of Susan Gibbs. He never inquired into the 
circumstances of her stay at Ormiston; he never 
spoke of them, nor of her, to her relations or to 
his own. He avoided the former; he was silent 
and reserved with the latter. Susan appeared 
to be, for him, as though she had never been.</p>
<p>And from that hour he was an altered being. 
He went about his work as actively, and did it 
as carefully, as ever; but it was done sternly, 
doggedly, like an imperative but unwelcome 
duty. No man ever saw a smile upon his lips; 
no jocular word ever escaped them. Grave 
and uncompromising, he went his ungenial way, 
seeking for no sympathy, and bestowing none, 
avoiding all companionship save that of his 
parents;--a sad and solitary man.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Mr. Gibbs's "Place" on Cumner 
Common was advertised as to be let; strangers 
hired it, and for nearly three years nothing was 
seen of him or of his wife. Then news arrived 
one day that they were to be expected shortly, 
and quite a ferment of expectation was created 
in the little village. They came, and certain 
rumours that had reached it from time to time were 
found to have only too much foundation in truth.</p>
<p>For it had oozed out, as such things do ooze, 
that Gibbs shamefully ill used his pretty wife, 
and that the marriage, which on his side 
had been one of love, had turned out miserably. 
Her father and brothers, who had 
been to see them more than once, had been 
strangely reserved on the subject of those visits, 
and it was generally understood that the old 
farmer lamented his daughter's marriage now, 
as much as he had formerly longed for it. No 
one wondered, when they saw her. She was the 
shadow of her former self; still lovely, but 
broken, cowed, pale; all the bloom faded; all 
the spirit crushed out of her. No smile was 
ever seen upon those pretty lips now, except 
when she played with her boy, a fair-haired 
little fellow, the image of herself. But even 
in her intercourse with this child she was sternly 
restricted, and her tyrant would not unfrequently 
dismiss him with an oath, and forbid her 
to follow him to his nursery.</p>
<p>In spite of their being such near neighbours, 
the Gibbses had been some time in the place 
before George met his former love. He never 
went to Cumner church (nor to any, indeed), 
and she never quitted her own house, except 
to drive with her husband, or walk through 
the Southanger Woods to her father's. George 
might have beheld her driving past his father's 
door with a high-stepping horse that always 
seemed on the point of running away; but 
he never looked at her, nor replied to his 
mother's remarks respecting her and her smart 
turn-out. Yet though he resolutely kept the 
door of his own lips, he could not close the 
lips of other people, or his own ears. Do 
what he would, the Gibbses and their doings 
pursued him still. His master's labourers 
gossiped about the husband's brutality; the 
baker's boy had no end of stories to tell, 
of the oaths he had heard, and even the 
blows he had witnessed, when "Gibbs was 
more than usual excited with drink." The 
poor frightened wife was understood to have 
declared that but for her dread of what he 
might be driven to do in his fury, she would go 
before a magistrate and swear the peace against 
him. George could not close his ears to all this; 
and men said that the expression of his eyes on 
those occasions was not good to look upon.</p>
<p>One Sunday, the Eades were sitting over 
their frugal one o'clock dinner, when they 
heard the sound of a carriage driving furiously 
past. Mrs. Eade caught up her stick, and, in 
spite of her lameness, hobbled to the window.</p>
<p>"I thought so!" she cried. "It's Gibbs 
driving to Tenelms, and drunk again, seemingly. 
See how he's flogging of the horse. 
And he's got the little lad, too! He'll not rest 
till he've broken that child's neck, or the 
mother's. Simmons declares----"</p>
<p>She stopped, suddenly aware of her son's 
breath upon her cheek. He had actually come 
to the window, and now, leaning over her, was 
gazing sternly at the figures in the carriage, 
flying down the hill towards the Tenelms road.</p>
<p>"I wish he might break his own neck!" 
George muttered between his teeth.</p>
<p>"Oh, George! George! don't name such 
things," Mrs. Eade cried, with a pale shocked 
face. "It ain't Christian. We've all need of 
repentance, and our times is in His hand."</p>
<p>"If ye frequented church, my lad, 'stead of 
keeping away, as I grieve to see ye do," his father 
said, severely, "ye'd have better feelings in your 
heart. <em>They'll</em> never prosper ye, mark my words."</p>
<p>George had returned to his seat, but he rose 
again as his father said this. "Church!" he cried, 
in a loud harsh voice--"I was going there once, 
and it wasn't permitted. I'll go there no more. 
D'ye think," he continued, while his white lips 
trembled with uncontrollable emotion--"d'ye 
think, because I'm quiet, and do my work 
reg'lar, d'ye think I've forgotten? <em>Forgotten!</em>" 
He brought his clenched fist down upon the table 
with startling violence. "I tell ye when I forget, 
I'll be lying stark and stiff in my coffin! Let 
be--let be!" as his mother tried to interrupt 
him; "ye mean well, I know, but women 
haven't the judgment to tell when to speak, and 
when to hold hard. Ye'd best never name that 
scoundrel 'fore me again, nor yet church." With 
that, he went from the room and from the house.</p>
<p>Mrs. Eade fretted sadly over these evidences 
of George's rancorous and ungodly disposition. 
To her, he seemed to be on the high road to 
perdition, and she ended by sending to Mr. 
Murray, the rector, to beg he would he pleased 
to look in upon her some morning soon, as she 
was greatly troubled in her mind. But Mr. Murray 
was at that time ill, and nearly a fortnight 
elapsed before he was able to answer her summons. 
Meanwhile, other events occurred.</p>
<p>It was notorious that one of Mrs. Gibbs's 
greatest trials was about her boy, whom her 
husband persisted in driving out, at the risk, as 
every one thought, of his life. Fearful had 
been the scenes between the parents on this 
account; but the more she wept and implored, 
the more he resisted her entreaties. One day, 
to frighten her still more, he placed the little 
fellow, with the whip in his hand, on the 
carriage-seat alone, and stood at his door himself, 
loosely holding the reins, and jeering at his wife, 
who in an agony of terror kept beseeching him 
to get in, or to let her do so. Suddenly the report 
of a gun was heard in a neighbouring field; the 
horse took fright, and started off wildly, jerking 
the reins from the hands of the half-intoxicated 
Gibbs; the whip fell from the hands of the child 
on the animal's back, still further exciting it; 
and the boy, thrown with violence to the bottom 
of the carriage, lay half stunned by the shock.</p>
<p>George was close by when this occurred. 
He threw himself on the flying horse, and, 
seizing the bearing-rein with his whole strength, 
held on like grim death, in spite of being 
half dragged, half borne, along in its headlong 
flight. At last the animal, getting its 
legs entangled in the long trailing reins, fell 
with fearful violence, and lay stunned and 
motionless. George was thrown to the ground, 
but escaped with a few trifling bruises. The 
child at the bottom of the carriage, though 
frightened and screaming, was altogether uninjured. 
In less than five minutes half the village 
was collected on the spot, inquiring, congratulating, 
applauding; and Susan, with her rescued 
child clinging to her bosom, was covering 
George's hands with passionate tears and kisses.</p>
<p>"Bless you! Bless you a thousand times!" 
she cried, sobbing hysterically. "You've saved 
my darling's life! He might have been killed 
but for you! How can I ever----"</p>
<p>But a rough hand shoved her aside. "What 
are you after now?" Gibbs's furious voice was 
heard to cry, with a shocking oath. "Leave 
that fellow alone, or I'll----! Are you making 
a fool of yourself this way, because he's lamed 
the horse so that he'll have to be shot?"</p>
<p>The poor thing sank down on the bank and 
broke into a fit of hysterical weeping; whilst a 
murmur of "Shame, shame!" rose among the 
bystanders.</p>
<p>George Eade had turned coldly from Susan 
when she rushed up to him, and had striven to 
withdraw his hands from her grasp; but now, 
confronting Gibbs, he said, "It'll be a good deed 
done, whoever shoots that brute of yours, and 
it'd be a better still to shoot you as a man would 
a mad dog!"</p>
<p>All heard the words. All trembled at his 
look as he uttered them. The whole of the pent-up 
rage and resentment of the last three years 
seemed concentrated in that one look of savage 
and unutterable hatred.</p>
<p>Mr. Murray found poor Mrs. Eade very suffering, 
when, two mornings after, he called to 
congratulate her on her son's escape. She had not 
closed her eyes since the accident. George's 
look and words, as they had been described to 
her, haunted her. The good clergyman could 
give her but scant comfort. He had tried again 
and again to reason with and soften her son, but 
ineffectually. George answered him, with a certain 
rude respect, that as long as he did his work 
properly, and injured no man, he had a right to 
decide for himself in matters concerning only 
himself; and one of his fixed decisions was never 
again to see the inside of a church.</p>
<p>"It's a hard trial, my good friend," said Mr. 
Murray, "a hard and mysterious trial. But I 
say to you, <em>have faith</em>. There is a hidden good 
in it, that we can't see now."</p>
<p>"It'd be strange if I wasn't thankful for his 
being spared," Mrs. Eade replied. "It'd be 
worse than anything to have tne dear lad took, 
revengeful and unforgiving as he is now. But 
you see, sir----"</p>
<p>She was stopped in her eager speech by a 
knock at the door. The son of Mr. Beach, 
the neighbouring butcher, peeped in. He 
scraped a bow on seeing the clergyman sitting 
with her, and looked from one to the other with 
a doubtful demeanour.</p>
<p>"I don't want nothing this morning, thank 
you, Jim," Mrs. Eade said. Then, struck with 
the peculiar expression of the young man's face, 
she added: "Ain't Mr. Beach so well this morning? 
You look all nohow."</p>
<p>"I'm--I'm a bit flustered," the youth replied, 
wiping his steaming forehead; "I've just been 
seeing <em>him</em>, and it gave me such a turn!"</p>
<p>"Him! who?"</p>
<p>"Sure! Haven't ye heard, sir? Gibbs have 
been found dead in Southanger Woods--murdered 
last night. They say----"</p>
<p>"Gibbs murdered!"</p>
<p>There was a pause of breathless horror.</p>
<p>"They've been carrying his corpse to the 
Dunstan Arms, and I see it."</p>
<p>Mrs. Eade turned so deadly faint that the 
clergyman called out hurriedly for Jemima, 
the servant girl. But Jemima had run out 
wildly on hearing the appalling intelligence, 
and was now midway between her master's 
house and the Gibbs's, listening to a knot of 
people, all wondering, surmising, gazing with 
scared eyes at that door in the high wall, the 
threshold of which its master would never cross 
again, except feet foremost.</p>
<p>The Eades' parlour was soon full to overflowing. 
Most of the dwellers on the common had 
congregated there--why, perhaps none would 
have cared to explain. Simon Eade came in 
among the first, and was doing his best to soothe 
and restore the poor fainting woman, who could 
hardly as yet realise what had occurred. In the 
midst of the confusion--the questioning, the 
describing of the position of the body, the rifled 
pockets, the dreadful blow from behind, the 
number of hours since the deed was done--in 
the midst of all this, steps were heard outside, 
and George came into the midst of them.</p>
<p>Then a sudden hush succeeded to the Babel 
of sounds, which he could not but have heard 
as he crossed the threshold. There was 
something ominous in that silence.</p>
<p>No need to ask if he knew. His face, pale 
as death, haggard, streaming with perspiration, 
proved all too plainly he was aware of the ghastly 
horror. But his first words, low, and uttered half 
unconsciously, were long after remembered:</p>
<p>"I WISH I'D BEEN FOUND DEAD IN THAT 
WOOD 'STEAD OF GIBBS!"</p>
<p>Various circumstances arose, one after 
another, that united to surround George with a 
kind of network of suspicion. Simon Eade 
sustained himself like a man, with a proud 
confidence in the innocence of his boy, touching even 
those who could not share it; and with a pious 
trust that Providence would yet see that 
innocence proved. But the poor feeble mother, 
shaken by ill health, half crazed by the remembrance 
of words and looks she would give the 
world to forget, could do little but weep, and 
utter broken supplications to Heaven.</p>
<p>George offered no resistance on his apprehension. 
Sternly, but without eagerness, he 
declared his innocence, and from that moment he 
kept entire silence. His features worked 
convulsively when he wrung his father's hand on 
parting, and gazed on the pale face of his mother, 
who had swooned away on seeing the police; 
but he soon recovered his self-possession, and 
accompanied the officers with a steady step, and 
a fixed, though gloomy countenance.</p>
<p>The body of the deceased had been discovered 
about ten A.M. by a farmer going to the Plashetts, 
who had been attracted to the spot by the howls 
of Gibbs's dog. The corpse lay among the 
underwood, at a short distance from the footpath 
leading from the stile so often mentioned, 
through the wood to the Plashetts, and had 
apparently been dragged that short distance. 
Evidences of a fierce struggle were visible on 
and around the footpath, and some blood also: 
which appeared to have flowed from a wound in 
the back of the head of the deceased, who must 
have been struck from behind, by some heavy, 
though not blunt, instrument. When found, he 
had been dead, according to the medical testimony, 
some eleven or twelve hours. The pockets 
were turned inside out, and the watch and a 
purse had been taken, as well as a seal ring.</p>
<p>Gibbs's two servants, James and Bridget 
Williams, deposed that their master had quitted 
his own house on the night of the murder, at 
twenty minutes past eight, being unusually sober; 
that he had set his watch, the last thing, by the 
kitchen clock, and had observed that he should 
go to the Dunstan Arms first, and afterwards to 
the Plashetts. That his not returning that night 
had occasioned no uneasiness, as he was in the 
habit of frequently absenting himself until morning, 
and had his latch-key always with him.</p>
<p>On the other hand, Simon Eade, his wife, and 
servant girl, all deposed that George returned 
home on the night of the murder, at nine o'clock, 
having been out since tea-time; that there was 
nothing unusual in either his manner or 
appearance; that he supped, and afterwards 
remained with his parents till ten, when the 
whole family retired to bed; and that he came 
down next morning in the sight of Jemima, who 
had herself risen somewhat earlier than usual.</p>
<p>On his left wrist was found a recent cut, 
which he stated had been caused by his clasp-knife 
slipping, as he was cutting his bread and 
cheese. In the same manner he sought to 
account for certain marks of blood on the inside 
of his coat sleeves and on his trousers. The 
only article belonging to the deceased that was 
found in his possession was a small lead pencil, 
marked with the initials "G. G." and three 
notches; these Job Brettle, the blacksmith, swore 
Gibbs had handed him the pencil to cut, on the 
afternoon of the murder. He (Brettle) noticed 
both notches and initials at the time, and could 
swear that the pencil in the prisoner's possession 
was the pencil he had cut. George maintained 
that he had picked it up on the common, and 
that he had no idea to whom it belonged.</p>
<p>It came out in cross-examination that a more 
desperate quarrel than ever, had taken place on 
the morning of the murder, between Mr. and 
Mrs. Gibbs; after which, she had been heard to 
declare that she could support that life no longer, 
and would apply for help to one who would not 
refuse it. That she had sent a letter soon after 
to George Eade, by the son of a neighbouring 
cottager, and had gone out herself at night, a 
few minutes after her husband, returning again 
in a quarter of an hour, more or less, when she 
had retired to her bedroom, and had not again 
quitted it until news was brought next morning 
of the discovery of the corpse.</p>
<p>When questioned by the coroner as to where 
she had been overnight, no reply could be elicited 
from her; but she fainted so frequently while 
under examination, that her evidence was singularly 
broken and incoherent.</p>
<p>George admitted having gone to the Southanger 
Woods at about twenty minutes to eight 
on the night of the murder; but he refused to 
assign any special reason for going there, 
declaring that he had not remained there more than 
a quarter of an hour at most. He stated that, as 
he was re-crossing the stile, he saw Gibbs and 
his dog at a distance, making directly for it. 
The moon shone almost as bright as day, and 
he recognised him distinctly. To avoid meeting 
him, he took the Dring road, and walked nearly 
as far as the turnpike, when he turned about, 
and so reached home at nine o'clock without 
having met a soul.</p>
<p>The following were (briefly) the points in the 
prisoner's favour:</p>
<p>1. The evidence of three credible witnesses 
that he returned home at nine o'clock, and sat 
down to supper without any appearance of hurry 
or agitation.</p>
<p>2. The shortness of the time in which to commit 
such a deed, and effectually to conceal the 
property taken from the deceased.</p>
<p>3. The high moral character born by the 
prisoner up to that time.</p>
<p>The points against him were:</p>
<p>1. The cut on his wrist, and marks of blood 
on his clothes.</p>
<p>2. Gibbs's pencil, found upon him.</p>
<p>3. The absence of testimony corroborative 
of his own account of his doings during the 
thirty minutes that intervened between Gibbs's 
leaving the Dunstan Arms (where he had gone 
straight from home) and his (George's) own 
return to his father's.</p>
<p>4. The bitter animosity he was known to 
cherish against the deceased, and certain words 
he had been heard to utter respecting him, 
indicating a desire for his life.</p>
<p>By the evidence of the landlord of the 
Dunstan Arms, it appeared that Gibbs had left his 
place to proceed to the Plashetts, at a few 
minutes before half-past eight o'clock. Now, it 
would take some four or five minutes' moderate 
walking for one leaving the public-house, to reach 
the spot where Gibbs's body was found; thus 
reducing the period for the murder to be 
committed in (if committed by George at that time) 
to three or four and twenty minutes, if he ran 
home at his full speed, or to nineteen or twenty 
minutes, if he walked at an average pace.</p>
<p>The demeanour of the prisoner before the 
magistrates, was stern, and even defiant; but 
he betrayed no emotion. He was fully 
committed for trial at the approaching assizes.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, opinion respecting him was greatly 
divided in Cumner. He had never been a popular 
man, and his extreme reserve during the 
last three years had alienated many who, at 
the period of his great trouble, had been 
disposed to sympathise with him. And, although 
he had always held a high place in public 
estimation, the impression that he was a man of 
unusually fierce passions, and implacable 
resentment, had gained ground of late. In short, 
not a few of those who knew him best, believed 
that, worked up to savage fury by the sufferings 
of the woman he had once so fondly loved, and by 
long brooding over his own wrongs, he had 
revenged both himself and her by taking the life 
of his enemy. He might, it was thought, have 
easily slipped out of his father's house in the 
dead of night, have waylaid and murdered Gibbs 
as he was returning from the Plashetts, and 
have secreted or destroyed the property in order 
to throw suspicion off the right scent.</p>
<p>His trial will long be remembered in those 
parts, as well from the intense excitement it 
occasioned in that particular locality, as from 
the strong interest manifested about it throughout 
the kingdom. The most eminent counsel 
were engaged on his behalf; and Mr. Malcolmson, 
who never could believe in his guilt, spared 
neither pains nor expense to aid his cause. He 
was perfectly calm when he stood in the dock, 
the one object on which countless eyes were 
eagerly riveted; but the change that had taken 
place in his outward seeming, struck even the 
most indifferent beholder with compassion, and 
possibly did more to impress the jury in his favour, 
than even the eloquence of his counsel, wonderful 
as that proved. For, his sufferings must have 
been intense. He had grown years older, during 
the last few weeks. His hair had thinned; his 
clothes hung upon his attenuated frame. He, 
once so ruddy and vigorous, stood there wan, 
haggard, drooping. Even the expression of his 
countenance had altered; it was stern no more.</p>
<p>A sound like one vast sobbing sigh went 
through the crowded court when the verdict, 
Not Guilty, was heard; but no applause, no 
public mark of joy or gratulation. And silently, 
with downcast eyes, like a doomed man, George 
Eade returned with one parent to the home 
where the other sat praying for his release.</p>
<p>It had been expected that, if acquitted, he 
would leave Cumner, and seek his fortunes 
elsewhere. But it was consistent with the 
character of the man, to brave the opinion of 
his fellows, and he did so in this instance. On 
the first Sunday, to the surprise of all, he made 
his appearance in church, sitting apart from the 
rest of the congregation, as though unwilling to 
obtrude himself upon them; from that time 
his attendance was invariable. Nor was this 
the only change observable in his conduct. His 
moroseness had passed away. He had become 
subdued, patient, manifesting a touching gratitude 
to those who treated him with common 
civility, as though he felt himself unworthy of 
their notice; unremitting in his devotion to his 
parents; working hard all the day; sometimes 
puzzling over a book at night; never alluding 
to the past--never forgetting it; melancholy--
more melancholy than ever; but no longer 
bitter nor resentful. Such had George Eade 
become; and when men saw him at a distance, 
they followed him with their eyes, and asked 
one another in a whisper, "Did he do it?"</p>
<p>He and Susan never met. She long lay 
dangerously ill at her father's house, whither she 
had removed after the tragical event. And the 
old farmer was fitly punished for his sordid 
coveting of Gibbs's wealth, when it was found 
that the latter had settled only fifty pounds a 
year upon his wife, to be forfeited altogether if 
she should make a second marriage.</p>
<break/>
<p>It was about a twelvemonth after these events 
that, one bright moonlight night, as Mr. Murray 
was sitting in his library alone, his servant 
entered to inform him that a stranger, who gave 
his name as Luke Williams, desired to speak 
with him. It was past ten o'clock, and the 
clergyman's hours were early and regular.</p>
<p>"Tell him to call to-morrow morning," said 
he; "this is not a fit hour for business."</p>
<p>"I did tell him so, sir," the man replied; 
"but he declared his was a business that would 
not wait an hour."</p>
<p>"Is he a beggar?"</p>
<p>"He didn't beg, sir; but he looks shocking, 
quite shocking----"</p>
<p>"Show him in."</p>
<p>The man entered; truly a shocking object. 
Pale, hollow-eyed, cadaverous, with a racking 
cough that caused him to pant and gasp for 
breath, he looked like one in the last stage of 
consumption. He gazed at Mr. Murray with a 
strange and mournful expression, and Mr. 
Murray gazed at him.</p>
<p>"Well?"</p>
<p>The stranger glanced at the servant.</p>
<p>"Leave the room, Robert."</p>
<p>Robert did so, but remained in close proximity 
outside.</p>
<p>"This is a strange hour at which to disturb 
me. Have you something to say?"</p>
<p>"It <em>is</em> a strange hour, sir, for coming; but 
my reason for coming is stranger."</p>
<p>The man turned to the window, the curtains of 
which were not drawn, and gazed at the full 
October moon, which lighted up the quaint old 
church hard by, the humble gravestones, the quiet 
home scene, and shed a solemn glory over all.</p>
<p>"Well?" Mr. Murray asked once more.</p>
<p>But the man's eyes were fixed on the sky.</p>
<p>"Yes," he said, shuddering, "it shone like 
that--like that--the night of the--murder. It 
did indeed. It shone on his face--Gibbs's--as 
he lay there--it shone on his open eyes--I 
couldn't get them to shut; do what I would, 
they would stare at me. I've never seen moonlight 
like that since, till to-night. And I'm come 
to give myself up to you. I always felt I should, 
and it's better done and over. Better over."</p>
<p>"You murdered Gibbs? You?"</p>
<p>"I did. I've been there to-night, to look at 
the place. I felt I must see it again; and I saw his 
eyes, as plain as I see you, open, with the moonlight 
shining on them. Ah, a horrible sight!"</p>
<p>"You look very wild and ill. Perhaps----"</p>
<p>"You doubt me. I wish <em>I</em> could doubt. See 
here."</p>
<p>With a trembling emaciated hand he drew 
from his pocket the watch, seal ring, and purse 
that had belonged to Gibbs; and laid them on 
the table. Mr. Murray knew them.</p>
<p>"I used the money," said the man, faintly. 
"There were but a few shillings, and I was in 
great want."</p>
<p>Then he sank down on a chair with a dreadful 
groan.</p>
<p>Mr. Murray gave him a restorative, and after 
a time he rallied. With his hollow eyes still 
gazing at the moonlight, and with that ever-recurring 
shudder, he faltered out at intervals the 
following story.</p>
<p>He and Gibbs had been formerly associated 
in disreputable money transactions, which had 
ended in his own ruin. Being in abject 
distress, he had, on the promise of a considerable 
bribe, agreed to aid Gibbs in a plot to obtain 
possession of Susan's person. When she and 
George had separated for the fortnight previous 
to their contemplated marriage, the two 
confederates had followed her to Ormiston, and, 
concealing themselves in a low part of the town, 
had kept close watch upon her movements. 
Ascertaining that she was to spend the day 
with a cousin, they sent a woman, a creature of 
their own, to waylay her on her road, with a 
message purporting to come from George Eade, 
imploring her to hasten to him immediately, as 
he was injured by an accident on the railroad, 
and might have but a few hours to live. 
Appalled by such intelligence, the poor girl 
hurried to the place where the woman led her, 
entered without a shadow of suspicion a lonely 
house in the suburbs, and found herself in the 
presence of Gibbs and Williams, who, instantly 
securing the door, informed her that this 
subterfuge had been resorted to in order to get her 
into the power of the former. They told her 
that she was now in a place where screams would 
not be heeded, even if heard, and whence she 
would find it impossible to escape, and that she 
would not be quitted night or day by them or 
their female assistant, until she should consent 
to become the wife of Gibbs. Who added, with 
furious oaths, that had her union with George 
Eade taken place, he would have shot him down 
on his way from church.</p>
<p>Wild with terror and astonishment, helpless, 
bewildered, the girl resisted longer than might 
have been expected in one naturally weak. But 
finding herself incessantly watched, trembling, 
too, for her life (for Gibbs stood over her with 
a loaded pistol and the most furious threats), 
she was frightened at last into writing, at 
his dictation, the letters to her aunt and lover, 
announcing her marriage; though that event did 
not really take place till nearly three weeks 
later, when, worn out, and almost stupified into 
acquiescence, she was married in due form. 
Even then, Williams declared that she would 
have resisted still, but for her fears for her lover's 
safety. His life seemed to be dearer to her than 
her own happiness, and Gibbs had sworn so 
vehemently that his life should be the immediate 
forfeit of his union with her, that she felt that union 
would be impossible. She married, therefore, 
offering herself up as a kind of ransom for the man 
she loved. Then Williams claimed his reward.</p>
<p>But his worthless confederate was not one to 
fulfil honestly any promise involving the sacrifice 
of money. He paid the first of three 
instalments agreed upon; but constantly shirked 
the payment of the others, until at last, 
Williams finding himself in immediate danger of 
arrest, made his way down to the neighbourhood 
of Cumner, and lurking about the Southanger 
Woods, the deep recesses of which were 
well calculated for concealment, watched his 
opportunity, and accosted Gibbs one evening as 
he was driving home from Tenelms alone. That 
worthy, though, as usual, half drunk, recognised 
him at once, and swearing at him for an impudent 
beggar, did his best to drive his horse over 
him. Infuriated by such treatment, Williams 
wrote him a letter, declaring that if he failed to 
bring, on a certain night to a certain spot in 
Southanger Woods, every shilling of the sum 
he had promised to pay, he (Williams) would 
the very next morning go before the nearest 
magistrate and reveal the whole plot of Susan's 
abduction and marriage.</p>
<p>Alarmed by this threat, Gibbs answered the 
appointment, but without bringing the money; 
indeed, it soon became clear that he had no more 
intention of paying it than before. Williams, 
exasperated beyond endurance by these 
repeated disappointments, and rendered desperate 
by want, swore he would at least possess himself 
of whatever money or valuables the other had 
about him. Gibbs resisted with fury, and a 
fierce struggle ensued, during which he 
repeatedly endeavoured to stab his opponent 
with his clasp-knife. At length Williams 
prevailed, and throwing all his strength into one 
supreme effort, hurled Gibbs to the ground, the 
back of whose head striking with fearful 
violence against a tree, he was killed by the force 
of the blow. Appalled by his own act, and by 
the probable consequences to himself, Williams 
hastily dragged the body from the footpath, 
rifled the pockets, and hurried away from the 
scene. The church clock struck ten as he 
emerged from Southanger Woods; he walked all 
that night, rested the next day in an old outhouse, 
and succeeded in reaching London undiscovered. 
But he was, almost immediately afterwards, 
arrested for debt, and had remained in prison 
until within the last few days, when he was 
released chiefly because he was believed to be 
dying of consumption. And he <em>was</em> dying, he 
added, despairingly. For, since that fearful 
night, the victim's upturned eyes had followed 
him everywhere--everywhere--and his life had 
been a burden to him.</p>
<p>Such was the tale, told in broken whispers in 
the dead of night, to the clergyman, by that 
miserable man: a tale impossible to doubt, and 
triumphantly proving the innocence of one who 
had been too Iong suspected. Before twelve 
o'clock next day, the whole village was ringing 
with the news of Williams's confession, which 
spread like wildfire.</p>
<p>George bore his triumph, as he had borne 
unjust suspicion. The man's character had 
been strangely purified in the furnace of that 
affliction. The awful fate of his enemy, overtaking 
him with the suddenness of a chastisement 
from Heaven, had struck George at the 
time with a strange compassion, as well as 
self-upbraiding. For, though guiltless of Gibbs's 
death, he was not guiltless of many and eager 
longings for it; and he would have given 
worlds to have forgiven him, as he hoped 
himself to be forgiven. Hence his first sad and 
self-accusing words in his father's house, after 
hearing of the murder.</p>
<p>It may be mentioned, by the way, that the 
object of the letter he had received from Susan 
on the morning of the fatal day, had been to 
implore him to call upon her father that very 
afternoon, and induce him to take immediate 
steps for effecting her separation from her husband, 
of whom she went in fear of her life, and 
by whom she was watched too closely to be able 
to assist herself. And as her letters were liable 
to be opened, she entreated George to meet her 
in Southanger Woods that night, in order 
to inform her of the result of his negotiation 
(which was never even entered into, as the 
farmer happened to be from home). Finding, 
however, that Gibbs was bound to the Plashetts 
from the public-house, she had rushed out hastily 
to warn George of the circumstance, and so prevent 
a meeting between the two, which was 
very near taking place.</p>
<p>Susan fully confirmed the testimony of Williams 
as to the circumstances of her abduction. 
That wretched man survived his confession little 
more than a week, and died in prison, penitent.</p>
<p>And once more George and Susan met. At 
that interview he took from his bosom a little 
silken bag, in which was a bunch of withered 
hops, so dried by time, that they almost crumbled 
beneath his touch. And he held them up to her.</p>
<p>There is a cottage on Cumner Common, not 
far from Simon Eade's, the walls of which are 
covered with roses and clematis. There you may 
see Susan, if not as beautiful as of yore, still 
fair; and happy now, with her brown-eyed 
baby in her arms; and, if you choose your hour, 
you may catch George, too, coming in to dinner 
or to tea, stalwart, handsome, with a bright 
cheery look on his honest English face, that will 
do you good to look upon.</p>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<info title="To Be Taken For Life."/>
<p>Sophy read through the whole of the foregoing 
several times over, and I sat in my seat in the 
Library Cart (that's the name we give it) seeing 
her read, and I was as pleased and as proud 
as a Pug-Dog with his muzzle black-leaded for 
an evening party and his tail extra curled by 
machinery. Every item of my plan was crowned 
with success. Our reunited life was more than 
all that we had looked forward to. Content and 
joy went with us as the wheels of the two carts 
went round, and the same stopped with us when 
the two carts stopped.</p>
<p>But I had left something out of my calculations. 
Now, what had I left out? To help 
you to a guess, I'll say, a figure. Come. Make 
a guess, and guess right. Nought? No. 
Nine? No. Eight? No. Seven? No. 
Six? No. Five? No. Four? No. Three? 
No. Two? No. One? No. Now I'll tell 
you what I'll do with you. I'll say it's another 
sort of figure altogether. There. Why then, 
says you, it's a mortal figure. No nor yet a 
mortal figure. By such means you get yourself 
penned into a corner, and you can't help guessing 
a <em>im</em>mortal figure. That's about it. Why 
didn't you say so sooner?</p>
<p>Yes. It was a immortal figure that I had 
altogether left out of my calculations. Neither 
man's nor woman's, but a child's. Girl's, or 
boy's? Boy's. "I says the sparrow, with my 
bow and arrow." Now you have got it.</p>
<p>We were down at Lancaster, and I had done 
two nights' more than fair average business 
(though I cannot in honour recommend them as 
a quick audience) in the open square there, near 
the end of the street where Mr. Sly's King's Arms 
and Royal Hotel stands. Mim's travelling giant 
otherwise Pickleson happened at the self-same 
time to be a trying it on in the town. The 
genteel lay was adopted with him. No hint of 
a van. Green baize alcove leading up to Pickleson 
in a Auction Room. Printed poster "Free 
list suspended, with the exception of that proud 
boast of an enlightened country, a free press. 
Schools admitted by private arrangement. 
Nothing to raise a blush in the cheek of youth or 
shock the most fastidious." Mim swearing most 
horrible and terrific in a pink calico pay-place, 
at the slackness of the public. Serious hand-bill 
in the shops, importing that it was all but 
impossible to come to a right understanding of 
the history of David, without seeing Pickleson.</p>
<p>I went to the Auction Room in question, and 
I found it entirely empty of everything but 
echoes and mouldiness, with the single exception 
of Pickleson on a piece of red drugget. 
This suited my purpose, as I wanted a private 
and confidential word with him, which was: 
"Pickleson. Owing much happiness to you, I 
put you in my will for a fypunnote; but, to save 
trouble here's fourpunten down, which may 
equally suit your views, and let us so conclude 
the transaction." Pickleson, who up to that 
remark had had the dejected appearance of a 
long Roman rushlight that couldn't anyhow get 
lighted, brightened up at his top extremity and 
made his acknowledgments in a way which (for 
him) was parliamentary eloquence. He likewise 
did add, that, having ceased to draw as a 
Roman, Mim had made proposals for his going 
in as a conwerted Indian Giant worked upon by 
The Dairyman's Daughter. This, Pickleson, 
having no acquaintance with the tract named 
after that young woman, and not being willing 
to couple gag with his serious views, had 
declined to do, thereby leading to words and the 
total stoppage of the unfortunate young man's 
beer. All of which, during the whole of the 
interview, was confirmed by the ferocious growling 
of Mim down below in the pay-place, which 
shook the giant like a leaf.</p>
<p>But what was to the present point in the 
remarks of the travelling giant otherwise Pickleson, 
was this: "Doctor Marigold"--I give his 
words without a hope of conweying their 
feebleness--"who is the strange young man that 
hangs about your carts?"--"The strange young 
<em>man</em>?" I gives him back, thinking that he meant 
her, and his languid circulation had dropped a 
syllable. "Doctor," he returns, with a pathos 
calculated to draw a tear from even a manly 
eye, "I am weak, but not so weak yet as that 
I don't know my words. I repeat them, Doctor. 
The strange young man." It then appeared 
that Pickleson being forced to stretch his legs 
(not that they wanted it) only at times when he 
couldn't be seen for nothing, to wit in the dead 
of the night and towards daybreak, had twice 
seen hanging about my carts, in that same town 
of Lancaster where I had been only two nights, 
this same unknown young man.</p>
<p>It put me rather out of sorts. What it meant 
as to particulars I no more foreboded then, than 
you forebode now, but it put me rather out of 
sorts. Howsoever, I made light of it to Pickleson, 
and I took leave of Pickleson advising him 
to spend his legacy in getting up his stamina, 
and to continue to stand by his religion. 
Towards morning I kept a look-out for the strange 
young man, and what was more--I saw the 
strange young man. He was well dressed and 
well looking. He loitered very nigh my carts, 
watching them like as if he was taking care of 
them, and soon after daybreak turned and went 
away. I sent a hail after him, but he never started 
or looked round, or took the smallest notice.</p>
<p>We left Lancaster within an hour or two, on 
our way towards Carlisle. Next morning at 
daybreak, I looked out again for the strange 
young man. I did not see him. But next 
morning I looked out again, and there he was 
once more. I sent another hail after him, but 
as before he gave not the slightest sign of being 
anyways disturbed. This put a thought into 
my head. Acting on it, I watched him in 
different manners and at different times not 
necessary to enter into, till I found that this 
strange young man was deaf and dumb.</p>
<p>The discovery turned me over, because I knew 
that a part of that establishment where she had 
been, was allotted to young men (some of them 
well off), and I thought to myself "If she 
favours him, where am I, and where is all that 
I have worked and planned for?" Hoping--I 
must confess to the selfishness--that she might 
not favour him. I set myself to find out. At last 
I was by accident present at a meeting between 
them in the open air, looking on leaning behind 
a fir-tree without their knowing of it. It was 
a moving meeting for all the three parties concerned. 
I knew every syllable that passed 
between them, as well as they did. I listened 
with my eyes, which had come to be as quick 
and true with deaf and dumb conversation, as 
my ears with the talk of people that can speak. 
He was a going out to China as clerk in 
a merchant's house, which his father had been 
before him. He was in circumstances to keep 
a wife, and he wanted her to marry him and go 
along with him. She persisted, no. He asked 
if she didn't love him? Yes, she loved him 
dearly, dearly, but she could never disappoint 
her beloved good noble generous and I 
don't-know-what-all father (meaning me, the Cheap 
Jack in the sleeved waistcoat), and she would 
stay with him, Heaven bless him, though it was 
to break her heart! Then she cried most bitterly, 
and that made up my mind.</p>
<p>While my mind had been in an unsettled state 
about her favouring this young man, I had felt 
that unreasonable towards Pickleson, that it was 
well for him he had got his legacy down. 
For I often thought "If it hadn't been for this 
same weak-minded giant, I might never have 
come to trouble my head and wex my soul about 
the young man." But, once that I knew she 
loved him--once that I had seen her weep for 
him--it was a different thing. I made it right in 
my mind with Pickleson on the spot, and I shook 
myself together to do what was right by all.</p>
<p>She had left the young man by that time (for 
it took a few minutes to get me thoroughly well 
shook together), and the young man was leaning 
against another of the fir-trees--of which there 
was a cluster--with his face upon his arm. I 
touched him on the back. Looking up and 
seeing me, he says, in our deaf and dumb talk: 
"Do not be angry."</p>
<p>"I am not angry, good boy. I am your friend. 
Come with me."</p>
<p>I left him at the foot of the steps of the 
Library Cart, and I went up alone. She was 
drying her eyes.</p>
<p>"You have been crying, my dear."</p>
<p>"Yes, father."</p>
<p>"Why?"</p>
<p>"A head-ache."</p>
<p>"Not a heart-ache?"</p>
<p>"I said a head-ache, father."</p>
<p>"Doctor Marigold must prescribe for that 
head-ache."</p>
<p>She took up the book of my Prescriptions, 
and held it up with a forced smile; but seeing 
me keep still and look earnest, she softly laid it 
down again, and her eyes were very attentive.</p>
<p>"The Prescription is not there, Sophy."</p>
<p>"Where is it?"</p>
<p>"Here, my dear."</p>
<p>I brought her young husband in, and I put 
her hand in his, and my only further words to 
both of them were these: "Doctor Marigold's 
last prescription. To be taken for life." After 
which I bolted.</p>
<p>When the wedding come off, I mounted a coat 
(blue, and bright buttons), for the first and last 
time in all my days, and I give Sophy away with 
my own hand. There were only us three and the 
gentleman who had had charge of her for those 
two years. I give the wedding dinner of four 
in the Library Cart. Pigeon pie, a leg of pickled 
pork, a pair of fowls, and suitable garden-stuff. 
The best of drinks. I give them a speech, and 
the gentlemen give us a speech, and all our jokes 
told, and the whole went off like a sky-rocket. 
In the course of the entertainment I explained 
to Sophy that I should keep the Library Cart as 
my living-cart when not upon the road, and that 
I should keep all her books for her just as they 
stood, till she come back to claim them. So she 
went to China with her young husband, and it 
was a parting sorrowful and heavy, and I got the 
boy I had another service, and so as of old when 
my child and wife were gone, I went plodding 
along alone, with my whip over my shoulder, at 
the old horse's head.</p>
<p>Sophy wrote me many letters, and I wrote her 
many letters. About the end of the first year 
she sent me one in an unsteady hand: "Dearest 
father, not a week ago I had a darling little 
daughter, but I am so well that they let me write 
these words to you. Dearest and best father, I 
hope my child may not be deaf and dumb, but I 
do not yet know." When I wrote back, I hinted 
the question; but as Sophy never answered that 
question, I felt it to be a sad one, and I never 
repeated it. For a long time our letters were 
regular, but then they got irregular through 
Sophy's husband being moved to another station, 
and through my being always on the move. But 
we were in one another's thoughts, I was equally 
sure, letters or no letters.</p>
<p>Five years, odd months, had gone since Sophy 
went away. I was still the King of the Cheap 
Jacks, and at a greater heighth of popularity 
than ever. I had had a first-rate autumn of it, 
and on the twenty-third of December, one thousand 
eight hundred and sixty-four, I found myself 
at Uxbridge, Middlesex, clean sold out. So 
I jogged up to London with the old horse, light 
and easy, to have my Christmas-Eve and Christmas 
Day alone by the fire in the Library Cart, 
and then to buy a regular new stock of goods 
all round, to sell 'em again and get the money.</p>
<p>I am a neat hand at cookery, and I'll tell you 
what I knocked up for my Christmas-Eve dinner 
in the Library Cart. I knocked up a beefsteak 
pudding for one, with two kidneys, a dozen 
oysters, and a couple of mushrooms, thrown in. 
It's a pudding to put a man in good humour with 
everything, except the two bottom buttons of 
his waistcoat. Having relished that pudding 
and cleared away, I turned the lamp low, and 
sat down by the light of the fire, watching it as 
it shone upon the backs of Sophy's books.</p>
<p>Sophy's books so brought up Sophy's self, that 
I saw her touching face quite plainly, before I 
dropped off dozing by the fire. This may be a 
reason why Sophy, with her deaf and dumb child 
in her arms, seemed to stand silent by me all 
through my nap. I was on the road, off the 
road, in all sorts of places, North and South and 
West and East, Winds liked best and winds 
liked least, Here and there and gone astray, Over 
the hills and far away, and still she stood silent 
by me, with her silent child in her arms. Even 
when I woke with a start, she seemed to vanish, 
as if she had stood by me in that very place 
only a single instant before.</p>
<p>I had started at a real sound, and the sound 
was on the steps of the cart. It was the light 
hurried tread of a child, coming clambering up. 
That tread of a child had once been so familiar 
to me, that for half a moment I believed I was a 
going to see a little ghost.</p>
<p>But the touch of a real child was laid upon 
the outer handle of the door, and the handle 
turned and the door opened a little way, and a 
real child peeped in. A bright little comely 
girl with large dark eyes.</p>
<p>Looking full at me, the tiny creature took off 
her mite of a straw hat, and a quantity of 
dark curls fell all about her face. Then she 
opened her lips, and said in a pretty voice:</p>
<p>"Grandfather!"</p>
<p>"Ah my God!" I cries out. "She can 
speak!"</p>
<p>"Yes, dear grandfather. And I am to ask 
you whether there was ever any one that I 
remind you of?"</p>
<p>In a moment Sophy was round my neck as 
well as the child, and her husband was a wringing 
my hand with his face hid, and we all had to 
shake ourselves together before we could get 
over it. And when we did begin to get over it, 
and I saw the pretty child a talking, pleased and 
quick and eager and busy, to her mother, in the 
signs that I had first taught her mother, the 
happy and yet pitying tears fell rolling down my 
face.</p>
</chapter>
</book>
