<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<book>
<info>
<author>Charles Dickens et al</author>
<title>Mrs. Lirriper's Lodgings</title>
<subtitle>(All The Year Round Christmas Edition)</subtitle>
<date>1863</date>
<option name="part.title_text" value="NONE"/>
<option name="part.number_style" value="I"/>
</info>
 
<prefix>
<info title="MRS. LIRRIPER'S LODGINGS"/>
<centre>THE EXTRA CHRISTMAS NUMBER</centre>
<centre><sc>OF</sc></centre>
<centre>ALL THE YEAR ROUND.</centre>
<centre><sc>CONDUCTED BY</sc></centre>
<centre>CHARLES DICKENS.</centre>
<centre>FOR CHRISTMAS, 1863.</centre>
<hr/>
<centre>Authors:</centre>
<centre>Charles Dickens</centre>
<centre>Elizabeth Gaskell</centre>
<centre>Charles Lever</centre>
<centre>Amelia Edwards</centre>
<centre>Charles Allston Collins</centre>
<centre>Edmund H. Yates</centre>
</prefix>

<part>
<info title="HOW MRS. LIRRIPER CARRIED ON THE BUSINESS."/>
<chapter>
<p>Whoever would begin to be worried with 
letting Lodgings that wasn't a lone woman with 
a living to get is a thing inconceivable to me my 
dear, excuse the familiarity but it comes natural 
to me in my own little room when wishing to 
open my mind to those that I can trust and I 
should be truly thankful if they were all 
mankind but such is not so, for have but a Furnished 
bill in the window and your watch on the 
mantelpiece and farewell to it if you turn your back 
for but a second however gentlemanly the 
manners, nor is being of your own sex any 
safeguard as I have reason in the form of sugar-tongs 
to know, for that lady (and a fine woman 
she was) got me to run for a glass of water on 
the plea of going to be confined, which certainly 
turned out true but it was in the Station-House.</p>
<p>Number Eighty-one Norfolk Street Strand--
situated midway between the City and St. James's 
and within five minutes' walk of the principal 
places of public amusement--is my address. I 
have rented this house many years as the parish 
rate-books will testify and I could wish my 
landlord was as alive to the fact as I am myself, 
but no bless you not a half a pound of paint to 
save his life nor so much my dear as a tile upon 
the roof though on your bended knees.</p>
<p>My dear you never have found Number 
Eighty-one Norfolk Street Strand advertised in 
Bradshaw's Railway Guide and with the blessing 
of Heaven you never will or shall so find it. 
Some there are who do not think it lowering 
themselves to make their names that cheap and 
even going the lengths of a portrait of the house 
not like it with a blot in every window and a coach 
and four at the door, but what will suit Wozenham's 
lower down on the other side of the way 
will not suit me, Miss Wozenham having her 
opinions and me having mine, though when it 
comes to systematic underbidding capable of 
being proved on oath in a court of justice and 
taking the form of "If Mrs. Lirriper names 
eighteen shillings a week, I name fifteen and 
six" it then comes to a settlement between 
yourself and your conscience supposing for the 
sake of argument your name to be Wozenham 
which I am well aware it is not or my opinion 
of you would be greatly lowered, and as to airy 
bedrooms and a night-porter in constant attendance 
the less said the better, the bedrooms 
being stuffy and the porter stuff.</p>
<p>It is forty years ago since me and my poor 
Lirriper got married at St. Clement's Danes 
where I now have a sitting in a very pleasant 
pew with genteel company and my own hassock 
and being partial to evening service not too 
crowded. My poor Lirriper was a handsome 
figure of a man with a beaming eye and a voice 
as mellow as a musical instrument made of 
honey and steel, but he had ever been a free liver 
being in the commercial travelling line and 
travelling what he called a limekiln road--"a dry 
road, Emma my dear," my poor Lirriper says to 
me "where I have to lay the dust with one drink 
or another all day long and half the night, and it 
wears me Emma"--and this led to his running 
through a good deal and might have run through 
the turnpike too when that dreadful horse that 
never would stand still for a single instant set 
off, but for its being night and the gate shut 
and consequently took his wheel my poor 
Lirriper and the gig smashed to atoms and never 
spoke afterwards. He was a handsome figure 
of a man and a man with a jovial heart and a 
sweet temper, but if they had come up then 
they never could have given you the mellowness 
of his voice, and indeed I consider photographs 
wanting in mellowness as a general rule and 
making you look like a new-ploughed field.</p>
<p>My poor Lirriper being behindhand with the 
world and being buried at Hatfield church in 
Hertfordshire, not that it was his native place 
but that he had a liking for the Salisbury Arms 
where we went upon our wedding-day and passed 
as happy a fortnight as ever happy was, I went 
round to the creditors and I says "Gentlemen 
I am acquainted with the fact that I am not 
answerable for my late husband's debts but I 
wish to pay them for I am his lawful wife and 
his good name is dear to me. I am going into 
the Lodgings gentlemen as a business and if I 
prosper every farthing that my late husband 
owed shall be paid for the sake of the love I 
bore him, by this right hand." It took a long 
time to do but it was done, and the silver 
cream-jug which is between ourselves and the 
bed and the mattress in my room up-stairs (or it 
would have found legs so sure as ever the 
Furnished bill was up) being presented by the 
gentlemen engraved "To Mrs. Lirriper a mark of 
grateful respect for her honourable conduct" 
gave me a turn which was too much for my 
feelings, till Mr. Betley which at that time had 
the parlours and loved his joke says "Cheer up 
Mrs. Lirriper, you should feel as if it was only 
your christening and they were your godfathers 
and godmothers which did promise for you." 
And it brought me round, and I don't mind 
confessing to you my dear that I then put a 
sandwich and a drop of sherry in a little basket and 
went down to Hatfield churchyard outside the 
coach and kissed my hand and laid it with a 
kind of a proud and swelling love on my 
husband's grave, though bless you it had taken me 
so long to clear his name that my wedding ring 
was worn quite fine and smooth when I laid it 
on the green green waving grass.</p>
<p>I am an old woman now and my good looks 
are gone but that's me my dear over the plate-warmer 
and considered like in the times when 
you used to pay two guineas on ivory and took 
your chance pretty much how you came out, 
which made you very careful how you left it 
about afterwards because people were turned so 
red and uncomfortable by mostly guessing it 
was somebody else quite different, and there was 
once a certain person that had put his money in 
a hop business that came in one morning to pay 
his rent and his respects being the second floor 
that would have taken it down from its hook 
and put it in his breast pocket--you understand 
my dear--for the L, he says, of the original--
only there was no mellowness in <em>his</em> voice and I 
wouldn't let him, but his opinion of it you may 
gather from his saying to it "Speak to me 
Emma!" which was far from a rational 
observation no doubt but still a tribute to its being 
a likeness, and I think myself it <em>was</em> like me 
when I was young and wore that sort of stays.</p>
<p>But it was about the Lodgings that I was 
intending to hold forth and certainly I ought to 
know something of the business having been in 
it so long, for it was early in the second year of 
my married life that I lost my poor Lirriper and 
I set up at Islington directly afterwards and 
afterwards came here, being two houses and 
eight and thirty years and some losses and a 
deal of experience.</p>
<p>Girls are your first trial after fixtures and 
they try you even worse than what I call the 
Wandering Christians, though why <em>they</em> should 
roam the earth looking for bills and then coming 
in and viewing the apartments and stickling 
about terms and never at all wanting them or 
dreaming of taking them being already provided, 
is a mystery I should be thankful to have 
explained if by any miracle it could be. It's 
wonderful they live so long and thrive so on it but 
I suppose the exercise makes it healthy, knocking 
so much and going from house to house and up 
and down stairs all day, and then their pretending 
to be so particular and punctual is a most 
astonishing thing, looking at their watches and 
saying "Could you give me the refusal of the 
rooms till twenty minutes past eleven the day 
after to-morrow in the forenoon, and supposing 
it to be considered essential by my friend from 
the country could there be a small iron bedstead 
put in the little room upon the stairs?" Why 
when I was new to it my dear I used to 
consider before I promised and to make my mind 
anxious with calculations and to get quite 
wearied out with disappointments, but now I 
says "Certainly by all means" well knowing 
it's a Wandering Christian and I shall hear 
no more about it, indeed by this time I know 
most of the Wandering Christians by sight 
as well as they know me, it being the habit 
of each individual revolving round London in 
that capacity to come back about twice a year, 
and it's very remarkable that it runs in families 
and the children grow up to it, but even were it 
otherwise I should no sooner hear of the friend 
from the country which is a certain sign than I 
should nod and say to myself You're a Wandering 
Christian, though whether they are (as I 
<em>have</em> heard) persons of small property with a 
taste for regular employment and frequent 
change of scene I cannot undertake to tell you.</p>
<p>Girls as I was beginning to remark are one 
of your first and your lasting troubles, being 
like your teeth which begin with convulsions 
and never cease tormenting you from the time 
you cut them till they cut you, and then you 
don't want to part with them which seems hard 
but we must all succumb or buy artificial, and 
even where you get a will nine times out of ten 
you'll get a dirty face with it and naturally 
lodgers do not like good society to be shown in 
with a smear of black across the nose or a 
smudgy eyebrow. Where they pick the black 
up is a mystery I cannot solve, as in the case of 
the willingest girl that ever came into a house 
half starved poor thing, a girl so willing that I 
called her Willing Sophy down upon her knees 
scrubbing early and late and ever cheerful but 
always smiling with a black face. And I says to 
Sophy "Now Sophy my good girl have a regular 
day for your stoves and keep the width of the 
Airy between yourself and the blacking and do 
not brush your hair with the bottoms of the 
saucepans and do not meddle with the snuffs of 
the candles and it stands to reason that it can 
no longer be" yet there it was and always on 
her nose, which turning up and being broad at 
the end seemed to boast of it and caused 
warning from a steady gentleman and excellent 
lodger with breakfast by the week but a little 
irritable and use of a sitting-room when 
required, his words being "Mrs. Lirriper I have 
arrived at the point of admitting that the Black 
is a man and a brother, but only in a natural 
form and when it can't be got off." Well 
consequently I put poor Sophy on to other work 
and forbid her answering the door or answering 
a bell on any account but she was so unfortunately 
willing that nothing would stop her flying 
up the kitchen stairs whenever a bell was 
heard to tingle. I put it to her "Oh Sophy Sophy 
for goodness goodness sake where does it come 
from?" To which that poor unlucky willing 
mortal bursting out crying to see me so vexed 
replied "I took a deal of black into me ma'am 
when I was a small child being much neglected 
and I think it must be, that it works out," so 
it continuing to work out of that poor thing 
and not having another fault to find with her I 
says Sophy "what do you seriously think of my 
helping you away to New South Wales where 
it might not be noticed?" Nor did I ever 
repent the money which was well spent, for she 
married the ship's cook on the voyage (himself 
a Mulotter) and did well and lived happy, and 
so far as ever I heard it was <em>not</em> noticed in a 
new state of society to her dying day.</p>
<p>In what way Miss Wozenham lower down on 
the other side of the way reconciled it to her 
feelings as a lady (which she is not) to entice 
Mary Anne Perkinsop from my service is best 
known to herself, I do not know and I do not 
wish to know how opinions are formed at 
Wozenham's on any point. But Mary Anne 
Perkinsop although I behaved handsomely to her 
and she behaved unhandsomely to me was worth 
her weight in gold as overawing lodgers without 
driving them away, for lodgers would be far 
more sparing of their bells with Mary Anne 
than I ever knew them be with Maid or 
Mistress, which is a great triumph especially when 
accompanied with a cast in the eye and a bag of 
bones, but it was the steadiness of her way with 
them through her father's having failed in Pork. 
It was Mary Anne's looking so respectable in 
her person and being so strict in her spirits that 
conquered the tea-and-sugarest gentleman (for 
he weighed them both in a pair of scales every 
morning) that I have ever had to deal with and 
no lamb grew meeker, still it afterwards came 
round to me that Miss Wozenham happening 
to pass and seeing Mary Anne take in the milk 
of a milkman that made free in a rosy-faced way 
(I think no worse of him) with every girl in the 
street but was quite frozen up like the statue 
at Charing Cross by her, saw Mary Anne's value 
in the lodging business and went as high as one 
pound per quarter more, consequently Mary 
Anne with not a word betwixt us says "If you 
will provide yourself Mrs. Lirriper in a month 
from this day <em>I</em> have already done the same," 
which hurt me and I said so, and she then hurt 
me more by insinuating that her father having 
failed in Pork had laid her open to it.</p>
<p>My dear I do assure you it's a harassing thing 
to know what kind of girls to give the 
preference to, for if they are lively they get bell'd 
off their legs and if they are sluggish you suffer 
from it yourself in complaints and if they are 
sparkling-eyed they get made love to and if they 
are smart in their persons they try on your 
Lodger's bonnets and if they are musical I defy 
you to keep them away from bands and organs, 
and allowing for any difference you like in their 
heads their heads will be always out of window 
just the same. And then what the gentlemen 
like in girls the ladies don't, which is fruitful 
hot water for all parties, and then there's temper 
though such a temper as Caroline Maxey's I 
hope not often. A good-looking black-eyed girl 
was Caroline and a comely-made girl to your cost 
when she did break out and laid about her, as 
took place first and last through a new-married 
couple come to see London in the first floor and 
the lady very high and it was supposed not liking 
the good looks of Caroline having none of her 
own to spare, but anyhow she did try Caroline 
though that was no excuse. So one afternoon 
Caroline comes down into the kitchen flushed 
and flashing, and she says to me "Mrs. Lirriper 
that woman in the first has aggravated me past 
bearing," I says "Caroline keep your temper," 
Caroline says with a curdling laugh" Keep my 
temper? You're right Mrs. Lirriper, so I will. 
Capital D her!" bursts out Caroline (you might 
have struck me into the centre of the earth with 
a feather when she said it) "I'll give her a touch 
of the temper that <em>I</em> keep!" Caroline downs with 
her hair my dear, screeches and rushes 
upstairs, I following as fast as my trembling legs 
could bear me, but before I got into the room the 
dinner cloth and pink and white service all 
dragged off upon the floor with a crash and the 
new married couple on their backs in the fire- 
grate, him with the shovel and tongs and a dish 
of cucumber across him and a mercy it was 
summer-time. "Caroline" I says "be calm," 
but she catches off my cap and tears it in her 
teeth as she passes me, then pounces on the 
new married lady makes her a bundle of ribbons 
takes her by the two ears and knocks the back 
of her head upon the carpet Murder screaming 
all the time Policemen running down the street 
and Wozenham's windows (judge of my feelings 
when I came to know it) thrown up and 
Miss Wozenham calling out from the balcony 
with crocodile's tears "It's Mrs. Lirriper been 
overcharging somebody to madness--she'll be 
murdered--I always thought so--Pleeseman 
save her!" My dear four of them and Caroline 
behind the chiffoniere attacking with the poker 
and when disarmed prize fighting with her 
double fists, and down and up and up and down 
and dreadful! But I couldn't bear to see the poor 
young creature roughly handled and her 
hair torn when they got the better of her, and 
I says "Gentlemen Policemen pray remember 
that her sex is the sex of your mothers and 
sisters and your sweethearts, and God bless 
them and you!" And there she was sitting down on 
the ground handcuffed, taking breath against the 
skirting-board and them cool with their coats in 
strips, and all she says was "Mrs. Lirriper I am 
sorry as ever I touched <em>you</em>, for you're a kind 
motherly old thing," and it made me think that 
I had often wished I had been a mother indeed 
and how would my heart have felt if I had been 
the mother of that girl! Well you know it 
turned out at the Police-office that she had done 
it before, and she had her clothes away and was 
sent to prison, and when she was to come out I 
trotted off to the gate in the evening with just 
a morsel of jelly in that little basket of mine to 
give her a mite of strength to face the world 
again, and there I met with a very decent mother 
waiting for her son through bad company and a 
stubborn one he was with his half boots not 
laced. So out came Caroline and I says "Caroline 
come along with me and sit down under the 
wall where it's retired and eat a little trifle that 
I have brought with me to do you good" and 
she throws her arms round my neck and says 
sobbing "O why were you never a mother when 
there are such mothers as there are!" she says, 
and in half a minute more she begins to laugh 
and says "Did I really tear your cap to shreds?" 
and when I told her "You certainly did so Caroline" 
she laughed again and said while she patted 
my face "Then why do you wear such queer old 
caps you dear old thing? If you hadn't worn 
such queer old caps I don't think I should have 
done it even then." Fancy the girl! Nothing 
could get out of her what she was going to do 
except O she would do well enough, and we 
parted she being very thankful and kissing my 
hands, and I never more saw or heard of that girl, 
except that I shall always believe that a very 
genteel cap which was brought anonymous to 
me one Saturday night in an oilskin basket by 
a most impertinent young sparrow of a monkey 
whistling with dirty shoes on the clean steps and 
playing the harp on the Airy railings with a 
hoop-stick came from Caroline.</p>
<p>What you lay yourself open to my dear in the 
way of being the object of uncharitable suspicions 
when you go into the Lodging business I 
have not the words to tell you, but never was I 
so dishonourable as to have two keys nor would 
I willingly think it even of Miss Wozenham 
lower down on the other side of the way 
sincerely hoping that it may not be, though 
doubtless at the same time money cannot 
come from nowhere and it is not reason to 
suppose that Bradshaws put it in for love be it 
blotty as it may. It <em>is</em> a hardship hurting to 
the feelings that Lodgers open their minds so 
wide to the idea that you are trying to get the 
better of them and shut their minds so close to 
the idea that they are trying to get the better 
of you, but as Major Jackman says to me "I 
know the ways of this circular world Mrs. Lirriper, 
and that's one of 'em all round it" and many 
is the little ruffle in my mind that the Major 
has smoothed, for he is a clever man who has 
seen much. Dear dear, thirteen years have 
passed though it seems but yesterday since I was 
sitting with my glasses on at the open front 
parlour window one evening in August (the parlours 
being then vacant) reading yesterday's paper 
my eyes for print being poor though still I am 
thankful to say a long sight at a distance, when 
I hear a gentleman come posting across the road 
and up the street in a dreadful rage talking to 
himself in a fury and d'ing and c'ing somebody. 
"By George!" says he out loud and clutching 
his walking-stick, "I'll go to Mrs. Lirriper's. 
Which is Mrs. Lirriper's?" Then looking round 
and seeing me he flourishes his hat right off his 
head as if I had been the queen and he says 
"Excuse the intrusion Madam, but pray Madam 
can you tell me at what number in this street 
there resides a well-known and much-respected 
lady by the name of Lirriper?" A little 
flustered though I must say gratified I took off my 
glasses and curtseyed and said "Sir, Mrs. Lirriper 
is your humble servant." "As-tonishing!" 
says he. "A million pardons! Madam, may I 
ask you to have the kindness to direct one of 
your domestics to open the door to a gentleman 
in search of apartments, by the name of Jackman?" 
I had never heard the name but a 
politer gentleman I never hope to see, for says 
he "Madam I am shocked at your opening the 
door yourself to no worthier a fellow than Jemmy 
Jackman. After you Madam. I never precede 
a lady." Then he comes into the parlours and 
he sniffs and he says "Hah! These are 
parlours! Not musty cupboards" he says "but 
parlours, and no smell of coal-sacks." Now my 
dear it having been remarked by some inimical 
to the whole neighbourhood that it always smells 
of coal-sacks which might prove a drawback to 
Lodgers if encouraged, I says to the Major 
gently though firmly that I think he is referring 
to Arundel or Surrey or Howard but not 
Norfolk. "Madam" says he "I refer to Wozenham's 
lower down over the way--Madam you 
can form no notion what Wozenham's is--
Madam it is a vast coal-sack, and Miss Wozenham 
has the principles and manners of a female 
heaver--Madam from the manner in which I 
have heard her mention you I know she has no 
appreciation of a lady, and from the manner in 
which she has conducted herself towards me I 
know she has no appreciation of a gentleman--
Madam my name is Jackman--should you 
require any other reference than what I have 
already said, I name the Bank of England--
perhaps you know it!" Such was the beginning 
of the Major's occupying the parlours and from 
that hour to this the same and a most obliging 
Lodger and punctual in all respects except one 
irregular which I need not particularly specify, 
but made up for by his being a protection and 
at all times ready to fill in the papers of the 
Assessed Taxes and Juries and that, and once 
collared a young man with the drawing-room 
clock under his cloak, and once on the parapets 
with his own hands and blankets put out the 
kitchen chimney and afterwards attending the 
summons made a most eloquent speech against 
the Parish before the magistrates and saved the 
engine, and ever quite the gentleman though 
passionate. And certainly Miss Wozenham's 
detaining the trunks and umbrella was not in a 
liberal spirit though it may have been according 
to her rights in law or an act <em>I</em> would myself 
have stooped to, the Major being so much the 
gentleman that though he is far from tall he 
seems almost so when he has his shirt frill out 
and his frock-coat on and his hat with the curly 
brims, and in what service he was I cannot truly 
tell you my dear whether Militia or Foreign, for 
I never heard him even name himself as Major 
but always simple "Jemmy Jackman" and once 
soon after he came when I felt it my duty to let 
him know that Miss Wozenham had put it about 
that he was no Major and I took the liberty of 
adding "which you are sir" his words were 
"Madam at any rate I am not a Minor, and 
sufficient for the day is the evil thereof" which 
cannot be denied to be the sacred truth, nor yet 
his military ways of having his boots with only 
the dirt brushed off taken to him in the front 
parlour every morning on a clean plate and 
varnishing them himself with a little sponge and a 
saucer and a whistle in a whisper so sure as ever 
his breakfast is ended, and so neat his ways that 
it never soils his linen which is scrupulous though 
more in quality than quantity, neither that nor his 
moustachios which to the best of my belief are 
done at the same time and which are as black 
and shining as his boots, his head of hair being 
a lovely white.</p>
<p>It was the third year nearly up of the Major's 
being in the parlours that early one morning in 
the month of February when Parliament was 
coming on and you may therefore suppose a 
number of impostors were about ready to take 
hold of anything they could get, a gentleman 
and lady from the country came in to view the 
Second, and I well remember that I had been 
looking out of window and had watched them 
and the heavy sleet driving down the street 
together looking for bills. I did not quite take 
to the face of the gentleman though he was 
good-looking too but the lady was a very pretty 
young thing and delicate, and it seemed too 
rough for her to be out at all though she had 
only come from the Adelphi Hotel which would 
not have been much above a quarter of a mile 
if the weather had been less severe. Now it 
did so happen my dear that I had been forced 
to put five shillings weekly additional on the 
second in consequence of a loss from running 
away full-dressed as if going out to a dinner-party, 
which was very artful and had made me 
rather suspicious taking it along with Parliament, 
so when the gentleman proposed three 
months certain and the money in advance and 
leave then reserved to renew on the same 
terms for six months more, I says I was not 
quite certain but that I might have engaged 
myself to another party but would step down 
stairs and look into it if they would take a seat. 
They took a seat and I went down to the 
handle of the Major's door that I had already 
began to consult finding it a great blessing, and 
I knew by his whistling in a whisper that he 
was varnishing his boots which was generally 
considered private, however he kindly calls out 
"If it's you, Madam, come in," and I went in 
and told him.</p>
<p>"Well, Madam," says the Major rubbing 
his nose--as I did fear at the moment with 
the black sponge but it was only his knuckle, he 
being always neat and dexterous with his 
fingers--"well, Madam, I suppose you would be 
glad of the money?"</p>
<p>I was delicate of saying "Yes" too out, for a 
little extra colour rose into the Major's cheeks 
and there was irregularity which I will not 
particularly specify in a quarter which I will not 
name.</p>
<p>"I am of opinion, Madam," says the Major 
"that when money is ready for you--when it is 
ready for you Mrs. Lirriper--you ought to take 
it. What is there against it, Madam, in this case 
up-stairs?"</p>
<p>"I really cannot say there is anything against 
it sir, still I thought I would consult you."</p>
<p>"You said a newly-married couple, I think, 
Madam?" says the Major.</p>
<p>I says "Ye-es. Evidently. And indeed the 
young lady mentioned to me in a casual way 
that she had not been married many months."</p>
<p>The Major rubbed his nose again and stirred 
the varnish round and round in its little saucer 
with his piece of sponge and took to his whistling 
in a whisper for a few moments. Then he 
says "You would call it a Good Let, Madam?"</p>
<p>"Oh certainly a Good Let sir."</p>
<p>"Say they renew for the additional six 
months. Would it put you about very much 
Madam if--if the worst was to come to the 
worst?" said the Major.</p>
<p>"Well I hardly know," I says to the Major. 
"It depends upon circumstances. Would you 
object Sir for instance?"</p>
<p>"I?" says the Major. "Object? Jemmy 
Jackman? Mrs. Lirriper close with the 
proposal."</p>
<p>So I went up-stairs and accepted, and they 
came in next day which was Saturday and 
the Major was so good as to draw up a 
Memorandum of an agreement in a beautiful round 
hand and expressions that sounded to me 
equally legal and military, and Mr. Edson 
signed it on the Monday morning and the Major 
called upon Mr. Edson on the Tuesday and Mr. 
Edson called upon the Major on the Wednesday 
and the Second and the parlours were as friendly 
as could be wished.</p>
<p>The three months paid for had run out and we 
had got without any fresh overtures as to 
payment into May my dear, when there came an 
obligation upon Mr. Edson to go a business 
expedition right across the Isle of Man, which fell 
quite unexpected on that pretty little thing and 
is not a place that according to my views is 
particularly in the way to anywhere at any 
time but that may be a matter of opinion. So 
short a notice was it that he was to go next 
day, and dreadfully she cried poor pretty and 
I am sure I cried too when I saw her on 
the cold pavement in the sharp east wind--it 
being a very backward spring that year taking 
a last leave of him with her pretty bright hair 
blowing this way and that and her arms clinging 
round his neck and him saying "There there 
there! Now let me go Peggy." And by that 
time it was plain that what the Major had been 
so accommodating as to say he would not object 
to happening in the house, would happen in it, 
and I told her as much when he was gone 
while I comforted her with my arm up the 
staircase, for I says "You will soon have others 
to keep up for my pretty and you must think of 
that."</p>
<p>His letter never came when it ought to have 
come and what she went through morning after 
morning when the postman brought none for 
her the very postman himself compassionated 
when she ran down to the door, and yet we 
cannot wonder at its being calculated to blunt 
the feelings to have all the trouble of other 
people's letters and none of the pleasure and 
doing it oftener in the mud and mizzle than not 
and at a rate of wages more resembling Little 
Britain than Great. But at last one morning 
when she was too poorly to come running down 
stairs he says to me with a pleased look in his 
face that made me next to love the man in his 
uniform coat though he was dripping wet "I have 
taken you first in the street this morning Mrs. 
Lirriper, for here's the one for Mrs. Edson." I 
went up to her bedroom with it fast as ever I 
could go, and she sat up in bed when she saw 
it and kissed it and tore it open and then a 
blank stare came upon her. "It's very short!" 
she says lifting her large eyes to my face. "O 
Mrs. Lirriper it's very short!" I says "My dear 
Mrs. Edson no doubt that's because your 
husband hadn't time to write more just at that 
time." "No doubt, no doubt," says she, and 
puts her two hands on her face and turns round 
in her bed.</p>
<p>I shut her softly in and I crept down stairs 
and I tapped at the Major's door, and when the 
Major having his thin slices of bacon in his 
own Dutch oven saw me he came out of his 
chair and put me down on the sofa. "Hush!" 
says he, "I see something's the matter. Don't 
speak--take time." I says "O Major I am 
afraid there's cruel work up-stairs." "Yes 
yes" says he "I had begun to be afraid of it--
take time." And then in opposition to his own 
words he rages out frightfully, and says "I 
shall never forgive myself Madam, that I, 
Jemmy Jackman, didn't see it all that morning 
--didn't go straight up-stairs when my boot- 
sponge was in my hand--didn't force it down 
his throat--and choke him dead with it on the 
spot!"</p>
<p>The Major and me agreed when we came to 
ourselves that just at present we could do no more 
than take on to suspect nothing and use our 
best endeavours to keep that poor young creature 
quiet, and what I ever should have done 
without the Major when it got about among the 
organ-men that quiet was our object is 
unknown, for he made lion and tiger war upon 
them to that degree that without seeing it I 
could not have believed it was in any gentleman 
to have such a power of bursting out with fire-irons 
walking-sticks water-jugs coals potatoes 
off his table the very hat off his head, and at 
the same time so furious in foreign languages 
that they would stand with their handles half 
turned fixed like the Sleeping Ugly--for I 
cannot say Beauty.</p>
<p>Ever to see the postman come near the house 
now gave me such a fear that it was a reprieve 
when he went by, but in about another ten days 
or a fortnight he says again "Here's one for 
Mrs. Edson.--Is she pretty well?" "She is 
pretty well postman, but not well enough to 
rise so early as she used" which was so far 
gospel-truth.</p>
<p>I carried the letter in to the Major at his 
breakfast and I says tottering "Major I have 
not the courage to take it up to her."</p>
<p>"It's an ill-looking villain of a letter," says 
the Major.</p>
<p>"I have not the courage Major" I says again 
in a tremble "to take it up to her."</p>
<p>After seeming lost in consideration for some 
moments the Major says, raising his head as if 
something new and useful had occurred to his 
mind "Mrs. Lirriper, I shall never forgive 
myself that I, Jemmy Jackman, didn't go straight 
up-stairs that morning when my boot-sponge 
was in my hand--and force it down his throat--
and choke him dead with it."</p>
<p>"Major" I says a little hasty "you didn't 
do it which is a Blessing, for it would have done 
no good and I think your sponge was better 
employed on your own honourable boots."</p>
<p>So we got to be rational, and planned that I 
should tap at her bedroom door and lay the 
letter on the mat outside and wait on the upper 
landing for what might happen, and never was 
gunpowder cannon-balls or shells or rockets 
more dreaded than that dreadful letter was by 
me as I took it to the second floor.</p>
<p>A terrible loud scream sounded through the 
house the minute after she had opened it, and 
I found her on the floor lying as if her life was 
gone. My dear I never looked at the face of 
the letter which was lying open by her, for there 
was no occasion.</p>
<p>Everything I needed to bring her round the 
Major brought up with his own hands, besides 
running out to the chemist's for what was not 
in the house and likewise having the fiercest of 
all his many skirmishes with a musical instrument 
representing a ball-room I do not know in 
what particular country and company waltzing in 
and out at folding-doors with rolling eyes. When 
after a long time I saw her coming to, I slipped 
on the landing till I heard her cry, and then I 
went in and says cheerily "Mrs. Edson you're 
not well my dear and it's not to be wondered 
at," as if I had not been in before. Whether 
she believed or disbelieved I cannot say and it 
would signify nothing if I could, but I stayed 
by her for hours and then she God ever blesses 
me! and says she will try to rest for her head is 
bad.</p>
<p>"Major," I whispers, looking in at the 
parlours, "I beg and pray of you don't go out."</p>
<p>The Major whispers "Madam, trust me I will 
do no such a thing. How is she?"</p>
<p>I says "Major the good Lord above us only 
knows what burns and rages in her poor mind. 
I left her sitting at her window. I am going 
to sit at mine."</p>
<p>It came on afternoon and it came on evening. 
Norfolk is a delightful street to lodge in--
provided you don't go lower down--but of a 
summer evening when the dust and waste paper lie 
in it and stray children play in it and a kind of 
a gritty calm and bake settles on it and a peal 
of church-bells is practising in the neighbourhood 
it is a trifle dull, and never have I seen it 
since at such a time and never shall I see 
it evermore at such a time without seeing 
the dull June evening when that forlorn young 
creature sat at her open corner window on the 
second and me at my open corner window 
(the other corner) on the third. Something 
merciful, something wiser and better far than 
my own self, had moved me while it was yet 
light to sit in my bonnet and shawl, and as 
the shadows fell and the tide rose I could 
sometimes--when I put out my head and looked 
at her window below--see that she leaned 
out a little looking down the street. It 
was just settling dark when I saw <em>her</em> in the 
street.</p>
<p>So fearful of losing sight of her that it almost 
stops my breath while I tell it, I went down 
stairs faster than I ever moved in all my life 
and only tapped with my hand at the Major's 
door in passing it and slipping out. She was gone 
already. I made the same speed down the street 
and when I came to the corner of Howard 
Street I saw that she had turned it and was 
there plain before me going towards the west. 
O with what a thankful heart I saw her going 
along!</p>
<p>She was quite unacquainted with London and 
had very seldom been out for more than an 
airing in our own street where she knew two or 
three little children belonging to neighbours 
and had sometimes stood among them at the 
end of the street looking at the water. She 
must be going at hazard I knew, still she kept 
the by-streets quite correctly as long as they 
would serve her, and then turned up into the 
Strand. But at every corner I could see her head 
turned one way, and that way was always the 
river way.</p>
<p>It may have been only the darkness and quiet 
of the Adelphi that caused her to strike into it 
but she struck into it much as readily as if 
she had set out to go there, which perhaps 
was the case. She went straight down to the 
Terrace and along it and looked over the iron 
rail, and I often woke afterwards in my own 
bed with the horror of seeing her doing it. 
The desertion of the wharf below and the 
flowing of the high water there seemed to 
settle her purpose. She looked about as if to 
make out the way down, and she struck out 
the right way or the wrong way--I don't 
know which, for I don't know the place 
before or since--and I followed her the way she 
went.</p>
<p>It was noticeable that all this time she never 
once looked back. But there was now a great 
change in the manner of her going, and instead 
of going at a steady quick walk with her arms 
folded before her,--among the dark dismal 
arches she went in a wild way with her arms 
opened wide, as if they were wings and she was 
flying to her death.</p>
<p>We were on the wharf and she stopped. I 
stopped. I saw her hands at her bonnet-strings, 
and I rushed between her and the brink and 
took her round the waist with both my arms. 
She might have drowned me, I felt then, but 
she could never have got quit of me.</p>
<p>Down to that moment my mind had been all 
in a maze and not half an idea had I had in it 
what I should say to her, but the instant I 
touched her it came to me like magic and I had 
my natural voice and my senses and even almost 
my breath.</p>
<p>"Mrs. Edson!" I says "My dear! Take care. 
How ever did you lose your way and stumble 
on a dangerous place like this? Why you 
must have come here by the most perplexing 
streets in all London. No wonder you are lost, 
I am sure. And this place too! Why I thought 
nobody ever got here, except me to order my 
coals and the Major in the parlours to smoke his 
cigar!"--for I saw that blessed man close by, 
pretending to it.</p>
<p>"Hah--Hah--Hum!" coughs the Major.</p>
<p>"And good gracious me" I says, "why here 
he is!"</p>
<p>"Halloa! who goes there!" says the Major 
in a military manner.</p>
<p>"Well!" I says, "if this don't beat everything! 
Don't yon know us Major Jackman?"</p>
<p>"Halloa!" says the Major. "Who calls on 
Jemmy Jackman?" (and more out of breath he 
was, and did it less like life, than I should have 
expected).</p>
<p>"Why here's Mrs. Edson Major" I says, 
"strolling out to cool her poor head which has 
been very bad, has missed her way and got lost, 
and Goodness knows where she might have got 
to but for me coming here to drop an order 
into my coal merchant's letter-box and you 
coming here to smoke your cigar!--And you 
really are not well enough my dear" I says to 
her "to be half so far from home without me. 
--And your arm will be very acceptable I am 
sure Major" I says to him "and I know she 
may lean upon it as heavy as she likes." And 
now we had both got her--thanks be Above!--
one on each side.</p>
<p>She was all in a cold shiver and she so 
continued till I laid her on her own bed, and up to 
the early morning she held me by the hand and 
moaned and moaned "O wicked, wicked, wicked!" 
But when at last I made believe to droop my 
head and be overpowered with a dead sleep, I 
heard that poor young creature give such 
touching and such humble thanks for being 
preserved from taking her own life in her 
madness that I thought I should have cried 
my eyes out on the counterpane and I knew 
she was safe.</p>
<p>Being well enough to do and able to afford 
it, me and the Major laid our little plans 
next day while she was asleep worn out, 
and so I says to her as soon as I could do it 
nicely:</p>
<p>"Mrs. Edson my dear, when Mr. Edson paid 
me the rent for these further six months--"</p>
<p>She gave a start and I felt her large eyes look 
at me, but I went on with it and with my needle-work.</p>
<p>"--I can't say that I am quite sure I 
dated the receipt right. Could you let me look 
at it?"</p>
<p>She laid her frozen cold hand upon mine 
and she looked through me when I was forced 
to look up from my needlework, but I had 
taken the precaution of having on my 
spectacles.</p>
<p>"I have no receipt" says she.</p>
<p>"Ah! Then he has got it" I says in a careless 
way. "It's of no great consequence. A 
receipt's a receipt."</p>
<p>From that time she always had hold of my 
hand when I could spare it which was generally 
only when I read to her, for of course she and 
me had our bits of needlework to plod at and 
neither of us was very handy at those little 
things, though I am still rather proud of my 
share in them too considering. And though she 
took to all I read to her, I used to fancy that 
next to what was taught upon the Mount she 
took most of all to His gentle compassion for 
us poor women and to His young life and to how 
His mother was proud of him and treasured His 
sayings in her heart. She had a grateful look 
in her eyes that never never never will be out of 
mine until they are closed in my last sleep, and 
when I chanced to look at her without thinking 
of it I would always meet that look, and she 
would often offer me her trembling lip to kiss, 
much more like a little affectionate half-broken- 
hearted child than ever I can imagine any grown 
person.</p>
<p>One time the trembling of this poor lip 
was so strong and her tears ran down so fast 
that I thought she was going to tell me all 
her woe, so I takes her two hands in mine and 
I says:</p>
<p>"No my dear not now, you had best not try 
to do it now. Wait for better times when you 
have got over this and are strong, and then you 
shall tell me whatever you will. Shall it be 
agreed?"</p>
<p>With our hands still joined she nodded her 
head many times, and she lifted my hands and 
put them to her lips and to her bosom.</p>
<p>"Only one word now my dear" I says. "Is 
there any one?"</p>
<p>She looked inquiringly "Any one?"</p>
<p>"That I can go to?"</p>
<p>She shook her head.</p>
<p>"No one that I can bring?"</p>
<p>She shook her head.</p>
<p>"No one is wanted by <em>me</em> my dear. Now 
that may be considered past and gone."</p>
<p>Not much more than a week afterwards--for 
this was far on in the time of our being so 
together--I was bending over at her bedside 
with my ear down to her lips, by turns listening 
for her breath and looking for a sign of life in 
her face. At last it came in a solemn way--not 
in a flash but like a kind of pale faint light 
brought very slow to the face.</p>
<p>She said something to me that had no sound 
in it, but I saw she asked me:</p>
<p>"Is this death?"</p>
<p>And I says "Poor dear poor dear, I think 
it is."</p>
<p>Knowing somehow that she wanted me to 
move her weak right hand, I took it and laid it 
on her breast and then folded her other hand 
upon it, and she prayed a good good prayer 
and I joined in it poor me though there 
were no words spoke. Then I brought the 
baby in its wrappers from where it lay, and I 
says:</p>
<p>"My dear this is sent to a childless old 
woman. This is for me to take care of."</p>
<p>The trembling lip was put up towards my 
face for the last time, and I dearly kissed it.</p>
<p>"Yes my dear" I says. "Please God! Me 
and the Major."</p>
<p>I don't know how to tell it right, but I saw 
her soul brighten and leap up, and get free and 
fly away in the grateful look</p>
<section>* * * * *</section>
<p>So this is the why and wherefore of its coming 
to pass my dear that we called him Jemmy, 
being after the Major his own godfather with 
Lirriper for a surname being after myself, and 
never was a dear child such a brightening thing 
in a Lodgings or such a playmate to his 
grandmother as Jemmy to this house and me, and 
always good and minding what he was told (upon 
the whole) and soothing for the temper and 
making everything pleasanter except when he 
grew old enough to drop his cap down Wozenham's 
Airy and they wouldn't hand it up to him, 
and being worked into a state I put on my 
best bonnet and gloves and parasol with the 
child in my hand and I says "Miss Wozenham 
I little thought ever to have entered <em>your</em> house 
but unless my grandson's cap is instantly 
restored, the laws of this country regulating the 
property of the Subject shall at length decide 
betwixt yourself and me, cost what it may." With a 
sneer upon her face which did strike me I must 
say as being expressive of two keys but it may 
have been a mistake and if there is any doubt 
let Miss Wozenham have the full benefit of it as 
is but right, she rang the bell and she says 
"Jane, is there a street-child's old cap down our 
Airy?" I says "Miss Wozenham before your 
housemaid answers that question you must allow 
me to inform you to your face that my grandson 
is not a street-child and is <em>not</em> in the habit 
of wearing old caps. In fact" I says "Miss 
Wozenham I am far from sure that my grandson's 
cap may not be newer than your own" 
which was perfectly savage in me, her lace being 
the commonest machine-make washed and torn 
besides, but I had been put into a state to begin 
with fomented by impertinence. Miss Wozenham 
says red in the face "Jane you heard my 
question, is there any child's cap down our 
Airy?" "Yes Ma'am'" says Jane "I think I 
did see some such rubbish a lying there." 
"Then" says Miss Wozenham "let these 
visitors out, and then throw up that worthless 
article out of my premises." But here the child 
who had been staring at Miss Wozenham with 
all his eyes and more, frowns down his little 
eyebrows purses up his little mouth puts his 
chubby legs far apart turns his little dimpled 
fists round and round slowly over one another 
like a little coffee-mill, and says to her "Oo 
impdent to mi Gran, me tut oor hi!" "Oh!" 
says Miss Wozenham looking down scornfully 
at the Mite "this is not a street-child 
is it not! Really!" I bursts out laughing 
and I says "Miss Wozenham if this an't a 
pretty sight to you I don't envy your feelings 
and I wish you good day. Jemmy come along 
with Gran." And I was still in the best of 
humours though his cap came flying up into the 
street as if it had been just turned on out of the 
water-plug, and I went home laughing all the 
way, all owing to that dear boy.</p>
<p>The miles and miles that me and the Major 
have travelled with Jemmy in the dusk between 
the lights are not to be calculated, Jemmy 
driving on the coach-box which is the Major's 
brass-bound writing-desk on the table, me inside 
in the easy-chair and the Major Guard up behind 
with a brown-paper horn doing it really 
wonderful. I do assure you my dear that sometimes 
when I have taken a few winks in my place 
inside the coach and have come half awake by 
the flashing light of the fire and have heard 
that precious pet driving and the Major blowing 
up behind to have the change of horses 
ready when we got to the Inn, I have half 
believed we were on the old North Road that 
my poor Lirriper knew so well. Then to see 
that child and the Major both wrapped up 
getting down to warm their feet and going 
stamping about and having glasses of ale out of 
the paper match-boxes on the chimney-piece is 
to see the Major enjoying it fully as much as 
the child I am very sure, and it's equal to any 
play when Coachee opens the coach-door to 
look in at me inside and say "Wery 'past that 
'tage. 'Prightened old lady?"</p>
<p>But what my inexpressible feelings were when 
we lost that child can only be compared to the 
Major's which were not a shade better, through 
his straying out at five years old and eleven 
o'clock in the forenoon and never heard of by 
word or sign or deed till half-past nine at night, 
when the Major had gone to the Editor of the 
Times newspaper to put in an advertisement, 
which came out next day four and twenty hours 
after he was found, and which I mean always 
carefully to keep in my lavender drawer as the first 
printed account of him. The more the day got 
on, the more I got distracted and the Major too 
and both of us made worse by the composed ways 
of the police though very civil and obliging 
and what I must call their obstinacy in not 
entertaining the idea that he was stolen. "We 
mostly find Mum" says the sergeant who came 
round to comfort me, which he didn't at all and 
he had been one of the private constables in 
Caroline's time to which he referred in his 
opening words when he said "Don't give way 
to uneasiness in your mind Mum, it'll all come 
as right as my nose did when I got the same 
barked by that young woman in your second 
floor"--says this sergeant "we mostly find 
Mum as people ain't over anxious to have what 
I may call second-hand children. You'll get 
him back Mum." "O but my dear good sir" 
I says clasping my hands and wringing them 
and clasping them again "he is such an 
uncommon child!" "Yes Mum" says the 
sergeant, "we mostly find that too Mum. The 
question is what his clothes were worth." 
"His clothes" I says "were not worth much 
sir for he had only got his playing-dress on, 
but the dear child!--" "All right Mum" 
says the sergeant. "<em>You'll</em> get him back, Mum. 
And even if he'd had his best clothes on, it 
wouldn't come to worse than his being found 
wrapped up in a cabbage-leaf, a shivering in a 
lane." His words pierced my heart like 
daggers and daggers, and me and the Major 
ran in and out like wild things all day long till 
the Major returning from his interview with the 
Editor of the Times at night rushes into my 
little room hysterical and squeezes my hand and 
wipes his eyes and says "Joy joy--officer in plain 
clothes came up on the steps as I was letting 
myself in--compose your feelings--Jemmy's 
found." Consequently I fainted away and 
when I came to, embraced the legs of the officer 
in plain clothes who seemed to be taking a kind 
of a quiet inventory in his mind of the property 
in my little room with brown whiskers, and I 
says "Blessings on you sir where is the 
Darling!" and he says "In Kennington Station 
House." I was dropping at his feet Stone at the 
image of that Innocence in cells with murderers 
when he adds "He followed the Monkey." I 
says deeming it slang language "Oh sir explain 
for a loving grandmother what Monkey!" He 
says "him in the spangled cap with the strap 
under the chin, as won't keep on--him as sweeps 
the crossings on a round table and don't want to 
draw his sabre more than he can help." Then I 
understood it all and most thankfully thanked 
him, and me and the Major and him drove over 
to Kennington and there we found our boy 
lying quite comfortable before a blazing fire 
having sweetly played himself to sleep upon 
a small accordion nothing like so big as 
a flat iron which they had been so kind as 
to lend him for the purpose and which it 
appeared had been stopped upon a very young 
person.</p>
<p>My dear the system upon which the Major 
commenced and as I may say perfected Jemmy's 
learning when he was so small that if the 
dear was on the other side of the table you 
had to look under it instead of over it to 
see him with his mother's own bright hair 
in beautiful curls, is a thing that ought to be 
known to the Throne and Lords and Commons 
and then might obtain some promotion for the 
Major which he well deserves and would be 
none the worse for (speaking between friends) 
L. S. D.-ically. When the Major first undertook 
his learning he says to me:</p>
<p>"I'm going Madam." he says "to make our 
child a Calculating Boy."</p>
<p>"Major" I says, "you terrify me and may do 
the pet a permanent injury you would never 
forgive yourself."</p>
<p>"Madam," says the Major, "next to my 
regret that when I had my boot-sponge in my 
hand, I didn't choke that scoundrel with it--on 
the spot--"</p>
<p>"There! For Gracious sake," I interrupts, 
"let his conscience find him without sponges."</p>
<p>"--I say next to that regret, Madam," says 
the Major "would be the regret with which my 
breast," which he tapped, "would be surcharged 
if this fine mind was not early cultivated. But 
mark me Madam," says the Major holding up 
his forefinger "cultivated on a principle that 
will make it a delight."</p>
<p>"Major" I says "I will be candid with you 
and tell you openly that if ever I find the dear 
child fall off in his appetite I shall know it is 
his calculations and shall put a stop to them at 
two minutes' notice. Or if I find them mounting 
to his head" I says, "or striking any ways 
cold to his stomach or leading to anything 
approaching flabbiness in his legs, the result will 
be the same, but Major you are a clever man 
and have seen much and you love the child and 
are his own godfather, and if you feel a 
confidence in trying try."</p>
<p>"Spoken Madam" says the Major "like 
Emma Lirriper. All I have to ask Madam, is, 
that you will leave my godson and myself 
to make a week or two's preparations for 
surprising you, and that you will give me leave to 
have up and down any small articles not 
actually in use that I may require from the 
kitchen."</p>
<p>"From the kitchen Major?" I says half feeling 
as if he had a mind to cook the child.</p>
<p>"From the kitchen" says the Major, and 
smiles and swells, and at the same time looks 
taller.</p>
<p>So I passed my word and the Major and the 
dear boy were shut up together for half an hour 
at a time through a certain while, and never 
could I hear anything going on betwixt them 
but talking and laughing and Jemmy clapping 
his hands and screaming out numbers, so I says 
to myself "it has not harmed him yet" nor 
could I on examining the dear find any signs of 
it anywhere about him which was likewise a 
great relief. At last one day Jemmy brings me 
a card in joke in the Major's neat writing "The 
Messrs. Jemmy Jackman" for we had given him 
the Major's other name too "request the honour 
of Mrs. Lirriper's company at the Jackman 
Institution in the front parlour this evening at five, 
military time, to witness a few slight feats of 
elementary arithmetic." And if you'll believe me 
there in the front parlour at five punctual to the 
moment was the Major behind the Pembroke 
table with both leaves up and a lot of things 
from the kitchen tidily set out on old 
newspapers spread atop of it, and there was the 
Mite stood up on a chair with his rosy cheeks 
flushing and his eyes sparkling clusters of 
diamonds.</p>
<p>"Now Gran" says he, "oo tit down and don't 
oo touch ler poople"--for he saw with every 
one of those diamonds of his that I was going 
to give him a squeeze.</p>
<p>"Very well sir" I says "I am obedient in 
this good company I am sure." And I sits 
down in the easy-chair that was put for me, 
shaking my sides.</p>
<p>But picture my admiration when the Major 
going on almost as quick as if he was conjuring 
sets out all the articles he names, and says, 
"Three saucepans, an Italian iron, a hand-bell, 
a toasting-fork, a nutmeg-grater, four pot-lids, a 
spice-box, two egg-cups, and a chopping-board--
how many?" and when that Mite instantly cries 
"Tifteen, tut down tive and carry ler 'toppin-board" 
and then claps his hands draws up his 
legs and dances on his chair!</p>
<p>My dear with the same astonishing ease and 
correctness him and the Major added up the 
tables chairs and sofy, the picters fender and fire- 
irons their own selves me and the cat and the 
eyes in Miss Wozenham's head, and whenever 
the sum was done Young Roses and Diamonds 
claps his hands and draws up his legs and 
dances on his chair.</p>
<p>The pride of the Major! ("<em>Here's</em> a mind 
Ma'am!" he says to me behind his hand.)</p>
<p>Then he says aloud, "We now come to the 
next elementary rule: which is called--"</p>
<p>"Umtraction!" cries Jemmy.</p>
<p>"Right" says the Major. "We have here a 
toasting-fork, a potato in its natural state, two 
pot-lids, one egg-cup, a wooden spoon, and two 
skewers, from which it is necessary for 
commercial purposes to subtract a sprat-gridiron, a 
small pickle-jar, two lemons, one pepper-castor, 
a blackbeetle-trap, and a knob of the dresser-drawer 
what remains?"</p>
<p>"Toatin-fork!" cries Jemmy.</p>
<p>"In numbers how many?" says the Major.</p>
<p>"One!" cries Jemmy.</p>
<p>("<em>Here's</em> a boy, Ma'am?" says the Major to 
me, behind his hand.)</p>
<p>Then the Major goes on:</p>
<p>"We now approach the next elementary rule: 
which is entitled--"</p>
<p>"Tickleication" cries Jemmy.</p>
<p>"Correct" says the Major.</p>
<p>But my dear to relate to you in detail the way 
in which they multiplied fourteen sticks of fire-wood 
by two bits of ginger and a larding-needle, 
or divided pretty well everything else there was 
on the table by the heater of the Italian iron 
and a chamber candlestick, and got a lemon over, 
would make my head spin round and round and 
round as it did at the time. So I says "if you'll 
excuse my addressing the chair Professor Jackman 
I think the period of the lecture has now 
arrived when it becomes necessary that I should 
take a good hug of this young scholar." Upon 
which Jemmy calls out from his station on the 
chair "Gran oo open oor arms and me'll make 
a 'pring into 'em." So I opened my arms to him 
as I had opened my sorrowful heart when his 
poor young mother lay a dying, and he had his 
jump and we had a good long hug together and 
the Major prouder than any peacock says to 
me behind his hand, "You" need not let him 
know it Madam" (which I certainly need not 
for the Major was quite audible) "but he is 
a boy!"</p>
<p>In this way Jemmy grew and grew and went to 
day-school and continued under the Major too, 
and in summer we were as happy as the days 
were long and in winter we were as happy as 
the days were short and there seemed to rest a 
Blessing on the Lodgings for they as good as 
Let themselves and would have done it if there 
had been twice the accommodation, when sore 
and hard against my will I one day says to the 
Major</p>
<p>"Major you know what I am going to break 
to you. Our boy must go to boarding-school."</p>
<p>It was a sad sight to see the Major's countenance 
drop, and I pitied the good soul with all 
my heart.</p>
<p>"Yes Major" I says "though he is as popular 
with the Lodgers as you are yourself and though 
he is to you and me what only you and me 
know, still it is in the course of things and Life 
is made of partings and we must part with our 
Pet."</p>
<p>Bold as I spoke, I saw two Majors and half 
a dozen fireplaces, and when the poor Major put 
one of his neat bright-varnished boots upon 
the fender and his elbow on his knee and his 
head upon his hand and rocked himself a little 
to and fro, I was dreadfully cut up.</p>
<p>"But" says I clearing my throat "you have 
so well prepared him Major--he has had such a 
Tutor in you--that he will have none of the first 
drudgery to go through. And he is so clever 
besides that he'll soon make his way to the front 
rank."</p>
<p>"He is a boy" says the Major--having sniffed 
--"that has not his like on the face of the 
earth."</p>
<p>"True as you say Major, and it is not for us 
merely for our own sakes to do anything to keep 
him back from being a credit and an ornament 
wherever he goes and perhaps even rising to be 
a great man, is it Major? He will have all my 
little savings when my work is done (being 
all the world to me) and we must try to make 
him a wise man and a good man, mustn't we 
Major?"</p>
<p>"Madam" says the Major rising "Jemmy 
Jackman is becoming an older file than I was 
aware of, and you put him to shame. You are 
thoroughly right Madam. You are simply and 
undeniably right--And if you'll excuse me, I'll 
take a walk."</p>
<p>So the Major being gone out and Jemmy being 
at home, I got the child into my little room here 
and I stood him by my chair and I took his 
mother's own curls in my hand and I spoke to 
him loving and serious. And when I had 
reminded the darling how that he was now in his 
tenth year and when I had said to him about his 
getting on in life pretty much what I had said 
to the Major I broke to him how that we must 
have this same parting, and there I was forced 
to stop for there I saw of a sudden the well 
remembered lip with its tremble, and it so 
brought back that time! But with the spirit 
that was in him he controlled it soon and he 
says gravely nodding through his tears, "I 
understand Gran--I know it <em>must</em> be, Gran--
go on Gran, don't be afraid of me." And when 
I had said all that ever I could think of, he 
turned his bright steady face to mine and he 
says just a little broken here and there "You 
shall see Gran that I can be a man and that I 
can do anything that is grateful and loving 
to you--and if I don't grow up to be what you 
would like to have me--I hope it will be--
because I shall die." And with that he sat 
down by me and I went on to tell him of the 
school of which I had excellent recommendations 
and where it was and how many scholars 
and what games they played as I had heard and 
what length of holidays, to all of which he 
listened bright and clear. And so it came that at 
last he says "And now dear Gran let me kneel 
down here where I have been used to say 
my prayers and let me fold my face for just 
a minute in your gown and let me cry, for you 
have been more than father--more than mother 
--more than brothers sisters friends--to me!" 
And so he did cry and I too and we were both 
much the better for it.</p>
<p>From that time forth he was true to his word 
and ever blithe and ready, and even when me 
and the Major took him down into Lincolnshire 
he was far the gayest of the party though 
for sure and certain he might easily have been 
that, but he really was and put life into us only 
when it came to the last Good-by, he says with 
a wistful look "You wouldn't have me not really 
sorry would you Gran?" and when I says "No 
dear, Lord forbid!" he says "I am glad of that!" 
and ran in out of sight.</p>
<p>But now that the child was gone out of the 
Lodgings the Major fell into a regularly moping 
state. It was taken notice of by all the 
Lodgers that the Major moped. He hadn't 
even the same air of being rather tall that he 
used to have, and if he varnished his boots with 
a single gleam of interest it was as much as he 
did.</p>
<p>One evening the Major came into my little 
room to take a cup of tea and a morsel of 
buttered toast and to read Jemmy's newest letter 
which had arrived that afternoon (by the very 
same postman more than middle-aged upon the 
Beat now), and the letter raising him up a little 
I says to the Major:</p>
<p>"Major you mustn't get into a moping 
way."</p>
<p>The Major shook his head. "Jemmy Jackman 
Madam," he says with a deep sigh, "is an 
older file than I thought him."</p>
<p>"Moping is not the way to grow younger 
Major."</p>
<p>"My dear Madam," says the Major, "is there 
<em>any</em> way of growing younger?"</p>
<p>Feeling that the Major was getting rather 
the best of that point I made a diversion to 
another.</p>
<p>"Thirteen years! Thir-teen years! Many 
Lodgers have come and gone, in the thirteen 
years that you have lived in the parlours Major."</p>
<p>"Hah!" says the Major warming. "Many 
Madam, many."</p>
<p>"And I should say you have been familiar 
with them all?"</p>
<p>"As a rule (with its exceptions like all rules) 
my dear Madam" says the Major, "they have 
honoured me with their acquaintance, and not 
infrequently with their confidence."</p>
<p>Watching the Major as he drooped his white 
head and stroked his black moustachios and 
moped again, a thought which I think must have 
been going about looking for an owner 
somewhere dropped into my old noddle if you will 
excuse the expression.</p>
<p>"The walls of my Lodgings" I says in a 
casual way--for my dear it is of no use going 
straight at a man who mopes--" might have 
something to tell, if they could tell it."</p>
<p>The Major neither moved nor said anything 
but I saw he was attending with his shoulders 
my dear--attending with his shoulders to what 
I said. In fact I saw that his shoulders were 
struck by it.</p>
<p>"The dear boy was always fond of story-books" 
I went on, like as if I was talking to 
myself. "I am sure this house--his own home 
--might write a story or two for his reading 
one day or another."</p>
<p>The Major's shoulders gave a dip and a curve 
and his head came up in his shirt-collar. The 
Major's head came up in his shirt-collar as I 
hadn't seen it come up since Jemmy went to 
school.</p>
<p>"It is unquestionable that in intervals of 
cribbage and a friendly rubber, my dear Madam," 
says the Major, "and also over what used to be 
called in my young times--in the salad days of 
Jemmy Jackman--the social glass, I have 
exchanged many a reminiscence with your 
Lodgers."</p>
<p>My remark was--I confess I made it with the 
deepest and artfullest of intentions--"I wish 
our dear boy had heard them!"</p>
<p>"Are you serious Madam?" asks the Major 
starting and turning full round.</p>
<p>"Why not Major?"</p>
<p>"Madam" says the Major, turning up one of 
his cuffs, "they shall be written for him."</p>
<p>"Ah! Now you speak" I says giving my 
hands a pleased clap. "Now you are in a way 
out of moping Major!"</p>
<p>"Between this and my holidays--I mean the 
dear boy's" says the Major turning up his other 
cuff, "a good deal may be done towards it."</p>
<p>"Major you are a clever man and you have 
seen much and not a doubt of it."</p>
<p>"I'll begin," says the Major looking as tall 
as ever he did, "to-morrow."</p>
<p>My dear the Major was another man in three 
days and he was himself again in a week and he 
wrote and wrote and wrote with his pen scratching 
like rats behind the wainscot, and whether 
he had many grounds to go upon or whether he 
did at all romance I cannot tell you, but what 
he has written is in the left-hand glass closet of 
the little bookcase close behind you, and if 
you'll put your hand in you'll find it come out 
heavy in lumps sewn together and being 
beautifully plain and unknown Greek and Hebrew 
to myself and me quite wakeful, I shall take 
it as a favour if you'll read out loud and read 
on.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE FIRST FLOOR WENT TO CROWLEY CASTLE."/>
<chapter>
<p>I have come back to London, Major, 
possessed by a family-story that I have picked up 
in the country. While I was out of town, I 
visited the ruins of the great old Norman castle 
of Sir Mark Crowley, the last baronet of his 
name, who has been dead nearly a hundred 
years. I stayed in the village near the castle, 
and thence I bring back some of the particulars 
of the tale I am going to tell you, derived from 
old inhabitants who heard them from their 
fathers;--no longer ago.</p>
<p>We drove from our little sea-bathing place, 
in Sussex, to see the massive ruins of Crowley 
Castle, which is the show-excursion of Merton. 
We had to alight at a field gate: the road further 
on being too bad for the slightly-built carriage, 
or the poor tired Merton horse: and we walked 
for about a quarter of a mile through uneven 
ground, which had once been an Italian garden; 
and then we came to a bridge over a dry moat, 
and went over the groove of a portcullis that 
had once closed the massive entrance, into an 
empty space surrounded by thick walls, 
draperied with ivy, unroofed, and open to the sky. 
We could judge of the beautiful tracery that 
had been in the windows, by the remains of the 
stonework here and there; and an old man 
--"ever so old," he called himself when we 
inquired his exact age--who scrambled and 
stumbled out of some lair in the least devastated 
part of the ruins at our approach, and who 
established himself as our guide, showed us a 
scrap of glass yet lingering in what was the 
window of the great drawing-room not above 
seventy years ago. After he had done his duty, 
he hobbled with us to the neighbouring church, 
where the knightly Crowleys lie buried: some 
commemorated by ancient brasses, some by altar- 
tombs, some by fine Latin epitaphs, bestowing 
upon them every virtue under the sun. He had 
to take the church-key back to the adjoining 
parsonage at the entrance of the long straggling 
street winch forms the village of Crowley. The 
castle and the church were on the summit of a 
hill, from which we could see the distant line of 
sea beyond the misty marshes. The village fell 
away from the church and parsonage, down the 
hill. The aspect of the place was little, if at 
all, changed, from its aspect in the year 1772.</p>
<p>But I must begin a little earlier. From one 
of the Latin epitaphs I learnt that Amelia 
Lady Crowley died in 1756, deeply regretted by 
her loving husband, Sir Mark. He never married 
again, though his wife had left him no heir to 
his name or his estate--only a little tiny girl--
Theresa Crowley. This child would inherit her 
mother's fortune, and all that Sir Mark was free 
to leave; but this little was not much; the castle 
and all the lands going to his sister's son, 
Marmaduke, or as he was usually called Duke, 
Brownlow. Duke's parents were dead, and his 
uncle was his guardian, and his guardian's house 
was his home. The lad was some seven or eight 
years older than his cousin; and probably Sir 
Mark thought it not unlikely that his daughter 
and his heir might make a match. Theresa's 
mother had had some foreign blood in her, and 
had been brought up in France--not so far away 
but that its shores might be seen by any one 
who chose to take an easy day's ride from 
Crowley Castle for the purpose.</p>
<p>Lady Crowley had been a delicate elegant 
creature, but no great beauty, judging from all 
accounts; Sir Mark's family were famous for their 
good looks; Theresa, an unusually lucky child, 
inherited the outward graces of both her parents. 
A portrait which I saw of her, degraded to a 
station over the parlour chimney-piece in the 
village inn, showed me black hair, soft yet arch 
grey eyes with brows and lashes of the same tint 
as her hair, a full pretty pouting passionate mouth, 
and a round slender throat. She was a wilful 
little creature, and her father's indulgence made 
her more wayward. She had a nurse, too, a 
French bonne, whose mother had been about 
my lady from her youth, who had followed my 
lady to England, and who had died there. 
Victorine had been in attendance on the young 
Theresa from her earliest infancy, and almost 
took the place of a parent in power and affection 
--in power, as to ordering and arranging 
almost what she liked, concerning the child's 
management--in love, because they speak to 
this day of the black year when virulent small- 
pox was rife in Crowley, and when, Sir Mark 
being far away on some diplomatic mission--in 
Vienna, I fancy--Victorine shut herself up with 
Miss Theresa when the child was taken ill with 
the disease, and nursed her night and day. She 
only succumbed to the dreadful illness when all 
danger to the child was over. Theresa came 
out of it with unblemished beauty; Victorine 
barely escaped with life, and was disfigured for 
life.</p>
<p>This disfigurement put a stop to much 
unfounded scandal which had been afloat respecting 
the French servant's great influence over 
Sir Mark. He was, in fact, an easy and indolent 
man, rarely excited to any vehemence of 
emotion, and who felt it to be a point of honour 
to carry out his dead wife's wish that Victorine 
should never leave Theresa, and that the 
management of the child should be confided to her. 
Only once had there been a struggle for power 
between Sir Mark and the bonne, and then she 
had won the victory. And no wonder, if the 
old butler's account were true; for he had gone 
into the room unawares, and had found Sir Mark 
and Victorine at high words; and he said that 
Victorine was white with rage, that her eyes 
were blazing with passionate lire, that her voice 
was low, and her words were few, but that, 
although she spoke in French, and he the butler 
only knew his native English, he would rather 
have been sworn at by a drunken grenadier 
with a sword in his hand, than have had those 
words of Victorine's addressed to him.</p>
<p>Even the choice of Theresa's masters was left 
to Victorine. A little reference was occasionally 
made to Madam Hawtrey, the parson's wife and 
a distant relation of Sir Mark's, but, seeing that, 
if Victorine chose so to order it, Madam 
Hawtrey's own little daughter Bessy would have been 
deprived of the advantages resulting from 
gratuitous companionship in all Theresa's lessons, 
she was careful how she opposed or made 
an enemy of Mademoiselle Victorine. Bessy 
was a gentle quiet child, and grew up to be a 
sensible sweet-tempered girl, with a very fair share 
of English beauty; fresh-complexion, brown-eyed 
round-faced, with a stiff though well-made figure, 
as different as possible from Theresa's slight 
lithe graceful form. Duke was a young man to 
these two maidens, while they to him were little 
more than children. Of course he admired his 
cousin Theresa the most--who would not?--
but he was establishing his first principles of 
morality for himself, and her conduct towards 
Bessy sometimes jarred against his ideas of 
right. One day, after she had been tyrannising 
over the self-contained and patient Bessy so as 
to make the latter cry--and both the amount of 
the tyranny and the crying were unusual 
circumstances, for Theresa was of a generous nature 
when not put out of the way--Duke spoke to 
his cousin:</p>
<p>"Theresa! You had no right to blame Bessy 
as you did. It was as much your fault as hers. 
You were as much bound to remember Mr. 
Dawson's directions about the sums you were 
to do for him, as she was,"</p>
<p>The girl opened her great grey eyes in 
surprise. She to blame!</p>
<p>"What does Bessy come to the castle for, I 
wonder? They pay nothing--we pay all. The 
least she can do, is to remember for me what we 
are told. I shan't trouble myself with attending 
to Mr. Dawson's directions; and if Bessy does 
not like to do so, she can stay away. She 
already knows enough to earn her bread as a 
maid: which I suppose is what she'll have to 
come to."</p>
<p>The moment Theresa had said this, she could 
have bitten her tongue out for the meanness and 
rancour of the speech. She saw pain and 
disappointment clearly expressed on Duke's face; 
and, in another moment, her impulses would have 
carried her to the opposite extreme, and she 
would have spoken out her self-reproach. But 
Duke thought it his duty to remonstrate with 
her, and to read her a homily, which, however 
true and just, weakened the effect of the look of 
distress on his face. Her wits were called into 
play to refute his arguments; her head rather 
than her heart took the prominent part in the 
controversy; and it ended unsatisfactorily to 
both; he, going away with dismal though 
unspoken prognostics touching what she would 
become as a woman if she were so supercilious 
and unfeeling as a girl; she, the moment his 
back was turned, throwing herself on the floor 
and sobbing as if her heart would break. 
Victorine heard her darling's passionate sobs, and 
came in.</p>
<p>"What hast thou, my angel! Who has been 
vexing thee,--tell me, my cherished?"</p>
<p>She tried to raise the girl, but Theresa would 
not be raised; neither would she speak till she 
chose, in spite of Victorine's entreaties. When 
she chose, she lifted herself up, still sitting on 
the floor, and putting her tangled hair off her 
flushed tear-stained face, said:</p>
<p>"Never mind, it was only something Duke 
said; I don't care for it now." And refusing 
Victorine's aid, she got up, and stood thoughtfully 
looking out of window.</p>
<p>"That Duke!" exclaimed Victorine. "What 
business has that Mr. Duke to go vex my 
darling? He is not your husband yet, that he 
should scold you, or that you should mind what 
he says."</p>
<p>Theresa listened and gained a new idea; but 
she gave no outward sign of attention, or of 
her now hearing for the first time how that she 
was supposed to be intended for her cousin's 
wife. She made no reply to Victorine's caresses 
and speeches; one might almost say she shook 
her off. As soon as she was left to herself, 
she took her hat, and going out alone, as she 
was wont, in the pleasure-grounds, she went 
down the terrace steps, crossed the bowling- 
green, and opened a little wicket-gate which led 
into the garden of the parsonage. There, were 
Bessy and her mother, gathering fruit. It was 
Bessy whom Theresa sought; for there was 
something in Madam Hawtrey's silky manner 
that was always rather repugnant to her. 
However, she was not going to shrink from her 
resolution because Madam Hawtrey was there. 
So she went up to the startled Bessy, and said 
to her, as if she were reciting a prepared speech: 
"Bessy, I behaved very crossly to you; I had 
no business to have spoken to you as I did."--
"Will you forgive me?" was the pre-determined 
end of this confession; but somehow, when it 
came to that, she could not say it with Madam 
Hawtrey standing by, ready to smile and to 
curtsey as soon as she could catch Theresa's 
eye. There was no need to ask forgiveness 
though; for Bessy had put down her half filled 
basket, and came softly up to Theresa, stealing 
her brown soil-stained little hand into the 
young lady's soft white one, and looking up at 
her with loving brown eyes.</p>
<p>"I am so sorry, but I think it was the sums 
on page 108. I have been looking and looking, 
and I am almost sure."</p>
<p>Her exculpatory tone caught her mother's 
ear, although her words did not.</p>
<p>"I am sure, Miss Theresa, Bessy is so grateful 
for the privileges of learning with you! It is 
such an advantage to her! I often tell her, 
'Take pattern by Miss Theresa, and do as she 
does, and try and speak as she does, and there'll 
not be a parson's daughter in all Sussex to 
compare with you.' Don't I, Bessy?"</p>
<p>Theresa shrugged her shoulders--a trick she 
had caught from Victorine--and, turning to 
Bessy, asked her what she was going to do with 
those gooseberries she was gathering? And as 
Theresa spoke, she lazily picked the ripest out 
of the basket, and ate them.</p>
<p>"They are for a pudding," said Bessy. "As 
soon as we have gathered enough, I am going in 
to make it."</p>
<p>"I'll come and help you," said Theresa, 
eagerly. "I should so like to make a pudding. 
Our Monsieur Antoine never makes gooseberry 
puddings."</p>
<p>Duke came past the parsonage an hour or so 
afterwards: and, looking in by chance through 
the open casement windows of the kitchen, 
saw Theresa pinned up in a bib and apron, 
her arms all over flour, flourishing a rolling- 
pin, and laughing and chattering with Bessy 
similarly attired. Duke had spent his morning 
ostensibly in fishing; but in reality in weighing 
in his own mind what he could do or say to 
soften the obdurate heart of his cousin. And 
here it was, all inexplicably right, as if by some 
enchanter's wand!</p>
<p>The only conclusion Duke could come to 
was the same that many a wise (and foolish) 
man had come to before his day:</p>
<p>"Well! Women are past my comprehension, 
that's all!"</p>
<p>When all this took place, Theresa was about 
fifteen; Bessy was perhaps six months older; 
Duke was just leaving Oxford. His uncle, 
Sir Mark, was excessively fond of him; yes! 
and proud, too, for he had distinguished 
himself at college, and every one spoke well of him. 
And he, for his part, loved Sir Mark, and, 
unspoiled by the fame and reputation he had 
gained at Christ Church, paid respectful deference 
to Sir Mark's opinions.</p>
<p>As Theresa grew older, her father supposed 
that he played his cards well in singing Duke's 
praises on every possible occasion. She tossed 
her head, and said nothing. Thanks to Victorine's 
revelations, she understood the tendency of her 
father's speeches. She intended to make her 
own choice of a husband when the time came; 
and it might be Duke, or it might be some one 
else. When Duke did not lecture or prose, but 
was sitting his horse so splendidly at the meet, 
before the huntsman gave the blast, "Found;" 
when Duke was holding his own in discourse 
with other men; when Duke gave her a short 
sharp word of command on any occasion; then 
she decided that she would marry him, and no 
one else. But when he found fault, or stumbled 
about awkwardly in a minuet, or talked moralities 
against duelling, then she was sure that Duke 
should never be her husband. She wondered if 
he knew about it; if any one had told him, as 
Victorine had told her; if her father had revealed 
his thoughts and wishes to his nephew, as plainly 
as he had done to his daughter? This last query 
made her cheeks burn; and, on days when the 
suspicion had been brought by any chance 
prominently before her mind, she was especially 
rude and disagreeable to Duke.</p>
<p>He was to go abroad on the grand tour of 
Europe, to which young men of fortune usually 
devoted three years. He was to have a tutor, 
because all young men of his rank had tutors; 
else he was quite wise enough, and steady 
enough, to have done without one, and probably 
knew a good deal more about what was best to be 
observed in the countries they were going to visit, 
than Mr. Roberts, his appointed bear-leader. 
He was to come back full of historical and 
political knowledge, speaking French and Italian 
like a native, and having a smattering of 
barbarous German, and he was to enter the House 
as a county member, if possible--as a borough 
member at the worst; and was to make a great 
success; and then, as every one understood, he 
was to marry his cousin Theresa.</p>
<p>He spoke to her father about it, before starting 
on his travels. It was after dinner in Crowley 
Castle. Sir Mark and Duke sat alone, each 
pensive at the thought of the coming parting.</p>
<p>"Theresa is but young," said Duke, breaking 
into speech after a long silence, "but if you 
have no objection, uncle, I should like to speak 
to her before I leave England, about my--my 
hopes."</p>
<p>Sir Mark played with his glass, poured out 
some more wine, drank it off at a draught, and 
then replied:</p>
<p>"No, Duke, no. Leave her in peace with 
me. I have looked forward to having her for 
my companion through these three years; they'll 
soon pass away" (to age, but not to youth), 
"and I should like to have her undivided 
heart till you come back. No, Duke! Three 
years will soon pass away, and then we'll have 
a royal wedding."</p>
<p>Duke sighed, but said no more. The next 
day was the last. He wanted Theresa to go with 
him to take leave of the Hawtreys at the 
Parsonage, and of the villagers; but she was wilful, 
and would not. He remembered, years afterwards, 
how Bessy's gentle peaceful manner had 
struck him as contrasted with Theresa's, on that 
last day. Both girls regretted his departure. 
He had been so uniformly gentle and thoughtful 
in his behaviour to Bessy, that, without any idea 
of love, she felt him to be her pattern of noble 
chivalrous manhood; the only person, except her 
father, who was steadily kind to her. She admired 
his sentiments, she esteemed his principles, she 
considered his long evolvement of his ideas as 
the truest eloquence. He had lent her books, 
he had directed her studies; all the advice and 
information which Theresa had rejected had 
fallen to Bessy's lot, and she had received it 
thankfully.</p>
<p>Theresa burst into a passion of tears as soon 
as Duke and his suite were out of sight. She 
had refused the farewell kiss her father had 
told her to give him, but had waved her white 
handkerchief out of the great drawing-room 
window (that very window in which the old 
guide showed me the small piece of glass 
still lingering). But Duke had ridden away 
with slack rein and downcast head, without 
looking back.</p>
<p>His absence was a great blank in Sir Mark's 
life. He had never sought London much as a 
place of residence; in former days he had been 
suspected of favouring the Stuarts; but nothing 
could be proved against him, and he had 
subsided into a very tolerably faithful subject of 
King George the Third. Still, a cold shoulder 
having been turned to him by the court party 
at one time, he had become prepossessed against 
the English capital. On the contrary, his wife's 
predilections and his own tendencies had always 
made Paris a very agreeable place of residence 
to him. To Paris he at length resorted again, 
when the blank in his life oppressed him; and 
from Paris, about two years after Duke's 
departure, he returned after a short absence from 
home, and suddenly announced to his daughter 
and the household that he had taken an apartment 
in the Rue Louis le Grand for the coming winter, 
to which there was to be an immediate removal 
of his daughter, Victorine, and certain other 
personal attendants and servants.</p>
<p>Nothing could exceed Theresa's mad joy 
at this unexpected news. She sprang upon 
her father's neck, and kissed him till she was 
tired--whatever he was. She ran to Victorine, 
and told her to guess what "heavenly bliss" 
was going to befall them, dancing round the 
middle-aged woman until she, in her spoilt 
impatience, was becoming angry, when, kissing 
her, she told her, and ran off to the Parsonage, 
and thence to the church, bursting in upon 
morning prayers--for it was All Saints' Day, 
although she had forgotten it--and filliping a 
scrap of paper on which she had hastily written, 
"We are going to Paris for the winter--all of 
us," rolled into a ball, from the castle pew to 
that of the parson. She saw Bessy redden as 
she caught it, put it into her pocket unread, 
and, after an apologetic glance at the curtained 
seat in which Theresa was, go on with her meek 
responses. Theresa went out by the private 
door in a momentary fit of passion. "Stupid 
cold-blooded creature!" she said to herself. 
But that afternoon Bessy came to the castle, so 
sorry and so losing her own sorrow in sympathy 
with her friend's gladness, that Theresa took 
her into favour again. The girls parted with 
promises of correspondence, and with some 
regret: the greatest on Bessy's side. Some 
grand promises of Paris fashion, and presents 
of dress, Theresa made in her patronising way; 
but Bessy did not seem to care much for them 
--which was fortunate, for they were never 
fulfilled.</p>
<p>Sir Mark had an idea in his head of perfecting 
Theresa's accomplishments and manners by 
Parisian masters and Parisian society. English 
residents in Venice, Florence, Rome, wrote to 
their friends at home about Duke. They spoke 
of him as of what we should, at the present day, 
call a "rising young man." His praises ran so 
high, that Sir Mark began to fear lest his 
handsome nephew, feted by princes, courted by 
ambassadors, made love to by lovely Italian ladies, 
might find Theresa too country-bred for his 
taste.</p>
<p>Thus had come about, the engaging of the 
splendid apartment in the Rue Louis le Grand. 
The street itself is narrow, and now-a-days we 
are apt to think the situation close; but in those 
days it was the height of fashion; for, the great 
arbiter of fashion, the Due de Richelieu, lived 
there, and, to inhabit an apartment in that 
street, was in itself a mark of bon ton. Victorine 
seemed almost crazy with delight when they 
took possession of their new abode. "This dear 
Paris! This lovely France! And now I see my 
young lady, my darling, my angel, in a room 
suited to her beauty and her rank: such as my 
lady her mother would have planned for her, if 
she had lived." Any allusion to her dead 
mother always touched Theresa to the quick. 
She was in her bed, under the blue silk curtains 
of an alcove, when Victorine said this,--being 
too much fatigued after her journey to respond 
to Victorine's rhapsodies; but now she put out 
her little hand and gave Victorine's a pressure 
of gratitude and pleasure. Next day she 
wandered about the rooms and admired their splendour 
almost to Victorine's content. Her father, 
Sir Mark, found a handsome carriage and 
horses for his darling's use; and also found that 
not less necessary article--a married lady of 
rank who would take his girl under her wing. 
When all these preliminary arrangements were 
made, who so wildly happy as Theresa! Her 
carriage was of the newest fashion, fit to 
vie with any on the Cours de la Reine, the 
then fashionable drive. The box at the Grand 
Opra, and at the Franais, which she shared 
with Madame la Duchesse de G., was the centre 
of observation; Victorine was in her best 
humour, Theresa's credit at her dressmaker's 
was unlimited, her indulgent father was charmed 
with all she did and said. She had masters, it 
is true; but, to a rich and beautiful young lady, 
masters were wonderfully complaisant, and with 
them as with all the world, she did what she 
pleased. Of Parisian society, she had enough 
and more than enough. The duchess went 
everywhere, and Theresa went too. So did a certain 
Count de la Grange: some relation or 
connexion of the duchess: handsome, with a south 
of France handsomeness: with delicate features, 
marred by an over-softness of expression, from 
which (so men said) the tiger was occasionally 
seen to peep forth. But, for elegance of dress and 
demeanour he had not his fellow in Paris--which 
of course meant, not in the world.</p>
<p>Sir Mark heard rumours of this man's conduct, 
which, were not pleasing to him; but when he 
accompanied his daughter into society, the count 
was only as deferential as it became a gentleman 
to be to so much beauty and grace. When 
Theresa was taken out by the duchess to the 
opera, to balls, to petits soupers, without her 
father, then the count was more than deferential; 
he was adoring. It was a little intoxicating 
for a girl brought up in the solitude of an 
English village, to have so many worshippers at 
her feet all at once, in the great gay city; and 
the inbred coquetry of her nature came out, 
adding to her outward grace, if taking away 
from the purity and dignity of her character. 
It was Victorine's delight to send her darling 
out arrayed for conquest; her hair delicately 
powdered, and scented with marchale; her little 
"mouches" put on with skill; the tiny half-moon 
patch, to lengthen the already almond-shaped 
eye; the minute star to give the effect of a 
dimple at the corner of her scarlet lips; the 
silver gauze looped up over the petticoat of 
blue brocade, distended over a hoop, much as 
*owns are worn in our days; the coral 
ornaments of her silver dress, matching with the tint 
of the high heels to her shoes. And, at night, 
Victorine was never tired of listening and 
questioning; of triumphing in Theresa's triumphs; 
of invariably reminding her that she was bound 
to marry the absent cousin, and return to the 
half-feudal state of the old castle in Sussex.</p>
<p>Still, even now, if Duke had returned from 
Italy, all might have gone well; but when Sir 
Mark, alarmed by the various proposals he 
received for Theresa's hand from needy French 
noblemen, and by the admiration she was 
exciting everywhere, wrote to Duke, and urged 
him to join them in Paris on his return from 
his travels, Duke answered that three months 
were yet unexpired of the time allotted for 
the grand tour; and that he was anxious 
to avail himself of that interval to see 
something of Spain. Sir Mark read this letter 
aloud to Theresa, with many expressions of 
annoyance as he read. Theresa merely said, "Of 
course, Duke does what he likes," and turned 
away to see some new lace brought for her 
inspection. She heard her father sigh over a 
reperusal of Duke's letter, and she set her teeth 
in the anger she would not show in acts or 
words. That day the Count de Grange met 
with gentler treatment from her than he had 
done for many days--than he had done since 
her father's letter to Duke had been sent off to 
Genoa. As ill fortune would have it, Sir Mark 
had occasion to return to England at this time, 
and he, guileless himself, consigned Theresa and 
her maid Victorine, and her man Felix, to the 
care of the duchess for three weeks. They were 
to reside at the Hotel de G. during this time. 
The duchess welcomed them in her most caressing 
manner, and showed Theresa the suite of 
rooms, with the little private staircase, 
appropriated to her use.</p>
<p>The Count de Grange was an habitual visitor 
at the house of his cousin the duchess, who was 
a gay Parisian, absorbed in her life of giddy 
dissipation. The count found means of influencing 
Victorine in his favour; not by money; so 
coarse a bribe would have had no power over 
her; but by many presents, accompanied with 
sentimental letters, breathing devotion to her 
charge, and extremest appreciation of the faithful 
friend whom Theresa looked upon as a 
mother, and whom for this reason he, the 
count, revered and loved. Intermixed, were 
wily allusions to his great possessions in 
Provence, and to his ancient lineage:--the one 
mortgaged, the other disgraced. Victorine, 
whose right hand had forgotten its cunning in 
the length of her dreary vegetation at Crowley 
Castle, was deceived, and became a vehement 
advocate of the dissolute Adonis of the Paris 
saloons, in his suit to her darling. When Sir 
Mark came back, he was dismayed and shocked 
beyond measure by finding the count and Theresa 
at his feet, entreating him to forgive their stolen 
marriage--a marriage which, though incomplete 
as to its legal forms, was yet too complete to be 
otherwise than sanctioned by Theresa's nearest 
friends. The duchess accused her cousin of 
perfidy and treason. Sir Mark said nothing. 
But his health failed from that time, and he 
sank into an old querulous grey-haired man.</p>
<p>There was some ado, I know not what, 
between Sir Mark and the count regarding the 
control and disposition of the fortune which 
Theresa inherited from her mother. The count 
gained the victory, owing to the different nature 
of the French laws from the English; and this 
made Sir Mark abjure the country and the city 
he had loved so long. Henceforward, he swore, 
his foot should never touch French soil; if 
Theresa liked to come and see him at Crowley 
Castle, she should be as welcome as a daughter 
of the house ought to be, and ever should be; 
but her husband should never enter the gates of 
the house in Sir Mark's lifetime.</p>
<p>For some months he was out of humour with 
Duke, because of his tardy return from his tour 
and his delay in joining them in Paris: through 
which, so Sir Mark fancied, Theresa's marriage 
had been brought about. But--when Duke came 
home, depressed in spirits and submissive to his 
uncle, even under unjust blame--Sir Mark 
restored him to favour in the course of a summer's 
day, and henceforth added another injury to the 
debtor side of the count's reckoning.</p>
<p>Duke never told his uncle of the woful ill- 
report he had heard of the count in Paris, where 
he had found all the better part of the French 
nobility pitying the lovely English heiress who' 
had been entrapped into a marriage with one of 
the most disreputable of their order, a gambler 
and a reprobate. He could not leave Paris without 
seeing Theresa, whom he believed to be as 
yet unacquainted with his arrival in the city, so 
he went to call upon her one evening. She was 
sitting alone, splendidly dressed, ravishingly 
beautiful; she made a step forward to meet 
him, hardly heeding the announcement of his 
name; for she had recognised a man's tread, and 
fancied it was her husband, coming to accompany 
her to some grand reception. Duke saw 
the quick change from hope to disappointment 
on her mobile face, and she spoke out at once 
her reason. "Adolphe promised to come and 
fetch me; the princess receives to-night. I 
hardly expected a visit from you, cousin Duke," 
recovering herself into a pretty proud reserve. 
"It is a fortnight, I think, since I heard you 
were in Paris. I had given up all expectation 
of the honour of a visit from you!"</p>
<p>Duke felt that, as she had heard of his being 
there, it would be awkward to make excuses 
which both she and he must know to be false, 
or explanations the very truth of which would 
be offensive to the loving, trusting, deceived 
wife. So, he turned the conversation to his 
travels, his heart aching for her all the time, as 
he noticed her wandering attention when she 
heard any passing sound. Ten, eleven, twelve 
o'clock; he would not leave her. He thought 
his presence was a comfort and a pleasure to 
her. But when one o'clock struck, she said some 
unexpected business must have detained her 
husband, and she was glad of it, as she had 
all along felt too much tired to go out: and 
besides, the happy consequence of her husband's 
detention had been that long talk with Duke.</p>
<p>He did not see her again after this polite 
dismissal, nor did he see her husband at all. 
Whether through ill chance, or carefully disguised 
purpose, it did so happen that he called several 
times, he wrote several notes requesting an 
appointment when he might come with the 
certainty of finding the count and countess at 
home, in order to wish them farewell before 
setting out for England. All in vain. But he 
said nothing to Sir Mark of all this. He only 
tried to fill up the blank in the old man's life. 
He went between Sir Mark and the tenants to 
whom he was unwilling to show himself 
unaccompanied by the beautiful daughter, who had 
so often been his companion in his walks and 
rides, before that ill-omened winter in Paris. 
He was thankful to have the power of 
returning the long kindness his uncle had shown 
him in childhood; thankful to be of use to him 
in his desertion; thankful to atone in some 
measure for his neglect of his uncle's wish that 
he should have made a hasty return to Paris.</p>
<p>But it was a little dull after the long excitement 
of travel, after associating with all that 
was most cultivated and seeing all that was 
most famous, in Europe, to be shut up in that 
vast magnificent dreary old castle, with Sir Mark 
for a perpetual companion--Sir Mark, and no 
other. The parsonage was near at hand, and 
occasionally Mr. Hawtrey came in to visit his 
parishioner in his trouble. But Sir Mark kept 
the clergyman at bay; he knew that his brother 
in age, his brother in circumstances (for had 
not Mr. Hawtrey an only child and she a 
daughter?), was sympathising with him in his 
sorrow, and he was too proud to bear it; 
indeed, sometimes he was so rude to his old neighbour, 
that Duke would go next morning to the 
Parsonage, to soothe the smart.</p>
<p>And so--and so--gradually, imperceptibly, at 
last his heart was drawn to Bessy. Her mother 
angled and angled skilfully; at first scarcely 
daring to hope; then remembering her own 
descent from the same stock as Duke, she 
drew herself up, and set to work with fresh skill 
and vigour. To be sure, it was a dangerous game 
for a mother to play; for her daughter's 
happiness was staked on her success. How could 
simple country-bred Bessy help being attracted 
to the courtly handsome man, travelled and 
accomplished, good and gentle, whom she saw 
every day, and who treated her with the kind 
familiarity of a brother; while he was not a 
brother, but in some measure a disappointed 
man, as everybody knew? Bessy was a daisy 
of an English maiden; pure good to the heart's 
core and most hidden thought; sensible in all 
her accustomed daily ways, yet not so much 
without imagination as not to desire something 
beyond the narrow range of knowledge and 
experience in which her days had hitherto been 
passed. Add to this her pretty figure, a bright 
healthy complexion, lovely teeth, and quite enough 
of beauty in her other features to have rendered 
her the belle of a country town, if her lot had 
been cast in such a place; and it is not to be 
wondered at, that, after she had been secretly 
in love with Duke with all her heart for nearly 
a year, almost worshipping him, he should 
discover that, of all the women he had ever 
known--except perhaps the lost Theresa--
Bessy Hawtrey had it in her power to make him 
the happiest of men.</p>
<p>Sir Mark grumbled a little; but now-a-days 
he grumbled at everything, poor disappointed, 
all but childless, old man! As to the vicar he 
stood astonished and almost dismayed. "Have 
you thought enough about it, Mr. Duke?" 
the parson asked. "Young men are apt to do 
things in a hurry, that they repent at leisure. 
Bessy is a good girl, a good girl, God bless her: 
but she has not been brought up as your wife 
should have been: at least as folks will say 
your wife should have been. Though I may say 
for her she has a very pretty sprinkling of 
mathematics. I taught her myself, Mr. Duke."</p>
<p>"May I go and ask her myself? I only want 
your permission," urged Duke.</p>
<p>"Ay, go! But perhaps you'd better ask 
Madam first. She will like to be told everything 
as soon as me."</p>
<p>But Duke did not care for Madam. He rushed 
through the open door of the Parsonage, into 
the homely sitting-rooms, and softly called for 
Bessy. When she came, he took her by the 
hand and led her forth into the field-path at the 
back of the orchard, and there he won his bride 
to the full content of both their hearts.</p>
<p>All this time the inhabitants of Crowley Castle 
and the quiet people of the neighbouring village 
of Crowley, heard but little of "The Countess," 
as it was their fashion to call her. Sir Mark 
had his letters from her, it is true, and he read 
them over and over again, and moaned over 
them, and sighed, and put them carefully away 
in a bundle. But they were like arrows of 
pain to him. None knew their contents; none, 
even knowing them, would have dreamed, any 
more than he did, for all his moans and sighs, 
of the utter wretchedness of the writer. Love 
had long since vanished from the habitation of 
that pair; a habitation, not a home, even in its 
brightest days. Love had gone out of the 
window, long before poverty had come in at the 
door: yet that grim visitant who never tarries 
in tracking a disreputable gambler, had now 
arrived. The count lost the last remnants of 
his character as a man who played honourably, 
and thenceforth--that being pretty nearly the 
only sin which banished men from good society 
in those days--he had to play where and how he 
could. Theresa's money went as her poor angry 
father had foretold. By-and-by, and without her 
consent, her jewel-box was rifled; the diamonds 
round the locket holding her mother's picture 
were wrenched and picked out by no careful 
hand. Victorine found Theresa crying over 
the poor relics;--crying at last, without 
disguise, as if her heart would break.</p>
<p>"Oh, mamma! mamma! mamma!" she sobbed 
out, holding up the smashed and disfigured 
miniature as an explanation of her grief. She 
was sitting on the floor, on which she had thrown 
herself in the first discovery of the theft. 
Victorine sat down by her, taking her head upon 
her breast, and soothing her. She did not ask 
who had done it; she asked Theresa no question 
which the latter would have shrunk from 
answering; she knew all in that hour, without 
the count's name having passed the lips of either 
of them. And from that time she watched him 
as a tiger watches his prey.</p>
<p>When the letters came from England, the 
three letters from Sir Mark and the affianced 
bride and bridegroom, announcing the approaching 
marriage of Duke and Bessy, Theresa took 
them straight to Victorine. Theresa's lips were 
tightened, her pale cheeks were paler. She 
waited for Victorine to speak. Not a word did 
the Frenchwoman utter; but she smoothed the 
letters one over the other, and tore them in 
two, throwing the pieces on the ground, and 
stamping on them.</p>
<p>"Oh, Victorine!" cried Theresa, dismayed at 
passion that went so far beyond her own, "I 
never expected it--I never thought of it--but, 
perhaps, it was but natural."</p>
<p>"It was not natural; it was infamous! To 
have loved you once, and not to wait for chances, 
but to take up with that mean poor girl at the 
Parsonage. Pah! and <em>her</em> letter! Sir Mark is 
of my mind though, I can see. I am sorry I 
tore up his letter. He feels, he knows, that Mr. 
Duke Brownlow ought to have waited, waited, 
waited. Some one waited fourteen years, did 
he not? The count will not live for ever."</p>
<p>Theresa did not see the face of wicked meaning 
as those last words were spoken.</p>
<p>Another year rolled heavily on its course of 
wretchedness to Theresa. That same revolution 
of time brought increase of peace and joy to the 
English couple, striving humbly, striving well, 
to do their duty as children to the unhappy and 
deserted Sir Mark. They had their reward in 
the birth of a little girl. Yet, close on the heels 
of this birth, followed a great sorrow. The 
good parson died, after a short sudden illness. 
Then came the customary trouble after the 
death of a clergyman. The widow had to leave 
the Parsonage, the home of a lifetime, and seek 
a new resting-place for her declining years.</p>
<p>Fortunately for all parties, the new vicar was 
a bachelor; no other than the tutor who had 
accompanied Duke on his grand tour; and it 
was made a condition that he should allow the 
widow of his predecessor to remain at the 
Parsonage as his housekeeper. Bessy would fain 
have had her mother at the castle, and this 
course would have been infinitely preferred by 
Madam Hawtrey, who, indeed, suggested the 
wish to her daughter. But Sir Mark was 
obstinately against it; nor did he spare his caustic 
remarks on Madam Hawtrey, even before her 
own daughter. He had never quite forgiven 
Duke's marriage, although he was personally 
exceedingly fond of Bessy. He referred this 
marriage, in some part, and perhaps to no greater 
extent than was true, to madam's good management 
in throwing the young people together; and 
he was explicit in the expression of his opinion.</p>
<p>Poor Theresa! Every day she more and more 
bitterly rued her ill-starred marriage. Often 
and often she cried to herself, when she was 
alone in the dead of the night, "I cannot 
bear it--I cannot bear it!" But again in 
the daylight her pride would help her to 
keep her woe to herself. She could not bear 
the gaze of pitying eyes; she could not bear 
even Victorine's fierce sympathy. She might 
have gone home like a poor prodigal to her 
father, if Duke and Bessy had not, as she 
imagined, reigned triumphant in her place, both in 
her father's heart and in her father's home. 
And all this while, that father almost hated the 
tender attentions which were rendered to him 
by those who were not his Theresa, his only 
child, for whose presence he yearned and longed 
in silent misery. Then again (to return to 
Theresa), her husband had his fits of kindness 
towards her. If he had been very fortunate in 
play, if he had heard other men admire her, he 
would come back for a few moments to his 
loyalty, and would lure back the poor tortured 
heart, only to crush it afresh. One day--after 
a short time of easy temper, caresses, and levity 
--she found out something, I know not what, in 
his life, which stung her to the quick. Her sharp 
wits and sharper tongue spoke out most cutting 
insults; at first he smiled, as if rather amused 
to see how she was ransacking her brain to find 
stabbing speeches; but at length she touched 
some sore; he scarcely lost the mocking smile 
upon his face, but his eyes flashed lurid fire, and 
his heavy closed hand fell on her white shoulder 
with a terrible blow!</p>
<p>She stood up, facing him, tearless, deadly 
white. "The poor old man at home!" was all 
she said, trembling, shivering all over, but with 
her eyes fixed on his coward face. He shrank 
from her look, laughed aloud to hide whatever 
feeling might be hidden in his bosom, and left 
the room. She only said again, "The poor old 
man--the poor old deserted, desolate man!" and 
felt about blindly for a chair.</p>
<p>She had not sat down a minute though, be- 
fore she started up and rang her bell. It was 
Victorine's office to answer it; but Theresa 
looked almost surprised to see her. "You!--I 
wanted the others--I want them all! They 
shall all see how their master treats his wife! 
Look here!" she pushed the gauze neckerchief 
from her shoulder--the mark was there red and 
swollen. "Bid them all come here Victorine, 
Amade, Jean, Adle, all--I will be justified by 
their testimony, whatever I do!" Then she 
fell to shaking and crying.</p>
<p>Victorine said nothing, but went to a certain 
cupboard where she kept medicines and drugs 
of which she alone knew the properties, and 
there she mixed a draught, which she made her 
mistress take. Whatever its nature was, it was 
soothing. Theresa leaned back in her chair, 
still sobbing heavily from time to time, until at 
last she dropped into a kind of doze. Then 
Victorine softly lifted the neckerchief, which 
had fallen into its place, and looked at the mark. 
She did not speak; but her whole face was a 
fearful threat. After she had looked her fill, 
she smiled a deadly smile. And then she 
touched the soft bruised flesh with her lips, 
much as though Theresa were the child she had 
been twenty years ago. Soft as the touch was 
Theresa shivered, and started and half awoke. 
"Are they come?" she murmured; "Amade, 
Jean, Adle?" but without waiting for an 
answer she fell asleep again.</p>
<p>Victorine went quietly back to the cupboard 
where she kept her drugs, and stayed there, 
mixing something noiselessly. When she had 
done what she wanted, she returned to her 
mistress's bedroom, and looked at her, still sleeping. 
Then she began to arrange the room. No blue 
silk curtains and silver mirrors, now, as in the 
Rue Louis le Grand. A washed-out faded Indian 
chintz, and an old battered toilette service of 
Japan-ware; the disorderly signs of the count's 
late presence; an emptied flask of liqueur.</p>
<p>All the time Victorine arranged this room she 
kept saying to herself, "At last! At last!" 
Theresa slept through the daylight, slept late 
into the evening, leaning back where she had 
fallen in her chair. She was so motionless that 
Victorine appeared alarmed. Once or twice she 
felt her pulse, and gazed earnestly into the tear- 
stained face. Once, she very carefully lifted one 
of the eyelids, and holding a lighted taper near, 
peered into the eye. Apparently satisfied, she 
went out and ordered a basin of broth to be 
ready when she asked for it. Again she sat 
in deep silence; nothing stirred in the closed 
chamber; but in the street the carriages began 
to roll, and the footmen and torch-bearers to cry 
aloud their masters' names and titles, to show 
what carriage in that narrow street below, was 
entitled to precedence. A carriage stopped at 
the hotel of which they occupied the third floor. 
Then the bell of their apartment rang loudly--
rang violently. Victorine went out to see what 
it was that might disturb her darling--as she 
called Theresa to herself--her sleeping lady as 
she spoke of her to her servants.</p>
<p>She met those servants bringing in their 
master, the count, dead. Dead with a sword- 
wound received in some infamous struggle. 
Victorine stood and looked at him. "Better so," 
she muttered. "Better so. But, monseigneur, 
you shall take this with you, whithersoever your 
wicked soul is fleeing." And she struck him a 
stroke on his shoulder, just where Theresa's 
bruise was. It was as light a stroke as well 
could be; but this irreverence to the dead called 
forth indignation even from the hardened bearers 
of the body. Little recked Victorine. She 
turned her back on the corpse, went to her 
cupboard, took out the mixture she had made 
with so much care, poured it out upon the bare 
wooden floor, and smeared it about with her foot.</p>
<p>A fortnight later, when no news had come 
from Theresa for many weeks, a poor chaise 
was seen from the castle windows lumbering 
slowly up the carriage road to the gate. No 
one thought much of it; perhaps it was some 
friend of the housekeeper's; perhaps it was 
some humble relation of Mrs. Duke's (for many 
such had found out their cousin since her 
marriage). No one noticed the shabby carriage 
much, until the hall-porter was startled by the 
sound of the great bell pealing, and, on opening 
wide the hall-doors, saw standing before him the 
Mademoiselle Victorine of old days--thinner, 
sallower, in mourning. In the carriage sat 
Theresa, in the deep widow's weeds of those 
days. She looked out of the carriage-window 
wistfully, in beyond Joseph, the hall-porter.</p>
<p>"My father!" she cried eagerly, before 
Victorine could speak. "Is Sir Mark--well?" 
(" alive" was her first thought, but she dared 
not give the word utterance.)</p>
<p>"Call Mr. Duke!" said Joseph, speaking to 
some one unseen. Then he came forward. 
"God bless you, Miss! God bless you! And this 
day of all days! Sir Mark is well--leastways 
he's sadly changed. Where's Mr. Duke? Call 
him! My young lady's fainting!"</p>
<p>And this was Theresa's return home. None 
ever knew how much she had suffered since she 
had left home. If any one had known, Victorine 
would never have stood there dressed in 
that mourning. She put it on, sorely against her 
will, for the purpose of upholding the lying 
fiction of Theresa's having been a happy 
prosperous marriage. She was always indignant if 
any of the old servants fell back into the once 
familiar appellation of Miss Theresa. "The 
countess," she would say, in lofty rebuke.</p>
<p>What passed between Theresa and her father 
at that first interview no one ever knew. 
Whether she told him anything of her married 
life, or whether she only soothed the tears he 
shed on seeing her again, by sweet repetition 
of tender words and caresses--such as are the 
sugared pabulum of age as well as of infancy--
no one ever knew. Neither Duke nor his wife 
ever heard her allude to the time she had passed 
in Paris, except in the most cursory and superficial 
manner. Sir Mark was anxious to show her that 
all was forgiven, and would fain have displaced 
Bessy from her place as lady of the castle, arid 
made Theresa take the headship of the house, and 
sit at table where the mistress ought to be. And 
Bessy would have given up her onerous dignities 
without a word; for Duke was always more 
jealous for his wife's position than she herself was, 
but Theresa declined to assume any such place in 
the household, saying, in the languid way which 
now seemed habitual to her, that English 
housekeeping, and all the domestic arrangements of an 
English country house were cumbrous and wearisome 
to her; that if Bessy would continue to act 
as she had done hitherto, and would so forestal 
what must be her natural duties at some future 
period, she, Theresa, should be infinitely obliged.</p>
<p>Bessy consented, and in everything tried to 
remember what Theresa liked, and how affairs 
were ordered in the old Theresa days. She 
wished the servants to feel that "the countess" 
had equal rights with herself in the management 
of the house. But she, to whom the 
housekeeper takes her accounts--she in whose 
hands the power of conferring favours and 
privileges remains de facto--will always be 
held by servants as the mistress; and Theresa's 
claims soon sank into the background. At first, 
she was too broken-spirited, too languid, to care 
for anything but quiet rest in her father's 
companionship. They sat sometimes for hours hand 
in hand; or they sauntered out on the terraces, 
hardly speaking, but happy; because they were 
once more together, and once more on loving 
terms. Theresa grew strong during this time 
of gentle brooding peace. The pinched pale 
face of anxiety lined with traces of suffering, 
relaxed into the soft oval; the light came into 
the eyes, the colour came into the cheeks.</p>
<p>But, in the autumn after Theresa's return, 
Sir Mark died; it had been a gradual decline of 
strength, and his last moments were passed in 
her arms. Her new misfortune threw her back 
into the wan worn creature she had been when 
she first came home, a widow, to Crowley Castle; 
she shut herself up in her rooms, and allowed 
no one to come near her but Victorine. Neither 
Duke nor Bessy was admitted into the darkened 
rooms, which she had hung with black cloth 
in solemn funereal state.</p>
<p>Victorine's life since her return to the castle 
had been anything but peaceable. New powers 
had arisen in the housekeeper's room. Madam 
Brownlow had her maid, far more exacting than 
Madam Brownlow herself; and a new 
housekeeper reigned in the place of her who was 
formerly but an echo of Victorine's opinions. 
Victorine's own temper, too, was not improved 
by her four years abroad, and there was a 
general disposition among the servants to resist 
all her assumption of authority. She felt her 
powerlessness after a struggle or two, but 
treasured up her vengeance. If she had lost power 
over the household, however, there was no 
diminution of her influence over her mistress. 
It was her device at last that lured the countess 
out of her gloomy seclusion.</p>
<p>Almost the only creature Victorine cared for, 
besides Theresa, was the little Mary Brownlow. 
What there was of softness in her woman's 
nature, seemed to come out towards children; 
though, if the child had been a boy instead of a 
girl, it is probable that Victorine might not have 
taken it into her good graces. As it was, the 
French nurse and the English child were capital 
friends; and when Victorine sent Mary into the 
countess's room, and bade her not be afraid, 
but ask the lady in her infantine babble to come 
out and see Mary's snow-man, she knew that the 
little one, for her sake, would put her small hand 
into Theresa's, and thus plead with more 
success, because with less purpose, than any one 
else had been able to plead. Out came Theresa, 
colourless and sad, holding Mary by the hand. 
They went, unobserved as they thought, to the 
great gallery-window, and looked out into the 
court-yard; then Theresa returned to her rooms. 
But the ice was broken, and before the winter 
was over, Theresa fell into her old ways, and 
sometimes smiled, and sometimes even laughed, 
until chance visitors again spoke of her rare 
beauty and her courtly grace.</p>
<p>It was noticeable that Theresa revived first 
out of her lassitude to an interest in all Duke's 
pursuits. She grew weary of Bessy's small cares 
and domestic talk--now about the servants, 
now about her mother and the Parsonage, now 
about the parish. She questioned Duke about 
his travels, and could enter into his appreciation 
and judgement of foreign nations; she 
perceived the latent powers of his mind; she became 
impatient of their remaining dormant in country 
seclusion. She had spoken of leaving Crowley 
Castle, and of finding some other home, soon 
after her father's death; but both Duke and 
Bessy had urged her to stay with them, Bessy 
saying, in the pure innocence of her heart, how 
glad she was that, in the probably increasing 
cares of her nursery, Duke would have a 
companion so much to his mind.</p>
<p>About a year after Sir Mark's death, the 
member for Sussex died, and Theresa set herself 
to stir up Duke to assume his place. With 
some difficulty (for Bessy was passive: perhaps 
even opposed to the scheme in her quiet way), 
Theresa succeeded, and Duke was elected. She 
was vexed at Bessy's torpor, as she called it, in 
the whole affair; vexed as she now often was 
with Bessy's sluggish interest in all things 
beyond her immediate ken. Once, when Theresa 
tried to make Bessy perceive how Duke might 
shine and rise in his new sphere, Bessy burst 
into tears, and said, "You speak as if his 
presence here were nothing, and his fame in London 
everything. I cannot help fearing that he will 
leave off caring for all the quiet ways in which we 
have been so happy ever since we were married."</p>
<p>"But when he is here," replied Theresa, "and 
when he wants to talk to you of politics, of 
foreign news, of great public interests, you drag 
him down to your level of woman's cares."</p>
<p>"Do I?" said Bessy. "Do I drag him 
down? I wish I was cleverer; but you know, 
Theresa, I was never clever in anything but 
housewifery."</p>
<p>Theresa was touched for a moment by this 
humility.</p>
<p>"Yet, Bessy, you have a great deal of 
judgement, if you will but exercise it. Try and take 
an interest in all he cares for, as well as making 
him try and take an interest in home affairs."</p>
<p>But, somehow, this kind of conversation too 
often ended in dissatisfaction on both sides; and 
the servants gathered, from induction rather than 
from words, that the two ladies were not on the 
most cordial terms; however friendly they might 
wish to be, and might strive to appear. Madam 
Hawtrey, too, allowed her jealousy of Theresa to 
deepen into dislike. She was jealous because, 
in some unreasonable way, she had taken it into 
her head that Theresa's presence at the castle 
was the reason why she was not urged to take 
up her abode there on Sir Mark's death: as if 
there were not rooms and suites of rooms enough 
to lodge a wilderness of dowagers in the building, 
if the owner so wished. But Duke had 
certain ideas pretty strongly fixed in his mind; 
and one was a repugnance to his mother-in-law's 
constant company. But he greatly increased her 
income as soon as he had it in his power, and 
left it entirely to herself how she should spend it.</p>
<p>Having now the means of travelling about, 
Madam Hawtrey betook herself pretty frequently 
to such watering-places as were in vogue at that 
day, or went to pay visits at the houses of those 
friends who occasionally came lumbering up in 
shabby vehicles to visit their cousin Bessy at the 
castle. Theresa cared little for Madam 
Hawtrey's coldness; perhaps, indeed, never 
perceived it. She gave up striving with Bessy, 
too; it was hopeless to try to make her an 
intellectual ambitious companion to her 
husband. He had spoken in the House; he had 
written a pamphlet that made much noise; the 
minister of the day had sought him out, and 
was trying to attach him to the government. 
Theresa, with her Parisian experience 
of the way in which women influenced 
politics, would have given anything for the 
Brownlows to have taken a house in London. She 
longed to see the great politicians, to find 
herself in the thick of the struggle for place 
and power, the brilliant centre of all that was 
worth hearing and seeing in the kingdom. 
There had been some talk of this same London, 
house; but Bessy had pleaded against it earnestly 
while Theresa sat by in indignant silence, until 
she could bear the discussion no longer; going 
off to her own sitting-room, where Victorine 
was at work. Here her pent-up words found 
vent--not addressed to her servant, but not 
restrained before her:</p>
<p>"I cannot bear it--to see him cramped in by 
her narrow mind, to hear her weak selfish 
arguments, urged because she feels she would be out 
of place beside him. And Duke is hampered 
with this woman: he whose powers are unknown 
even to himself, or he would put her feeble 
nature on one side, and seek his higher 
atmosphere. How he would shine! How he does 
shine! Good Heaven! To think--"</p>
<p>And here she sank into silence, watched by 
Victorine's furtive eyes.</p>
<p>Duke had excelled all he had previously 
done by some great burst of eloquence, and 
the country rang with his words. He was 
to come down to Crowley Castle for a 
parliamentary recess, which occurred almost 
immediately after this. Theresa calculated the 
hours of each part of the complicated journey, 
and could have told to five minutes when he 
might be expected; but the baby was ill and 
absorbed all Bessy's attention. She was in the 
nursery by the cradle in which the child slept, 
when her husband came riding up to the castle 
gate. But Theresa was at the gate; her hair 
all out of powder, and blowing away into 
dishevelled curls, as the hood of her cloak fell back; 
her lips parted with a breathless welcome; her 
eyes shining out love and pride. Duke was but 
mortal. All London chanted his rising fame; 
and here in his home Theresa seemed to be the 
only person who appreciated him.</p>
<p>The servants clustered in the great hall; for it 
was now some length of time since lie had been 
at home. Victorine was there, with some head- 
gear for her lady; and when, in reply to his 
inquiry for his wife, the grave butler asserted that 
she was with young master, who was, they feared, 
very seriously ill, Victorine said, with the 
familiarity of an old servant, and as if to assuage 
Duke's anxiety: "Madam fancies the child is ill, 
because she can think of nothing but him, and 
perpetual watching has made her nervous." The 
child, however, was really ill; and after a brief 
greeting to her husband, Bessy returned to her 
nursery, leaving Theresa to question, to hear, to 
sympathise. That night she gave way to 
another burst of disparaging remarks on poor 
motherly homely Bessy, and that night Victorine 
thought she read a deeper secret in Theresa's 
heart.</p>
<p>The child was scarcely ever out of its mother's 
arms; but the illness became worse, and it was 
nigh unto death. Some cream had been set aside 
for the little wailing creature, and Victorine had 
unwittingly used it for the making of a cosmetic 
for her mistress. When the servant in charge 
of it reproved her, a quarrel began as to their 
respective mistress's right to give orders in the 
household. Before the dispute ended, pretty 
strong things had been said on both sides.</p>
<p>The child died. The heir was lifeless; the 
servants were in whispering dismay, and bustling 
discussion of their mourning; Duke felt the 
vanity of fame, as compared to a baby's life. 
Theresa was full of sympathy, but dared not 
express it to him; so tender was her heart 
becoming. Victorine regretted the death in her 
own way. Bessy lay speechless, and tearless; 
not caring for loving voices, nor for gentle 
touches; taking neither food nor drink; neither 
sleeping nor weeping. "Send for her mother," 
the doctor said; for Madam Hawtrey was away 
on her visits, and the letters telling her of her 
grandchild's illness had not reached her in the 
slow-delaying cross-country posts of those days. 
So she vas sent for; by a man riding express, 
as a quicker and surer means than the post.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the nurses, exhausted by their 
watching, found the care of little Mary by day, 
quite enough. Madam's maid sat up with Bessy 
for a night or two; Duke striding in from time 
to time through the dark hours to look at the 
white motionless face, which would have seemed 
like the face of one dead, but for the long- 
quivering sighs that came up from the 
overladen heart. The doctor tried his drugs, in 
vain, and then he tried again. This night, 
Victorine at her own earliest request, sat 
up instead of the maid. As usual, towards 
midnight, Duke came stealing in with shaded 
light. "Hush!" said Victorine, her finger 
on her lips. "She sleeps at last." Morning 
dawned faint and pale, and still she slept. The 
doctor came, and stole in on tip-toe, rejoicing in 
the effect of his drugs. They all stood round 
the bed; Duke, Theresa, Victorine. Suddenly 
the doctor--a strange change upon him, a 
strange fear in his face--felt the patient's pulse, 
put his car to her open lips, called for a glass 
--a feather. The mirror was not dimmed, the 
delicate fibres stirred not. Bessy was dead.</p>
<p>I pass rapidly over many months. Theresa 
was again overwhelmed with grief, or rather, I 
should say, remorse; for now that Bessy was 
gone, and buried out of sight, all her innocent 
virtues, all her feminine homeliness, came vividly 
into Theresa's mind--not as wearisome, but as 
admirable, qualities of which she had been too 
blind to perceive the value. Bessy had been 
her own old companion too, in the happy days 
of childhood, and of innocence. Theresa rather 
shunned than sought Duke's company now. 
She remained at the castle, it is true, and Madam 
Hawtrey, as Theresa's only condition of 
continuing where she was, came to live under the 
same roof. Duke felt his wife's death deeply, 
but reasonably, as became his character. He 
was perplexed by Theresa's bursts of grief, 
knowing, as he dimly did, that she and Bessy 
had not lived together in perfect harmony. But 
he was much in London now; a rising statesman; 
and when, in autumn, he spent some time 
at the castle, he was full of admiration for the 
strangely patient way in which Theresa behaved 
towards the old lady. It seemed to Duke that 
in his absence Madam Hawtrey had assumed 
absolute power in his household, and that the high- 
spirited Theresa submitted to her fantasies with 
even more docility than her own daughter would 
have done. Towards Mary, Theresa was always 
kind and indulgent.</p>
<p>Another autumn came; and before it went, 
old ties were renewed, and Theresa was pledged 
to become her cousin's wife.</p>
<p>There were two people strongly affected by 
this news when it was promulgated; one--and 
this was natural under the circumstances--was 
Madam Hawtrey; who chose to resent the 
marriage as a deep personal offence to herself 
as well as to her daughter's memory, and who 
sternly rejecting all Theresa's entreaties, and 
Duke's invitation to continue her residence at 
the castle, went off into lodgings in the village. 
The other person strongly affected by the news, 
was Victorine.</p>
<p>From being a dry active energetic middle- 
aged woman, she now, at the time of Theresa's 
engagement, sank into the passive languor of 
advanced life. It seemed as if she felt no more 
need of effort, or strain, or exertion. She sought 
solitude; liked nothing better than to sit in 
her room adjoining Theresa's dressing-room, 
sometimes sunk in a reverie, sometimes 
employed on an intricate piece of knitting with 
almost spasmodic activity. But wherever 
Theresa went, thither would Victorine go. Theresa 
had imagined that her old nurse would prefer 
being left at the castle, in the soothing 
tranquillity of the country, to accompanying her and 
her husband to the house in Grosvenor-square, 
which they had taken for the parliamentary 
season. But the mere offer of a choice seemed 
to irritate Victorine inexpressibly. She looked 
upon the proposal as a sign that Theresa 
considered her as superannuated--that her nursling 
was weary of her, and wished to supplant her 
services by those of a younger maid. It seemed 
impossible to dislodge this idea when it had once 
entered into her head, and it led to frequent 
bursts of temper, in which she violently upbraided 
Theresa for her ingratitude towards so faithful 
a follower.</p>
<p>One day, Victorine went a little further in 
her expressions than usual, and Theresa, usually 
so forbearing towards her, turned at last. 
"Really, Victorine!" she said, "this is misery 
to both of us. You say you never feel so wicked 
as when I am near you; that my ingratitude is 
such as would be disowned by fiends; what can 
I, what must I do? You say you are never so 
unhappy as when you are near me; must we, then, 
part? Would that be for your happiness?"</p>
<p>"And is that what it has come to!" exclaimed 
Victorine. "In my country they reckon a building 
secure against wind and storm and all the 
ravages of time, if the first mortar used has been 
tempered with human blood. But not even our 
joint secret, though it was tempered well with 
blood, can hold our lives together! How much 
less all the care, all the love, that I lavished upon 
you in the days of my youth and strength!"</p>
<p>Theresa came close to the chair in which 
Victorine was seated. She took hold of her hand 
and held it fast in her own. "Speak, Victorine," 
said she, hoarsely, "and tell me what you mean. 
<em>What</em> is our joint secret? And what do you 
mean by its being a secret of blood? Speak out. 
I WILL know."</p>
<p>"As if you do not know!" replied Victorine, 
harshly. "You don't remember my visits to 
Bianconi, the Italian chemist in the Marais, 
long ago?" She looked into Theresa's face, to 
see if her words had suggested any deeper meaning 
than met the ear. No; Theresa's look was 
stern, but free and innocent.</p>
<p>"You told me you went there to learn the 
composition of certain unguents, and cosmetics, 
and domestic medicines."</p>
<p>"Ay, and paid high for my knowledge, too," 
said Victorine, with a low chuckle. "I learned 
more than you have mentioned, my lady countess. 
I learnt the secret nature of many drugs 
--to speak plainly, I learnt the art of poisoning. 
And," suddenly standing up, "it was for your 
sake I learnt it. For your service you who 
would fain cast me off in my old age. For you!"</p>
<p>Theresa blanched to a deadly white. But she 
tried to move neither feature nor limb, nor to 
avert her eyes for one moment from the eyes 
that defied her. "For my service, Victorine"?"</p>
<p>"Yes! The quieting draught was all ready 
for your husband, when they brought him home 
dead."</p>
<p>"Thank God his death does not lie at your 
door!"</p>
<p>"Thank God?" mocked Victorine. "The 
wish for his death does lie at your door; and 
the intent to rid you of him does lie at my door. 
And I am not ashamed of it. Not I! It was 
not for myself I would have done it, but because 
you suffered so. He had struck you, whom I 
had nursed on my breast."</p>
<p>"Oh, Victorine!" said Theresa, with, a 
shudder. "Those days are past. Do not let 
us recall them. I was so wicked because I was 
so miserable; and now I am so happy, so 
inexpressibly happy, that--do let me try to make 
you happy too!"</p>
<p>"You ought to try," said Victorine, not yet 
pacified; "can't you see how the incomplete 
action once stopped by Fate, was tried again, 
and with success; and how you are now reaping 
the benefit of my sin, if sin it was?"</p>
<p>"Victorine! I do not know what you mean!" 
But some terror must have come over her, she 
so trembled and so shivered.</p>
<p>"Do you not indeed? Madame Brownlow, 
the country girl from Crowley Parsonage, needed 
sleep, and would fain forget the little child's 
death that was pressing on her brain. I helped 
the doctor to his end. She sleeps now, and she 
has met her baby before this, if priests' tales 
are true. And you, my beauty, my queen, 
you reign in her stead! Don't treat the poor 
Victorine as if she were mad, and speaking in 
her madness. I have heard of tricks like that 
being played, when the crime was done, and the 
criminal of use no longer."</p>
<p>That evening, Duke was surprised by his wife's 
entreaty and petition that she might leave him, 
and return with Victorine and her other 
personal servants to the seclusion of Crowley Castle. 
She, the great London toast, the powerful 
enchantress of society, and most of all, the 
darling wife and true companion, with this sudden 
fancy for this complete retirement, and for 
leaving her husband when he was first fully 
entering into the comprehension of all that 
a wife might be! Was it ill health? Only 
last night she had been in dazzling beauty, 
in brilliant spirits; this morning only, she had 
been so merry and tender. But Theresa 
denied that she was in any way indisposed; and 
seemed suddenly so unwilling to speak of 
herself, and so much depressed, that Duke saw 
nothing for it but to grant her wish and let her 
go. He missed her terribly. No more pleasant 
tte--tte breakfasts, enlivened by her sense 
and wit, and cheered by her pretty caressing 
ways. No gentle secretary now, to sit by his side 
through long long hours, never weary. When 
he went into society, he no longer found his 
appearance watched and waited for by the loveliest 
woman there. When he came home from the 
House at night, there was no one to take an 
interest in his speeches, to be indignant at all that 
annoyed him, and charmed and proud of all the 
admiration he had won. He longed for the 
time to come when he would be able to go down 
for a day or two to see his wife; for her letters 
appeared to him dull and flat after her bright 
companionship. No wonder that her letters came 
out of a heavy heart, knowing what she knew.</p>
<p>She scarcely dared to go near Victorine, 
whose moods were becoming as variable as 
though she were indeed the mad woman she had 
tauntingly defied Theresa to call her. At times 
she was miserable because Theresa looked so 
ill, and seemed so deeply unhappy. At other 
times she was jealous because she fancied 
Theresa shrank from her and avoided her. So, 
wearing her life out with passion, Victorine's 
health grew daily worse and worse during that 
summer.</p>
<p>Theresa's only comfort seemed to be little 
Mary's society. She seemed as though she 
could not lavish love enough upon the 
motherless child, who repaid Theresa's affection 
with all the pretty demonstrativeness of 
her age. She would carry the little three-year-old 
maiden in her arms when she went to 
see Victorine, or would have Mary playing 
about in her dressing-room, if the old French-woman, 
for some jealous freak, would come 
and arrange her lady's hair with her 
trembling hands. To avoid giving offence to 
Victorine, Theresa engaged no other maid; to 
shun over-much or over-frank conversation with 
Victorine, she always had little Mary with her 
when there was a chance of the French waiting-maid 
coming in. For, the presence of the child 
was a holy restraint even on Victorine's tongue; 
she would sometimes check her fierce temper, to 
caress the little creature playing at her knees; 
and would only dart a covert bitter sting at 
Theresa under the guise of a warning against 
ingratitude, to Mary.</p>
<p>Theresa drooped and drooped in this dreadful 
life. She sought out Madam Hawtrey, and 
prayed her to come on a long visit to the castle. 
She was lonely, she said, asking for madam's 
company as a favour to herself. Madam 
Hawtrey was difficult to persuade; but the more 
she resisted, the more Theresa entreated; and, 
when once madam was at the castle, her own 
daughter had never been so dutiful, so humble 
a slave to her slightest fancy as was the proud 
Theresa now.</p>
<p>Yet, for all this, the lady of the castle drooped 
and drooped, and when Duke came down to see 
his darling he was in utter dismay at her looks. 
Yet she said she was well enough, only tired. 
If she had anything more upon her mind, 
she refused him her confidence. He watched 
her narrowly, trying to forestal her smallest 
desires. He saw her tender affection for Mary, 
and thought he had never seen so lovely and 
tender a mother to another woman's child. He 
wondered at her patience with Madam Hawtrey, 
remembering how often his own stock had been 
exhausted by his mother-in-law, and how the 
brilliant Theresa had formerly scouted and 
flouted at the vicar's wife. With all this 
renewed sense of his darling's virtues and charms, 
the idea of losing her was too terrible to bear.</p>
<p>He would listen to no pleas, to no objections. 
Before he returned to town, where his presence 
was a political necessity, he sought the best 
medical advice that could be had in the 
neighbourhood. The doctors came; they could make 
but little out of Theresa, if her vehement 
assertion were true that she had nothing on her 
mind. Nothing.</p>
<p>"Humour him at least, my dear lady!" said 
the doctor, who had known Theresa from her 
infancy, but who, living at the distant county 
own, was only called in on the Olympian 
occasions of great state illnesses. "Humour your 
husband, and perhaps do yourself some good 
too, by consenting to his desire that you should 
have change of air. Brighthelmstone is a quiet 
village by the sea-side. Consent, like a gracious 
lady, to go there for a few weeks."</p>
<p>So, Theresa, worn out with opposition, 
consented, and Duke made all the arrangements 
for taking her, and little Mary, and the 
necessary suite of servants, to Brighton, as we 
call it now. He resolved in his own mind that 
Theresa's personal attendant should be some 
woman young enough to watch and wait upon 
her mistress, and not Victorine, to whom Theresa 
was in reality a servant. But of this plan, neither 
Theresa nor Victorine knew anything until the 
former was in the carriage with her husband 
some miles distant from the castle. Then he, a 
little exultant in the good management by which 
he supposed he had spared his wife the pain and 
trouble of decision, told her that Victorine was 
left behind, and that a new accomplished London 
maid would await her at her journey's end.</p>
<p>Theresa only exclaimed "O! What will 
Victorine say?" and covered her face, and sat 
shivering and speechless.</p>
<p>What Victorine did say, when she found out 
the trick, as she esteemed it, that had been 
played upon her, was too terrible to repeat. She 
lashed herself up into an ungoverned passion; 
and then became so really and seriously ill that 
the servants went to fetch Madam Hawtrey in 
terror and dismay. But when that lady came, 
Victorine shut her eyes, and refused to look at 
her. "She has got her daughter in her hand! 
I will not look!" Shaking all the time she 
uttered these awe-stricken words, as if she were 
in an ague-fit. "Bring the countess back to 
me. Let <em>her</em> face the dead woman standing there, 
I will not do it. They wanted her to sleep--and 
so did the countess, that she might step into her 
lawful place. Theresa, Theresa, where are you? 
You tempted me. What I did, I did in your 
service. And you have gone away, and left me alone 
with the dead woman! It was the same drug as 
the doctor gave, after all--only he gave little, 
and I gave much. My lady the countess spent 
her money well, when she sent me to the old 
Italian to learn his trade. Lotions for the 
complexion, and a discriminating use of poisonous 
drugs. I discriminated, and Theresa profited; 
and now she is his wife, and has left me here 
alone with the dead woman. Theresa, Theresa, 
come back and save me from the dead woman!"</p>
<p>Madam Hawtrey stood by, horror-stricken. 
"Fetch the vicar," said she, under her breath, 
to a servant.</p>
<p>"The village doctor is coming," said some one 
near. "How she raves! Is it delirium?"</p>
<p>"It is no delirium," said Bessy's mother. 
"Would to Heaven it were!"</p>
<p>Theresa had a happy day with her husband at 
Brighthelmstone before he set off on his return 
to London. She watched him riding away, his 
servant following with his portmanteau. Often 
and often did Duke look back at the figure of 
his wife, waving her handkerchief, till a turn of 
the road hid her from his sight. He had to pass 
through a little village not ten miles from his 
home, and there a servant, with his letters and 
further luggage, was to await him. There he 
found a mysterious, imperative note, requiring 
his immediate presence at Crowley Castle. 
Something in the awe-stricken face of the 
servant from the castle, led Duke to question 
him. But all he could say was, that Victorine 
lay dying, and that Madam Hawtrey had said 
that after that letter the master was sure to 
return, and so would need no luggage. 
Something lurked behind, evidently. Duke rode home 
at speed. The vicar was looking out for him. 
"My dear boy," said he, relapsing into the old 
relations of tutor and pupil, "prepare yourself."</p>
<p>"What for?" said Duke, abruptly; for the 
being told to prepare himself, without being 
told for what, irritated him in his present mood. 
"Victorine is dead?"</p>
<p>"No! She says she will not die until she has 
seen you, and got you to forgive her, if Madam 
Hawtrey will not. But first read this: it is a 
terrible confession, made by her before me, a 
magistrate, believing herself to be on the point 
of death!"</p>
<p>Duke read the paper--containing little more 
in point of detail than I have already given--
the horrible words taken down in the short-hand 
in which the vicar used to write his mild prosy 
sermons: his pupil knew the character of old. 
Duke read it twice. Then he said: "She is 
raving, poor creature!" But for all that, his 
heart's blood ran cold, and he would fain not 
have faced the woman, but would rather have 
remained in doubt to his dying day.</p>
<p>He went up the stairs three steps at a time, 
and then turned and faced the vicar, with a look 
like the stern calmness of death. "I wish to 
see her alone." He turned out all the watching 
women, and then he went to the bedside where 
Victoriue sat, half propped up with pillows, 
watching all his doings and his looks, with her 
hollow awful eyes. "Now, Victorine, I will 
read this paper aloud to you. Perhaps your 
mind has been wandering; but you understand 
me now?" A feeble murmur of assent met his 
listening ear. "If any statement in this paper 
be not true, make me a sign. Hold up your hand 
for God's sake hold up your hand. And if 
you can do it with truth in this, your hour of 
dying, Lord have mercy upon you; but if you 
cannot hold up your hand, then Lord have 
mercy upon me!"</p>
<p>He read the paper slowly; clause by clause 
he read the paper. No sign; no uplifted hand. 
At the end she spoke, and he bent his head to 
listen. "The Countess--Theresa you know--
she who has left me to die alone--she"--then 
mortal strength failed, and Duke was left alone 
in the chamber, of death.</p>
<p>He stayed in the chamber many minutes, quite 
still. Then he left the room, and said to the 
first domestic he could find, "The woman is 
dead. See that she is attended to." But he 
went to the vicar, and had a long long talk with, 
him. He sent a confidential servant for little 
Mary--on some pretext, hardly careful, or 
plausible enough; but his mood was desperate, 
and he seemed to forget almost everything but 
Bessy, his first wife, his innocent girlish bride.</p>
<p>Theresa could ill spare her little darling, and 
was perplexed by the summons; but an explanation 
of it was to come in a day or two. It came.</p>
<p>"Victorine is dead; I need say no more. She 
could not carry her awful secret into the next 
world, but told all. I can think of nothing but 
my poor Bessy, delivered over to the cruelty of 
such a woman. And you, Theresa, I leave you 
to your conscience, for you have slept in my 
bosom. Henceforward I am a stranger to you. 
By the time you receive this, I, and my child, and 
that poor murdered girl's mother, will have left 
England. What will be our next step I know 
not. My agent will do for you what you need."</p>
<p>Theresa sprang up and rang her bell with 
mad haste. "Get me a horse!" she cried, "and 
bid William be ready to ride with me for his 
life--for my life--along the coast, to Dover!"</p>
<p>They rode and they galloped through the night, 
scarcely staying to bait their horses. But when 
they came to Dover, they looked out to sea upon 
the white sails that bore Duke and his child 
away. Theresa was too late, and it broke her 
heart. She lies buried in Dover churchyard. 
After long years Duke returned to England; but 
his place in parliament knew him no more, and 
his daughter's husband sold Crowley Castle to a 
stranger.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE SIDE-ROOM WAS ATTENDED BY A DOCTOR."/>
<chapter>
<p>How the Doctor found his way into our 
society, none of us can tell. It did not occur to 
us to inquire into the matter at the time, and 
now the point is lost in the dim obscurity of 
the past. We only know that he appeared 
suddenly and mysteriously. It was shortly after 
we had formed our Mutual Admiration Society, 
in this very room in Mrs. Lirriper's Lodgings. 
We were discussing things in general in our 
usual amiable way, admiring poets, worshipping 
heroes, and taking all men and all things for 
what they seemed. We were young and 
ingenuous, pleased with our own ideas, and with 
each other's; full of belief and trust in all things 
good and noble, and with no hatred, save for 
what was false, and base, and mean. In this 
spirit we were commenting with indignation 
upon a new heresy with regard to the age of 
the world, when a strange voice broke in upon 
our conversation.</p>
<p>"I beg your pardon; you are wrong. The 
age of the world is exactly three millions eight 
hundred and ninety-seven thousand four 
hundred and twenty-five years, eight months, 
fourteen days, nine hours, thirty-five minutes, and 
seventeen seconds."</p>
<p>At the first sound of this mysterious voice we 
all looked up, and perceived standing on the 
hearth-rug before the fire by which you sit, 
Major, a little closely-knit, middle-aged man, 
dressed in black. He had a hooked nose, piercing 
black eyes, and a grizzled beard, and his head 
was covered with a shock of crisp dark hair. 
Our first impulse was to resent the stranger's 
interference as an impertinence, and to demand 
what business he had in that room in Mrs. 
Lirriper's house, sacred to the social meetings of 
the Mutual Admiration Society? But we no 
sooner set eyes upon him than the impulse was 
checked, and we remained for a minute or so 
gazing upon the stranger in silence. We saw 
at a glance that he was no mere meddling fool. 
He was considerably older than any of us there 
present, his face beamed with intelligence, his 
eyes sparkled with humour, and his whole 
expression was that of a man confident of mental 
strength and superiority. The look on his face 
seemed to imply that he had reckoned us all up 
in an instant. So much were we impressed by 
the stranger's appearance, that we quite forgot 
the queries which had naturally occurred too us 
when he interrupted our conversation: Who are 
you? Where do you belong to? How did you 
come here? It was allowable for a member of 
the society to introduce a friend; but none of 
us had introduced him, and we were the only 
members in the room. None of us had seen 
him enter, nor had we been conscious of his 
presence until we heard his voice. On 
comparing notes afterwards, it was found that the 
same thought had flitted across all our minds. 
Had he come down the chimney? Or up through 
the floor? But at the time, as we saw no 
smoke and smelt no brimstone, we dismissed 
the suspicion for the more natural explanation 
that some member had introduced him, and had 
gone away, leaving him there. I was mentally 
framing a civil question with the view of 
elucidating this point, when the stranger, who spoke 
with a foreign accent, again addressed us.</p>
<p>"I trust," he said, "I am not intruding upon 
your society; but the subject of your discussion 
is one that I have studied deeply, and I was 
betrayed into a remark by--by my enthusiasm: I 
beg you will pardon me."</p>
<p>He said this so affably, and with so much 
dignified politeness of an elderly kind, that we 
were all disarmed, and protested, in a body, that 
there was no occasion for any apology. And it 
followed upon this, in some sort of insensible 
way, that the stranger came and took a seat 
among us, and spent the evening with us, proving 
a match for us in the airy gaiety of our discussions, 
and more than a match for us in all kinds 
of knowledge. We were all charmed with the 
stranger, and he appeared to be highly pleased 
with us. When he went away he shook hands 
with us with marked cordiality and warmth, and 
left us his card. It bore this inscription:</p>
<p>DOCTOR GOLIATH, PH.D.</p>
<p>After this, the doctor regularly frequented our 
society, and we took his coming as a matter of 
course; being quite content to accept his great 
learning and numerous accomplishments as a 
certificate of his eligibility for membership in 
our fraternity. It was no wonder that we came 
to look upon the doctor as a great personage. 
His fund of knowledge was inexhaustible. He 
seemed to know everything--not generally and 
in a superficial manner--but particularly and 
minutely. It was not, however, by making a 
parade of his knowledge that he gave us this 
impression. He let it out incidentally, as 
occasion required. If language were the topic, 
the doctor, by a few off-hand remarks, made it 
plain to us that he was acquainted with almost 
every language under the sun. He spoke 
English with an accent which partook of the 
character of almost every modern tongue. If law 
came up, he could discourse of codes and 
judgements with the utmost familiarity, citing act, 
chapter, and section, as if the whole study of his 
life had been law. So with politics, history, 
geology, chemistry, mechanics, and even 
medicine. Nothing came amiss to Doctor Goliath. 
He was an animated Cyclopdia of universal 
knowledge. But there was nothing of the pedant 
about him. He treated his learning as bagatelle; 
he threw off his knowledge as other people throw 
off jokes; he was only serious when he mixed 
a salad, brewed a bowl of punch, or played a 
game of piquet, he was not at all proud of 
being able to translate the Ratcatcher's Daughter 
into six languages, including Greek and Arabic; 
but he believed he was the only man on the face 
of the earth who knew the exact proportions of 
oil and vinegar requisite for the proper mixture 
of a potato-salad. It was impossible to resist 
the spell of Doctor Goliath's wonderful character. 
He was learned in the highest degree; yet he had 
all the reckless jollity of a schoolboy, and could 
talk nonsense and make sport of wisdom and 
philosophy better than any of us. He took our 
society by storm; he became an oracle; we 
quoted him as an authority, and spoke of him 
as <em>the</em> doctor, as if there were no other doctor 
on the face of the earth.</p>
<p>Shortly before the doctor's appearance among 
us, we, the members of the Mutual Admiration 
Society, had sworn eternal friendship. We had 
vowed ever to love each other, ever to believe in 
each other, ever to be true and just and kindly 
towards each other, and never to be estranged 
one from another either by prosperity or 
adversity. As a sign and symbol of our brotherhood, 
we had agreed to call each other by 
familiar and affectionate abbreviations of our 
Christian names; and, in pursuance of this 
amiable scheme, we had arranged to present 
each other with loving cups. As we were a 
society of little wealth, except in the matter of 
loving kindness and mutual admiration, it was 
resolved that the cups should be fashioned of 
pewter, of the measure of one quart, and each 
with two handles. The order was given, the 
loving-cups were, made, and each bore an 
inscription in this wise: "To Tom from Sam, 
Jack, Will, Ned, Charley, and Harry, a token of 
Friendship;" this inscription being only varied 
as regarded the relative positions of donors and 
recipient. The cups were all ready, and nothing 
remained to be done but to pay the money and 
bring them away from the shop of our Benvenuto 
Cellini, which was situated in the parish of St. 
Martin's-in-the-Fields. A delay, however, 
occurred, owing to circumstances which I need 
not particularise further than to say, that they 
were circumstances over which we had no 
control.</p>
<p>This delay, owing to the obduracy of these 
uncontrollable circumstances, continued for some 
weeks, when, one evening, Tom came in with a 
large brown paper parcel under his arm. It was 
a parcel of strange and unwonted aspect.</p>
<p>"Ha! ha!" cried the doctor, "what have 
we here? Say, my Tom, is it something to eat, 
something to drink, something perchance to 
smoke? For in such things only doth my soul 
delight,"</p>
<p>"I don't believe you when you say that, 
doctor," said Tom, quite seriously; for Tom had 
fallen more prostrate than any of us before the 
doctor's great character.</p>
<p>"Not believe me?" cried the doctor. "I 
mean it. Man, sir, is an animal whose only 
misfortune is, that lie is endowed with the 
accursed power of thinking. If I were not 
possessed by this evil spirit of Thought, do you 
know what I would do?"</p>
<p>Tom could form no idea what he would do.</p>
<p>"Well, then," said the doctor, "I would lie 
all day in the sun, and eat potato-salad out of 
a trough!"</p>
<p>"What! like a pig?" Tom exclaimed.</p>
<p>"Yes, like a pig," said the doctor. "I never 
see a pig lying on clean straw, with his snout 
poked into a delightful mess of barley-meal and 
cabbage-leaves, but I become frightfully 
envious!"</p>
<p>"Oh, doctor!" we all exclaimed in chorus.</p>
<p>"Fact. I say to myself, How much better 
off, how much happier, is this pig than I! To 
obtain my potato-salad, without which life 
would be a blank, I have to do a deed my soul 
abhors. I have to work. The pig has no work 
to do for that troughful of barley-meal and 
cabbage-leaves. Because I am an animal endowed 
with the power of thought and reason, I was 
sent to school and taught to read. See what 
misfortune, what misery, that has brought upon 
me! You laugh, but am I not driven to read 
books, and parliamentary debates, and leading 
articles? I was induced the other day to attend 
a social congress. If I had been a pig, I should 
not have had to endure that."</p>
<p>"Ah, but, doctor," said Tom, "the pig has no 
better part."</p>
<p>The doctor burst into a yell of exultation.</p>
<p>"What! The pig no better part? Ha! 
ha! Sir, the better part of pig is pork. The 
butcher comes to me, and to the pig alike; 
but what remains of me when he has done his 
fell work? You put me in a box and screw me 
down, and stow me away out of sight; and you 
pretend to grieve for me. But the pig--you eat 
him, and rejoice in earnest! And that reminds 
me that I shall have a pork-chop for supper. By 
the way, is it a lettuce you have in that paper 
parcel, Tom?"</p>
<p>"It is not a lettuce, doctor."</p>
<p>"Not a lettuce! Ha! I see something glitter 
--precious metal--gold? no, silver! to obtain 
which, in a commensurate quantity, I would 
commit crimes--murder!"</p>
<p>"Oh, doctor," said Tom, "you are giving 
yourself a character which you don't deserve."</p>
<p>"Am I?" said the doctor. "You don't 
know me. And after all, what is murder? 
Nothing. You kill two or three of your 
fellow-creatures--a dozen for that matter; what 
then? There are plenty more. Do you know 
what is the population of the earth? I will 
tell you. Exactly one thousand three hundred 
millions eight hundred and ninety-nine thousand 
six hundred and twenty souls. How many 
murders are committed in the course of a year do you 
imagine? You think only those you read of in 
the newspapers. Bah! An intimate knowledge 
of the subject enables me to inform you that the 
number of murders committed in Great Britain 
and Ireland, and the Channel Islands, annually, 
amounts to fifteen thousand seven hundred and 
forty-five. It is one of the laws of nature for 
keeping down the population. Every man who 
commits a murder, obeys this law."</p>
<p>Tom's hair was beginning to stand on end, for 
the doctor said all this with a terrible fierceness 
of manner. His strange philosophy was not 
without its effect upon the rest of us. We had 
been accustomed to a good deal of freedom in 
our discussions, but we had never ventured upon 
anything so audacious as this.</p>
<p>"Come, Tom," said the doctor, "unveil your 
treasure, and let me see if it be worth my while 
lying in wait for you in the dark lanes as you go 
home to-night."</p>
<p>"Well, no, it isn't, doctor," said Tom, "for the 
article is only of pewter." And Tom uncovered 
his loving-cup. Circumstances had relented in 
Tom's case, and he had gone and paid for his 
own loving-cup.</p>
<p>"Pewter!" said the doctor. "Bah! it is not 
worth my while; but if it had been silver, now, 
why then I might--" And the doctor put on 
a diabolical expression, that seemed to signify 
highway robbery accompanied with violence, 
and murder followed by immediate dissection. 
Presently the doctor noticed the inscription. 
"Ha! ha!" he said, "what is this? An 
inscription! ' To Tom, from Sam, Jack, Will, 
Ned, Charley, and Harry--a token of Friendship.' 
Friendship? Ha! ha! 'tis but a name, 
an empty name, a mockery, a delusion, and a 
snare. I tell you there is no such thing in the 
world."</p>
<p>"Oh, don't say that, doctor!" cried Tom, 
looking quite hurt.</p>
<p>"Ah," returned the doctor, "you will find it 
out. I have always found it out; and since I 
formed my first friendship and was deceived 
--it is now--let me see how many years?--
one thousand eight hundred--and but no 
matter."</p>
<p>The doctor paused, as if oppressed with painful 
recollections.</p>
<p>"Ned," said Sam, leaning across to me, "do 
you know what I think the doctor is?"</p>
<p>"No," I said.</p>
<p>"Well," he said, "hang'd if I don't think he 
is the Wandering Jew. Look at his boots!"</p>
<p>I looked at his boots. They were not neat 
boots: that was all I perceived about them.</p>
<p>"Don't you observe," said Sam, "how flat 
and trodden down they are? The doctor has 
done a deal of walking in those boots. Mark 
their strange and ancient shape! Look at 
the dust upon them--it is the dust of 
centuries!"</p>
<p>The doctor was roaring with laughter at the 
idea of our mutual presentation scheme, and 
was calling us "innocents," and Tom's loving- 
cup a "mug."</p>
<p>Tom was getting red in the face and looking 
ashamed. In fact, we were all looking rather 
sheepish; for it had never struck us until now, 
how silly and sentimental we all were. We 
said nothing to the doctor about the six other 
loving-cups that were waiting to be paid for 
and claimed; and when Tom, with a face as red 
as a coal, covered up his "mug" as the doctor 
called it and put it away, we were glad to 
change the subject, to escape from our 
embarrassment. We were so thoroughly ashamed of 
ourselves, that we endeavoured to redeem our 
characters in the eyes of the doctor, by plunging 
recklessly into any depth of cynical opinion that 
he chose to sound. And the doctor, in the 
course of time, led us to the very bottom of 
the pit of cynicism. As we listened to him, and 
held converse with him day after day, we began 
to see how very green and unsophisticated we 
had all been. We came to know that the poets 
and heroes whom we had worshipped were 
nothing but humbugs and pretenders; that the 
great statesmen whom we had believed in and 
admired, were blunderers or traitors; that the 
mighty potentates whose power and sagacity 
we had extolled, were tyrannical miscreants, 
or puppets in the hands of others; that the 
philanthropists whom all men praised, were 
conceited self-seeking hypocrites; that the 
patriots whose names we had reverenced in 
common with all the world, were scoundrels of 
the deepest dye. The doctor's influence led us 
on insensibly, step by step. How could we 
resist it? It was a fascination. He knew 
everything, could prove everything, and had 
such a store of facts that we had never heard 
of in support of his conclusions, that it was 
impossible, with our limited knowledge, to 
withstand him. We were shocked at first; but, as 
the revolution proceeded, we got used to the 
sight of blood, and saw the heads of our heroes 
fall, with the utmost indifference. At length 
we came to revel in it, and sought for new 
victims, that we might demolish them and do 
our despite upon them. The doctor led the way 
more boldly as we advanced. He hinted darkly 
at crimes in which he had had a hand, and at 
crimes which he would yet commit when the 
opportunity arrived. Whenever a murder was 
committed, the doctor was the friend and 
advocate of the murderer, and vowed fierce 
vengeance against the judge and jury who 
condemned him to be hanged. When news of war 
and disaster came, he rubbed his hands and 
gloated over it with glee, because he had 
prophesied what would happen through the 
imbecility and treason of infamous scoundrels 
who called themselves statesmen and 
generals.</p>
<p>From a Mutual Admiration Society, we 
became a society of iconoclasts. Tom, and 
Jack, and Sam, and Harry, and the rest of us, 
who had begun by swearing eternal friendship, 
were now bitter disputants, despising each 
other's mental qualities, calling each other 
duffers behind each other's backs, and laughing 
all the old modest pretensions to scorn. The 
loving-cups had faded out of memory. I passed 
the shop of our Benveuuto Cellini, the pewterer, 
one day, and saw the whole six exposed in 
the window for sale. I called upon Tom, to 
show him an article demolishing a popular 
author whom we had once idolised, and I 
noticed his loving-cup stowed away under the 
table with a waste-paper-basket and a spittoon. 
It had grown dull and battered like a public- 
house pot, and was filled with short black pipes, 
and matches, and ends of cigars, and rubbish. 
I kicked it playfully with my foot, and 
laughed; and Tom blushed and put it away out 
of sight.</p>
<p>Our society, in its new form, prospered 
exceedingly. We became famous for the freedom 
of our speech and the audacity of our opinions. 
Our company was much sought after, and we 
were proud of our originality and independence. 
We spent all our leisure hours together, and 
our defiant discussions kept us in a constant 
state of mental intoxication. But a sober 
moment arrived.</p>
<p>Tom and I sat together, one gloomy day, 
alone. We were solemn and moody, and smoked 
in silence. At length Tom said:</p>
<p>"Ned, I passed the shop to-day, and saw 
those six loving-cups in the window."</p>
<p>I replied, fretfully, "Bother the loving-cups!"</p>
<p>"No," said Tom, "I have other thoughts at 
this present moment; I have had them often, 
but have smothered them--smothered them 
ruthlessly, Ned; but they have always come to 
life again. They are very lively to-night--owing, 
perhaps, to the fog, or the state of my liver, or 
the state of my conscience--and I can't 
smother them."</p>
<p>"What do you mean, Tom?"</p>
<p>"You remember when we ordered the cups?'</p>
<p>"Yes."</p>
<p>"The doctor came among us shortly afterwards."</p>
<p>"He did."</p>
<p>"And we didn't carry out our intention."</p>
<p>"No. You paid for yours, Tom, and brought 
it away, but the rest are still unredeemed pledges 
of affection."</p>
<p>"Exactly," said Tom; "and that was owing 
to the doctor. He laughed at us. He made 
us ashamed of ourselves. He made me ashamed 
of myself. But I had paid for my cup, and 
brought it away, and the thing was done. If I 
had not done it when I did, I should never have 
done it. What were we ashamed of?"</p>
<p>"Silliness," I said.</p>
<p>"No, kindliness and good feeling, which we 
can't have too much of in this short journey."</p>
<p>I did not answer. Tom went on.</p>
<p>"This doctor has upset us all. He has 
changed our nature. He has turned the milk 
of human kindness that was in us, sour. He 
is a very fascinating person, I grant; but who 
is he? None of us know. He came among us 
mysteriously; we accepted him without question. 
Yet we don't know anything about him. 
We don't know what he is; what he does; 
where he lives; or even what country he 
belongs to."</p>
<p>"Well?"</p>
<p>"Well, I sometimes think he is the devil. 
He is very pleasant, but he is diabolical in all 
his views and opinions, nevertheless. If he 
is not the devil, he has, at any rate, played the 
devil with <em>us</em>. I feel it at quiet moments like 
these, when we are not excited and bandying 
flippant jokes and unbelieving sarcasms."</p>
<p>I smoked for a few moments in silence, and 
I then said:</p>
<p>"I feel it, too, exactly as you do, Tom. I 
have wished to say so often, only--only I didn't 
like."</p>
<p>"Ned that is exactly what I have felt. 
Suppose we take courage now."</p>
<p>"Suppose we do," I said.</p>
<p>"Very well, then," said Tom. "Let us find 
out who this Doctor Goliath is, what he is, and 
all about him."</p>
<p>Tom had scarcely said the words when the 
doctor came in. He had a small bag in his hand, 
and a parcel under his arm.</p>
<p>I am not going to stay this evening," he 
said. "I have work to do--work that the world 
will hear of. Ha?" And he contracted his brows 
darkly, and laid his finger on his nose in a 
portentous manner.</p>
<p>"Good night," he said; "if I survive, well 
and good; if not, remember me--but as to 
that, I don't imagine for a moment that you 
will do anything of the sort. You will say 
' poor wretch,' and then go on with your jokes 
and your sport. 'Tis the way of this vile world, 
which has been a huge mistake from the 
beginning. Farewell."</p>
<p>"Ned," said Tom, "let us follow him."</p>
<p>We did so. We followed him into the 
Strand and on to the bridge, where he had an 
altercation with the toll-keeper. We could 
hear the words "swindle," "imposition," 
"highway robbery;" and we saw the doctor's 
face under the lamp glaring savagely at the man. 
At length he flung down his halfpenny, and 
walked hurriedly on, but stopped abruptly at 
the first recess, turned into it, and looked over 
the parapet at the river. We had long 
seriously entertained the suspicion--among many 
others of a like kind--that the doctor knew 
something about the mysterious, and as yet 
undiscovered, murder, which is associated with 
that spot. He had hinted at it himself often.</p>
<p>"Look!" said Tom. "Fascination draws him 
to the scene of his crime.--I almost wish he 
would throw himself over."</p>
<p>But the doctor did no such thing. After 
looking down at the river for a few moments, 
he leaped off the stone ledge, and passed on. We 
followed at a safe distance, and kept him in 
sight through a great many narrow and gloomy 
streets, where our only guide was the dark figure 
moving like a shadow before us. At length the 
doctor turned up a narrow passage, and 
disappeared. We ran forward to the entrance, but 
the passage was completely dark, and we could 
see nothing. We hesitated for a moment, but 
immediately summoned up courage and 
followed, groping our way in the dark with the 
assistance of the wall. On coming out at the 
other end of this dark tunnel, we found 
ourselves in a triangular court lighted by a single 
gas-lamp placed at the apex of the triangle. 
There seemed to be no entrance to it save 
by the narrow passage through which we had 
passed. All these strange and mysterious 
characteristics of the place we were enabled to 
see at a glance, by the aid of the one gas-lamp 
that stood like a mark of admiration in the 
corner. And that glance took in the cloudy 
figure of the doctor standing at a door in 
the darkest nook of the court, knocking. He 
was admitted before we reached the spot, but 
we had marked the house. It was number 
thirteen.</p>
<p>"An ogglesome number," said Tom. And 
there was an ogglesome plaster head over the 
doorway--a head, with a leer upon its face, and a 
reckoning-tip expression, just like the doctor's. 
It seemed to be laughing at the fool's errand 
we had come upon.</p>
<p>I said, "What are we to do now?"</p>
<p>"Well, really, I don't know," said Tom.</p>
<p>"Stop," I cried; "I see a bill in the window. 
What does it say?"</p>
<p>Tom suggested, "Mangling done," as being 
most appropriate to a house inhabited by Doctor 
Goliath.</p>
<p>But it was not mangling. It was "Lodgings 
to Let for a Single Gentleman."</p>
<p>"Let us knock," I said, "and inquire about 
the lodgings, and ascertain what sort of a place 
it is."</p>
<p>We saw a light pass into the first floor. That 
was evidently the doctor's room, and he had 
gone up-stairs. We waited a little, and then 
knocked. The door was opened by an elderly 
lady of exceedingly benignant aspect, who wore 
the remnants of a smile upon her face. The 
smile was evidently not intended for us, but we 
took it as if it were, and reciprocated with a 
smiling inquiry about the lodgings. Would 
we step in and look at them? They were two 
rooms down stairs: a sitting-room and a 
bedroom. As the elderly lady, with a candle in 
her hand, was leading the way along the 
passage, the doctor called from above,</p>
<p>"Mrs. Mavor, I want you here directly."</p>
<p>"Excuse me a moment, gentlemen," said Mrs. 
Mavor; "the doctor, my first-floor lodger, has 
just come in, and wants his coffee. Pray take 
a seat in the parlour."</p>
<p>Mrs. Mavor left us, and went up-stairs, and 
the next moment we heard the doctor saying in 
loud and angry tones:</p>
<p>"Where is my spider? How dare you 
sweep away my spider with your murderous 
broom?"</p>
<p>"Oh, the nasty thing!" we heard Mrs. Mavor 
begin to say, but the doctor would not let her 
speak.</p>
<p>"Nasty thing! That's <em>your</em> opinion. What 
do you suppose that spider's opinion is of <em>you</em>, 
when you come and bring his house about his 
ears in the midst of his industry? How would 
you like it? Let me tell you that spider had 
as much right to live as you have; more--more! 
He was industrious, which you are not; he had 
a large family to support, which you have not; 
and if he did spread a net to catch the flies, 
don't you hang up ' Lodgings to Let,' and take 
in single young men, like myself, and <em>do</em> for 
them? You are a heartless, wicked woman, 
Mrs. Mavor."</p>
<p>Mrs. Mavor came down almost immediately, 
laughing.</p>
<p>"That's my first-floor lodger, Doctor Goliath." 
she said; "he has strange ways in some things, 
and pretends to get in an awful temper if any 
one touches his pets; but he is such a good kind 
soul!"</p>
<p>Tom and I began to stare.</p>
<p>"He has been with me now over seven years," 
Mrs. Mavor continued, "and he has behaved so 
well to me, and has been so kind to me when I have 
been ill, that nothing should induce me to take 
any person into the house that might disturb him 
or put him out of his ways. If the doctor were to 
leave Povis-place, I am sure I don't know what 
all the neighbours and the poor people about 
here would do; for he doctors them when they 
are ill, and he advises them when they are well, 
and he writes letters for them, and gets up 
subscriptions for them when there's any misfortune; 
and the children--they're all wild after 
him! Very often you'll see him here in the 
place, when he has been the gentlest and best 
of friends to their fathers and mothers, playing 
games with them, and a score of romping boys 
and girls on the top of his back--but <em>he</em> don't 
mind; he's so good natured, and so fond of 
children!"</p>
<p>Tom and I were opening our eyes wider and 
wider. The doctor called again: "Mrs. Mavor, 
bring me a ball of worsted, and let it be nice 
and soft."</p>
<p>Mrs. Mavor went up-stairs with the worsted, 
and came back again smiling.</p>
<p>"He has got his dumb pets round him now," 
she said, "and one of them has had an accident, 
and he can't bear to see the poor creature suffer. 
He is so tender-hearted!"</p>
<p>Tom and I were speechless. The doctor's 
pets, what could they be? Imps?</p>
<p>I said to Mrs. Mavor, that we had heard of 
Doctor Goliath, that he was a very learned and 
skilful man, and that we would like to have a 
peep at him, if she would permit us. Mrs. Mavor 
hesitated. He would be angry, she said, if he 
knew it. We put it upon our admiration for 
the man, and she consented; but we were only 
to peep through the door, and were not to make 
a noise.</p>
<p>We went up-stairs quietly to the doctor's 
landing. His door was ajar, and we could see 
nearly half the room through the crack, without 
being seen. If it had been possible to open 
our eyes any wider, we should have done it 
now.</p>
<p>For, the doctor was seated at a table on which 
his tea-things were laid. A canary-bird sat 
perched upon his head, a kitten was sporting at 
his feet, and he himself was occupied in binding 
up the leg of a guinea-pig.</p>
<p>"Poor little thing!" he was saying. "l am 
so sorry, so sorry; but never mind. There, 
there! I will bind up its poor little leg, and it 
will get well and run about as nicely as ever. 
Ah, little cat; now you know what I told you 
about that canary-bird. If you kill that canary-bird, 
I shall kill you. That is the law of Moses, 
little cat: it is a cruel law, I think, but I am 
afraid I should have to put it in force; for I 
love that little bird, and I love you, too, little 
cat, so you will not kill my pretty canary, will 
you? Sweet, sweet!" And the bird, perched 
upon the doctor's head, was answering "Sweet, 
sweet!"</p>
<p>Mrs. Mavor was behind us, calling to us in a 
loud whisper to come away. We astonished Mrs. 
Mavor and her lodger both. We walked right 
into the doctor's room.</p>
<p>He started at the sound of our footsteps; and 
when he saw us he turned pale with anger.</p>
<p>"What means this--this unwarrantable--
this impertinent intrusion?"</p>
<p>He poured such a volley of angry words upon 
us that we were confused, and scarcely knew 
how to act. I saw that the only course was to 
take the bull by the horns.</p>
<p>"Doctor," I said, "you are an old humbug."</p>
<p>"What do you mean; what do you mean, 
sir? How dare you!" returned the doctor.</p>
<p>"And I say so too," struck in the mild 
Tom, who had never before been known to 
speak so bold; "doctor, you are an old humbug."</p>
<p>"Well, upon my word," said the doctor, "the 
audacity of this proceeding"</p>
<p>"Who taught us to be audacious, doctor?" 
Tom asked, before he could finish the 
sentence.</p>
<p>The doctor gave way. He laughed, and he 
looked sheepish--as sheepish as we had looked 
when he discovered our loving-cup scheme. He 
scarcely knew what to say, and he put on a fierce 
look again, and called Mrs. Mavor.</p>
<p>"How dare you allow strangers to enter my 
room in this manner? Take that bird and that 
mischievous cat and that nasty guinea-pig, away, 
directly."</p>
<p>"It's of no use, doctor," said Tom; "we 
have found you out, and you can't deceive us any 
more. I have thought until now that you were 
an incarnate fiend, but I find you belong to the 
other side." Tom evidently meant that the 
doctor was a sort of angel, but he did not 
use the word; being probably struck with 
the incongruity of associating an angelic 
embodiment with a wide-awake hat and Blucher 
boots.</p>
<p>The doctor laughed: which encouraged Tom 
to address a moral lesson, on the doctor's 
conduct, to Mrs. Mavor.</p>
<p>"To all of us, Mrs. Mavor, he has made 
himself out a diabolical person: fierce, bloodthirsty, 
cruel. We had made a little Paradise among 
ourselves, and he entered it, like the beguiling 
serpent, and made us all wicked and unhappy. 
What did he do it for?"</p>
<p>Mrs. Mavor, seeing that the doctor was getting 
the worst of it, plucked up courage and spoke out. 
"He does it everywhere beyond the boundaries 
of Povis-place, and I'll tell you what he does it 
for. <em>He is ashamed of being good, and kind, and 
tender-hearted!</em>"</p>
<p>"A pretty thing to be ashamed of," said Tom. 
"I've half a mind to punch his head!"</p>
<p>"No, don't," said the doctor, laughing. "Sit 
down and have a cup of coffee, and then Mrs. 
Mavor will come and join us in a game of whist, 
and we'll have a potato-salad for supper, and 
I'll brew such a bowl of punch as I flatter 
myself no man on the face of the earth besides 
myself--"</p>
<p>"Doctor," said Tom again, "you're a humbug."</p>
<p>We told all to the society, and the next time 
the doctor came among us at Mrs. Lirriper's 
here, he was received with shouts of derisive 
welcome.</p>
<p>The doctor gave a party in Povis-place, and 
we were all invited. There was so much victuals, 
there were so many bottles of German wine, and 
there was so large a number of guests, that Mrs. 
Mavor's small tenement was in some danger of 
bursting. If I remember rightly, the provisions 
were on the scale of a ham and two fowls and a 
dozen of hocheimer, to each guest: to say 
nothing of the potato-salad, which was made in a 
bran new wash-hand basin, purchased for the 
occasion.</p>
<p>And after supper there was a presentation. 
The loving-cups had been redeemed; and one 
more was added to the number; and there they 
were, all bright and glittering--having been 
rubbed up expressly for the occasion--in a row 
upon the table. And the extra one was 
inscribed, "To the Doctor, from Tom, Ned, Sam, 
Will, Jack, Charley, and Harry, a Token of 
Friendship and Esteem."</p>
<p>Though our old heroes and idols are all set 
up on their pedestals long ago, Major, we are 
still given to cynical and audacious talk in our 
society, which is still held in my rooms here. 
But it deceives no one; and when the doctor 
tries to be fierce, he blushes at the feeble 
and foolish attempt he is making to conceal 
the tenderness of the kindest heart that ever 
beat.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE SECOND FLOOR KEPT A DOG."/>
<chapter>
<p>Mrs. Lirriper rather objects to dogs, you 
say, Major? Very natural in a London house. 
Shall I tell you why I hope she will not object 
to <em>my</em> dog, major? Help yourself. So I will.</p>
<br/>
<p>"Ah, but, to goodness, look you, will her 
bite?" exclaimed an old Welshwoman, as she 
pulled her big hat further on her head, and 
looked askance at the big black dog which the 
man sitting next her had just hauled on to the 
coach-roof.</p>
<p>"It isn't a her, and he won't bite," was the 
sententious reply of the dog's master.</p>
<p>Not a pleasant-looking man, this; tall and 
thin, whiskerless and sallow faced; his head 
looking more like a bladder of lard surmounted 
by a scratch-wig, than anything human: dressed 
all in black, with a stiff shiny hat, beaver gloves, 
and thick lustreless Wellington boots. He had 
enormous collars encircling his face and growing 
peakedly out of a huge black silk cravat; he 
had a black satin waistcoat and a silver watch- 
guard, and an umbrella in a shiny oilskin case, 
and a hard slippery cold black cowskin bag, with 
J. M. upon it in staring white letters; and he 
looked very much like what he was--Mr. John 
Mortiboy, junior partner in the house of Crump 
and Mortiboy, Manchester warehousemen, 
Friday-street, Cheapside, London.</p>
<p>What brought Mr. John Mortiboy into Wales 
to spend his holiday, or what induced such a 
pillar of British commerce to encumber himself 
with a dog, is no business of ours, Major. All I 
know, is, that he had been set down at the 
Barberth-road station, had dragged the black 
cowskin bag from under his seat, had released the 
dog from a square bare receptacle which the 
animal had filled with howls, and had mounted 
himself and his dog on to the top of the coach 
travelling toward the little watering-place of 
Penethly. The dog, a big black retriever, lay 
on the coach-roof with his fine head erect, now 
gazing round the landscape, now dropping 
his cold muzzle between his paws and taking 
snatches of sleep. His master sat on the 
extreme edge of the seat, with one Wellington 
boot very much displayed and dangling in 
the air, and he, the Wellington boot's owner, 
apparently deriving much enjoyment from the 
suction of his umbrella-handle. He cast his 
big eyes round him now and then at certain 
portions of the scenery pointed out by the 
coachman, and expressed his opinion that it 
was "handsome," but beyond that never vouch-safed 
a word until the coach drew up at the 
Royal Inn at Penethly, when he went at once 
round to the stables and superintended the 
preparation of a meal for his dog, then ordered a 
"point steak well beat, potatoes, and a pint of 
sherry," to be ready for him in an hour's time; 
inquired the way to Albion Villa; and set 
off for Albion Villa accompanied by his dog 
Beppo.</p>
<p>I don't think Mr. John Mortiboy was much 
wanted at Albion Villa, nor that he was exactly 
the kind of man who would have suited its 
inmates. They were little conscious of the 
approach of his hard creaking boots, striding 
over the ill-paved High-street of the little town, 
and were enjoying themselves after their own 
simple fashion. The blinds were down, the 
candles were lighted, and Mrs. Barford was 
pretending to be knitting, but really enjoying a 
placid sleep; Ellen, her eldest daughter, was 
reading a magazine; Kate, her youngest, was 
making some sketches under the observant 
tuition of a slim gentleman with a light beard, 
who apparently took the greatest interest in his 
pupil. Upon this little group the clang of the 
gate bell, the creaking of Mr. John Mortiboy's 
boots, and the strident tones of Mr. John 
Mortiboy's voice, fell uncomfortably. "Say Mr. 
John Mortiboy, of London," he exclaimed, while 
yet in the little passage outside. The startled 
Welsh servant having obeyed him, he followed 
close upon her heels into the room.</p>
<p>"Servant, ladies!" said he, with a short 
circular nod, "servant, Mrs. Barford! Best to 
explain matters wholesale. You wonder who I 
am. You're sister-in-law to my uncle, Jonas 
Crump. I'm my uncle's partner in Friday-street. 
Done too much; rather baked in the head--
heavy consignments and sitting up late at night 
poring over figures. The doctor recommended 
change of air; uncle Crump recommended 
Penethly, and mentioned you. I came down 
here, and have taken the liberty of calling. 
Down, Beppo! Don't mind him, miss, he won't 
hurt you."</p>
<p>"Oh! I'm not afraid of the <em>dog</em>!" said 
Ellen, with a slight start at Mr. Mortiboy's 
general manner, and at his calling her "Miss." 
Kate looked on in wonder, and the slim 
gentleman with the light beard confided to the said 
beard, the word "Brute."</p>
<p>"We're--very--pleased to see you, Mr. 
Mortiboy," said Mrs. Barford, "and--and hope that 
you will soon recover your health in our quiet 
village. I'm sure anything that we can--can 
do--my daughters, Miss Ellen, Miss Kate 
Barford; a friend of ours, Mr. Sandham--we 
shall be most happy to--" As Mrs. Barford's 
voice died away in the contemplation of the 
happiness before her, the young ladies and 
Mr. Sandham bowed, and Mr. Mortiboy 
favoured them with a series of short nods. Then 
he said, abruptly turning to the slim gentleman, 
"In the army, sir?"</p>
<p>"No, sir, I am not!" retorted the slim 
gentleman, with great promptitude.</p>
<p>"Beg pardon, no offence! Volunteer, 
perhaps? Hair, you know, beard, et ctera, made 
me think you were in the military line. Many 
young gents now-a-days are volunteers!"</p>
<p>"Mr. Sandham is an artist," said Mrs. 
Barford, interposing in dread lest there should be 
an outbreak.</p>
<p>"Oh ah!" said Mr. Mortiboy. "Bad trade 
that--demand not equal to supply, is it? Too 
many hands employed; barely bread and cheese, 
I'm told, for any but the top-sawyers."</p>
<p>"Sir!" said Mr. Sandham, in a loud tone of 
voice, and fiercely.</p>
<p>"Edward!" said Miss Kate, beneath her 
breath, appealingly.</p>
<p>"Won't you take some refreshment, Mr. 
Mortiboy?" asked Mrs. Barford, warningly. 
"We're just going to supper."</p>
<p>"No, thank you, mam," said Mr. Mortiboy. 
"I've a steak and potatoes waiting for me at the 
Royal, after which I shall turn in at once, as I'm 
done up by my journey. Good night, ladies 
all! Good night to you, sir! I'll look you up 
to-morrow morning, and if any of you want to 
go for a turn, I shall be proud to beau you 
about. Good night!" And beckoning his dog, 
Mr. Mortiboy took his departure.</p>
<p>Scarcely had the door closed behind him, than 
the long-restrained comments began.</p>
<p>"A pleasant visitor uncle Crump has sent us, 
mamma!" said Kate.</p>
<p>"Uncle Crump, indeed! Who never sent us 
anything before, except a five-pound note when 
poor papa died!" exclaimed Ellen.</p>
<p>"But you won't, will you, mamma, you won't 
be put upon in this way? You won't have this 
horrid man running in and out at all times and 
seasons, and--"</p>
<p>"And <em>beau</em>-ing us about! the vulgar wretch!" 
interrupted Kate.</p>
<p>"My dears! my dears!" said Mrs. Barford, 
"it strikes me that some one has been teaching 
you very strong language."</p>
<p>"Not I, Mrs. Barford," said Mr. Sandham; 
"absolve me from that; though I must own 
that if ever I saw a man who wanted kicking--"</p>
<p>"Nonsense, Mr. Sandham. This gentleman 
is imbued with certain London peculiarities, no 
doubt; but I dare say there's good in him. 
There must be, or he would never be the partner 
of such an upright man as Jonas Crump."</p>
<p>"Upright man! Pooh!" said Kate; and then 
the supper came in, and the subject dropped.</p>
<p>At nine o'clock next morning, just as the 
breakfast-things had been cleared, and Mrs. 
Barford was going through her usual interview 
with the cook, Kate, who was sitting in the 
little bay-window, started and exclaimed: "Oh, 
mamma! Here's this horrid man!"</p>
<p>Ellen peeped over her shoulder, and said, "I 
think he looks, if possible, more dreadful by 
daylight than by candlelight!"</p>
<p>Mr. John Mortiboy, utterly unconscious of 
the effect he was producing, unlatched the 
garden-gate, and then for the first time looking 
up, nodded shortly and familiarly at the sisters. 
"How do, young ladies?" he called from the 
garden. "Fine morning this; fresh and all 
that sort of thing! I feel better already. When 
a London man's a little overdone, nothing sets 
him up so soon, as a sniff of the briny."</p>
<p>And then he took a great gulp, as if to swallow 
as much fresh air as possible, and entered the 
house, followed by his dog.</p>
<p>"Did you hear him, Nelly?" asked Kate. 
"The wretch! I'm sure <em>I</em> won't be seen walking 
with him, in his nasty black clothes, like an 
undertaker!"</p>
<p>"He has a chimney-pot hat on, and has 
brought his umbrella! Fancy! At the sea!" 
said Ellen.</p>
<p>"Good morning, Mrs. Barford," said Mr. 
Mortiboy; "domestic arrangements, eh? I 
understand. If you've no objection, I'll do 
myself the pleasure of cutting my mutton with you 
to-day. And mutton it will be, I suppose! 
Can't get any beef here, I understand, 
except on Friday, which is killing-day for the 
barracks. Bad arrangement that; wants alteration."</p>
<p>"Hadn't you better alter it then, Mr. Mortiboy," 
said Kate; "superintending the 
butcher will be a pleasant way of spending your holiday."</p>
<p>"Joking, miss, eh? Well, I don't mind. But 
ain't you coming out; young ladies, for a mouthful 
of air. I suppose the old lady don't move so 
early."</p>
<p>"If you refer to mamma," said Ellen, frigidly, 
"she never goes out until just before dinner."</p>
<p>"Ah, I thought not. Old folks must wait 
until the air is what they call warmed by the sun. 
But that won't hinder our taking a turn, I 
suppose. Where's Whiskerandos?"</p>
<p>"If, as I presume, you mean Mr. Sandham, 
the gentleman who was here last night, 
cannot inform you, Mr. Mortiboy," said Kate, with 
a very flushed face, and a slightly trembling 
voice; "but I would advise you not to let him 
hear you joking about him, as he is rather quick- 
tempered."</p>
<p>"Oh, indeed?" exclaimed Mr. Mortiboy, "a 
fire-eater is he? Well, there's no duelling now, 
you know. Any nonsense of that sort,--give 
a man in charge of a policeman, or summons 
him before a magistrate, and get him bound 
over."</p>
<p>Just at this moment Mrs. Barford came in 
and told the girls to get their hats on, and 
show Mr. Mortiboy the prettiest spots in the 
village, the Castle Hill, the ruined Abbey, and 
the Smuggler's Leap. To these places they 
went, Mr. Mortiboy discoursing the whole 
way of the badness of the roads, and of what 
improvements might be made if they had a 
properly constituted local board of health at 
Penethly; declaring that the cries of "Milford 
oysters," and "fresh haddick," were entirely 
unconstitutional and illegal, as no one had a 
right to shout in the public streets; that there 
ought to be proper stands provided for the car-drivers; 
and that a regular police supervision 
was urgently demanded. He did not think 
much of the Abbey ruins, and he laughed in 
scorn at the story of the Smuggler's Leap. 
As they were on their homeward way, coming 
round the Castle-hill, they met Mr. Sandham, 
very ruddy and fresh, and shiny, and with a 
couple of towels in his hand. He took off his 
wide-awake as he approached the ladies, and 
bowed slightly to Mr. Mortiboy.</p>
<p>"Ah, Mr. Sandham!" said Ellen, with an 
admonitory finger, "you have been bathing again 
by St. Catherine's Rock, after all the warning 
we gave you!"</p>
<p>"My dear Ellen," interposed Kate, with a 
petulant air, "how can you? If Mr. Sandham 
chooses to risk his life after what he has been 
told, it surely is nothing to us!"</p>
<p>"Now, Miss Kate, Miss Kate, that's not 
fair!" said Sandham; "you know," he added, 
dropping his voice, "that every word of yours 
would have weight with me, but the tide was 
slack this morning, and really there is no other 
place where a swimmer can really enjoy a bath. 
You are a swimmer, Mr. Mortiboy?"</p>
<p>"Yes, sir," replied that gentleman. "Yes, sir, I 
can manage it. I've had lessons at Peerless Pool 
and the Holborn Baths, and can keep up well 
enough. But I don't like it. I don't see much fun 
in what are absurdly called the ' manly exercises.' 
Twenty years ago, young men used to like 
driving coaches; now I can't conceive duller 
work than holding a bunch of thick leather 
reins in your hand, steering four tired horses, 
sitting on a hard seat, and listening to the 
conversation of an uneducated coachman. I never 
ride, because I hate bumping up and down on a 
hard saddle and rubbing the skin off my body; 
I never play cricket, because in the hot weather 
I like to keep quiet and cool, and not toil in the 
sun; and as to going out shooting and stumping 
over miles of stubble in September, lugging a 
big gun and tiring myself to death, I look upon 
that, as the pursuit of a maniac! I am a 
practical man!"</p>
<p>"You are indeed!" said Kate, as she dropped 
gradually behind with Mr. Sandham, and left 
the practical man and her sister Ellen to lead 
the way to the house.</p>
<p>It is unnecessary to recount the sayings and 
doings of Mr. John Mortiboy during the next 
few days. It is enough that he spent the 
greater portion of them with the Barford 
family, and that he so elaborated his ideas of 
practicality, and so inveighed against everything 
that was not absolutely useful in a 
mercantile point of view--including, in a measure, 
art, poetry, music, and the domestic affections--
that he incurred the unmitigated hatred of the 
young ladies, and even fell to zero in Mrs. 
Barford's estimation.</p>
<p>It was about the fifth morning after the 
intrusion of this utterly incongruous element 
into the society of Albion Villa, that Ellen 
and Kate strolled out immediately after breakfast 
with the view of escaping the expected 
visit of their persecutor, and made their 
way to the Castle Hill. The night had been 
tempestuous, and from their window they had 
noticed that a heavy sea was running: they 
consequently were not surprised to see a little 
group of people gathered on the heights looking 
towards St. Catherine's Rock: a huge mass 
of granite surmounted by an old ruin, round 
which, when it was insulated at high water, 
the tide always swept with a peculiar and 
dangerous swirl. But when they joined the group, 
among which were several of their friends, they 
found that the concourse were regarding, with 
interest mingled with fright, the movements of 
a swimmer who had rounded the extremity 
of Catherine's, and was seen making for the 
shore.</p>
<p>"He'll never do it," said Captain Calthorp, 
an old half-pay dragoon, who had been tempted 
by the cheapness of Penethly to pitch his tent 
there; "he'll never do it, by Jove! Yes! Well 
struggled, sir; he made a point there--hold on, 
now, and he's in."</p>
<p>"Who is it?" asked the coast-guard 
lieutenant, who was standing by. "Any one we 
know?"</p>
<p>"I can't tell at this distance*!" said 
Captain Calthorp, "though it looks like--stay! 
There's one of your look-out men on the height, 
with a glass; give him a hail!"</p>
<p>"Yoho! Morgan!" cried the lieutenant. "Ay, 
ay, sir!" was the man's ready response, though 
the glass was never moved. "Bring that glass 
down here!" "Ay, ay, sir;" and in two minutes 
the old coast-guard-man was by his officer's side. 
He saluted and handed the glass, but as he did 
so he said, in an under tone, "God help the 
gentleman, he's done! Ah, look you now, poor 
thing, nothing can save him."</p>
<p>"What!" cries the lieutenant, clapping the 
glass to his eye. "By Jove, you're right! he's 
in a bad way, and it--why it's the artist-chap, 
that friend of the Barfords'!"</p>
<p>"Who?" screamed Kate, rushing up at the 
moment. "<em>Who</em> did you say, Mr. Lawford? 
Oh, for God's sake, save him! Save him, Mr. 
Lawford! Save him, Captain Calthorp!"</p>
<p>"My clear young lady," said the last-named 
gentleman, "I am sure Lawford didn't know 
<em>you</em> were here, or he wouldn't--"</p>
<p>"This is no time for ceremony, Captain Cal- 
thorp," said Ellen; "for Heaven's sake, let 
some effort be made to save my sister's--to 
save Mr. Sandham!"</p>
<p>"My dear Miss Barford," said Lawford, who 
had been whispering with Morgan, "I fear no 
mortal aid can avail the poor dear fellow now. 
Before we could descend the rock, and launch 
a boat, with the tide ebbing at the rate it now 
is--"</p>
<p>"Hur would have been swep' round 
Cath'rine's, and away out to sea!" said Morgan.</p>
<p>"Oh, help him!" screamed Kate. "Oh, how 
cruel! how cowardly! Oh, help him, Mr. 
Lawford!" She lifted up her hands piteously to 
the lieutenant. "Oh, Mr. Mortiboy," she 
exclaimed, as that gentleman came slowly 
sauntering up the hill with Beppo at his heels, "for 
God's sake, save Mr. Sandham!"</p>
<p>"Save--Mr. Sandham--my dear young lady; 
I don't exactly comprehend!" began Mr. 
Mortiboy, looking vaguely in the direction of her 
outstretched hand; then suddenly, "Good 
Lord! is that his head? There! Down 
there!"</p>
<p>"Yes!" whispered Ellen Barford; "yes! 
They say he will be whirled away before a boat 
could be launched--they say he is lost now!"</p>
<p>"Not at all! Not yet; at least!" replied 
Mortiboy, excited, but without much perceptible 
alteration of manner. "While there's life there's 
hope, you know, Miss B., and even yet we 
may--Here, Beppo! Hi, man! hi! Good 
boy!" The dog came, leaping round his 
master. "Hi! ho! Not here! There! there! 
Look, boy!" catching him by the collar, and 
pointing down to where Sandham's head was 
a mere speck on the water. "Look, man! 
Look, old boy! He sees it, by Jove!" as the 
dog uttered a low growl, and became restive. 
"In, old man! In, fine fellow! In, Beppo! 
Look! Noble dog, in he goes!"</p>
<p>In he went, with one bound over the low 
stone wall, then quickly down the sloping 
slippery boulders, then with a plunge into the 
sea--lost sight of for a moment, rising to 
view again, paddling off straight for the drowning 
man. The swift current whirled him in 
eddies here and there, but still the brave dog 
persevered; the spectators held their breath, 
as they saw him bearing down upon the black 
speck, which was every second growing smaller 
and smaller, and receding further and further 
from the land. But the dog made grand 
progress, the strong sucking under-current helped 
him, and he arrived at Sandham's side just 
in time for the drowning man to fling his 
arm round the dog's neck, and to feel his 
shoulder seized by the dog's teeth. They saw 
this from the shore, and then Kate Barford 
fainted.</p>
<p>But the work was only half done: the dog 
turned round, and battled bravely for the shore, 
but he was encumbered by his burden, and now 
the current was against him. He strove and 
strove, but the way he made was small, and every 
foot was gained with intense struggling and 
exertion. "By Jove! He'll never do it," cried 
Lieutenant Lawford, with the glass at his eye; 
and, as he said the words, old Morgan, the 
preventive-man, added through his teeth, "Hur 
must be helped, at any cost," and sped away 
down the rock, shaping his course to where 
a small pleasure-boat lay high and dry on 
the sand. "I'm with you, governor," cried 
John Mortiboy; "I can't feather, but I pull a 
strongish oar;" and he followed the old man as 
best he could. The boat was reached, and 
pushed by main force to the water's edge, where 
Mortiboy entered it, and old Morgan ran in, 
waist-deep, to give it the starting shove, and 
then, leaped in to join his comrade. On they 
pulled, Morgan with a measured steady stroke, 
Mortiboy with fevered strong jerks that sent 
the boat's head now to the right, now to the 
left: when old Morgan, suddenly looking over 
his shoulder, called out, "Hur's done! Hur's 
sinking now, both on 'em!" Mortiboy looked 
round too; they were still some ten boats' length 
from the objects of their pursuit, and both dog 
and man were vanishing. "Not yet!" cried 
he; and in an instant he had torn off the black 
coat and the Wellington boots, and had flung 
himself, as nobly as his own dog, into the 
sea.</p>
<p>A very few strokes brought him to Sandham; 
he seized him by the hair of his head, 
and battled bravely with the waves; the 
dog, recognising his master, seemed to take 
fresh courage, and the trio floated until old 
Morgan dragged them one by one into the boat. 
When they reached the shore, all Penethly was 
on the beach, cheering with all its might: they 
lifted out Mr. Sandham, insensible but likely to 
recover, and they administered a very stiff glass 
of grog to Mr. Mortiboy, who was shivering 
like an aspen-leaf, but who received even greater 
warmth from a warm pressure of Ellen Barford's 
hand, and a whispered "God bless you, Mr. 
Mortiboy!" than from the grog--though he 
took that, too, like a man whom it comforted. 
As for Beppo, I don't know what the fishing 
population would not have done for him, but 
that he positively refused to stir from Sandham's 
side. As they carried the artist up to his lodgings 
the dog buried his nose in the pendent 
hand, and did not leave until he had seen his 
charge safely placed in bed.</p>
<p>Mr. Sandham was, in his own words, "All 
right" next day, but Mr. Mortiboy, unaccustomed 
to exercise and damp, fell ill, and was 
confined to his bed for several weeks:--would 
have never left it, I think, but for the care and 
attention of his three nurses from Albion Villa. 
Of these, Ellen was the most constant and the 
most regular, and the patient always seemed 
better under her care.</p>
<p>"He is making progress, Kate," she said one 
night to her sister. "He is a good patient. You 
know, as he would say himself, he is so 
practical."</p>
<p>"God bless his practicality, Nell," said 
Kate, with tears in her eyes. "Think what it 
did for us!"</p>
<br/>
<p>Three years have passed since then, Major, 
and a family group is going to be gathered in a 
large square room built as a kind of excrescence 
to a very pretty villa in Kensington. This is to 
be the studio of Mr. Sandham, A.R.A.. But as 
the mortar and plaster are extraordinarily slow 
in drying (when were they not, Major?), Mr. 
Sandham, A.R.A., come up from Wales with 
the family group, to take possession, has 
established the group at the excellent Lodgings of 
the excellent Mrs. Lirriper, and he, the owner 
of said studio, is smoking a pipe with a worthy 
Major, and smoothing with his slippered foot 
the rough curly back of his dog Beppo, who is 
stretched in front of the fire. Mrs. Sandham, 
formerly Kate Barford, is working at a baby's 
frock, and asking now and then the advice of her 
sister, who is frilling a little cap. (There they 
are, Major. Don't tell them that I said so.)</p>
<p>"How late John is to-night, Ellen," says old 
Mrs. Barford, from her place in the chimney-corner. 
(You hear her, Major?)</p>
<p>"Always at Christmas-time, dear mother,' 
says Ellen. (There she is, Major.) "Since 
uncle Crump's death, you know, John's 
business is trebled, and it all hangs on him, dear old 
fellow!"</p>
<p>"He will be late for supper, Nelly," says 
Sandham. "(--Excuse me, Major.)"</p>
<p>"No he won't, Ned!" cries a cheery voice 
at the door as John Mortiboy appears; "no he 
won't. He's never late for anything good. 
Don't you know, he's a practical man?"</p>
<p>--Mr. Mortiboy, Major Jackman, Major, Mr. 
Mortiboy!</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE THIRD FLOOR KNEW THE POTTERIES."/>
<chapter>
<p>I am a plain man, Major, and you may not 
dislike to hear a plain statement of facts from me. 
Some of those facts lie beyond my understanding. 
I do not pretend to explain them. I only 
know that they happened as I relate them, and 
that I pledge myself for the truth of every word 
of them.</p>
<p>I began life roughly enough, down among the 
Potteries. I was an orphan; and my earliest 
recollections are of a great porcelain manufactory 
in the country of the Potteries, where I helped 
about the yard, picked up what halfpence fell 
in my way, and slept in a harness-loft over the 
stable. Those were hard times; but things 
bettered themselves as I grew older and stronger, 
especially after George Barnard had come to 
be foreman of the yard.</p>
<p>George Barnard was a Wesleyan--we were 
mostly dissenters in the Potteries--sober, clear- 
headed, somewhat sulky and silent, but a good 
fellow every inch of him, and my best friend 
at the time when I most needed a good friend. 
He took me out of the yard, and set me to the 
furnace-work. He entered me on the books 
at a fixed rate of wages. He helped me to 
pay for a little cheap schooling four nights a 
week; and he led me to go with him on Sundays 
to the chapel down by the river-side, where I 
first saw Leah Payne. She was his sweetheart, 
and so pretty that I used to forget the preacher 
and everybody else, when I looked at her. When 
she joined in the singing, I heard no voice but 
hers. If she asked me for the hymn-book, 
I used to blush and tremble. I believe I 
worshipped her, in my stupid ignorant way; 
and I think I worshipped Barnard almost as 
blindly, though after a different fashion. I felt 
I owed him everything. I knew that he had 
saved me, body and mind; and I looked up to 
him as a savage might look up to a missionary.</p>
<p>Leah was the daughter of a plumber, who lived 
close by the chapel. She was twenty, and George 
about seven or eight-and-thirty. Some captious 
folks said there was too much difference in their 
ages; but she was so serious-minded, and they 
loved each other so earnestly and quietly, that, 
if nothing had come between them during their 
courtship, I don't believe the question of 
disparity would ever have troubled the happiness 
of their married lives. Something did come, 
however; and that something was a Frenchman, 
called Louis Laroche. He was a painter on 
porcelain, from the famous works at Svres; 
and our master, it was said, had engaged him 
for three years certain, at such wages as none 
of our own people, however skilful, could hope 
to command. It was about the beginning or 
middle of September when he first came among 
us. He looked very young; was small, dark, 
and well made; had little white soft hands, and 
a silky moustache; and spoke English nearly 
as well as I do. None of us liked him; but 
that was only natural, seeing how he was put 
over the head of every Englishman in the place. 
Besides, though he was always smiling and 
civil, we couldn't help seeing that he thought 
himself ever so much better than the rest of us; 
and that was not pleasant. Neither was it 
pleasant to see him strolling about the town, 
dressed just like a gentleman, when working 
hours were over; smoking good cigars, when 
we were forced to be content with, a pipe of 
common tobacco; hiring a horse on Sunday 
afternoons, when we were trudging a-foot; and 
taking his pleasure as if the world was made for 
him to enjoy, and us to work in.</p>
<p>"Ben, boy," said George, "there's something 
wrong about that Frenchman."</p>
<p>It was on a Saturday afternoon, and we 
were sitting on a pile of empty seggars against 
the door of my furnace-room, waiting till the 
men should all have cleared out of the yard. 
Seggars are deep earthen boxes in which the 
pottery is put, while being fired in the kiln.</p>
<p>I looked up, inquiringly.</p>
<p>"About the Count?" said I, for that was the 
nickname by which he went in the pottery.</p>
<p>George nodded, and paused for a moment 
with his chin resting on his palms.</p>
<p>"He has an evil eye," said he; "and a false 
smile. Something wrong about him."</p>
<p>I drew nearer, and listened to George as if he 
had been an oracle.</p>
<p>"Besides," added he, in his slow quiet way, 
with his eyes fixed straight before him as if he 
was thinking aloud, "there's a young look about 
him that isn't natural. Take him just at sight, 
and you'd think he was almost a boy; but look 
close at him--see the little fine wrinkles under 
his eyes, and the hard lines about his mouth, 
and then tell me his age, if you can! Why, Ben 
boy, he's as old as I am, pretty near; ay, and 
as strong, too. You stare; but I tell you that, 
slight as he looks, he could fling you over his 
shoulder as if you were a feather. And as for his 
hands, little and white as they are, there are 
muscles of iron inside them, take my word for it."</p>
<p>"But, George, how can you know?"</p>
<p>"Because 1 have a warning against him," 
replied George, very gravely. "Because, 
whenever he is by, I feel as if my eyes saw clearer, 
and my ears heard keener, than at other times. 
Maybe it's presumption, but I sometimes feel as 
if I had a call to guard myself and others against 
him. Look at the children, Ben, how they 
shrink away from him; and see there, now! 
Ask Captain what he thinks of him! Ben, that 
dog likes him no better than I do."</p>
<p>I looked, and saw Captain crouching by his 
kennel with his ears laid back, growling audibly, 
as the Frenchman came slowly down the steps 
leading from his own workshop at the upper 
end of the yard. On the last step he paused; 
lighted a cigar; glanced round, as if to see 
whether any one was by; and then walked straight 
over to within a couple of yards of the kennel. 
Captain gave a short angry snarl, and laid his 
muzzle close down upon his paws, ready for a 
spring. The Frenchman folded his arms 
deliberately, fixed his eyes on the dog, and stood 
calmly smoking. He knew exactly how far he 
dared go, and kept just that one foot out of harm's 
way. All at once he stooped, puffed a mouthful 
of smoke in the dog's eyes, burst into a mocking 
laugh, turned lightly on his heel, and walked 
away; leaving Captain straining at his chain, 
and barking after him like a mad creature.</p>
<p>Days went by, and I, at work in my own department, 
saw no more of the Count. Sunday came--
the third, I think, after I had talked with George 
in the yard. Going with George to chapel, as 
usual, in the morning, I noticed that there was 
something strange and anxious in his face, and 
that he scarcely opened his lips to me on the way. 
Still I said nothing. It was not my place to 
question him; and I remember thinking to 
myself that the cloud would all clear off as soon as 
he found himself by Leah's side, holding the 
same book, and joining in the same hymn. It 
did not, however, for no Leah was there. I 
looked every moment to the door, expecting to 
see her sweet face coming in; but George never 
lifted his eyes from his book, or seemed to 
notice that her place was empty. Thus the 
whole service went by, and my thoughts 
wandered continually from the words of the preacher. 
As soon as the last blessing was spoken, and we 
were fairly across the threshold, 1 turned to 
George, and asked if Leah was ill?</p>
<p>"No," said he, gloomily. "She's not ill."</p>
<p>"Then why wasn't she--?"</p>
<p>"I'll tell you why," he interrupted, 
impatiently. "Because you've seen her here for the 
last time. She's never coming to chapel again."</p>
<p>"Never coming to the chapel again?" I 
faltered, laying my hand on his sleeve in the 
earnestness of my surprise. "Why, George, 
what is the matter?"</p>
<p>But he shook my hand off, and stamped with 
his iron heel till the pavement rang again.</p>
<p>"Don't ask me," said he, roughly. "Let me 
alone. You'll know soon enough."</p>
<p>And with this he turned off down a by-lane 
leading towards the hills, and left me without 
another word.</p>
<p>I had had plenty of hard treatment in my 
time; but never, until that moment, an angry 
look or syllable from George. I did not 
know how to bear it. That day my dinner 
seemed as if it would choke me; and in 
the afternoon I went out and wandered 
restlessly about the fields till the hour for evening 
prayers came round. I then returned to the 
chapel, and sat down on a tomb outside, waiting 
for George. I saw the congregation go in by twos 
and threes; I heard the first psalm-tune echo 
solemnly through the evening stillness; but no</p>
<p>George came. Then the service began, and I 
knew that, punctual as his habits were, it was 
of no use to expect him any longer. Where 
could he be? What could have happened? 
"Why should Leah Payne never come to chapel 
again? Had she gone over to some other sect, 
and was that why George seemed so unhappy?</p>
<p>Sitting there in the little dreary churchyard 
with the darkness fast gathering around me, I 
asked myself these questions over and over 
again, till my brain ached; for I was not much 
used to thinking about anything in those times. 
At last, I could bear to sit quiet no longer. The 
sudden thought struck me that I would go to 
Leah, and learn what the matter was, from her 
own lips. I sprang to my feet, and set off at 
once towards her home.</p>
<p>It was quite dark, and a light rain was 
beginning to fall. I found the garden-gate open, 
and a quick hope flashed across me that 
George might be there. I drew back for a 
moment, hesitating whether to knock or ring, 
when a sound of voices in the passage, and the 
sudden gleaming of a bright line of light under 
the door, warned me that some one was coming 
out. Taken by surprise, and quite unprepared 
for the moment with anything to say, I shrank 
back behind the porch, and waited until those 
within should have passed out. The door 
opened, and the light streamed suddenly upon 
the roses and the wet gravel.</p>
<p>"It rains," said Leah, bending forward and 
shading the candle with her hand.</p>
<p>"And is as cold as Siberia," added another 
voice, which was not George's, and yet sounded 
strangely familiar. "Ugh! what a climate for 
such a flower as my darling to bloom in!"</p>
<p>"Is it so much finer in France?" asked Leah, 
softly.</p>
<p>"As much finer as blue skies and sunshine 
can make it. Why, my angel, even your bright 
eyes will be ten times brighter, and your rosy 
cheeks ten times rosier, when they are 
transplanted to Paris. Ah! I can give you no idea 
of the wonders of Paris--the broad streets 
planted with trees, the palaces, the shops, the 
gardens!--it is a city of enchantment."</p>
<p>"It must be, indeed!" said Leah. "And you 
will really take me to see all those beautiful 
shops?"</p>
<p>"Every Sunday, my darling--Bah! don't 
look so shocked. The shops in Paris are always 
open on Sunday, and everybody makes holiday. 
You will soon get over these prejudices."</p>
<p>"I fear it is very wrong to take so much 
pleasure in the things of this world," sighed 
Leah.</p>
<p>The Frenchman laughed, and answered her 
with a kiss.</p>
<p>"Good night, my sweet little saint!" and 
he ran lightly down the path, and disappeared 
in the darkness. Leah sighed again, lingered a 
moment, and then closed the door.</p>
<p>Stupified and bewildered, I stood for some 
seconds like a stone statue, unable to move; 
scarcely able to think. At length, I roused 
myself, as it were mechanically, and went towards 
the gate. At that instant, a heavy hand was 
laid upon my shoulder, and a hoarse voice close 
beside my ear, said:</p>
<p>"Who are you? What are you doing here?"</p>
<p>It was George. I knew him at once, in spite 
of the darkness, and stammered his name. He 
took his hand quickly from my shoulder.</p>
<p>"How long have you been here?" said he, 
fiercely. "What right have you to lurk about, 
like a spy in the dark? God help me, Ben--
I'm half mad. I don't mean to be harsh to you."</p>
<p>"I'm sure you don't," I cried, earnestly.</p>
<p>"It's that cursed Frenchman," he went on, in 
a voice that sounded like the groan of one in 
pain. "He's a villain. I know he's a villain; 
and I've had a warning against him ever since 
the first moment he came among us. He'll 
make her miserable, and break her heart some 
day--my pretty Leah--and I loved her so! 
But I'll be revenged as sure as there's a sun 
in heaven, I'll be revenged!"</p>
<p>His vehemence terrified me. I tried to 
persuade him to go home; but he would not listen 
to me.</p>
<p>"No, no," he said. "Go home yourself, 
boy, and let me be. My blood is on fire: this 
rain is good for me, and I am better alone."</p>
<p>"If I could only do something to help 
you--"</p>
<p>"You can't," interrupted he. "Nobody can 
help me. I'm a ruined man, and I don't care 
what becomes of me. The Lord forgive me! 
my heart is full of wickedness, and my thoughts 
are the promptings of Satan. There go--for 
Heaven's sake, go. I don't know what I say, 
or what I do!"</p>
<p>I went, for I did not dare refuse any longer; 
but I lingered awhile at the corner of the street, 
and watched him pacing to and fro, to and fro 
in the driving rain. At length I turned 
reluctantly away, and went home.</p>
<p>I lay awake that night for hours, thinking 
over the events of the day, and hating the 
Frenchman from my very soul. I could not 
hate Leah. I had worshipped her too long 
and too faithfully for that; but I looked upon, 
her as a creature given over to destruction. 
I fell asleep towards morning, and woke again 
shortly after daybreak. When I reached the 
pottery, I found George there before me, looking 
very pale, but quite himself, and setting the men 
to their work the same as usual. I said nothing 
about what had happened the day before. 
Something in his face silenced me; but seeing him, 
so steady and composed, I took heart, and began 
to hope he had fought through the worst of his 
trouble. By-and-by the Frenchman came through, 
the yard, gay and off-hand, with his cigar in 
his mouth, and his hands in his pockets. George 
turned sharply away into one of the workshops, 
and shut the door. I drew a deep breath of 
relief. My dread was to see them come to an 
open quarrel; and I felt that as long as they 
kept clear of that, all would be well.</p>
<p>Thus the Monday went by, and the Tuesday; 
and still George kept aloof from me. I had 
sense enough not to be hurt by this. I felt he 
had a good right to be silent, if silence helped 
him to bear his trial better; and I made up my 
mind never to breathe another syllable on the 
subject, unless he began.</p>
<p>Wednesday came. I had overslept myself 
that morning, and came to work a quarter after 
the hour, expecting to be fined; for George 
was very strict as foreman of the yard, and 
treated friends and enemies just the same. 
Instead of blaming me, however, he called me 
up, and said:</p>
<p>"Ben, whose turn is it this week to sit up?"</p>
<p>"Mine, sir," I replied. (I always called him 
"Sir" in working hours.)</p>
<p>"Well, then, you may go home to-day, and 
the same on Thursday and Friday; for there's 
a large batch of work for the ovens to-night, 
and there'll be the same to-morrow night and 
the night after."</p>
<p>"All right, sir," said I. "Then I'll be here 
by seven this evening."</p>
<p>"No, half-past nine will be soon enough. 
I've some accounts to make up, and I shall be 
here myself till then. Mind you are true to 
time, though."</p>
<p>"I'll be as true as the clock, sir," I replied, 
and was turning away when he called me back 
again.</p>
<p>"You're a good lad, Ben," said he. "Shake 
hands."</p>
<p>I seized his hand, and pressed it warmly.</p>
<p>"If I'm good for anything, George," I 
answered with all my heart, "it's you who have 
made me so. God bless you for it!"</p>
<p>"Amen!" said he, in a troubled voice, putting 
his hand to his hat.</p>
<p>And so we parted.</p>
<p>In general, I went to bed by day when I was 
attending to the firing by night; but this morning 
I had already slept longer than usual, and 
wanted exercise more than rest. So I ran 
home; put a bit of bread and meat in my 
pocket; snatched up my big thorn stick; and 
started off for a long day in the country. When 
I came home, it was quite dark and beginning 
to rain, just as it had begun to rain at about the 
same time that wretched Sunday evening: so I 
changed my wet boots, had an early supper and 
a nap in the chimney-corner, and went down to 
the works at a few minutes before half-past nine. 
Arriving at the factory gate, I found it ajar, and 
so walked in and closed it after me. I remember 
thinking at the time that it was unlike George's 
usual caution to leave it so; but it passed from 
my mind next moment. Having slipped in the 
bolt, I then went straight over to George's little 
counting-house, where the gas was shining 
cheerfully in the window. Here also, somewhat 
to my surprise, I found the door open, and the 
room empty. I went in. The threshold and part 
of the floor was wetted by the driving rain. The 
wages-book was open on the desk, George's 
pen stood in the ink, and his hat hung on its 
usual peg in the corner. I concluded, of course, 
that he had gone round to the ovens; so, 
following him, I took down his hat and carried it 
with me, for it was now raining fast.</p>
<p>The baking-houses lay just opposite, on the 
other side of the yard. There were three of 
them, opening one out of the other; and in each, 
the great furnace filled all the middle of the 
room. These furnaces are, in fact, large kilns 
built of brick, with an oven closed in by an iron 
door in the centre of each, and a chimney going 
up through the roof. The pottery, enclosed in 
seggars, stands round inside on shelves, and has 
to be turned from time to time while the firing 
is going on. To turn these seggars, test the 
heat, and keep the fires up, was my work at the 
period of which I am now telling you, Major.</p>
<p>Well! I went through the baking-houses one 
after the other, and found all empty alike. Then 
a strange vague uneasy feeling came over me, and 
I began to wonder what could have become of 
George. It was possible that he might be in one 
of the workshops; so I ran over to the counting-house, 
lighted a lantern, and made a thorough 
survey of the yards. I tried the doors; they 
were all locked as usual. I peeped into the 
open sheds; they were all vacant. I called 
"George! George!" in every part of the outer 
premises; but the wind and rain drove back my 
voice, and no other voice replied to it. Forced 
at last to believe that he was really gone, I took 
his hat back to the counting-house, put away 
the wages-book, extinguished the gas, and 
prepared for my solitary watch.</p>
<p>The night was mild, and the heat in the 
baking-rooms intense. I knew, by experience, 
that the ovens had been overheated, and that 
none of the porcelain must go in at least for 
the next two hours; so I carried my stool 
to the door, settled myself in a sheltered 
corner where the air could reach me, but not 
the rain, and fell to wondering where George 
could have gone, and why he should not have 
waited till the time appointed. That he had left 
in haste was clear--not because his hat remained 
behind, for he might have had a cap with him--
but because he had left the book open, and the 
gas lighted. Perhaps one of the workmen had 
met with some accident, and he had been 
summoned away so urgently that he had no time to 
think of anything; perhaps he would even now 
come back presently to see that all was right 
before he went home to his lodgings. Turning 
these things over in my mind, I grew drowsy, 
my thoughts wandered, and I fell asleep.</p>
<p>I cannot tell how long my nap lasted. I had 
walked a great distance that day, and I slept 
heavily; but I awoke all in a moment, with 
a sort of terror upon me, and, looking up, saw 
George Barnard sitting on a stool before the 
oven door, with the firelight full upon his face.</p>
<p>Ashamed to be found sleeping, I started to 
my feet. At the same instant, he rose, turned 
away without even looking towards me, and 
went out into the next room.</p>
<p>"Don't be angry, George!" I cried, following 
him. "None of the seggars are in. I knew 
the fires were too strong, and--"</p>
<p>The words died on my lips. I had followed him 
from the first room to the second, from the second 
to the third, and in the third--I lost him!</p>
<p>I could not believe my eyes. I opened the 
end door leading into the yard, and looked out; 
but he was nowhere in sight. I went round to 
the back of the baking-houses, looked behind 
the furnaces, ran over to the counting-house, 
called him by his name over and over again; but 
all was dark, silent, lonely, as ever.</p>
<p>Then I remembered how I had bolted the 
outer gate, and how impossible it was that he 
should have come in without ringing. Then, too, 
I began again to doubt the evidence of my own 
senses, and to think I must have been dreaming.</p>
<p>I went back to my old post by the door of the 
first baking-house, and sat down for a moment 
to collect my thoughts.</p>
<p>"In the first place," said I to myself, "there 
is but one outer gate. That outer gate I bolted 
on the inside, and it is bolted still. In the 
next place, I searched the premises, and found 
all the sheds empty, and the workshop-doors 
padlocked as usual on the outside. I proved 
that George was nowhere about, when I came, 
and I know he could not have come in since, 
without my knowledge. Therefore it is a dream. 
It is certainly a dream, and there's an end 
of it."</p>
<p>And with this I trimmed my lantern and 
proceeded to test the temperature of the furnaces. 
We used to do this, I should tell you, by the 
introduction of little roughly-moulded lumps of 
common fire-clay. If the heat is too great, they 
crack; if too little, they remain damp and moist; 
if just right, they become firm and smooth all 
over, and pass into the biscuit stage. Well! I took 
my three little lumps of clay, put one in each 
oven, waited while I counted five hundred, and 
then went round again to see the results. The 
two first were in capital condition, the third had 
flown into a dozen pieces. This proved that the 
seggars might at once go into ovens One and 
Two, but that number Three had been over- 
heated, and must be allowed to go on cooling 
for an hour or two longer.</p>
<p>I therefore stocked One and Two with nine 
rows of seggars, three deep on each shelf; left 
the rest waiting till number Three was in a 
condition to be trusted; and, fearful of falling 
asleep again, now that the firing was in progress, 
walked up and down the rooms to keep myself 
awake. This was hot work, however, and I 
could not stand it very long; so I went back 
presently to my stool by the door, and fell to 
thinking about my dream. The more I thought 
of it, the more strangely real it seemed, and 
the more I felt convinced that I was actually 
on my feet, when I saw George get up and walk 
into the adjoining room. I was also certain 
that I had still continued to see him as he 
passed out of the second room into the third, 
and that, at that time I was even following his 
very footsteps. Was it possible, I asked myself, 
that I could have been up and moving, and yet 
not quite awake? I had heard of people walking 
in their sleep. Could it be that I was walking 
in mine, and never waked till I reached the 
cool air of the yard? All this seemed likely 
enough, so I dismissed the matter from my mind, 
and passed the rest of the night in attending to 
the seggars, adding fresh fuel from time to time 
to the furnaces of the first and second ovens, and 
now and then taking a turn through the yards. 
As for Number Three, it kept up its heat to such 
a degree that it was almost day before I dared 
trust the seggars to go in it.</p>
<p>Thus the hours went by; and at half-past seven 
on Thursday morning, the men came to their 
work. It was now my turn to go off duty, but 
I wanted to see George before I left, and so 
waited for him in the counting-house, while a 
lad named Steve Storr took my place at the 
ovens. But the clock went on from half-past 
seven to a quarter to eight; then to eight 
o'clock; then to a quarter-past eight--and still 
George never made his appearance. At length, 
when the hand got round to half-past eight, I 
grew weary of waiting, took up my hat, ran 
home, went to bed, and slept profoundly until 
past four in the afternoon.</p>
<p>That evening I went down to the factory 
quite early; for I had a restlessness upon me, 
and I wanted to see George before he left for 
the night. This time, I found the gate bolted, 
and I rang for admittance.</p>
<p>"How early you are, Ben!" said Steve Storr, 
as he let me in.</p>
<p>"Mr. Barnard's not gone?" I asked, quickly; 
for I saw at the first glance that the gas was 
out in the counting-house.</p>
<p>"He's not gone," said Steve, "because he's 
never been."</p>
<p>"Never been?"</p>
<p>"No: and what's stranger still, he's not been 
home either, since dinner yesterday."</p>
<p>"But he was here last night."</p>
<p>"Oh yes, he was here last night, making up 
the books. John Parker was with him till past 
six; and you found him here, didn't you, at 
half-past nine?"</p>
<p>I shook my head.</p>
<p>"Well, he's gone, anyhow. Good night!"</p>
<p>"Good night!"</p>
<p>I took the lantern from his hand, bolted him 
out mechanically, and made my way to the 
baking-houses like one in a stupor. George 
gone? Gone without a word of warning to his 
employer, or of farewell to his fellow-workmen? 
I could not understand it. I could not believe it. 
I sat down bewildered, incredulous, stunned. 
Then came hot tears, doubts, terrifying 
suspicions. I remembered the wild words he had 
spoken a few nights back; the strange calm by 
which they were followed; my dream of the evening 
before. I had heard of men who drowned 
themselves for love; and the turbid Severn ran 
close by--so close, that one might pitch a stone 
into it from some of the workshop windows.</p>
<p>These thoughts were too horrible. I dared 
not dwell upon them. I turned to work, to 
free myself from them, if I could; and began by 
examining the ovens. The temperature of all 
was much higher than on the previous night, the 
heat having been gradually increased during the 
last twelve hours. It was now my business to 
keep the heat on the increase for twelve more; 
after which it would be allowed, as gradually, to 
subside, until the pottery was cool enough for 
removal. To turn, the seggars, and add fuel to 
the two first furnaces, was my first work. As 
before, I found number three in advance of the 
others, and so left it for half an hour, or an 
hour. I then went round the yard; tried the 
doors; let the dog loose; and brought him back 
with me to the baking-houses, for company. 
After that, I set my lantern on a shelf beside 
the door, took a book from my pocket, and 
began to read.</p>
<p>I remember the title of the book as well as 
possible. It was called Bowlker's Art of 
Angling, and contained little rude cuts of all kinds 
of artificial flies, hooks, and other tackle. But 
I could not keep my mind to it for two minutes 
together; and at last I gave it up in despair, 
covered my face with my hands, and fell into a 
long absorbing painful train of thought. A 
considerable time had gone by thus--maybe an 
hour--when I was roused by a low whimpering 
howl from Captain, who was lying at my feet. 
I looked up with a start, just as I had started 
from sleep the night before, and with the same 
vague terror; and saw, exactly in the same 
place and in the same attitude, with the 
firelight full upon him--George Barnard!</p>
<p>At this sight, a fear heavier than the fear of 
death fell upon me, and my tongue seemed 
paralysed in my mouth. Then, just as last night, 
he rose, or seemed to rise, and went slowly 
out into the next room. A power stronger than 
myself appeared to compel me, reluctantly, to 
follow him. I saw him pass through the second 
room--cross the threshold of the third room--
walk straight up to the oven--and there pause. 
He then turned, for the first time, with the 
glare of the red firelight pouring out upon him 
from the open door of the furnace, and looked 
at me, face to face. In the same instant, his 
whole frame and countenance seemed to glow 
and become transparent, as if the fire were all 
within him and around him and in that glow 
he became, as it were, absorbed into the furnace, 
and disappeared!</p>
<p>I uttered a wild cry, tried to stagger from 
the room, and fell insensible before I reached 
the door.</p>
<p>When I next opened my eyes, the grey dawn 
was in the sky; the furnace doors were all 
closed as I had left them when I last went 
round; the dog was quietly sleeping not far 
from my side; and the men were ringing at the 
gate, to be let in.</p>
<br/>
<p>I told my tale from beginning to end, and was 
laughed at, as a matter of course, by all who 
heard it. When it was found, however, that 
my statements never varied, and, above all, that 
George Barnard continued absent, some few 
began to talk it over seriously, and among 
those few, the master of the works. He 
forbade the furnace to be cleared out, called in 
the aid of a celebrated naturalist, and had the 
ashes submitted to a scientific examination. 
The result was as follows:</p>
<br/>
<p>The ashes were found to have been largely 
saturated with some kind of fatty animal matter. 
A considerable portion of those ashes consisted 
of charred bone. A semi-circular piece of iron, 
which evidently had once been the heel of a 
workman's heavy boot, was found, half fused, 
at one corner of the furnace. Near it, a tibia 
bone, which still retained sufficient of its 
original form and texture to render identification 
possible. This bone, however, was so much 
charred, that it fell into powder on being 
handled.</p>
<p>After this, not many doubted that George 
Barnard had been foully murdered, and that his 
body had been thrust into the furnace. 
Suspicion fell upon Louis Laroche. He was 
arrested, a coroner's inquest was held, and 
every circumstance connected with the night 
of the murder was as thoroughly sifted and 
investigated as possible. All the sifting in the 
world, however, failed either to clear or to 
condemn Louis Laroche. On the very night of his 
release, he left the place by the mail train, and 
was never seen or heard of there, again. As 
for Leah, I know not what became of her. I 
went away myself before many weeks were over, 
and never have set foot among the Potteries 
from that hour to this.</p>
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE BEST ATTIC WAS UNDER A CLOUD."/>
<chapter>
<p>Major, you have assured me of your sympathy; 
you shall receive my confidence. I not only 
seem--as you have searchingly observed--
"under a cloud," but I am. I entered (shall I 
say like a balloon?) into a dense stratum of 
cloud, obscuring the wretched earth from view, 
in the year eighteen hundred and dash, in the 
sweet summer season, when nature, as has been 
remarked by some distinguished poet, puts on her 
gayest garb, and when her countenance is 
adorned with the sunniest and loveliest of smiles. 
Ah! what are now those smiles to me? What 
care I for sunshine or for verdure? For me, 
summer is no more. For, I must ever remember 
that it was in the summer that the canker 
ate its way into my heart's core--that it was in 
the summer that I parted with my belief in 
mankind--that it was in summer that I knew 
for the first time that WOMAN--but this is 
premature. Pray be seated.</p>
<p>I have no doubt that my appearance and 
words convey to you, Major, and to all observant 
persons, that I have an elevated soul. In fact, 
were it otherwise, how could I be under a cloud? 
The sordid soul won't blight. To one possessing 
an elevated soul like myself, the task of keeping 
accounts at a furrier's (in a large way) could 
not be otherwise than repugnant. It <em>was</em> 
repugnant, and the rapture of getting a holiday, 
which was annually accorded me in June--not 
a busy month in the fur-trade--was something 
perfectly indescribable. Of course, whenever my 
vacation time came round, I invariably rushed 
off to the country; there to indulge my natural 
tastes and commune with our mother, Nature.</p>
<p>On the particular occasion of which I have now 
to speak, I had, however, other communings to 
look forward to, besides those in which nature 
takes her silent yet eloquent part. I loved 
Aha!--Love--Woman--Vertigo--Despair--I 
beg your pardon--I will be calm. I loved 
Miss Nuttlebury. Miss Nuttlebury lived in the 
neighbourhood of Dartford (at a convenient 
distance from the Powder-Mills), so in the 
neighbourhood of Dartford (rather further from 
the Powder-Mills) I determined to spend my 
vacation. I made arrangements at a certain 
small roadside inn for my board and lodging.</p>
<p>I was acquainted--nay, I was on friendly 
terms--with the Nuttleburys. Mr. Nuttlebury, 
a land surveyor in a rather small way, 
was an old friend of my father's; so I had access 
to the house. I had access also, as I thought, 
to the heart of Mary, which was Miss Nuttlebury's 
name. If I was mistaken--Aha!--but I 
am again premature. You are aware, or perhaps 
you are not aware, that my name is Oliver 
Cromwell Shrubsole--so called after the great 
Protector of British rights; the man who, or rather 
but for whom--but I am again premature, or 
rather, I should say, on the whole the reverse.</p>
<p>The first days of my residence near Fordleigh, 
the name of the village where the Nuttleburys 
dwelt, were happy in the extreme. I saw much 
of Mary. I walked with Mary, made hay with 
Mary, observed the moon in Mary's society, 
and in vain sought to interest Mary in those 
mysterious shadows which diversify the surface of 
that luminary. I subsequently endeavoured to 
interest the fair girl in other matters nearer 
home--in short, in myself; and I fondly 
imagined that I succeeded in doing so.</p>
<p>One day, when I had dropped in at the family 
dinner-hour--not from base motives, for I was 
boarded at my inn by contract--I found the 
family conversing on a subject which caused me 
considerable uneasiness. At the moment of my 
arrival, Mr. Nuttlebury was uttering these 
words:</p>
<p>"At what time will he be here, then?" 
(He?)</p>
<p>I listened breathless, after the first salutation 
had passed, for more; I was not long in 
ascertaining that "he" was a cousin of Mary's, who 
was coming down to spend some days at 
Fordleigh, and whose arrival was anticipated by the 
whole family with expressions of delight. The 
younger boy and girl Nuttleburys seemed to be 
especially rapturous at the prospect of the 
Beast's arrival, and from this I augured ill. 
Altogether, I felt that there was a trying scene 
coming; that my opportunities of converse with 
my soul's idol would be fewer than they had 
been, and that general discomfort and misery 
were about to ensue. I was right.</p>
<p>Oho!--I beg your pardon--I will be calm.</p>
<p>The Beast, "He," arrived in the course of 
that very afternoon, and I believe I am not 
speaking too strongly in affirming that we--" he" 
and I--hated each other cordially from the first 
moment of our exchanging glances. He was 
an under-hand looking beast, short of stature; 
such a creature as any high-souled woman should 
have abhorred the sight of; but his prospects 
were good, he having some small situation in the 
Custom-house, on the strength of which, he gave 
himself airs, as if he was a member of the 
government; and when he talked of the country, 
he spoke of it as "we." Alas! how could I 
compete with him? What could I talk about, 
except the fur-trade, and the best method of 
keeping the moths under? So, having nothing 
to talk about, I remained sulky and glum and 
silent: a condition in which a man does not 
usually tell to advantage in society. I felt that I 
was not telling to advantage, and this made me 
hate the beast--whose disgusting name was 
Huffell--more cordially than before. It affords 
me a gloomy pleasure to think that I never once 
lost an opportunity of contradicting him--flat 
--in the course of that first evening. But, 
somehow or other, he generally got the best of 
it: possibly because I had contradicted him for 
the sake of doing so, and without bestowing a 
thought upon the rights or wrongs of the matter 
under discussion. But the worst of it was, that 
it did appear to me, that Mary--my Mary--
seemed to be on the side of Huffell. Her eyes 
would brighten--or I thought so--when he 
triumphed. And what right had she to go and 
fig herself out like that, in all her finery for 
Huffell? She never did so for me.</p>
<p>"This must be put a stop to, and promptly," 
I muttered to myself, as I walked back to my 
inn in a state of the most intense fury. And 
to leave him there with the field all to himself! 
What might he not be saying of me at that 
moment? Turning me into ridicule, perhaps? 
I resolved to crush him next day, or perish in 
the attempt.</p>
<p>Next day I lay in wait for him, and 
presently I thought my opportunity had come:</p>
<p>"WE shall have to make some change about 
that appointment of Sir Cornelius," said Huffell, 
"or he'll have all his family in the office in a 
week."</p>
<p>"What do you mean by '<em>we</em>?' "I asked, with 
ferocious emphasis.</p>
<p>"I mean government," he answered, coolly.</p>
<p>"Well but <em>you</em>'re not government," was my 
dignified reply. "The Custom-house, even as 
represented by those who hold high positions 
in it, has as little to do with governing the 
country as can well be imagined. The higher 
officials in the Custom-house, are at best rather 
government servants than government advisers, 
while the lower--"</p>
<p>"Well, sir, 'the lower?'"</p>
<p>"The less they try to connect themselves 
with their betters by talking about 'we,' the 
better for all parties." I said this in a scathing 
manner, and feeling painfully warm in the forehead.</p>
<p>"You're talking about what you don't understand, 
sir," said the exciseman, or the tide-waiter, 
or whatever he was. "<em>We</em>'re all in the same boat. 
Pray do you never say 'we' when talking of 
your master's shop?"</p>
<p>"Master's shop, sir?"</p>
<p>"Oh, I beg your pardon," said he mockingly, 
"aren't you a cashier in a fur-shop?"</p>
<p>Shop! Fur-shop! I could have seen him--
seen him--moth eaten.</p>
<p>"I'll tell you what I'm not, sir," I burst out, 
losing self-control, "I am not the man to put 
up with the con--foun--ded impudence of an 
obscure tide-waiter."</p>
<p>"Tide-waiter!" repeated the beast, starting 
to his feet.</p>
<p>"Tide-waiter," I calmly reiterated.</p>
<p>At this, the whole family of the Nuttleburys, 
who had hitherto appeared to be paralysed, 
interposed, one screeching out one thing, another 
yelling another. But they were all--Mary and 
all--against me, and affirmed that I had 
purposely picked a quarrel with their relation--
which, by-the-by, I rather think I had. The 
unpleasantness ended in Mr. Nuttlebury's 
requesting me, in so many words, to withdraw.</p>
<p>"After what has occurred there is nothing 
left for me, but to do so," I remarked, making 
towards the door with much majesty; "but if 
Mr. Huffell thinks he has heard the last of this, 
he is a good deal mistaken. As for you, Mary," 
I continued;--but before I could complete my 
sentence I experienced a sensation of an elderly 
hand in my coat-collar, and found myself in the 
passage, with the room door closed against me. 
I lost no time in vacating this ignominious position, 
and seeking the open air. Presently I 
found myself at my desk writing to Dewsnap.</p>
<p>Dewsnap was then my greatest friend. He 
was, like me, in the fur business, and was a fine 
honourable upright noble fellow, as bold as 
brass, and always especially sensitive about 
the point of honour. To this friend I wrote 
a long account of all that had happened; asking 
his advice. I mentioned at the end of my 
letter that I was only restrained by the want 
of a pair of pistols, from inviting this wretched 
being to a hostile meeting.</p>
<p>The next day I passed in retirement, 
speculating much on what Dewsnap's answer would 
be. It was a day of heavy rain, and I had 
plenty of time to mourn over my exclusion from 
the cheerful abode of the Nuttleburys, and to 
reflect how much better off my rival was (sunning 
himself in my adored one's smiles) than I, a 
lonely exile, flattening my nose against the 
window of a country inn, and watching the 
drippings of the roof-drain as they splashed into 
the last-filling water-butt. It is needless to say 
that I retired to rest early, and that I was 
unable to sleep.</p>
<p>I could sleep next morning, however, and 
did so till a late hour. I was aroused from a 
heavy slumber, by a loud knocking at my door, 
and the sound of a voice which I seemed to 
recognise.</p>
<p>"Here, Shrubsole! Hi, Oliver! Let me in. 
Shrubsole, what a lazy fellow you are!"</p>
<p>Gracious Heaven, was it possible? Was it 
the voice of Dewsnap? I rose, unlocked the 
door, and jumped into bed again.</p>
<p>Yes, it was my friend. He entered erect, 
vigorous, energetic as usual, deposited a small 
carpet-bag near the door, and, retaining a 
curious-looking oblong mahogany box under his 
arm, advanced to greet me.</p>
<p>"What on earth do you do lying in bed at 
this time of the day?" said Dewsnap, grasping 
my hand.</p>
<p>"I couldn't sleep till morning came," I 
answered, passing my hand athwart my brow. 
"But how did you get away?"</p>
<p>"Oh, I've got a few days' holiday, and am 
come down to answer your letter in person. 
Well? How's this affair going on?"</p>
<p>"Do not ask me," I groaned. "It has made 
me wretched. I know no more. You don't know 
how fond I was of that girl."</p>
<p>"Well, and you shall have her yet. I'm going 
to settle it all for you," said Dewsnap, 
confidently.</p>
<p>"What do you mean to do?" I asked, with 
some hesitation.</p>
<p>"Do? Why, there's only one thing <em>to</em> do!" 
He rattled the queer-looking mahogany box as 
though it contained metallic pills.</p>
<p>"What have you got in that box?" I asked.</p>
<p>"There's a pair of pistols in this box," said 
Dewsnap, proudly, "with either one of which it 
would almost be a pleasure to find yourself 
winged."</p>
<p>"Sir?" I observed, sitting up in bed with 
marked displeasure.</p>
<p>"You mentioned your difficulty about 
weapons, so I borrowed them of a friend of mine--
a gunmaker--and brought them down with 
me."</p>
<p>"Hang him!" I thought, "how very prompt 
he has been about it. Amazingly prompt, to be 
sure.--You think, then," I added, aloud, "that 
there's no--no other way out of the difficulty?"</p>
<p>"Apology," said Dewsnap, who had now 
opened the box, and was clicking away with the 
lock of one of the weapons, with the muzzle 
directed towards my head--"ample apology on 
the part of the other side--is the only 
alternative. Written apology, in fact."</p>
<p>"Ah," I replied, "I don't think the other 
side will agree to that."</p>
<p>"Then," said my friend, extending his pistol, 
and aiming at a portrait of the Marquis of 
Granby hanging over the fireplace: "then we 
must put a bullet into the exciseman."</p>
<p>(And suppose the exciseman puts a bullet into 
me, I thought to myself. So erratic is thought!)</p>
<p>"Where does the exciseman live?" inquired 
my friend, putting on his hat. "There is not a 
moment to be lost in these cases."</p>
<p>"Wait till I'm dressed," I remonstrated, "and 
I'll show you. Or you can go after breakfast."</p>
<p>"Not a bit of it. The people down stairs will 
tell me where to find him. Nuttlebury's, I 
think you said? I'll be there and back, by the 
time you're ready for breakfast."</p>
<p>He was out of the room almost before he had 
done speaking, and I was left to make my toilet 
and improve my appetite for breakfast with the 
reflection that the number of such meals in store 
for me was, perhaps, more limited than I could 
have wished. Perhaps I a little regretted having 
put the affair into the hands of my energetic 
friend. So erratic (I may again remark) is 
human thought!</p>
<p>I waited some time for my friend, but was 
obliged at last to begin breakfast without him. 
As the meal was approaching its termination, 
I saw him pass the window of the little parlour 
in which I took my meals, and immediately 
afterwards he entered the room.</p>
<p>"Well," he said, sitting down at the table 
and commencing a vigorous attack on the 
eatables, '" it is as I expected. We are driven 
to extremities."</p>
<p>"What do you mean?" I asked.</p>
<p>"I mean," remarked Dewsnap, chipping away 
at his egg, "that the other side declines to 
apologise, and that consequently the other side 
must be bowled down;--shot."</p>
<p>"Oh dear me," I said--relenting, Major, 
relenting--" I shouldn't like to do that."</p>
<p>"You wouldn't like to do that? May I 
ask, Mr. Shrubsole, what you mean by that 
remark?"</p>
<p>"I mean that, that--is there no other way 
out of it?"</p>
<p>"Now look here, Shrubsole," said my 
companion, with a severe air, and suspending for 
a moment his attack on the breakfast; "you 
have put this affair in my hands, and you must 
allow me to carry it through, according to the 
laws of honour. It is extremely painful to me 
to be engaged in such an affair" (I couldn't 
help thinking that he seemed rather to enjoy it), 
"but, being engaged in it, I shall go through 
with it to the end. Come! We'll get these things 
cleared away, and then you shall sit down and 
write a formal challenge, which I will undertake 
to deliver in the proper quarter."</p>
<p>Dewsnap was too much for me. He seemed 
to have all the right phrases at his tongue's 
end; he was so tremendously well-informed as 
to what was the right thing to do, and the right 
thing to say when conducting an affair of this 
kind, that I could not help asking him whether 
he had ever been engaged in one before?</p>
<p>"No," he said, "no; but I believe I have a 
sort of aptitude for the kind of thing. Indeed, 
I have always felt that I should be in my element 
in arranging the details of an affair of honour."</p>
<p>"How you would enjoy being a principal, 
instead of a second!" I said--rather maliciously ; 
for Dewsnap's alacrity aggravated me.</p>
<p>"No, not a bit, my dear fellow. I take such 
an interest in this affair that I identify myself 
with you entirely, and quite feel as if I was a 
principal."</p>
<p>(Then you feel a very curious sensation about 
the pit of the stomach, my boy, I thought to 
myself. I did not however give the thought 
expression. I merely mention it as an instance 
of the erratic nature of thought.)</p>
<p>"By-the-by," remarked Dewsnap, as he 
pocketed my challenge and prepared to depart, 
"I forgot to mention that one or two fellows of 
our acquaintance are coming down."</p>
<p>"One or two fellows?" I repeated, in a 
highly displeased, nay, crushing tone.</p>
<p>"Yes, Cripps is coming, and Fowler, and 
perhaps Kershaw, if he can get away. We 
were talking your affair over, the evening before 
I left, and they were all so much interested in 
it--for I predicted from the first, that there must 
be a meeting--that they're all coming down to 
see you through it."</p>
<p>How I cursed my own folly in haying 
entrusted the keeping of my honour to this dreadfully 
zealous friend of mine! I thought, as he 
marched off erect and fussy with that wretched 
challenge in his pocket, that there was 
something positively bloodthirsty about the man. 
And then those other fellows coming down for 
the express purpose of seeing somebody shot! 
For that was their purpose, I felt. I fully 
believed that, if by any fortunate chance there 
should be no blood shed, those so-called friends 
of mine would go away disgusted.</p>
<p>The train of reflection into which I had fallen 
was interrupted at this juncture, by the appearance 
outside the window, of three human 
figures. These turned out, on inspection, to be 
no other than the individuals whose taste for 
excitement I had been condemning so strongly 
in my own mind. There they were, Messrs. 
Cripps, Fowler, and Kershaw, grinning and 
gesticulating at me through the window, like 
vulgar unfeeling idiots as they were. And one 
of them (I think it was Cripps) had the brutality 
to put himself into the attitude supposed to be 
the correct one for a duellist, with his left hand 
behind his back, and his right raised as if to 
discharge an imaginary pistol.</p>
<p>They were in the room with me directly, 
large, noisy, and vulgar, laughing and guffawing 
--making comments on my appearance, asking 
me if I had made my will, what I had left to 
each of them, and otherwise conducting 
themselves in a manner calculated to turn one's milk 
of human kindness to bitterest gall. How they 
enjoyed it! When they learned that Dewsnap 
was actually at that time away on a war 
mission, and that he might return at any moment 
with the fatal answer--I say when they heard 
that, they positively gloated over me. They 
sat down and stared at me, and every now 
and then one of them would say, with a low, 
chuckling giggle, "I say, old fellow! How do 
you feel about it now?" It was a hideous 
relief to me when Dewsnap returned with the 
baleful news that the challenge was accepted, 
and that the meeting was appointed for the next 
morning at eight o'clock.</p>
<p>Those ruffians enjoyed themselves that afternoon 
to the utmost. They had such a pleasure 
in store for next day, that it gave an added 
zest to everything they did. It sharpened their 
appetites, it stimulated their thirst, it 
imparted to the skittles with which they amused 
themselves during the afternoon, an additional 
charm. The evening was devoted to conviviality. 
Dewsnap, after spending some time in 
oiling the triggers of the pistols, remarked that 
now they were in such prime condition, that 
they would "snap a fellow's head off, almost 
without his knowing it." This inhuman remark 
was made at the moment when we were 
separating for the night.</p>
<p>I passed the greater part of the dark hours, 
in writing letters of farewell to my relations, and 
in composing a stinger for Miss Mary Nuttlebury, 
which I trusted would embitter the whole 
of her future life. Then I threw myself on my 
bed--which was not wholly devoid of knobs--
and found for a few hours the oblivion I desired.</p>
<p>We were first on the ground. Indeed, it was 
necessary that we should be, as those three 
ferocious Anabaptists, Cripps, Fowler, and 
Kershaw, had to be stowed away in places of 
concealment whence they could see without being 
seen; but even when this stowage had been 
accomplished and the fatal hour had arrived, we 
were still kept waiting so long that a faint hope 
--misgiving, I meant to say--began to dawn in 
my heart that my adversary had been seized 
with a sudden panic, and had fled at the last 
moment, leaving me master of the situation, 
with a bloodless victory.</p>
<p>The sound of voices, and of laughter--laughter! 
--reached me while I was musing on the prospect 
of an honourable escape from my perilous 
position. In another moment my antagonist, 
still talking and laughing with some one who 
closely followed him, jumped over a stile at the 
side of the field in which we awaited him. 
Grinning in the most impudent manner, my 
antagonist inquired of his second, who was the 
village apothecary's assistant, whether he was a 
good hand at patching up bullet wounds?</p>
<p>It was at this moment that an incident 
occurred which caused a small delay in our 
proceedings. One of the Anabaptists--Cripps--
had, with a view to concealment, and also 
perhaps with a view to keeping out of harm's way, 
perched himself in a tree which commanded a 
good view of the field of action; but not 
having used sufficient caution in the choice 
of his position, he had trusted his weight to 
a bough which proved unequal to the task of 
sustaining it. Consequently it happened that 
just as the seconds were beginning their 
preliminary arrangements, and during an awful 
pause, the unlucky Cripps came plunging and 
crashing to the ground, where he remained 
seated at the foot of the tree in a state of 
undignified ruin and prostration.</p>
<p>After this there was a prodigious row and 
confusion. My opponent having thus 
discovered that there was one person observing 
our proceedings from a place of concealment, 
concluded naturally enough that there might be 
others. Accordingly a search was promptly 
instituted, which ended in the unearthing of my 
two other friends, who were obliged to emerge 
from their hiding-places in a very humiliated 
and crestfallen condition. My adversary would 
not hear of fighting a duel in the presence of 
so large an audience, and so it ended in the three 
brutal Anabaptists being--very much to my 
satisfaction--expelled from the field. The 
appearance they presented as they retired along 
the pathway in Indian file, was the most abject 
thing I have ever beheld.</p>
<p>This little business disposed of, there remained 
the great affair of the day to settle, and it took 
a great deal of settlement. There were 
diversities of opinions about every detail connected 
with the murderous operations. There were 
disputes about the number of paces which should 
separate the combatants, about the length of 
those paces, about the proper method of loading 
pistols, about the best way of giving the 
signal to fire--about everything. But what 
disgusted me most, was the levity displayed 
by my opponent, who seemed to think the whole 
thing a capital joke, sneering and sniggering at 
everything that was done or said. Does the man 
bear a charmed life, I asked myself, that he 
behaves with such sickening flippancy when about 
to risk it?</p>
<p>At last all these endless preliminaries were 
settled, and Mr. Huffell and I remained staring 
defiance at each other with a distance of 
only twelve paces between us. The beast was 
grinning even now, and when he was asked for 
the last time whether he was prepared to make 
an apology, he absolutely laughed.</p>
<p>It had been arranged that one of the seconds, 
Huffell's as it happened, should count one, two, 
three, and that at the word "three" we should 
both fire (if we could) at the same moment. 
My heart felt so tight at about this period, that 
I fancied it must have contracted to half its 
usual size, and I had a sensation of being light 
on my legs, and inordinately tall, such as one 
has after having had a fever.</p>
<p>"One!" said the apothecary, and the 
monosyllable was followed by quite a long pause.</p>
<p>"Two!"</p>
<p>"Stop!" cried a voice, which I recognised 
as the voice of my adversary, "I have something 
to say."</p>
<p>I whisked myself round in a moment, and 
saw that Mr. Huffell had thrown his weapon 
down on the ground, and had left the position 
which had been assigned to him.</p>
<p>"What have you to say, sir?" asked the 
inexorable Dewsnap, in a severe tone; "whatever 
it is, you have chosen a most extraordinary 
moment to say it in."</p>
<p>"I have changed my mind," said Mr. Huffell, 
in a lachrymose tone; "I think that duelling is 
sinful, and I consent to apologise."</p>
<p>Astounded as I was at this announcement, I 
had yet leisure to observe that the apothecary 
did not look in the least surprised at what had 
happened.</p>
<p>"You consent to apologise?" asked Dewsnap, 
"to resign all claim to the lady, to express your 
deep contrition for the insolent expressions you 
have made use of towards my friend?"</p>
<p>"I consent," was the reply.</p>
<p>"We must have it all down in writing, mind!" 
stipulated my uncompromising friend.</p>
<p>"You shall have it all down in writing," 
said the contrite one.</p>
<p>"Well, this is a most extraordinary and 
unsatisfactory sort of thing," said Dewsnap, turning 
to me. "What are we to do?"</p>
<p>"It is unsatisfactory, but I suppose we must 
accept his apology," I answered, in a leisurely 
and nonchalant manner. My heart expanded at 
about this period.</p>
<p>"Has anybody got writing materials about 
him by chance?" asked my second, in a not 
very conciliatory tone.</p>
<p>Yes, the apothecary had, and he whipped them 
out in a moment--a note-book of unusual size 
and an indelible ink-pencil.</p>
<p>An apology of the most humble and abject 
kind was now dictated by my friend 
Dewsnap, and written down by the crushed and 
conquered Huffell. When he had affixed his 
signature to the document, it exactly filled 
one leaf of the apothecary's memorandum-book. 
The leaf was torn out and handed to my 
representative. At that moment the sound of the 
village-clock striking nine reached us from the 
distant church.</p>
<p>Mr. Huffell started as if the day were more 
advanced than he anticipated.</p>
<p>"I believe that the document is regular?" he 
asked. "If so, there is nothing to detain us 
in a spot henceforth replete with painful 
associations. Gentlemen both, good morning."</p>
<p>"Good morning, sir," said Dewsnap, sharply; 
"and allow me to add, that you have reason to 
consider yourself an uncommonly lucky young 
man."</p>
<p>"I do so consider myself, I assure you," 
retorted the servile wretch.</p>
<p>With that, he took his leave and disappeared 
over the stile, closely followed by his companion. 
Again I thought I heard this precious pair 
explode into fits of laughter as soon as they were 
On the other side of the hedge.</p>
<p>Dewsnap looked at me, and I looked at 
Dewsnap, but we could make nothing of it. It was 
the most inexplicable thing that the man should 
have gone so far, should have had his finger on 
the trigger of his pistol, should have waited till 
the very signal to fire was on the lips of his 
second, and should then have broken down in 
that lamentable manner. It really was, as my 
friend and I agreed, the most disgraceful piece 
of cowardice of which we had ever had 
experience. Another point on which we were 
agreed, was, that our side had come out of this 
affair with an amount of honour and glory such 
as is rarely achieved by the sons of men in this 
practical and un-romantic age.</p>
<p>And now behold the victor and his friends 
assembled round the small dining-table at the 
George and Dragon, and celebrating their 
triumph by a breakfast! in preparing which nil 
the resources of the establishment were brought 
into play.</p>
<p>It was a solemn occasion. The moment, I 
acknowledge, was to me a glorious one. My 
friends, naturally proud of their associate, and 
anxious to commemorate in some fitting manner 
the event of the morning, had invited me to this 
meal to be provided at their own expense. These 
dear fellows were no longer my guests. I was 
theirs. Dewsnap was in the chair--it was of the 
Windsor pattern--I was placed on his right: 
while at the other end of the table, which 
was not very far off, another Windsor chair 
supported the person of Mr. Cripps, the vice. 
The viands set before us were of the most recherch 
description, and when these had been 
done full justice to, and the chair had called for 
a bottle of champagne, our hilarity began almost 
to verge on the boisterous. My own mirth, 
indeed, was chastened by one pervading thought, 
of which I never for a moment lost sight. Had 
I not a secret joy which champagne could neither 
increase nor diminish ? Had not my rival formally 
abdicated, and was I not that very day to appear 
in the presence of Mary Nuttlebury as one who 
had risked his life for her sake ? Yes. I waited 
impatiently for the hour when these good fellows 
should take their departure, determining that, the 
moment they were gone, I would take possession 
of the field ingloriously vacated by my rival, and 
would enjoy the fruits of my victory. I was 
aroused from these reflections by the voice of 
my friend Dewsnap. It was, however, no longer 
the familiar acquaintance who spoke, but the 
official chairman.</p>
<p>Mr. Dewsnap began by remarking that we 
were met together on an occasion and under 
circumstances, of a very peculiar--he might 
almost say of an anomalous--nature. To begin 
with, here was a social meeting--nay, a convivial 
meeting, taking place at ten o'clock in the 
forenoon. That was the first anomaly. And for 
what was that meeting convened? To 
commemorate an act belonging to a class of achievements 
usually associated with a bygone age, 
rather than with that in which an inexorable 
Destiny had cast the lots of the present generation. 
Here was the second anomaly. Yes, these 
were anomalies, but anomalies of what a delightful 
kind! Would there were more such! It was 
--Mr. Dewsnap went on to say--the fashion of 
the day to decry the practice of duelling, but he, 
for his part, had always felt that circumstances 
might occur in the course of any man's career 
which would render an appeal to arms desirable 
--nay, to one who was sensitive on the point of 
honour, inevitable--and he therefore thought it 
highly important that the practice of duelling 
should not wholly fall into desuetude, but should 
be occasionally revived, as it had been on--on 
--in short, the present occasion.</p>
<p>At this moment, curiously enough, a faint 
cheer was heard in the distance. It came, doubtless, 
from the throats of some of the village- 
boys, and presently subsided. It was enough, 
however, to deprive our worthy chair of the 
thread of his eloquence, so that he was 
compelled to start again on a new tack.</p>
<p>"Gentlemen," said Mr. Dewsnap, "I must 
throw myself on your indulgence if my words 
fail to flow as freely as I could wish. I am, to 
begin with, gentlemen, powerfully moved, and 
that alone is enough to deprive me of any small 
amount of eloquence of which I may at other 
times be possessed. Likewise, I must frankly 
own that I am unaccustomed to public speaking 
at ten o'clock in the morning, and that 
the day-light puts me out. And yet," 
continued the chair, "I do not know why this 
should be so. Do not wedding-breakfasts take 
place by daylight? And are not speeches made 
on those occasions? And, after all, why should 
we not look upon this very meal as, to a 
certain extent, a wedding-breakfast? You seem 
surprised, gentlemen, at this inquiry, but I will 
ask you whether the event we are met together 
to celebrate--the event of this--morning has 
not been the first act of a drama which we all 
hope will terminate in a wedding--the wedding 
of our noble and courageous friend?"</p>
<p>It was a curious thing that, just when our 
chairman had got as far as this in his speech, 
the cheering we had heard before was repeated; 
though now much more loudly. It was also 
a curious thing that the bells of the village 
church, which was not very far off, began to 
ring a merry peal. There might not be much to 
concern us, in this, but still it was curious. 
The attention of Mr. Dewsnap's audience began 
to wander, and their glances were, from time to 
time, directed towards the window. Mr. 
Dewsnap's own attention began also to wander, and 
the thread of his discourse seemed once more to 
elude his grasp.</p>
<p>"Gentlemen," he began again, resolved, like 
a true orator as he was, to avail himself of 
accident, "I was remarking that this festive meal 
was, in some sort and by a figure of speech, a 
kind of wedding-breakfast, and while the words 
were yet upon my lips, behold the bells of the 
village church break out into a joyous peal! 
Gentlemen, there is something almost 
supernatural about this. It is a happy augury, and 
as such I accept it."</p>
<p>The bells were becoming quite frantic now, 
and the cheering was louder.</p>
<p>"And as such I accept it!" repeated Mr. 
Dewsnap. "Gentlemen, I should not be 
surprised if this were an ovation offered to our 
noble and courageous friend. The villagers 
have heard of his noble and courageous conduct, 
and arc approaching the inn to offer their humble 
congratulations."</p>
<p>It was quite certain that the villagers were 
approaching the inn, for the sound of their 
voices became every moment louder and louder. 
We all began to be restless under our chairman's 
eloquence, and when at length the sound 
of wheels rapidly approaching was added to the 
cheering and the bell-ringing, I could bear it 
no longer, and rushed hastily to the window, 
followed by everybody else in the room, the 
chair himself included.</p>
<p>A carriage and pair drove swiftly past 
the window. Major, I sicken while I speak. 
There was a postilion on the near horse, and 
on that postilion's jacket was a--Oho!--
Excuse me, I beg--a wedding-favour. It was 
an open carriage, and in it were seated two 
persons; one, was the gentleman, who had 
made me that humble apology not much more 
than an hour ago; the other, was Mary Nuttlebury, 
now, if I were to believe the evidence of 
my senses, Mary Huffell. They both laughed 
when they saw me at the window, and kissed 
their hands to me as they whirled away.</p>
<p>I became as one frantic. I pushed my friends, 
who in vain sought to restrain me, on one side. 
I rushed out into the village street. I yelled 
after the carriage. I gesticulated at the carriage. 
I ran after the carriage. But to what purpose? 
It was over. The thing was done. I had to 
return to the inn, the laughing-stock of the 
rude and ignorant populace.</p>
<p>I know no more. I don't know what became 
of me, how my bill at the inn was defrayed, how 
I got away. I only know that I am finally, 
hopelessly, and irretrievably under a cloud; 
that all my old companions, and my old habits 
have become odious to me; and that even the 
very lodgings in which I formerly resided were 
so unbearable, owing to the furniture being 
impregnated with painful associations, that I was 
obliged to remove and take up my quarters 
elsewhere. This, sir, is how I came to occupy these 
rooms, and I may here mention--if indeed the 
testimonial of a blighted wretch is of any value 
--that I have no cause to regret my change of 
abode, and that I regard Mrs. Lirriper as a 
most unexceptionable person, labouring indeed, 
as far as I can see, under only one defect. 
She is A WOMAN</p>. 
</chapter>
</part>
 
<part>
<info title="HOW THE PARLOURS ADDED A FEW WORDS."/>
<chapter>
<p>I have the honour of presenting myself by 
the name of Jackman. I esteem it a proud 
privilege to go down to posterity through the 
instrumentality of the most remarkable boy that 
ever lived--by the name of JEMMY JACKMAN 
LIRRIPER--and of my most worthy and most 
highly respected friend, Mrs. Emma Lirriper, of 
Eighty-one, Norfolk-street, Strand, in the County 
of Middlesex, in the United Kingdom of Great 
Britain and Ireland.</p>
<p>It is not for me to express the rapture with 
which we received that dear and eminently 
remarkable boy, on the occurrence of his first 
Christmas holidays. Suffice it to observe that 
when he came flying into the house with two 
splendid prizes (Arithmetic, and Exemplary 
Conduct), Mrs. Lirriper and myself embraced 
with emotion, and instantly took him to the 
Play, where we were all three admirably 
entertained.</p>
<p>Nor, is it to render homage to the virtues of 
the best of her good and honoured sex--whom, 
in deference to her unassuming worth, I will 
only here designate by the initials E. L.--that 
I add this record to the bundle of papers with 
which our, in a most distinguished degree, 
remarkable boy has expressed himself delighted, 
before re-consigning the same to the left-hand 
glass closet of Mrs. Lirriper's little bookcase.</p>
<p>Neither, is it to obtrude the name of the old 
original superannuated obscure Jemmy Jackman, 
once (to his degradation) of Wozenham's, long 
(to his elevation) of Lirriper's. If I could be 
consciously guilty of that piece of bad taste, it 
would indeed be a work of supererogation, now 
that the name is borne by JEMMY JACKMAN 
LIRRIPER.</p>
<p>No. I take up my humble pen to register a 
little record of our strikingly remarkable boy, 
which my poor capacity regards as presenting a 
pleasant little picture of the dear boy's mind. 
The picture may be interesting to himself when 
he is a man.</p>
<p>Our first re-united Christmas-day was the 
most delightful one we have ever passed together. 
Jemmy was never silent for five minutes, except 
in church-time. He talked as we sat by the fire, 
lie talked when we were out walking, he talked as 
we sat by the fire again, he talked incessantly at 
dinner, though he made a dinner almost as remarkable 
as himself. It was the spring of happiness 
in his fresh young heart flowing and flowing, 
and it fertilised (if I may be allowed so bold 
a figure) my much-esteemed friend, and J-- J--
the present writer.</p>
<p>There were only we three. We dined in my 
esteemed friend's little room, and our entertainment 
was perfect. But everything in the 
establishment is, in neatness, order, and comfort, 
always perfect. After dinner, our boy slipt away 
to his old stool at my esteemed friend's knee, and 
there, with his hot chesnuts and his glass of 
brown sherry (really, a most excellent wine!) 
on a chair for a table, his face outshone the 
apples in the dish.</p>
<p>We talked of these jottings of mine, which 
Jemmy had read through and through by that 
time; and so it came about that my esteemed 
friend remarked, as she sat smoothing Jemmy's 
curls:</p>
<p>"And as you belong to the house too, Jemmy, 
--and so much more than the Lodgers, having 
been born in it--why, your story ought to be 
added to the rest, I think, one of these days."</p>
<p>Jemmy's eye sparkled at this, and he said, 
"So <em>I</em> think, Gran."</p>
<p>Then, he sat looking at the fire, and then he 
began to laugh, in a sort of confidence with the 
fire, and then he said, folding his arms across 
my esteemed friend's lap and raising his bright 
face to hers:</p>
<p>"Would you like to hear a boy's story, 
Gran?"</p>
<p>"Of all things," replied my esteemed friend.</p>
<p>"Would you, godfather?"</p>
<p>"Of all things," I too replied.</p>
<p>"Well then," said Jemmy, "I'll tell you one."</p>
<p>Here, our indisputably remarkable boy gave 
himself a hug, and laughed again, musically, at 
the idea of his coming out in that new line. 
Then, he once more took the fire into the same 
sort of confidence as before, and began:</p>
<p>"Once upon a time, When pigs drank wine, 
And monkeys chewed tobaccer, 'Twas 
neither in your time nor mine, But that's no 
macker--"</p>
<p>"Bless the child!" cried my esteemed friend, 
"what's amiss with his brain'!"</p>
<p>"It's poetry, Gran," returned Jemmy, shouting 
with laughter. "We always begin stories 
that way, at school."</p>
<p>"Gave me quite a turn, Major," said my 
esteemed friend, fanning herself with a plate. 
"Thought he was light-headed!"</p>
<p>"In those remarkable times, Gran and God- 
father, there was once a boy;--not me, you 
know."</p>
<p>"No, no," says my respected friend, "not 
you. Not him, Major, you understand?"</p>
<p>"No, no," says I.</p>
<p>"And he went to school in Rutlandshire"</p>
<p>"Why not Lincolnshire?" says my respected 
friend.</p>
<p>"Why not, you dear old Gran? Because I 
go to school in Lincolnshire, don't I?"</p>
<p>"Ah, to be sure!" says my respected friend. 
"And it's not Jemmy, you understand, Major?"</p>
<p>"No, no," says I.</p>
<p>"Well!" our boy proceeded, hugging himself 
comfortably, and laughing merrily (again in 
confidence with the fire), before he again looked up 
in Mrs. Lirriper's face, "and so he was 
tremendously in love with his schoolmaster's daughter, 
and she was the most beautiful creature that 
ever was seen, and she had brown eyes, and she 
had brown hair all curling beautifully, and she 
had a delicious voice, and she was delicious 
altogether, and her name was Seraphina."</p>
<p>"What's the name of <em>your</em> schoolmaster's 
daughter, Jemmy?" asks my respected friend.</p>
<p>"Polly!" replied Jemmy, pointing his 
forefinger at her. "There now! Caught you! 
Ha! ha! ha!"</p>
<p>When he and my respected friend had had a 
laugh and a hug together, our admittedly 
remarkable boy resumed with a great relish:</p>
<p>"Well! And so he loved her. And so he 
thought about her, and dreamed about her, and 
made her presents of oranges and nuts, and 
would have made her presents of pearls and 
diamonds if he could have afforded it out of his 
pocket-money, but he couldn't. And so her 
father--O, he WAS a Tartar! Keeping the boys 
up to the mark, holding examinations once a 
month, lecturing upon all sorts of subjects at all 
sorts of times, and knowing everything in the 
world out of book. And so this boy--"</p>
<p>"Had he any name?" asks my respected 
friend.</p>
<p>"No he hadn't, Gran. Ha! ha! There 
now! Caught you again!"</p>
<p>After this, they had another laugh and 
another hug, and then our boy went on.</p>
<p>"Well! And so this boy he had a friend 
about as old as himself, at the same school, and 
his name (for He <em>had</em> a name, as it happened) 
was--let me remember--was Bobbo."</p>
<p>"Not Bob," says my respected friend.</p>
<p>"Of course not," says Jemmy. "What 
made you think it was, Gran? Well! And 
so this friend was the cleverest and bravest and 
best looking and most generous of all the friends 
that ever were, and so he was in love with 
Seraphina's sister, and so Seraphina's sister was 
in love with him, and so they all grew up."</p>
<p>"Bless us!" says my respected friend. "They 
were very sudden about it."</p>
<p>"So they all grew up," our boy repeated, 
laughing heartily, "and Bobbo and this boy went 
away together on horseback to seek their fortunes, 
and they partly got their horses by favour, and 
partly in a bargain; that is to say, they had 
saved up between them seven-and-fourpence, and 
the two horses, being Arabs, were worth more, 
only the man said he would take that, to favour 
them. Well! And so they made their fortunes 
and came prancing back to the school, with 
their pockets full of gold enough to last for 
ever. And so they rang at the parents' and 
visitors' bell (not the back gate), and when the 
bell was answered they proclaimed, ' The same 
as if it was scarlet fever! Every boy goes 
home for an indefinite period!' And then there 
was great hurrahing, and then they kissed 
Seraphina and her sister--each his own love and not 
the other's on any account--and then they 
ordered the Tartar into instant confinement."</p>
<p>"Poor man!" said my respected friend.</p>
<p>"Into instant confinement, Gran," repeated 
Jemmy, trying to look severe and roaring with 
laughter, "and he was to have nothing to eat 
but the boys' dinners, and was to drink half a 
cask of their beer, every day. And so then the 
preparations were made for the two weddings, 
and there were hampers, and potted things, and 
sweet things, and nuts, and postage-stamps, and 
all manner of things. And so they were so 
jolly, that they let the Tartar out, and he was 
jolly too."</p>
<p>"I am glad they let him out," says my 
respected friend, "because he had only done his 
duty."</p>
<p>"Oh but hadn't he overdone it though!" 
cried Jemmy. "Well! And so then this boy 
mounted his horse, with his bride in his arms, 
and cantered away, and cantered on and on till 
he came to a certain place where he had a 
certain Gran and a certain godfather--not you 
two, you know."</p>
<p>"No, no," we both said.</p>
<p>"And there he was received with great 
rejoicings, and he filled the cupboard and the 
bookcase with gold, and he showered it out 
on his Gran and his godfather because they were 
the two kindest and dearest people that ever 
lived in this world. And so while they were 
sitting up to their knees in gold, a knocking 
was heard at the street door, and who should it 
be but Bobbo, also on horseback with his bride 
in his arms, and what had he come to say but 
that he would take (at double rent) all the 
Lodgings for ever, that were not wanted by 
this boy and this Gran and this godfather, and 
that they would all live together, and all be 
happy! And so they were, and so it never 
ended!"</p>
<p>"And was there no quarrelling?" asked my 
respected friend, as Jemmy sat upon her lap, 
and hugged her.</p>
<p>"No! Nobody ever quarrelled."</p>
<p>"And did the money never melt away?"</p>
<p>"No! Nobody could ever spend it all."</p>
<p>"And did none of them ever grow older?"</p>
<p>"No! Nobody ever grew older after that."</p>
<p>"And did none of them ever die?"</p>
<p>"O no, no, no, Gran!" exclaimed our dear 
boy, laying his cheek upon her breast, and drawing 
her closer to him. "Nobody ever died."</p>
<p>"Ah Major, Major," says my respected friend, 
smiling benignly upon me. "This beats our 
stories. Let us end with the Boy's story, 
Major, for the Boy's story is the best that is 
ever told!"</p>
<p>In submission to which request on the part 
of the best of women, I have here noted it 
down as faithfully as my best abilities, coupled 
with my best intentions, would admit, subscribing 
it with my name,</p>
<centre>J. JACKMAN.</centre>
<centre>THE PARLOURS.</centre>
<centre>MRS. LIRRIPER'S LODGINGS.</centre>
</chapter>
</part>
</book>
